<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>178</id>
<a1>Aarnisalo,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Pietola,L.</a1>
<a1>Joensuu,J.</a1>
<a1>Isosomppi,J.</a1>
<a1>Aarnisalo,P.</a1>
<a1>Dinculescu,A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Sankila,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Jero,J.</a1>
<t1>Anti-clarin-1 AAV-delivered ribozyme induced apoptosis in the mouse cochlea</t1>
<jf>Hearing research</jf>
<jo>Hear.Res.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>230</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>9</sp>
<op>16</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Fluorescence</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Stria Vascularis/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Usher Syndromes/genetics/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<ab>Usher syndrome type 3 is caused by mutations in the USH3A gene, which encodes the protein clarin-1. Clarin-1 is a member of the tetraspanin superfamily (TM4SF) of transmembrane proteins, expressed in the organ of Corti and spiral ganglion cells of the mouse ear. We have examined whether the AAV-mediated anti-clarin ribozyme delivery causes apoptotic cell death in vivo in the organ of Corti. We used an AAV-2 vector delivered hammerhead ribozyme, AAV-CBA-Rz, which specifically recognizes and cleaves wild type mouse clarin-1 mRNA. Cochleae of CD-1 mice were injected either with 1mul of the AAV-CBA-Rz, or control AAV vectors containing the green fluorescent protein (GFP) marker gene (AAV-CBA-GFP). Additional controls were performed with saline only. At one-week and one-month post-injection, the animals were sacrificed and the cochleae were studied by histology and fluorescence imaging. Mice injected with AAV-CBA-GFP displayed GFP reporter expression of varying fluorescence intensity throughout the length of the cochlea in the outer and inner hair cells and stria vascularis, and to a lesser extent, in vestibular epithelial cells. GFP expression was not detectable in the spiral ganglion. The pro-apoptotic effect of AAV-CBA-delivered anti-clarin-1 ribozymes was evaluated by TUNEL-staining. We observed in the AAV-CBA-Rz, AAV-CBA-GFP and saline control groups apoptotic nuclei in the outer and inner hair cells and in the stria vascularis one week after the microinjection. The vestibular epithelium was also observed to contain apoptotic cells. No TUNEL-positive spiral ganglion neurons were detected. After one-month post-injection, the AAV-CBA-Rz-injected group had significantly more apoptotic outer and inner hair cells and cells of the stria vascularis than the AAV-CBA-GFP group. In this study, we demonstrate that AAV-CBA mediated clarin-1 ribozyme may induce apoptosis of the cochlear hair cells and cells of the stria vascularis. Surprisingly, we did not observe apoptosis in spiral ganglion cells, which should also be susceptible to clarin-1 mRNA cleavage. This result may be due to the injection technique, the promoter used, or tropism of the AAV serotype 2 viral vector. These results suggest the role of apoptosis in the progression of USH3A hearing loss warrants further evaluation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 7900445; 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Ush3a protein, mouse); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); 2006/06/30 [received]; 2007/03/19 [revised]; 2007/03/20 [accepted]; 2007/04/05 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0378-5955; 0378-5955</sn>
<ad>Department Otorhinolaryngology, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland. antti.aarnisalo@hus.fi</ad>
<an>PMID: 17493778; S0378-5955(07)00106-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.heares.2007.03.004</do>
<wp>20070405</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17493778</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>197</id>
<a1>Afzal,A.</a1>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Caballero,S.</a1>
<a1>Spoerri,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Zeng,D.</a1>
<a1>Belardinelli,L.</a1>
<a1>Grant,M. B.</a1>
<t1>Reduction in preretinal neovascularization by ribozymes that cleave the A2B adenosine receptor mRNA</t1>
<jf>Circulation research</jf>
<jo>Circ.Res.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Sep 19</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>500</sp>
<op>506</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Endothelium/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Adenosine A2B</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Purinergic P1/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retina/cytology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Retinal Neovascularization/pathology/therapy</k1>
<ab>Adenosine modulates a variety of cellular functions by interacting with specific cell surface G protein-coupled receptors (A1, A2A, A2B, and A3) and is a potential mediator of angiogenesis through the A2B receptor. The lack of a potent, selective A2B receptor inhibitor has hampered its characterization. Our goal was to design a hammerhead ribozyme that would specifically cleave the A2B receptor mRNA and examine its effect on retinal angiogenesis. Ribozymes specific for the mouse and human A2B receptor mRNAs were designed and cloned in expression plasmids. Human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293 cells were transfected with these plasmids and A2B receptor mRNA levels were determined by quantitative real-time RT-PCR. Human retinal endothelial cells (HRECs) were also transfected and cell migration was examined. The effects of these ribozymes on the levels of preretinal neovascularization were determined using a neonatal mouse model of oxygen-induced retinopathy (OIR). We produced a ribozyme with a Vmax of 515+/-125 pmol/min and a Kcat of 36.1+/-8.3 min(-1) (P&amp;lt; or =1x10(-5)). Transfection of HEK293 cells with the plasmid expressing the ribozyme reduced A2B receptor mRNA levels by 45+/-4.8% (P=5.1x10(-5)). Transfection of HRECs reduced NECA-stimulated migration of cells by 47.3+/-1.2% (P=7x10(-4)). Intraocular injection of the constructs into the mouse model reduced preretinal neovascularization by 53.5+/-8.2% (P=4.5x10(-5)). Our results suggest that the A2B receptor ribozyme will provide a tool for the selective inhibition of this receptor and provide further support for the role of A2B receptor in retinal angiogenesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY007739/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY012601/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0047103; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Receptor, Adenosine A2B); 0 (Receptors, Purinergic P1); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); 2003/08/14 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1524-4571; 0009-7330</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, University of Florida, PO Box 100267, Gainesville, FL 32610-0267, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12919950; 01.RES.0000091260.78959.BC [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1161/01.RES.0000091260.78959.BC</do>
<wp>20030814</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12919950</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>173</id>
<a1>Andino,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Conlon,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Porvasnik,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Boye,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Rapid, widespread transduction of the murine myocardium using self-complementary Adeno-associated virus</t1>
<jf>Genetic vaccines and therapy</jf>
<jo>Genet.Vaccines Ther.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec 10</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<sp>13</sp>
<ab>Adeno-associated virus (AAV) has shown great promise as a gene transfer vector. However, the incubation time needed to attain significant levels of gene expression is often too long for some clinical applications. Self-complementary AAV (scAAV) enters the cell as double stranded DNA, eliminating the step of second-strand synthesis, proven to be the rate-limiting step for gene expression of single-stranded AAV (ssAAV). The aim of this study was to compare the efficiency of these two types of AAV vectors in the murine myocardium. Four day old CD-1 mice were injected with either of the two AAV constructs, both expressing GFP and packaged into the AAV1 capsid. The animals were held for 4, 6, 11 or 21 days, after which they were euthanized and their hearts were excised. Serial sections of the myocardial tissue were used for real-time PCR quantification of AAV genome copies and for confocal microscopy. Although we observed similar numbers of AAV genomes at each of the different time points present in both the scAAV and the ssAAV infected hearts, microscopic analysis showed expression of GFP as early as 4 days in animals injected with the scAAV, while little or no expression was observed with the ssAAV constructs until day 11. AAV transduction of murine myocardium is therefore significantly enhanced using scAAV constructs.</ab>
<no>JID: 101178414; OID: NLM: PMC2222599; 2007/10/01 [received]; 2007/12/10 [accepted]; 2007/12/10 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1479-0556; 1479-0556</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA. LAndino@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18070352; 1479-0556-5-13 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<do>10.1186/1479-0556-5-13</do>
<wp>20071210</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18070352</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2222599</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>174</id>
<a1>Andino,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Takeda,M.</a1>
<a1>Kasahara,H.</a1>
<a1>Jakymiw,A.</a1>
<a1>Byrne,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>AAV-mediated knockdown of phospholamban leads to improved contractility and calcium handling in cardiomyocytes</t1>
<jf>The journal of gene medicine</jf>
<jo>J.Gene Med.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>132</sp>
<op>142</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Calcium/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Calcium-Binding Proteins/deficiency/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Separation</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Myocardial Contraction</k1>
<k1>Myocytes, Cardiac/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Reduced contractility due to dysregulation of intracellular calcium (Ca(2+)) is a common pathologic feature of chronic heart failure. Calcium stores in the sarcoplasmic reticulum play a major role in regulating cardiac contractility. Several animal models of heart failure have been treated by altering the regulation of the sarcoplamic reticulum ATPase through ablation or down-regulation of its inhibitor peptide, phospholamban (PLN). METHODS: We have designed two small hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) to block the synthesis of PLN via RNA interference. These were tested in cell culture using a co-transfection assay and using adeno-associated virus (AAV)-mediated delivery to cardiomyocytes. Reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and Western blots were used to measure reduction in PLN mRNA and protein levels. Reduction of PLN was also documented by indirect immunofluorescence. Free cytosolic calcium and contractile properties of transduced cardiomyocytes was examined on fura-2-loaded cells. Direct cardiac injection was used to deliver AAV1-shRNAs to mice, and reduction of PLN was measured by indirect immunofluorescence. RESULTS: Both siRNAs led to significant reduction of PLN RNA and protein levels in cultured cells. Down-regulation of PLN led to enhanced cell shortening and relaxation and to a decrease in the time constant of calcium decay, signs of improved contractility and calcium handling. In the hearts of AAV-infected mice, shRNA-transduced cells showed significant reduction in the level of PLN. CONCLUSIONS: Our results suggest that AAV-delivered shRNAs mediated physiologically significant suppression of phospholamban that may be useful in combating the effects of chronic heart failure.</ab>
<no>JID: 9815764; 0 (Calcium-Binding Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 0 (phospholamban); 7440-70-2 (Calcium); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1099-498X; 1099-498X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18064719</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/jgm.1131</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18064719</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>161</id>
<a1>Beltran,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Boye,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Boye,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V. A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Aguirre,G. D.</a1>
<t1>rAAV2/5 gene-targeting to rods:dose-dependent efficiency and complications associated with different promoters</t1>
<jf>Gene therapy</jf>
<jo>Gene Ther.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Apr 29</fd>
<ab>A prerequisite for using corrective gene therapy to treat humans with inherited retinal degenerative diseases that primarily affect rods is to develop viral vectors that target specifically this population of photoreceptors. The delivery of a viral vector with photoreceptor tropism coupled with a rod-specific promoter is likely to be the safest and most efficient approach to target expression of the therapeutic gene to rods. Three promoters that included a fragment of the proximal mouse opsin promoter (mOP), the human G-protein-coupled receptor protein kinase 1 promoter (hGRK1), or the cytomegalovirus immediate early enhancer combined with the chicken beta actin proximal promoter CBA were evaluated for their specificity and robustness in driving GFP reporter gene expression in rods, when packaged in a recombinant adeno-associated viral vector of serotype 2/5 (AAV2/5), and delivered via subretinal injection to the normal canine retina. Photoreceptor-specific promoters (mOP, hGRK1) targeted robust GFP expression to rods, whereas the ubiquitously expressed CBA promoter led to transgene expression in the retinal pigment epithelium, rods, cones and rare Muller, horizontal and ganglion cells. Late onset inflammation was frequently observed both clinically and histologically with all three constructs when the highest viral titers were injected. Cone loss in the injected regions of the retinas that received the highest titers occurred with both the hGRK1 and CBA promoters. Efficient and specific rod transduction, together with preservation of retinal structure was achieved with both mOP and hGRK1 promoters when viral titers in the order of 10(11) vg ml(-1) were used.Gene Therapy advance online publication, 29 April 2010; doi:10.1038/gt.2010.56.</ab>
<no>JID: 9421525; 2010/04/29 [aheadofprint]; aheadofprint</no>
<sn>1476-5462; 0969-7128</sn>
<ad>Section of Ophthalmology, Department of Clinical Studies School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20428215; gt201056 [pii]</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1038/gt.2010.56</do>
<wp>20100429</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20428215</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>250</id>
<a1>Berg,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Christianson,T.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Propagation of restriction fragments from the mitochondrial DNA of Saccharomyces cerevisiae in E. coli by means of plasmid vectors</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2133</sp>
<op>2150</op>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Recombinant/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drug Stability</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Some of the EcoRI fragments of yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) mitochondrial DNA were cloned into E. coli using plasmid pMB9. The five smallest fragments in molecular weight appeared to be preferentially retained by E coli; partial fragments derived from larger mitochondrial DNA fragments were also found. One of the fragments, R7 (2.4 kb), may contain the OII gene. Cloned R7 DNA was stable under a variety of growth conditions, but showed some changes in molecular weight after transfer to different E. coli strains. Fragment R7 is transcribed in minicells, producing RNA that hybridizes specifically to mitochondrial DNA. Both DNA strands are transcribed, in contrast to the asymmetric transcription found in mitochondria. No new polypeptides were observed in minicells containing cloned fragment 7.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0411011; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (DNA, Recombinant); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); OID: NLM: PMC327841; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<an>PMID: 379817</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>379817</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC327841</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>193</id>
<a1>Blalock,T. D.</a1>
<a1>Yuan,R.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Hammerhead ribozyme targeting connective tissue growth factor mRNA blocks transforming growth factor-beta mediated cell proliferation</t1>
<jf>Experimental eye research</jf>
<jo>Exp.Eye Res.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1127</sp>
<op>1136</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Catalysis</k1>
<k1>Cell Division/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Connective Tissue Growth Factor</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immediate-Early Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Intercellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/biosynthesis/genetics/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Transforming Growth Factor beta/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Excessive scarring following trauma or surgery of cornea, conjunctiva or retina can greatly impair visual outcome. At present, no agents are clinically available that selectively reduce activity of genes that regulate fibrosis. Connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) has been linked to fibrosis in several tissues, including cornea and conjunctiva. In this study, hammerhead ribozymes targeting CTGF mRNA were synthesized, kinetic parameters were measured, and the effect on TGF-beta-mediated cell proliferation was measured in cultured human fibroblasts. METHODS: The mRNA sequence of human CTGF was scanned for potential hammerhead ribozyme cleavage sites, and predicted secondary folding structures around the sites were calculated. Synthetic 12mer ribozymes and 33mer oligonucleotide mRNA targets corresponding to two sites were synthesized, and kinetic constants calculated from Hanes-Wolff plots of in vitro cleavage reactions. The ribozyme with higher percentage cleavage and kinetic rate was cloned into an expression plasmid (pTR-UF21) and stably transfected into cultured human fibroblasts. An inactive ribozyme plasmid served as a negative control. The effects of the ribozyme on expression of TGF-beta-induced CTGF mRNA and protein levels were measured using ELISA and real-time TaqMan quantitative RT-PCR. Finally, the effect of the CTGF ribozyme on TGF-beta-mediated proliferation of fibroblasts was measured using a non-radioactive cell proliferation microtiter assay. RESULTS: Of the eight potential hammerhead ribozyme cleavage sites in human CTGF mRNA, two sites (CHR 745, and CHR 859) were identified with optimal secondary folding. CHR 859 cleaved 94% of the target mRNA, compared to 46% cleavage for CHR 745 after 16 hr of reaction. CHR 859 had a K(m) of 1.56 microM and a K(cat) of 2.97 min(-1), while CHR 745 had a K(m) of 7.80 microM and a K(cat) of 5.7 min(-1). The turnover numbers (K(cat)/K(m)) of CHR 859 and CHR 745 were 1.9 x 10(6) M min(-1) and 7.4 x 10(5) M min(-1), respectively, indicating CHR 859 is 2.6 times more efficient than CHR 745 in destroying CTGF mRNA. Stable transfection of CHR 859 into human fibroblasts reduced CTGF mRNA levels 55% and protein levels 72% compared to the inactive ribozyme control. Furthermore, TGF-beta-induced cell proliferation was reduced 90% in fibroblasts stably transfected with CHR 859 compared to control cell groups. CONCLUSIONS: The CHR 859 hammerhead ribozyme cleaved human CTGF mRNA with high kinetic efficiency in vitro, effectively reduced levels of CTGF mRNA and protein in cultured human fibroblasts, and blocked TGF-beta-induced cell proliferation without nonspecific toxicity. These data support the concept that CTGF mediates TGF-beta-induced cell proliferation, and imply that regulating CTGF expression with ribozymes may be effective in reducing ocular scarring.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: EY05587/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0370707; 0 (CTGF protein, human); 0 (Immediate-Early Proteins); 0 (Intercellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Transforming Growth Factor beta); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); 139568-91-5 (Connective Tissue Growth Factor); 2003/07/31 [received]; 2004/01/23 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0014-4835; 0014-4835</sn>
<ad>Department of Ob/Gyn, College of Medicine, Institute for Wound Research, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0294, USA. tablalock@obgyn.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15109919; S0014483504000533 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.exer.2004.01.012</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15109919</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>249</id>
<a1>Burns,D.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<t1>Inhibition of the import of mitochondrial proteins by RNase</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>May 15</fd>
<vo>261</vo>
<is>14</is>
<sp>6153</sp>
<op>6155</op>
<k1>Biological Transport, Active/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cell-Free System</k1>
<k1>Citrate (si)-Synthase/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Precursors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Proton-Translocating ATPases/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ribosomes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/ultrastructure</k1>
<ab>RNase treatment of a cell-free translation system prevents transport of mitochondrial precursor proteins from that system into isolated yeast mitochondria. This inhibition depends on the presence of ribosomes in the reticulocyte lysate; if they are cleared by centrifugation, RNase treatment does not specifically inhibit protein uptake by mitochondria. Since protein import can occur in the absence of polyribosomes, RNase treatment does not degrade a structure essential for this process. Rather, the inhibition may be an effect of degraded ribosomes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 2R01 GM29387-04A1/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Enzyme Precursors); 0 (RNA, Messenger); EC 2.3.3.1 (Citrate (si)-Synthase); EC 3.1.- (Ribonucleases); EC 3.6.3.14 (Proton-Translocating ATPases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 2871023</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2871023</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>227</id>
<a1>Burns,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>The rate of import and assembly of F1-ATPase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Sep 15</fd>
<vo>261</vo>
<is>26</is>
<sp>12066</sp>
<op>12073</op>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Proton-Translocating ATPases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology</k1>
<ab>Subunit specific antiserum can be employed to study the course of ATPase assembly in mitochondria isolated from bakers&amp;#39; yeast. Comparing rates of subunit import with rates of enzyme assembly indicated that no substantial pool of unassembled subunits exists for the three largest ATPase peptides (alpha, beta, and gamma). Blocking import of specific ATPase subunits, however, did reveal a possible accumulation of unassembled alpha and gamma subunits in isolated mitochondria. The kinetic experiments also revealed a lag in the import of beta subunit relative to the uptake of alpha and gamma precursors. Experiments conducted in yeast cells confirmed that beta subunit is assembled soon after it is imported, but did not indicate a delay in import relative to the other subunits of F1.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01-GM29387-04/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Macromolecular Substances); EC 3.6.3.14 (Proton-Translocating ATPases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 2875070</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2875070</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>171</id>
<a1>Chakraborty,D.</a1>
<a1>Whalen,P.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Naash,M. I.</a1>
<t1>In vitro analysis of ribozyme-mediated knockdown of an ADRP associated rhodopsin mutation</t1>
<jf>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</jf>
<jo>Adv.Exp.Med.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>613</vo>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>106</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Substitution</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Histidine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/analysis/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/genetics</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<no>LR: 20091216; JID: 0121103; 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 148349-60-4 (Adfp protein, mouse); 71-00-1 (Histidine); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); NIHMS163554; OID: NLM: NIHMS163554; OID: NLM: PMC2793173; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0065-2598; 0065-2598</sn>
<ad>Department of Cell Biology, University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center, 940 Stanton L. Young Blvd. (BMSB781), Oklahoma City, OK 73104, USA. dchakrab@ouhsc.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18188933</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/978-0-387-74904-4_10</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18188933</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2793173</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>165</id>
<a1>Chen,B.</a1>
<a1>Caballero,S.</a1>
<a1>Seo,S.</a1>
<a1>Grant,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Delivery of antioxidant enzyme genes to protect against ischemia/reperfusion-induced injury to retinal microvasculature</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5587</sp>
<op>5595</op>
<k1>Aldehydes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Capillaries/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Catalase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen Peroxide/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling</k1>
<k1>Liposomes</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reperfusion Injury/metabolism/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Retinal Degeneration/metabolism/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Retinal Vessels/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Spectrometry, Fluorescence</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Superoxides/metabolism</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Retinal ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) injury results in the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS). The aim of this study was to investigate whether delivery of the manganese superoxide dismutase gene (SOD2) or the catalase gene (CAT) could rescue the retinal vascular damage induced by I/R in mice. METHODS: I/R injury to the retina was induced in mice by elevating intraocular pressure for 2 hours, and reperfusion was established immediately afterward. One eye of each mouse was pretreated with plasmids encoding manganese superoxide dismutase or catalase complexed with cationic liposomes and delivered by intravitreous injection 48 hours before initiation of the procedure. Superoxide ion, hydrogen peroxide, and 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE) protein modifications were measured by fluorescence staining, immunohistochemistry, and Western blot analysis 1 day after the I/R injury. At 7 days after injury, retinal vascular cell apoptosis and acellular capillaries were quantitated. RESULTS: Superoxide ion, hydrogen peroxide, and 4-HNE protein modifications increased at 24 hours after I/R injury. Administration of plasmids encoding SOD2 or CAT significantly reduced levels of superoxide ion, hydrogen peroxide, and 4-HNE. Retinal vascular cell apoptosis and acellular capillary numbers increased greatly by 7 days after the injury. Delivery of SOD2 or CAT inhibited the I/R-induced apoptosis of retinal vascular cell and retinal capillary degeneration. CONCLUSIONS: Delivery of antioxidant genes inhibited I/R-induced retinal capillary degeneration, apoptosis of vascular cells, and ROS production, suggesting that antioxidant gene therapy might be a treatment for I/R-related disease.</ab>
<no>JID: 7703701; 0 (Aldehydes); 0 (Liposomes); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 11062-77-4 (Superoxides); 29343-52-0 (4-hydroxy-2-nonenal); 7722-84-1 (Hydrogen Peroxide); EC 1.11.1.6 (Catalase); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); 2009/07/23 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1552-5783; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, Second Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha Hunan Province, People&#39;s Republic of China.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19628743; iovs.09-3633 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.09-3633</do>
<wp>20090723</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19628743</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>196</id>
<a1>Cheng,S.</a1>
<a1>Clancy,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Checkley,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Hillman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Progulske-Fox,A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Fidel,P. L.</a1>
<a1>Nguyen,M. H.</a1>
<t1>Identification of Candida albicans genes induced during thrush offers insight into pathogenesis</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1275</sp>
<op>1288</op>
<k1>AIDS-Related Opportunistic Infections/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Fungal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Fungal/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Candida albicans/genetics/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Candidiasis, Oral/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>HIV Infections/complications</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Candida albicans causes a wide spectrum of diseases, ranging from mucocutaneous infections like oral thrush to disseminated candidiasis. Screening for C. albicans genes expressed within infected hosts might advance understanding of candidal pathogenesis, but is impractical using existing techniques. In this study, we used an antibody-based strategy to identify C. albicans genes expressed during thrush. We adsorbed sera from HIV-infected patients with thrush against candidal cells grown in vitro and screened a C. albicans genomic expression library. We identified 10 genes encoding immunogenic antigens and used reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction to verify that they were induced within thrush pseudomembranes recovered from a patient. The in vivo induced genes are involved in diverse functions, including regulation of yeast-hyphal morphogenesis, adhesion to host cells, nutrient uptake, phospholipid biosynthesis and amino acid catabolism. Four genes encode known virulence determinants (HWP1, CST20, CPP1 and RBF1). Another gene, LPD1, for which a role in candidal pathogenesis is unknown, encodes a protein homologous to a bacterial virulence determinant. Most importantly, disruption of CaNOT5, a newly identified gene, conferred defects in morphogenesis, decreased adherence to human buccal epithelial cells and attenuated mortality during murine disseminated candidiasis, proving that our strategy can identify genes encoding novel virulence determinants.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 1K08AI101758-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-DE13523/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-DE13980/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Antibodies, Fungal); 0 (Antigens, Fungal); 0 (Fungal Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12787355; 3521 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12787355</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>242</id>
<a1>Clancy,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Yu,Y. C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Nguyen,M. H.</a1>
<t1>Inhibition of RNA synthesis as a therapeutic strategy against Aspergillus and Fusarium: demonstration of in vitro synergy between rifabutin and amphotericin B</t1>
<jf>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</jf>
<jo>Antimicrob.Agents Chemother.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>513</op>
<k1>Amphotericin B/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Aspergillus/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Drug Synergism</k1>
<k1>Drug Therapy, Combination/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Fusarium/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microbial Sensitivity Tests</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/biosynthesis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Rifabutin/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>We investigated the in vitro antifungal activity of amphotericin B, alone and in combination with rifabutin, an inhibitor of bacterial RNA polymerase, against 26 clinical isolates of Aspergillus and 25 clinical isolates of Fusarium. Synergy or additivism between these drugs was demonstrated against all isolates tested. Amphotericin B MICs were reduced upon combination with rifabutin from a mean of 0.65 microg/ml to a mean of 0.16 microg/ml against Aspergillus, and from a mean of 0.97 microg/ml to a mean of 0.39 microLg/ml against Fusarium (P 32 microg/ml to a mean of 1.1 microg/ml against both fungi (P &amp;lt; 0.000001 for both). These positive interactions were corroborated by a colony count study with two Fusarium isolates, for which treatment with the combination of subinhibitory concentrations of amphotericin B (at concentrations 2- and 4-fold less than the MIC) and rifabutin (at concentrations ranging from 4- to 64-fold less than the MIC) resulted in 3.2-log reductions in colony counts compared to those after treatment with either drug alone. Inhibition of RNA synthesis was shown to be the mechanism of antifungal activity. These results suggest that inhibition of fungal RNA synthesis might be a potential target for antifungal therapy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0315061; 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 1397-89-3 (Amphotericin B); 72559-06-9 (Rifabutin); OID: NLM: PMC105490; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0066-4804; 0066-4804</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, and the Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9517924</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9517924</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC105490</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>172</id>
<a1>Denovan-Wright,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Rodriguez-Lebron,E.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Unexpected off-targeting effects of anti-huntingtin ribozymes and siRNA in vivo</t1>
<jf>Neurobiology of disease</jf>
<jo>Neurobiol.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>446</sp>
<op>455</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Brain/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Gene Targeting/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Huntington Disease/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/biosynthesis/physiology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/physiology</k1>
<ab>Gene transfer strategies to reduce levels of mutant huntingtin (mHtt) mRNA and protein by targeting human Htt have shown therapeutic promise in vivo. Previously, we have reported that a specific, adeno-associated viral vector (rAAV)-delivered short-hairpin RNA (siHUNT-2) targeting human Htt mRNA unexpectedly decreased levels of striatal-specific transcripts in both wild-type and R6/1 transgenic HD mice. The goal of this study was to determine whether the siHUNT-2-mediated effect was due to adverse effects of RNA interference (RNAi) expression in the brain. To this end, we designed two catalytically active hammerhead ribozymes directed against the same region of human Htt mRNA targeted by siHUNT-2 and delivered them to wild-type and R6/1 transgenic HD mice. After 10 weeks of continuous expression, these ribozymes, like siHUNT-2, negatively impacted the expression of a subset of genes in the striatum. This effect was independent of rAAV transduction and specific to the targeting of a unique sequence in human Htt mRNA. After consideration of the known potential RNAi-specific toxic mechanisms, only cleavage of an unintended RNA target can account for the data reported herein. Thus, long-term rAAV-mediated RNAi in the brain does not, in and of itself, negatively affect striatal gene expression. These findings have important implications in the development of therapeutic RNAi for the treatment of neurological disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 5 F31 NS 011182-05/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS048588-01A1/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS048588-02/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS048588-03/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS048588-04/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS48588-01/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9500169; 0 (HD protein, human); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); NIHMS42361; OID: NLM: NIHMS42361; OID: NLM: PMC2695881; 2007/07/28 [received]; 2007/10/30 [revised]; 2007/11/05 [accepted]; 2007/11/12 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1095-953X; 0969-9961</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacology, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18166484; S0969-9961(07)00249-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.nbd.2007.11.003</do>
<wp>20071112</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18166484</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2695881</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>210</id>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Timmers,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme-targeted destruction of RNA associated with autosomal-dominant retinitis pigmentosa</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>681</sp>
<op>689</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Probes</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>RNA/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Retinal Rod Photoreceptor Cells/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/chemistry/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To design ribozymes--catalytic RNA molecules--to cleave the P23H and S334Ter mutant mRNA selectively and to test them in vitro to determine their potential as therapeutic agents in the prevention of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa. METHODS: Synthetic RNA targets were used in cleavage assays to determine the catalytic efficiencies of the ribozymes in vitro. Cleavage products were analyzed by denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. Total retinal RNA was also used as a substrate, and opsin mRNA cleavage was assayed by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction. RESULTS: All three ribozymes cleaved the mutant target specifically. Substrate cleavage was seen in less than 5 mM magnesium and was detectable after 15 minutes of incubation. The most active ribozyme against the P23H target was the hammerhead (kcat:K(m) [Michaelis-Menton constant] ratio = 5 x 10(7) M/min), then the P23H hairpin ribozyme (kcat:K(m) ratio = 9 x 10(5) M/min) and the S334Ter hammerhead (kcat:K(m) ratio = 8 x 10(5) M/min). No cleavage activity was observed, when wild-type target sequences or inactive control ribozymes were used. The ribozymes bound and specifically digested the intact mutant opsin mRNA in the presence of all normal retinal RNA. CONCLUSIONS: Ribozymes can discriminate between the mutant and wild-type sequences of mRNA associated with autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa. The kinetics and specificity of ribozyme cleavage indicate that they should reduce the amount of aberrant rhodopsin in the rod cells and may have potential as therapeutic agents against genetic disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: EY07132/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: etc.; JID: 7703701; 0 (Oligonucleotide Probes); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Rod Opsins); 63231-63-0 (RNA); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9538873</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9538873</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>217</id>
<a1>Fernandez,A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Rabitz,H.</a1>
<t1>Structure-induced strain determining the internal cyclization site in the yeast cobI5 autocatalytic intron: theory and experimental tests</t1>
<jf>Journal of theoretical biology</jf>
<jo>J.Theor.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Sep 7</fd>
<vo>164</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>121</sp>
<op>133</op>
<k1>Apoproteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cyclization</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cytochromes b</k1>
<k1>Introns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Monte Carlo Method</k1>
<k1>RNA, Guide/genetics</k1>
<k1>Yeasts/genetics</k1>
<ab>The terminal intron of the apocytochrome b gene of yeast is endowed with autocatalytic potential in vitro and has been also shown to be capable of internal circularization at the linkage 236-237 from the 5&amp;#39; extremity. The aim of this work is to identify the secondary interaction responsible for shaping and activating the internal cyclization site (ICS). This is done by simulating the sequential folding of an abnormally large fragment of 237 nucleotides which starts at the 5&amp;#39; cleavage site and contains the internal guide sequence (IGS) starting 220 nucleotides into the intron. The resulting portion of the overall structure features the conserved interaction P1 and is compatible with the complete consensus secondary structure for this intron. The structural motif which emerges from sequential folding and is responsible for shaping the ICS is confirmed by analyzing the localization of structure-induced strain in the RNA backbone. It is shown that after the conserved stem P1 has been dismantled, the highest strain in a phosphodiester linkage is localized internally precisely at the experimentally determined cyclization site. Moreover, it is shown that our dynamical model of folding is compatible with the actual reaction pathways. Thus, internal cyclization becomes feasible only after conserved interaction P1 has been dismantled. This last event, in turn, might take place as a consequence of either of the following events: (i) 5&amp;#39; cleavage caused by nucleophilic attack by the GTP-cosubstrate or (ii) excision of the 3&amp;#39; exon after prior formation of P10. This last event, in turn, requires dismantling helix P1. Moreover, event (ii) is necessary for internal circularization since it habilitates the 3&amp;#39; terminal guanosine as a nucleophilic agent.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0376342; 0 (Apoproteins); 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (RNA, Guide); 9035-37-4 (Cytochromes b); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-5193; 0022-5193</sn>
<ad>Departmento de Matematica, Universidad Nacional del Sur, Bahia Blanca, Argentina.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8264241; S0022-5193(83)71143-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/jtbi.1993.1143</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8264241</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>251</id>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Nishikawa,S.</a1>
<a1>Yasumura,D.</a1>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>International symposium</a1>
<a1>8th</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme-Mediated Gene Therapy for Autosomal Dominant Retinal Degeneration</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<no>ID: 304782896</no>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>194</id>
<a1>Fritz,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Design and validation of therapeutic hammerhead ribozymes for autosomal dominant diseases</t1>
<jf>Methods in molecular biology (Clifton, N.J.)</jf>
<jo>Methods Mol.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>252</vo>
<sp>221</sp>
<op>236</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Drug Design</k1>
<k1>Genetic Diseases, Inborn/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<ab>Hammerhead ribozymes are small, catalytic RNAs that can be designed to effectively inhibit gene expression in an allele-specific manner. It is the high level of sequence discrimination, coupled with the minimal cleavage-site requirements of hammerhead ribozymes, that makes these catalytic RNAs so amenable for use as therapeutic agents for autosomal dominant diseases. Here, we present a detailed set of protocols for the design and validation of hammerhead ribozymes for the treatment of autosomal dominant disease, with specific examples of hammerhead ribozymes targeted against human P23H rod opsin mRNA, a major cause of dominant retinitis pigmentosa.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060501; JID: 9214969; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1064-3745; 1064-3745</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15017052; 1-59259-746-7:221 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1385/1-59259-746-7:221</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15017052</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>237</id>
<a1>Fritz,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W.</a1>
<a1>Agarwal,A.</a1>
<a1>Grant,M.</a1>
<a1>Shaw,L.</a1>
<t1>Development of hammerhead ribozymes to modulate endogenous gene expression for functional studies</t1>
<jf>Methods (San Diego, Calif.)</jf>
<jo>Methods</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>276</sp>
<op>285</op>
<k1>Adenoviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Calibration</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Endothelium/cytology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transfection/methods</k1>
<ab>Hammerhead ribozymes are catalytic RNAs that are being used to inhibit endogenous gene expression to study key components of basic biochemical pathways such as angiogenesis. In addition, these ribozymes have the potential to be used as components of gene therapy protocols for the treatment of disease states. We detail here a set of protocols for the design and testing of hammerhead ribozymes that will efficiently inhibit gene expression both in cell culture and in vivo.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 2002; JID: 9426302; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); ppublish</no>
<pb>Elsevier Science (USA)</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1046-2023; 1046-2023</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Box 100267, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12413427; S1046202302002335 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12413427</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>201</id>
<a1>Fritz,J. J.</a1>
<a1>White,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Designing and characterizing hammerhead ribozymes for use in AAV vector-mediated retinal gene therapies</t1>
<jf>Methods in enzymology</jf>
<jo>Methods Enzymol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>346</vo>
<sp>358</sp>
<op>377</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>RNA/chemistry</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Retinaldehyde/metabolism</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0212271; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 116-31-4 (Retinaldehyde); 63231-63-0 (RNA); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0076-6879; 0076-6879</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11883079</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11883079</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>186</id>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M.</a1>
<a1>Justilien,V.</a1>
<a1>Liu,J.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Preservation of photoreceptor morphology and function in P23H rats using an allele independent ribozyme</t1>
<jf>Experimental eye research</jf>
<jo>Exp.Eye Res.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>44</sp>
<op>52</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Retina/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/metabolism/pathology/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>To develop an allele independent ribozyme for the treatment of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa (ADRP) associated with mutations in the rhodopsin (RHO) gene, a ribozyme targeting dog, mouse, human but not rat rhodopsin (RHO) mRNA was designed and tested in vitro. Activity of this ribozyme was tested in tissue culture by co-transfection of HEK 293 cells with plasmids expressing opsin mRNA and ribozyme, followed by quantitative RT-PCR to evaluate the level of RHO mRNA. For experiments in vivo, Rz525 driven by the mouse opsin proximal promoter was inserted in plasmids with AAV 2 terminal repeats (TR) and packaged in AAV serotype 5 capsids. AAV-Rz525 was injected subretinally into the right eyes of P23H rat pups. Left eyes were injected with virus expressing GFP from the identical promoter. Animals were analyzed at 4, 8 and 12 weeks post-injection by full field scotopic electroretinography (ERG). After 12 weeks, animals were sacrificed and retinas were dissected, fixed and sectioned. Rz525 had high catalytic activity in vitro and led to a 50% reduction of RHO mRNA in cells. AAV-Rz525 injection into P23H transgenic rats led to significant preservation (about 50%) of scotopic ERG a- and b-wave amplitudes. Histological analysis showed an increased number of ONL nuclei in the central and superior retina of treated eyes relative to control eyes. RT-PCR analysis revealed 46% reduction of transgenic (mouse) RHO mRNA in right eyes relative to left eyes and no change in rat RHO mRNA. AAV5 delivery of Rz525 resulted in a partial rescue of the light response and structural preservation of photoreceptors in transgenic rats. This ribozyme may be a useful component of an RNA replacement gene therapy for ADRP.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 EY011596-05/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 EY011596-09/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01EY011596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0370707; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Rod Opsins); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); NIHMS15436; OID: NLM: NIHMS15436; OID: NLM: PMC1778459; 2006/03/24 [received]; 2006/08/21 [revised]; 2006/08/25 [accepted]; 2006/11/01 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0014-4835; 0014-4835</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mari543@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17083931; S0014-4835(06)00366-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.exer.2006.08.014</do>
<wp>20061101</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17083931</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1778459</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>182</id>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M.</a1>
<a1>Justilien,V.</a1>
<a1>Liu,J.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of mouse rhodopsin expression in vivo by AAV mediated siRNA delivery</t1>
<jf>Vision research</jf>
<jo>Vision Res.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1202</sp>
<op>1208</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>RNA Interference</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/genetics</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: The purpose of this study is to demonstrate that the expression of rhodopsin can be down regulated in vivo by AAV-delivered siRNA. This is the first step in an RNA replacement strategy for the allele-independent treatment of Autosomal Dominant Retinitis Pigmentosa (ADRP). METHODS: HEK 293 cells were co-transfected with a plasmid carrying mouse RHO cDNA driven by the CMV promoter and a chemically synthesized siRNA duplex of 21 nucleotides. Reduction of RHO mRNA was confirmed by RT-PCR. One active siRNA and a control siRNA were embedded in a small hairpin RNA (shRNA) and cloned in Adeno-associated virus (AAV) vector under regulation of the H1 promoter and containing a GFP reporter. AAV5 expressing either active siRNA or an irrelevant siRNA were subretinaly injected into the right eyes of wild-type or RHO+/- heterozygote mice at post-natal day 16. At 1 and 2 months post-injection, animals were analyzed by electroretinography (ERG). Animals were then sacrificed, and retinas were examined by Western blot, RT-PCR, histology and immunohistochemistry. RESULTS: All of the siRNAs tested in HEK 293 cells caused degradation of RHO mRNA, although the efficiency varied from 25% to 80%. In vivo siRNA delivery to the retina led to more than 40% reduction of scotopic a- and b-wave amplitudes in RHO+/- heterozygotes. Although the reduction of RHO mRNA was estimated at 30% compared to control animals, Western blots revealed 60% decrease in rhodopsin content. Histological analysis showed significant reduction in the thickness of the ONL, ranging between 53% and 86%. CONCLUSIONS: AAV-siRNA delivery into the subretinal space resulted in the reduction of retinal function caused by diminished RHO mRNA and protein content. This level of reduction may permit the replacement of endogenous mRNA with siRNA-resistant mRNA encoding wild-type RHO.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 EY011596-09/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0417402; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); NIHMS21588; OID: NLM: NIHMS21588; OID: NLM: PMC1892214; 2006/09/29 [received]; 2006/11/20 [revised]; 2006/11/29 [accepted]; 2007/02/12 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0042-6989; 0042-6989</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mari653@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17292939; S0042-6989(06)00558-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.visres.2006.11.026</do>
<wp>20070212</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17292939</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1892214</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>170</id>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Gene therapy for mouse models of ADRP</t1>
<jf>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</jf>
<jo>Adv.Exp.Med.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>613</vo>
<sp>107</sp>
<op>112</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kidney/cytology</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/etiology/genetics</k1>
<no>JID: 0121103; 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 148349-60-4 (Adfp protein, mouse); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0065-2598; 0065-2598</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA. mari653@mgm.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18188934</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/978-0-387-74904-4_11</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18188934</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>162</id>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Knox,T.</a1>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,O. S.</a1>
<a1>Noorwez,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lin,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Restoration of visual function in P23H rhodopsin transgenic rats by gene delivery of BiP/Grp78</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar 30</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<is>13</is>
<sp>5961</sp>
<op>5966</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Substitution</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Endoplasmic Reticulum/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Heat-Shock Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Multiprotein Complexes</k1>
<k1>Mutation, Missense</k1>
<k1>Photoreceptor Cells, Vertebrate/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Rats, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retina/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/pathology/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Stress, Physiological</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factor CHOP/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Unfolded Protein Response/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vision, Ocular/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>The P23H mutation within the rhodopsin gene (RHO) causes rhodopsin misfolding, endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress, and activates the unfolded protein response (UPR), leading to rod photoreceptor degeneration and autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa (ADRP). Grp78/BiP is an ER-localized chaperone that is induced by UPR signaling in response to ER stress. We have previously demonstrated that BiP mRNA levels are selectively reduced in animal models of ADRP arising from P23H rhodopsin expression at ages that precede photoreceptor degeneration. We have now overexpressed BiP to test the hypothesis that this chaperone promotes the trafficking of P23H rhodopsin to the cell membrane, reprograms the UPR favoring the survival of photoreceptors, blocks apoptosis, and, ultimately, preserves vision in ADRP rats. In cell culture, increasing levels of BiP had no impact on the localization of P23H rhodopsin. However, BiP overexpression alleviated ER stress by reducing levels of cleaved pATF6 protein, phosphorylated eIF2alpha and the proapoptotic protein CHOP. In P23H rats, photoreceptor levels of cleaved ATF6, pEIF2alpha, CHOP, and caspase-7 were much higher than those of wild-type rats. Subretinal delivery of AAV5 expressing BiP to transgenic rats led to reduction in CHOP and photoreceptor apoptosis and to a sustained increase in electroretinogram amplitudes. We detected complexes between BiP, caspase-12, and the BH3-only protein BiK that may contribute to the antiapoptotic activity of BiP. Thus, the preservation of photoreceptor function resulting from elevated levels of BiP is due to suppression of apoptosis rather than to a promotion of rhodopsin folding.</ab>
<no>GR: EY013280/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY018313/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY01919/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY02162/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY06842/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13729/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Ddit3 protein, mouse); 0 (Heat-Shock Proteins); 0 (Multiprotein Complexes); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (molecular chaperone GRP78); 147336-12-7 (Transcription Factor CHOP); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); OID: NLM: PMC2851865; 2010/03/15 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1091-6490; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mari653@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 20231467; 0911991107 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0911991107</do>
<wp>20100315</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20231467</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2851865</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>191</id>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Pang,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Thomas,J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Knockdown of wild-type mouse rhodopsin using an AAV vectored ribozyme as part of an RNA replacement approach</t1>
<jf>Molecular vision</jf>
<jo>Mol.Vis.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Aug 29</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<sp>648</sp>
<op>656</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Kidney/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To develop a hammerhead ribozymes (Rz) that might be exploited in a &amp;quot;digest and replace&amp;quot; gene therapy strategy for autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa (ADRP) caused by mutations in the gene for rhodopsin (RHO). METHODS: A ribozyme (Rz397) was designed to hybridize with an accessible region in rhodopsin mRNA. It was tested in vitro to determine the kinetics of cleavage of a target oligonucleotide. Following transfection of cultured cells, reduction of rhodopsin mRNA in response to Rz397 was measured RT-PCR. The gene for the ribozyme (Rz397) was inserted in an adeno-associated virus (AAV2) vector and packaged in AAV2 capsids. The virus was injected subretinally in the eyes of C57BL/6J (RHO+/+) and rhodopsin knockout hemizygous (RHO+/-) mice at postnatal days 6 (P6) and 30 (P30). Mice were analyzed by full-field electroretinography (ERG). The reduction of opsin protein was measured by western blot analysis and visualized by immunocytochemistry. Reduction of rhodopsin mRNA was assessed using in situ hybridization. Morphometric microscopy of fluorescent antibody-antigen complexes and autoradiography of retinas were used to quantify levels of rhodopsin protein and mRNA, respectively. RESULTS: Transient co-transfection of HEK 293 cells with a wild-type rhodopsin cDNA and Rz397 resulted in an approximately 60% reduction of RHO mRNA one day after transfection. RHO+/- -mice injected with AAV2-Rz397 at P6 showed a 50% reduction in b-wave amplitudes in injected eyes relative to saline injected contralateral eyes. However, injection of RHO+/- -animals at one month and of RHO+/+-animals at either age had no impact on ERG. Nevertheless, we detected an 80% reduction of opsin protein in ribozyme-injected eyes of hemizygous mice (by western blot) and a 50% reduction in opsin content in RHO+/+ mice (by morphometry). These reductions were confirmed by in situ hybridization. CONCLUSIONS: AAV2-Rz397 led to significant (greater than or equal to 50%) reduction of rhodopsin mRNA and protein in mice. It affected ERG amplitudes only when injected in hemizygous RHO knockout pups. This RNA inhibitor may prove useful in treating animal models of ADRP as part of an RNA replacement approach.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: R01 EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9605351; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Rod Opsins); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); epublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1090-0535; 1090-0535</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mari653@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16145542; v11/a77 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<wp>20050829</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16145542</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>164</id>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Koilkonda,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Arguello,T.</a1>
<a1>Chou,T. H.</a1>
<a1>Ruggeri,M.</a1>
<a1>Porciatti,V.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Efficiency and safety of AAV-mediated gene delivery of the human ND4 complex I subunit in the mouse visual system</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>4205</sp>
<op>4214</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Axons/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex I/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Epitopes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique, Indirect</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Immunoprecipitation</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Confocal</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>NADH Dehydrogenase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Peptides/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phosphorylation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Tomography, Optical Coherence</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To evaluate the efficiency and safety of AAV-mediated gene delivery of a normal human ND4 complex I subunit in the mouse visual system. METHODS: A nuclear encoded human ND4 subunit fused to the ATPc mitochondrial targeting sequence and FLAG epitope were packaged in AAV2 capsids that were injected into the right eyes of mice. AAV-GFP was injected into the left eyes. One month later, pattern electroretinography (PERG), rate of ATP synthesis, gene expression, and incorporation of the human ND4 subunit into the murine complex I were evaluated. Quantitative analysis of ND4FLAG-injected eyes was assessed compared with green fluorescent protein (GFP)-injected eyes. RESULTS: Rates of ATP synthesis and PERG amplitudes were similar in ND4FLAG- and GFP-inoculated eyes. PERG latency was shorter in eyes that received ND4FLAG. Immunoprecipitated murine complex I gave the expected 52-kDa band of processed human ND4FLAG. Confocal microscopy revealed perinuclear expression of FLAG colocalized with mitochondria-specific fluorescent dye. Transmission electron microscopy revealed FLAG immunogold within mitochondria. Compared with Thy1.2-positive retinal ganglion cells (RGCs), quantification was 38% for FLAG-positive RGCs and 65% for GFP-positive RGCs. Thy1.2 positive-RGC counts in AAV-ND4FLAG were similar to counts in control eyes injected with AAV-GFP. CONCLUSIONS: Human ND4 was properly processed and imported into the mitochondria of RGCs and axons of mouse optic nerve after intravitreal injection. Although it had approximately two-thirds the efficiency of GFP, the expression of normal human ND4 in murine mitochondria did not induce the loss of RGCs, ATP synthesis, or PERG amplitude, suggesting that allotopic ND4 may be safe for the treatment of patients with Leber hereditary optic neuropathy.</ab>
<no>GR: EY014801/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01EY017141/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R24EY018600/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (Epitopes); 0 (Peptides); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); 98849-88-8 (FLAG peptide); EC 1.6.5.3 (Electron Transport Complex I); EC 1.6.5.3 (NADH dehydrogenase subunit 4); EC 1.6.99.3 (NADH Dehydrogenase); 2009/04/22 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1552-5783; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Bascom Palmer Eye Institute, University of Miami, Miller School of Medicine, Miami, Florida 33136, USA. jguy@med.miami.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19387075; iovs.08-3214 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.08-3214</do>
<wp>20090422</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19387075</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>200</id>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Pallotti,F.</a1>
<a1>Schon,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Manfredi,G.</a1>
<a1>Carelli,V.</a1>
<a1>Martinuzzi,A.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Rescue of a mitochondrial deficiency causing Leber Hereditary Optic Neuropathy</t1>
<jf>Annals of Neurology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Neurol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>534</sp>
<op>542</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex I</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hybrid Cells/physiology</k1>
<k1>NADH, NADPH Oxidoreductases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Optic Atrophy, Hereditary, Leber/genetics/metabolism/therapy</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Phosphorylation</k1>
<k1>Point Mutation</k1>
<k1>Sequence Tagged Sites</k1>
<ab>A G to A transition at nucleotide 11778 in the ND4 subunit gene of complex I was the first point mutation in the mitochondrial genome linked to a human disease. It causes Leber Hereditary Optic Neuropathy, a disorder with oxidative phosphorylation deficiency. To overcome this defect, we made a synthetic ND4 subunit compatible with the &amp;quot;universal&amp;quot; genetic code and imported it into mitochondria by adding a mitochondrial targeting sequence. For detection we added a FLAG tag. This gene was inserted in an adeno-associated viral vector. The ND4FLAG protein was imported into the mitochondria of cybrids harboring the G11778A mutation, where it increased their survival rate threefold, under restrictive conditions that forced the cells to rely predominantly on oxidative phosphorylation to produce ATP. Since assays of complex I activity were normal in G11778A cybrids we focused on changes in ATP synthesis using complex I substrates. The G11778A cybrids showed a 60% reduction in the rate of ATP synthesis. Relative to mock-transfected G11778A cybrids, complemented G11778A cybrids showed a threefold increase in ATP synthesis, to a level indistinguishable from that in cybrids containing normal mitochondrial DNA. Restoration of respiration by allotopic expression opens the door for gene therapy of Leber Hereditary Optic Neuropathy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY 11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY 12335/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS 28828/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7707449; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); EC 1.6.- (NADH, NADPH Oxidoreductases); EC 1.6.5.3 (Electron Transport Complex I); CIN: Ann Neurol. 2002 Nov;52(5):529-30. PMID: 12402246; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0364-5134; 0364-5134</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, Neuro-Opthalmology Service, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. neurop@att.net</ad>
<an>PMID: 12402249</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ana.10354</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12402249</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>232</id>
<a1>Hampsey,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Kohlhaw,G. B.</a1>
<t1>Submitochondrial localization, cell-free synthesis, and mitochondrial import of 2-isopropylmalate synthase of yeast</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>80</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1270</sp>
<op>1274</op>
<k1>2-Isopropylmalate Synthase/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Cell-Free System</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oxo-Acid-Lyases/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Submitochondrial Particles/enzymology</k1>
<ab>2-Isopropylmalate synthase (EC 4.1.3.12) of yeast is a mitochondrial enzyme. We now provide evidence showing that a large part of the 2-isopropylmalate synthase activity that is associated with the mitochondria is located in the mitochondrial matrix. In vitro translation of total yeast RNA followed by immunoprecipitation with anti-2-isopropylmalate synthase antibody yields two polypeptides. The larger of these has an apparent molecular weight identical to that of purified 2-isopropylmalate synthase subunit (ca. 65,000). It is incorporated into isolated yeast mitochondria with no detectable change in molecular weight. The import requires energy. The smaller polypeptide migrates to a position corresponding to a molecular weight of 63,000-64,000. It is not taken up by mitochondria. Both polypeptides, which also can be obtained by immunoprecipitation of crude extracts, become labeled when in vitro translation is performed in the presence of N-formyl[35S]methionyl-tRNAf. Mutants with no detectable 2-isopropylmalate synthase activity are deficient in either one or both synthase-related polypeptides. These results are discussed in the light of recent evidence for two 2-isopropylmalate synthase-encoding genes in yeast.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM15102/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM29387/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; EC 2.3.3.13 (2-Isopropylmalate Synthase); EC 4.1.3.- (Oxo-Acid-Lyases); OID: NLM: PMC393577; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 6338500</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6338500</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC393577</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>180</id>
<a1>Han,Z.</a1>
<a1>Gorbatyuk,M.</a1>
<a1>Thomas,J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Srivastava,A.</a1>
<a1>Stacpoole,P. W.</a1>
<t1>Down-regulation of expression of rat pyruvate dehydrogenase E1alpha gene by self-complementary adeno-associated virus-mediated small interfering RNA delivery</t1>
<jf>Mitochondrion</jf>
<jo>Mitochondrion</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>259</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Lung/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Pyruvate Dehydrogenase (Lipoamide)/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Transition Temperature</k1>
<ab>Mutations in the E1alpha subunit gene (PDHA1) of the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDC) are common causes of congenital lactic acidosis. An animal model of E1alpha deficiency could provide insight into the pathological consequences of mutations and serve to test potential therapies. Small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) were designed to cleave the messenger RNA (mRNA) of the E1alpha subunit and were tested in vitro to assess the feasibility of producing a gene knockdown in rats. HEK 293 cells were co-transfected with a rat PDHA1 expression vector and eight naked siRNAs that specifically targeted rat E1alpha mRNA. Quantitative PCR (qPCR) analyses showed that four siRNAs reduced rat PDHA1 RNA levels up to 85% by 24h and up to 65% by 56h, compared to negative and positive controls. Since oligonucleotide-mediated siRNA delivery provided only transient suppression, we next selected two siRNA candidates and generated self-complementary, double-stranded adeno-associated virus (scAAV) vectors (serotypes 2 and 5) expressing a rat short hairpin siRNA expression cassette (scAAVsi-PDHA1). Rat lung fibroblast (RLF) cultures were infected with scAAVsi-PDHA1 vectors. The RLF PDHA1 mRNA level was reduced 53-80% 72h after infection and 54-70% 10 days after infection in RLF cultures. The expression of E1alpha and the specific activity of pyruvate dehydrogenase were also decreased at 10 days after infection in RLF cultures. Thus, scAAV siRNA-mediated knockdown of PDHA1 gene expression provides a strategy that may be applied to create a useful animal model of PDC deficiency.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: DK-058327/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: MO1-000082/PHS HHS/United States; GR: P01 DK058327-070004/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100968751; 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); EC 1.2.4.1 (Pyruvate Dehydrogenase (Lipoamide)); EC 1.2.4.1 (pyruvate dehydrogenase E1alpha subunit); NIHMS25301; OID: NLM: NIHMS25301; OID: NLM: PMC1973157; 2006/12/20 [received]; 2007/02/08 [accepted]; 2007/02/20 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>1567-7249; 1567-7249</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Cellular and Molecular Therapy, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17392036; S1567-7249(07)00009-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.mito.2007.02.003</do>
<wp>20070220</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17392036</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1973157</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>236</id>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme gene therapy for autosomal dominant retinal disease</t1>
<jf>Clinical chemistry and laboratory medicine : CCLM / FESCC</jf>
<jo>Clin.Chem.Lab.Med.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>147</sp>
<op>153</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Point Mutation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/chemistry/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/genetics</k1>
<ab>Gene delivery to cells of the retina, particularly to photoreceptor cells, has broad potential both for answering basic questions of retinal biology and for more applied therapeutic purposes. The use of ribozymes as therapy for autosomal dominant retinal diseases is a promising technique, and the theoretical and practical basis for their use is discussed. The process involves designing and testing ribozymes first in vitro and then in animal models of retinal disease. Viral vectors based on the nonpathogenic human adeno-associated virus, when coupled with the strong, rod photoreceptor specific opsin promoter, offer an efficient and nontoxic way to deliver and express ribozymes in photoreceptor cells for long time periods of time. Effective ribozyme-mediated therapy also demands careful in vitro analysis of a ribozyme&amp;#39;s ability to efficiently and specifically distinguish between mutant and wild type RNAs. Finally, effective demonstration of therapy in an animal model requires careful analysis of any rescue effect in the retina using multiple criteria, including biochemical, structural and physiological assays. For this purpose, ribozyme therapy in a transgenic rat model of retinitis pigmentosa containing a dominant rod opsin mutation (proline-to-histidine change at position 23) is discussed in detail.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 9806306; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (Rod Opsins); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>1434-6621; 1434-6621</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA. hauswrth@eye1.eye.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10834402</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1515/CCLM.2000.022</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10834402</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>206</id>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme uses in retinal gene therapy</t1>
<jf>Progress in retinal and eye research</jf>
<jo>Prog.Retin.Eye Res.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>689</sp>
<op>710</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Protein Structure, Secondary</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Retinal Diseases/therapy</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/therapy</k1>
<ab>In this chapter we discuss the design, delivery and preclinical testing of mutation-specific ribozymes for the treatment of dominantly inherited retinal disease. We focus particular attention on the initial screening of ribozymes in vitro, because the activity of RNA enzymes in cell-free systems can be used to predict their suitability for animal experiments. Current techniques for delivering genes of interest to cells of the retina using viral vectors are then briefly surveyed emphasizing vector properties that best match to the needs of a ribozyme-based therapy. Using these considerations, analysis of ribozyme gene therapy for an autosomal dominant RP-like disease in a rodent model is outlined emphasizing the desirability of combining biochemical, morphological and electrophysiological measures of therapy. Finally, we describe alternative, perhaps more general, ribozyme approaches that have yet to be tested in the context of retinal disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090115; JID: 9431859; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); RF: 123; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1350-9462; 1350-9462</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11029552; S1350946200000070 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11029552</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>208</id>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Zolotukhin,S.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<t1>Production and purification of recombinant adeno-associated virus</t1>
<jf>Methods in enzymology</jf>
<jo>Methods Enzymol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>316</vo>
<sp>743</sp>
<op>761</op>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, Affinity</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0212271; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0076-6879; 0076-6879</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10800712</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10800712</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>195</id>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Raisler,B.</a1>
<a1>Timmers,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Berns,K. I.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Range of retinal diseases potentially treatable by AAV-vectored gene therapy</t1>
<jf>Novartis Foundation symposium</jf>
<jo>Novartis Found.Symp.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>255</vo>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>88; discussion 188-94</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus</k1>
<k1>Eye Proteins</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Genes, Recessive</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Nerve Growth Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic</k1>
<k1>Retinal Diseases/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Retinal Neovascularization/therapy</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Viable strategies for retinal gene therapy must be designed to cope with the genetic nature of the disease and/or the primary pathologic process responsible for retinal malfunction. For dominant gene defects the aim must be to destroy the presumably toxic gene product, for recessive gene defects the direct approach aims to provide a wild-type copy of the gene to the affected retinal cell type, and for diseases of either complex or unknown genetic origin, more general cell survival strategies that deal with preserving affected retinal cells are often the best and only option. Hence examples of each type of therapy will be briefly discussed in several animal models, including ribozyme therapy for autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa in the transgenic P23H opsin rat, beta-PDE gene augmentation therapy for autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa in the rd mouse, glial cell-derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF) gene therapy for autosomal dominant RP in the transgenic S334ter opsin rat and pigment epithelial cell-derived neurotrophic factor (PEDF) gene therapy for neovascular retinal disease in rodents. Each employs a recombinant AAV vectored passenger gene controlled by one of several promoters supporting either photoreceptor-specific expression or more general retinal cell expression depending on the therapeutic requirements.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY01919/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY06842/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13101/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9807767; 0 (Eye Proteins); 0 (Gdnf protein, mouse); 0 (Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor); 0 (Nerve Growth Factors); 0 (Proteins); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (Serpins); 0 (pigment epithelium-derived factor); RF: 32; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1528-2511; 1528-2511</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14750604</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14750604</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>226</id>
<a1>Hefta,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Daignan-Fornier,B.</a1>
<a1>Bolotin-Fukuhara,M.</a1>
<t1>Nuclear and mitochondrial revertants of a mitochondrial mutant with a defect in the ATP synthetase complex</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>207</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>106</sp>
<op>113</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Microbial</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Oligomycins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Proton-Translocating ATPases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/drug effects/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<ab>Yeast strain 990 carries a mutation mapping to the oli1 locus of the mitochondrial genome, the gene encoding ATPase subunit 9. DNA sequence analysis indicated a substitution of valine for alanine at residue 22 of the protein. The strain failed to grow on nonfermentable carbon sources such as glycerol at low temperature (20 degrees C). At 28 degrees C the strain grew on nonfermentable carbon sources and was resistant to the antibiotic oligomycin. ATPase activity in mitochondria isolated from 990 was reduced relative to the wild-type strain from which it was derived, but the residual activity was oligomycin resistant. Subunit 9 (the DCCD-binding proteolipid) from the mutant strain exhibited reduced mobility in SDS-polyacrylamide gels relative to the wild-type proteolipid. Ten revertant strains of 990 were analyzed. All restored the ability to grow on glycerol at 20 degrees C. Mitotic segregation data showed that eight of the ten revertants were attributable to mitochondrial genetic events and two were caused by nuclear events since they appeared to be recessive nuclear suppressors. These nuclear mutations retained partial resistance to oligomycin and did not alter the electrophoretic behavior of subunit 9 or any other ATPase subunit. When mitochondrial DNA from each of the revertant strains was hybridized with an oligonucleotide probe covering the oli1 mutation, seven of the mitochondrial revertants were found to be true revertants and one a second mutation at the site of the original 990 mutation. The oli1 gene from this strain contained a substitution of glycine for valine at residue 22. The proteolipid isolated from this strain had increased electrophoretic mobility relative to the wild-type proteolipid.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/X05357; GENBANK/X05358; GR: 2RO1 GM2937-O4A1/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0125036; 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Oligomycins); EC 3.6.3.14 (Proton-Translocating ATPases); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<an>PMID: 2885722</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2885722</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>230</id>
<a1>Hoosein,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Derepression of citrate synthase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae may occur at the level of transcription</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>253</op>
<k1>Citrate (si)-Synthase/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Repression</k1>
<k1>Ethanol/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Glucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Glycerol/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Immunochemistry</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oxo-Acid-Lyases/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Pulse-chase labeling in whole cells and cell-free protein synthesis were used to establish that the mitochondrial enzyme citrate synthase is made as a larger precursor in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. A 54,000 Mr precursor form appeared to be a primary translation product since it could be labeled with N-[35S]formylmethionine in vitro. The induction of citrate synthase was monitored in S. cerevisiae cells grown on fermentable (glucose) and nonfermentable (ethanol and glycerol) carbon sources. The amount of citrate synthase activity and immune-reactive protein increased more than 15-fold as S. cerevisiae cells entered the stationary growth phase on glucose-containing medium. This increase was paralleled by an increase in translatable RNA for the enzyme. When cells were grown on a nonfermentable carbon source, no increase in either citrate synthase or its mRNA was detected. The results suggest that the release of citrate synthase from catabolite repression may occur at the level of transcription.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM 29387-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 50-99-7 (Glucose); 56-81-5 (Glycerol); 63231-63-0 (RNA); 64-17-5 (Ethanol); EC 2.3.3.1 (Citrate (si)-Synthase); EC 4.1.3.- (Oxo-Acid-Lyases); OID: NLM: PMC368688; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<an>PMID: 6199662</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6199662</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC368688</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>229</id>
<a1>Jenkins,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Marshall,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Hypothesis--a chemical mechanism for the biosynthesis of ATP involving ion-exchange reactions</t1>
<jf>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</jf>
<jo>Arch.Biochem.Biophys.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Aug 1</fd>
<vo>232</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>496</sp>
<op>504</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphatases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/biosynthesis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Anion Exchange Resins</k1>
<k1>Binding, Competitive</k1>
<k1>Cations, Divalent</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen-Ion Concentration</k1>
<k1>Hydroxides/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ion Exchange</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Magnesium/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Models, Chemical</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Thermodynamics</k1>
<ab>Dissociation constants for Mg . ATP were determined by displacing ATP from Dowex-1 resin with magnesium. These constants were then used to analyze the kinetics of yeast mitochondrial ATPase, in terms of the concentrations of free magnesium and free ATP, at a series of pH values. Both Mg . ATP and hydroxide ions were found to compete with the binding of ATP to the enzyme. These results were interpreted, in terms of an ion-exchange model, to mean that the synthesis of ATP may require the utilization of both magnesium and hydroxide ions for the dissociation of ATP from the enzyme as Mg . ATP. The concentrations of Mg and hydroxide required to compete with ATP were both found to be about three orders of magnitude greater than those required to form products, indicating that magnesium and hydroxide ions can contribute about 8 kcal of energy when ATP is synthesized.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: GM 29387-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: SO7 RR07031/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372430; 0 (Anion Exchange Resins); 0 (Cations, Divalent); 0 (Hydroxides); 14280-30-9 (hydroxide ion); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); 7439-95-4 (Magnesium); EC 3.6.1.- (Adenosine Triphosphatases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-9861; 0003-9861</sn>
<an>PMID: 6235776</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6235776</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>176</id>
<a1>Justilien,V.</a1>
<a1>Pang,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Renganathan,K.</a1>
<a1>Zhan,X.</a1>
<a1>Crabb,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Kim,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Sparrow,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>SOD2 knockdown mouse model of early AMD</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>4407</sp>
<op>4420</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Macular Degeneration/genetics/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Pigment Epithelium of Eye/drug effects/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Pyridinium Compounds/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Retinoids/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tandem Mass Spectrometry</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To test the hypothesis that oxidative injury to the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) may lead to retinal damage similar to that associated with the early stages of age-related macular degeneration (AMD). METHODS: A ribozyme that targets the protective enzyme manganese superoxide dismutase (MnSOD) was expressed in RPE-J cells, and adeno-associated virus (AAV) expressing the ribozyme gene was injected beneath the retinas of adult C57BL/6 mice. The RPE/choroid complex was examined for SOD2 protein levels and protein markers of oxidative damage using immunoblot analysis and LC MS/MS-identification of proteins and nitration sites. Lipids were extracted from retinal tissue and analyzed for the bis-retinoid compounds A2E and iso-A2E. The mice were analyzed by full-field electroretinography (ERG) for light response. Light and electron microscopy were used to measure cytological changes in the retinas. RESULTS: The treatment of RPE-J cells with Rz432 resulted in decreased MnSOD mRNA and protein as well as increased levels of superoxide anion and apoptotic cell death. When delivered by AAV, Rz432 reduced MnSOD protein and increased markers of oxidative damage, including nitrated and carboxyethylpyrrole-modified proteins in the RPE-choroid of mice. Ribozyme delivery caused a progressive loss of electroretinograph response, vacuolization, degeneration of the RPE, thickening of Bruch&amp;#39;s membrane, and shortening and disorganization of the photoreceptor outer and inner segments. Progressive thinning of the photoreceptor outer nuclear layer resulted from apoptotic cell death. Similar to the eyes of patients with AMD, ribozyme-treated eyes exhibited increased autofluorescence and elevated levels of A2E and iso-A2E, major bis-retinoid pigments of lipofuscin. CONCLUSIONS: These results support the hypothesis that oxidative damage to the RPE may play a role in some of the key features of AMD.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: EY016073/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY12951/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13729/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY14239/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY15638/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (A2E compound); 0 (Pyridinium Compounds); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Retinoids); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); EC 1.15.1.1 (superoxide dismutase 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17898259; 48/10/4407 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.07-0432</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17898259</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>257</id>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Yasumura,D.</a1>
<a1>Matthes,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Nishikawa,S.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<t1>Neurotrophic factors and gene therapy for possible treatment of retinal degeneration</t1>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<a2>Christen,Y.</a2><a2> Doly,M.</a2><a2>Droy-Lefaix,M. -T</a2>
<t2>Les Seminaires Ophtalmologiques d&amp;#39;IPSEN</t2>
<pb>Irvinn Editions</pb>
<pp>Neuilly-sur-Seine</pp>
<t3>Les Seminaires Ophtalmologiques d&amp;#39;IPSEN</t3>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>209</id>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Yasumura,D.</a1>
<a1>Matthes,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme rescue of photoreceptor cells in P23H transgenic rats: long-term survival and late-stage therapy</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Oct 10</fd>
<vo>97</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>11488</sp>
<op>11493</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Photoreceptor Cells/cytology/drug effects</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Retinal Diseases/genetics/therapy</k1>
<ab>Ribozyme-directed cleavage of mutant mRNAs appears to be a potentially effective therapeutic measure for dominantly inherited diseases. We previously demonstrated that two ribozymes targeted to the P23H mutation in rhodopsin slow photoreceptor degeneration in transgenic rats for up to 3 months of age when injected before significant degeneration at postnatal day (P) 15. We now have explored whether ribozyme rescue persists at older ages, and whether ribozymes are effective when injected later in the degeneration after significant photoreceptor cell loss. Recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) vectors incorporating a proximal bovine rod opsin promoter were used to transfer either hairpin or hammerhead ribozyme genes to photoreceptors. For the study of long-term survival, rAAV was administered by subretinal injection at P15, and the rats were allowed to live up to 8 months of age. For the study of late-stage gene transfer, rAAV was administered at P30 or P45, when 40-45% of the photoreceptors already had degenerated. Eyes were examined functionally by the electroretinogram and structurally by morphometric analysis. When injected at P15, expression of either ribozyme markedly slowed the rate of photoreceptor degeneration for at least 8 months and resulted in significantly greater electroretinogram amplitudes at least up to P180. When injected at P30 or P45, virtually the same number of photoreceptors survived at P130 as when injected at P15. Ribozyme rescue appears to be a potentially effective, long-term therapy for autosomal dominant retinal degeneration and is highly effective even when the gene transfer is done after significant photoreceptor cell loss.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: EY01919/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY02162/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY06842/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: etc.; JID: 7505876; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); OID: NLM: PMC17227; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Beckman Vision Center, University of California, San Francisco, CA 94143-0730, USA. mmlv@itsa.ucsf.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11005848; 210319397 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.210319397</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11005848</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC17227</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>255</id>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<t1>Mitochondrial structure, function and biogenesis</t1>
<yr>1998</yr>
<is>Chapter 2</is>
<sp>17</sp>
<op>41</op>
<a2>Singh,K. K.</a2>
<t2>Mitochondrial DNA Mutations in Aging, Disease and Cancer</t2>
<pb>Springer</pb>
<pp>Berlin</pp>
<sn>3-350-64342-7</sn>
<cn>QU 58.5 M684 1998</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>245</id>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Restriction enzyme analysis of mitochondrial DNAs of petite mutants of yeast: classification of petites, and deletion mapping of mitochondrial genes</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<fd>Jul 25</fd>
<vo>163</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>257</sp>
<op>275</op>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genetic Techniques</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<ab>We have analyzed the restriction digest patterns of the mitochondrial DNA from 41 cytoplasmic petite strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, that have been extensively characterized with respect to genetic markers. Each mitochondrial DNA was digested with seven restriction endonucleases (EcoRI, HPaI, HindIII, BamHI, HhaI, SalI, and PstI) which together make 41 cuts in grande mitochondrial DNA and for which we have derived fragment maps. The petite mitochondrial DNAs were also analyzed with HpaII, HaeIII, and AluI, each of which makes more than 80 cleavages in grande mitochondrial DNA. On the basis of the restriction patterns observed (i.e., only one fragment migrating differently from grande for a single deletion, and more than one for multiple deletions) and by comparing petite and grande mitochondrial DNA restriction maps, the petite clones could be classified into two main groups: (1) petites representing a single deletion of grande mitochondrial DNA and (2) petites containing multiple deletions of the grande mitochondrial DNA resulting in rearranged sequences. Single deletion petites may retain a large portion of the grande mitochondrial genome or may be of low kinetic cimplexity. Many petites which are scored as single continuous deletions by genetic criteria were later demonstrated to be internally deleted by restriction endonuclease analysis. Heterogeneous sequences, manifested by the presence of sub-stoichiometric amounts of some restriction fragments, may accompany the single or multiple deletions. Single deletions with heterogeneous sequences remain useful for mapping if the low concentration sequences represent a subset of the stoichiometric bands. Using a group of petites which retain single continuous regions of the grande mitochondrial DNA, we have physically mapped antibiotic resistance and mit- markers to regions of the grande restriction map as follows: C (99.3--1.4 map units)--OXI-1 (2.5--15.7)--OXI-2 (18.5--25)--P (28.1--34.2)--OXI-3 (32.2--61.2--OII (60--62)--COB (64.6--80.8--0I (80.4--85.7)--E (95--98.9).</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0125036; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<an>PMID: 355853</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>355853</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>254</id>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Moritmoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Merten,S.</a1>
<a1>Martin,N.</a1>
<a1>Berg,P. Christianson,T.</a1>
<a1>Levens,D.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Physical mapping of mitochondrial genes and transcripts in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<yr>1977</yr>
<sp>271</sp>
<op>289</op>
<t2>Genetics and Biogenesis of Mitochondria</t2>
<ed>Kaudewitz,F. et al</ed>
<pb>DeGruyter</pb>
<pp>Berlin</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>211</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Nishikawa,S.</a1>
<a1>Yasumura,D.</a1>
<a1>Flannery,J. G.</a1>
<a1>LaVail,M. M.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme rescue of photoreceptor cells in a transgenic rat model of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa</t1>
<jf>Nature medicine</jf>
<jo>Nat.Med.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>967</sp>
<op>971</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Histidine</k1>
<k1>Photoreceptor Cells/pathology</k1>
<k1>Point Mutation</k1>
<k1>Proline</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/biosynthesis/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Retinal Rod Photoreceptor Cells/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/genetics</k1>
<ab>Ribozymes, catalytic RNA molecules that cleave a complementary mRNA sequence, have potential as therapeutics for dominantly inherited disease. Twelve percent of American patients with the blinding disease autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa (ADRP) carry a substitution of histidine for proline at codon 23 (P23H) in their rhodopsin gene, resulting in photoreceptor cell death from the synthesis of the abnormal gene product. Ribozymes can discriminate and catalyze the in vitro destruction of P23H mutant mRNAs from a transgenic rat model of ADRP. Here, we demonstrate that in vivo expression of either a hammerhead or hairpin ribozyme in this rat model considerably slows the rate of photoreceptor degeneration for at least three months. Catalytically inactive control ribozymes had less effect on the retinal degeneration. Intracellular production of ribozymes in photoreceptors was achieved by transduction with a recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) incorporating a rod opsin promoter. Ribozyme-directed cleavage of mutant mRNAs, therefore, may be an effective therapy for ADRP and also may be applicable to other inherited diseases.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 9502015; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (Rod Opsins); 147-85-3 (Proline); 71-00-1 (Histidine); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); EIN: Nat Med 1998 Sep;4(9):1081; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1078-8956; 1078-8956</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Gene Therapy Center, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA. lewin@college.med.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 9701253</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9701253</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>189</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Glazer,P. M.</a1>
<a1>Milstone,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Gene therapy for autosomal dominant disorders of keratin</t1>
<jf>The journal of investigative dermatology.Symposium proceedings / the Society for Investigative Dermatology, Inc.[and] European Society for Dermatological Research</jf>
<jo>J.Investig.Dermatol.Symp.Proc.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>47</sp>
<op>61</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Darier Disease/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ectodermal Dysplasia/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Epidermolysis Bullosa Simplex/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Gene Targeting</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Keratins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Keratoderma, Palmoplantar/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nails, Malformed/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotides, Antisense/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>RNA Interference</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>Dominant mutations that interfere with the assembly of keratin filaments cause painful and disfiguring epidermal diseases like pachyonychia congenita and epidermolysis bullosa simplex. Genetic therapies for such diseases must either suppress the production of the toxic proteins or correct the genetic defect in the chromosome. Because epidermal skin cells may be genetically modified in tissue culture or in situ, gene correction is a legitimate goal for keratin diseases. In addition, recent innovations, such as RNA interference in animals, make an RNA knockdown approach plausible in the near future. Although agents of RNA reduction (small interfering RNA, ribozymes, triplex oligonucleotides, or antisense DNA) can be delivered as nucleotides, the impermeability of the skin to large charged molecules presents a serious impediment. Using viral vectors to deliver genes for selective inhibitors of gene expression presents an attractive alternative for long-term treatment of genetic disease in the skin.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 9609059; 0 (Oligonucleotides, Antisense); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 68238-35-7 (Keratins); RF: 112; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1087-0024; 1087-0024</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA. lewin@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16250209</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1087-0024.2005.10207.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16250209</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>233</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Gregor,I.</a1>
<a1>Mason,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Nelson,N.</a1>
<a1>Schatz,G.</a1>
<t1>Cytoplasmically made subunits of yeast mitochondrial F1-ATPase and cytochrome c oxidase are synthesized as individual precursors, not as polyproteins</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>3998</sp>
<op>4002</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphatases/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex IV/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Intracellular Membranes/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Peptide Fragments/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Precursors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/metabolism</k1>
<ab>At least three subunits of yeast mitochondrial F1-ATPase (ATP phosphohydrolase, EC 3.6.1.3) and at least two subunits of cytochrome c oxidase (ferrocytochrome c:oxygen oxidoreductase, EC 1.9.3.1) are synthesized outside the mitochondria and imported into the organelles as individual precursors that are between 2000 and 6000 daltons larger than the mature subunits. These precursors were shown to be primary translation products. Therefore, neither the five F1 subunits nor the four small cytochrome c oxidase subunits are synthesized as a single polyprotein.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (Macromolecular Substances); 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (Peptide Fragments); 0 (Protein Precursors); EC 1.9.3.1 (Electron Transport Complex IV); EC 3.6.1.- (Adenosine Triphosphatases); OID: NLM: PMC349755; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 6254007</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6254007</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC349755</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>203</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme gene therapy: applications for molecular medicine</t1>
<jf>Trends in molecular medicine</jf>
<jo>Trends Mol.Med.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>221</sp>
<op>228</op>
<k1>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome/therapy</k1>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Codon</k1>
<k1>DNA Repair</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms/therapy</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Transduction, Genetic</k1>
<ab>RNA enzymes--ribozymes--are being developed as treatments for a variety of diseases ranging from inborn metabolic disorders to viral infections and acquired diseases such as cancer. Ribozymes can be used both to downregulate and to repair pathogenic genes. In some instances, short-term exogenous delivery of stabilized RNA is desirable, but many treatments will require viral-mediated delivery to provide long-term expression of the therapeutic catalyst. Current gene therapy applications employ variations on naturally occurring ribozymes, but in vitro selection has provided new RNA and DNA catalysts, and research on trans-splicing and RNase P has suggested ways to harness the endogenous ribozymes of the cell for therapeutic purposes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 100966035; 0 (Codon); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); RF: 54; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-4914; 1471-4914</sn>
<ad>Dept of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology and the Powell Gene Therapy Center, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA. lewin@mgm.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11325634; S1471-4914(01)01965-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11325634</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>223</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hines,V.</a1>
<a1>Small,G. M.</a1>
<t1>Citrate synthase encoded by the CIT2 gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae is peroxisomal</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1399</sp>
<op>1405</op>
<k1>Cell Fractionation</k1>
<k1>Centrifugation, Density Gradient</k1>
<k1>Citrate (si)-Synthase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Microbodies/enzymology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Oxo-Acid-Lyases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<ab>The product of the CIT2 gene has the tripeptide SKL at its carboxyl terminus. This amino acid sequence has been shown to act as a peroxisomal targeting signal in mammalian cells. We examined the subcellular site of this extramitochondrial citrate synthase. Cells of Saccharomyces cerevisiae were grown on oleate medium to induce peroxisome proliferation. A fraction containing membrane-enclosed vesicles and organelles was analyzed by sedimentation on density gradients. In wild-type cells, the major peak of citrate synthase activity was recovered in the mitochondrial fraction, but a second peak of activity cosedimented with peroxisomes. The peroxisomal activity, but not the mitochondrial activity, was inhibited by incubation at pH 8.1, a characteristic of the extramitochondrial citrate synthase encoded by the CIT2 gene. In a strain in which the CIT1 gene encoding mitochondrial citrate synthase had been disrupted, the major peak of citrate synthase activity was peroxisomal, and all of the activity was sensitive to incubation at pH 8.1. Yeast cells bearing a cit2 disruption were unable to mobilize stored lipids and did not form stable peroxisomes in oleate. We conclude that citrate synthase encoded by CIT2 is peroxisomal and participates in the glyoxylate cycle.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 8109087; EC 2.3.3.1 (Citrate (si)-Synthase); EC 4.1.3.- (Oxo-Acid-Lyases); OID: NLM: PMC362242; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2181273</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2181273</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC362242</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>234</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Stable heterogeneity of mitochondrial DNA in grande and petite strains of S. cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>Plasmid</jf>
<jo>Plasmid</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>474</sp>
<op>484</op>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/analysis</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7802221; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0147-619X; 0147-619X</sn>
<an>PMID: 384424; 0147-619X(79)90031-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>384424</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>231</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Norman,D. K.</a1>
<t1>Assembly of F1-ATPase in isolated mitochondria</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Jun 10</fd>
<vo>258</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>6750</sp>
<op>6755</op>
<k1>Antigen-Antibody Complex</k1>
<k1>Immune Sera</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Proton-Translocating ATPases/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology</k1>
<ab>The assembly of the proton-translocating ATPase complex was studied in isolated mitochondria by incubating yeast mitochondria with radiolabeled precursors of mitochondrial proteins which had been made in a cell-free protein synthesis system. Following such an incubation, the ATPase complex (F1F0) was isolated. Newly assembled F1-ATPase was detected by autoradiography of the isolated enzyme, only peptide subunits which had been made in vitro and imported into the isolated mitochondria could be radioactive. Incorporation of radiolabeled ATPase subunits into the enzyme does not occur in the presence of an uncoupler of oxidative phosphorylation or of a divalent metal chelator, nor does it occur in submitochondrial particles rather than intact mitochondria. Incorporation of labeled ATPase subunits into the enzyme can be completed by unlabeled subunits, provided the unlabeled proteins are added before the mitochondria are incubated with radioactive precursors. These findings suggest that F1-ATPase is assembled from a pool of subunits in mitochondria.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01 GM29387/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: SO7 RR 7031/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Antigen-Antibody Complex); 0 (Immune Sera); 0 (Macromolecular Substances); EC 3.6.3.14 (Proton-Translocating ATPases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 6222049</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6222049</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>215</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Thomas,J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Tirupati,H. K.</a1>
<t1>Cotranscriptional splicing of a group I intron is facilitated by the Cbp2 protein</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>6971</sp>
<op>6978</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>RNA/biosynthesis/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/biosynthesis/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins</k1>
<ab>The nuclear CBP2 gene encodes a protein essential for the splicing of a mitochondrial group I intron in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. This intron (bI5) is spliced autocatalytically in the presence of high concentrations of magnesium and monovalent salt but requires the Cbp2 protein for splicing under physiological conditions. Addition of Cbp2 during RNA synthesis permitted cotranscriptional splicing. Splicing did not occur in the transcription buffer in the absence of synthesis. The Cbp2 protein appeared to modify the folding of the intron during RNA synthesis: pause sites for RNA polymerase were altered in the presence of the protein, and some mutant transcripts that did not splice after transcription did so during transcription in the presence of Cbp2. Cotranscriptional splicing also reduced hydrolysis at the 3&amp;#39; splice junction. These results suggest that Cbp2 modulates the sequential folding of the ribozyme during its synthesis. In addition, splicing during transcription led to an increase in RNA synthesis with both T7 RNA polymerase and mitochondrial RNA polymerase, implying a functional coupling between transcription and splicing.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 0 (CBP2 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 0 (RNA, mitochondrial); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 2.7.7.- (bacteriophage T7 RNA polymerase); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); OID: NLM: PMC230952; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8524264</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8524264</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC230952</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>258</id>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Wells,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Norman,D. K.</a1>
<t1>Assembly of the mitochondrial APTase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<yr>1983</yr>
<sp>621</sp>
<op>621-635</op>
<a2>Schweyen,R. J.</a2><a2> Wolf,K.</a2><a2>Kaudewitz,F.</a2>
<t2>Mitochondria 1983</t2>
<pb>DeGruyter</pb>
<pp>Berlin</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>168</id>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Dinculescu,A.</a1>
<a1>Shan,Z.</a1>
<a1>Miller,R.</a1>
<a1>Pang,J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Raizada,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Downregulation of p22phox in retinal pigment epithelial cells inhibits choroidal neovascularization in mice</t1>
<jf>Molecular therapy : the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Mol.Ther.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1688</sp>
<op>1694</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Choroidal Neovascularization</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>NADPH Oxidase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Pigment Epithelium/cytology/enzymology/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Choroidal neovascularization (CNV) occurs in a variety of chorioretinal diseases including age-related macular degeneration (AMD), and is the major cause of severe visual loss in patients with AMD. Oxidative stress has been thought to play an important role in the development of CNV. Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) oxidase is one of the major intracellular sources of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in the vascular system. In this study, we examined the expression of p22phox, an integral subunit in the NADPH oxidase complex, in the mouse eye. We determined that p22phox is expressed in the retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells and inner retinal neurons. A small-interfering RNA (siRNA) designed against p22phox efficiently reduced the expression of the protein in the eye when delivered by means of recombinant adeno-associated virus (AAV) vector. Vector treatment inhibited CNV in the mouse when delivered into the subretinal space where RPE cells were transduced. These results suggest that NADPH oxidase-mediated ROS production in RPE cells may play an important role in the pathogenesis of neovascular AMD, and that this pathway may represent a new target for therapeutic intervention in AMD.</ab>
<no>GR: EY016073/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13729/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: HL56921/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100890581; 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); EC 1.6.3.1 (NADPH Oxidase); EC 1.6.3.1 (p22(phox) protein, mouse); 2008/07/29 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-0024; 1525-0016</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0284, USA. qli@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18665154; mt2008164 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/mt.2008.164</do>
<wp>20080729</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18665154</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>202</id>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Timmers,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Hunter,K.</a1>
<a1>Gonzalez-Pola,C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Reitze,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Noninvasive imaging by optical coherence tomography to monitor retinal degeneration in the mouse</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2981</sp>
<op>2989</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Diagnostic Imaging/methods</k1>
<k1>Diagnostic Techniques, Ophthalmological</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Interferometry</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C3H</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Retina/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Retinal Degeneration/diagnosis/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Retinal Detachment/diagnosis/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Tomography/methods</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Optical coherence tomography (OCT) is a high-resolution imaging technique that measures the intensity of backscattered light from biological microstructures in living tissue. The objective was to evaluate OCT as a routine, noninvasive technique for quantitative measurements of retinal thickness and detachment in small animal models of retinal degenerative diseases. METHODS: An OCT scanning unit was designed and built to visualize retinal tissue from rodents at high resolution in vivo. Several normal and retinal degeneration (rd) mouse strains with different pigmentation, as well as a transgenic mouse strain that carries a wild-type beta-PDE gene in an rd/rd background, were analyzed at different ages. Retinal detachment was induced by subretinal injection of saline. Retinal function was evaluated by full-field ERG, and then each retina was cross-sectionally scanned by OCT. OCT image analysis and measurements of retinal thickness were performed. Animals were then killed and retinal histology was documented. RESULTS: OCT images of the mouse retina revealed structural landmarks allowing assignment of retinal structures. There was no difference in the OCT pattern between pigmented and nonpigmented mice. Changes in the retinal thickness measured by OCT correlated very well with the loss in function measured by ERG and histology in rd/rd and rd/rd/tg(+) transgenic mice at a variety of ages. In addition, retinal detachment caused by surgery was easily visualized and observed by OCT imaging. CONCLUSIONS: OCT imaging is applicable to the mouse retina. There is excellent agreement between the retinal thickness measured by OCT, ERG amplitude, and retinal histology, thus validating OCT imaging as a sensitive and noninvasive tool for monitoring the structural progression of retinal diseases in rodent models. OCT also appears useful for visualizing retinal detachments in the mouse.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY07864/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36303/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA. qli@eye1.eye.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11687546</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11687546</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>169</id>
<a1>Liu,J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Tuli,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Ghivizzani,S. C.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<t1>Reduction in severity of a herpes simplex virus type 1 murine infection by treatment with a ribozyme targeting the UL20 gene RNA</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>15</is>
<sp>7467</sp>
<op>7474</op>
<k1>Adenoviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/metabolism/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Foot/virology</k1>
<k1>Ganglia, Spinal/virology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Herpes Simplex</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 1, Human/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/metabolism/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord/virology</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Transduction, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics</k1>
<ab>Hammerhead ribozymes were designed to target mRNA of several essential herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) genes. A ribozyme specific for the late gene U(L)20 was packaged in an adenovirus vector (Ad-U(L)20 Rz) and evaluated for its capacity to inhibit the viral replication of several HSV-1 strains, including that of the wild-type HSV-1 (17syn+ and KOS) and several acycloguanosine-resistant strains (PAAr5, tkLTRZ1, and ACGr4) in tissue culture. The Ad-U(L)20 Rz was also tested for its ability to block an HSV-1 infection, using the mouse footpad model. Mouse footpads were treated with either the Ad-U(L)20 Rz or an adenoviral vector expressing green fluorescent protein (Ad-GFP) and then infected immediately thereafter with 10(4) PFU of HSV-1 strain 17syn+. Ad-U(L)20 ribozyme treatment consistently led to a 90% rate of protection for mice from lethal HSV-1 infection, while the survival rate in the control groups was less than 45%. Consistent with this protective effect, treatment with the Ad-U(L)20 Rz reduced the viral DNA load in the feet, the dorsal root ganglia, and the spinal cord relative to that of the Ad-GFP-treated animals. This study suggests that ribozymes targeting essential genes of the late kinetic class may represent a new therapeutic strategy for inhibiting HSV infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AR48566/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY05587/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (UL20 protein, Herpes simplex virus type 1); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); OID: NLM: PMC2493317; 2008/05/28 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5514; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Box 100266, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18508896; JVI.02720-07 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.02720-07</do>
<wp>20080528</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18508896</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2493317</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>166</id>
<a1>Liu,J.</a1>
<a1>Saghizadeh,M.</a1>
<a1>Tuli,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Kramerov,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Castro,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Ljubimov,A. V.</a1>
<t1>Different tropism of adenoviruses and adeno-associated viruses to corneal cells: implications for corneal gene therapy</t1>
<jf>Molecular vision</jf>
<jo>Mol.Vis.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>14</vo>
<sp>2087</sp>
<op>2096</op>
<k1>Adenoviridae/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Cornea/cytology/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Diabetes Mellitus/pathology</k1>
<k1>Epithelium, Corneal/cytology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Organ Culture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Organ Specificity</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Transduction, Genetic</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Diseased corneas are potential targets for viral-based gene therapy to normalize (stimulate or inhibit) the expression of specific proteins. The choice of viral vectors is important to achieve optimal effect. The purpose of this study was to compare the tropism to different corneal cells of recombinant adenovirus (rAV) and recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) constructs using live rabbit and organ-cultured human corneas. METHODS: rAV constructs harbored the green fluorescent protein (GFP) gene under the control of major immediate early cytomegalovirus (CMV) promoter. rAAV constructs from virus serotypes 1, 2 5, 7, and 8 had GFP under the chicken beta-actin promoter and CMV enhancer. For organ culture, 16 healthy and diabetic postmortem human corneas were used. Five or fifteen microl rAV at 10(7) plaque forming units per 1 microl were added for 2 days to culture medium of uninjured corneas that were further cultured for 5-32 days. rAAV were added at 1.2-7.8x10(10) vector genomes per cornea for 3 days to each cornea; the culture then continued for another 14-23 days. Corneal cryostat sections were examined by immunohistochemistry. Live rabbit corneas were used following excimer laser ablation of the corneal epithelium with preservation of the basal cell layer. Equal numbers of rAAV particles (2x10(11) vector genomes) were applied to the cornea for 10 min. After seven days to allow for corneal healing and gene expression the animals were euthanized, the corneas were excised, and sections analyzed by immunohistochemistry. RESULTS: By direct fluorescence microscopy of live organ-cultured human corneas GFP signal after rAV transduction was strong in the epithelium with dose-dependent intensity. On corneal sections, GFP was seen in all epithelial layers and some endothelial cells but most keratocytes were negative. In rAAV-transduced organ-cultured human corneas GFP signal could only be detected with anti-GFP antibody immunohistochemistry. GFP was observed in the epithelium, keratocytes, and endothelium, with more pronounced basal epithelial cell staining with rAAV1 than with other serotypes. No difference in the GFP expression patterns or levels between normal and diabetic corneas was noted. The rabbit corneas showed very similar patterns of GFP distribution to human corneas. With all rAAV serotype vectors, GFP staining in the epithelium was significantly (p=0.007) higher than the background staining in non-transduced corneas, with a trend for rAAV1 and rAAV8 to produce higher staining intensities than for rAAV2, rAAV5 (p=0.03; rAAV5 versus rAAV1), and rAAV7. rAAV serotype vectors also transduced stromal and endothelial cells in rabbit corneas to a different extent. CONCLUSIONS: rAAV appears to reach many more corneal cells than rAV, especially keratocytes, although GFP expression levels were lower compared to rAV. rAV may be more useful than rAAV for gene therapy applications requiring high protein expression levels, but rAAV may be superior for keratocyte targeting.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: EY05587/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13431/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: M01 RR00425/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS052465/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS44556/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 EY013431-08/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9605351; 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC2584774; 2008/09/17 [received]; 2008/11/11 [accepted]; 2008/11/18 [epublish]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1090-0535; 1090-0535</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19023450</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<wp>20081118</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19023450</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2584774</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>190</id>
<a1>Liu,J.</a1>
<a1>Timmers,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Ribozyme knockdown of the gamma-subunit of rod cGMP phosphodiesterase alters the ERG and retinal morphology in wild-type mice</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>3836</sp>
<op>3844</op>
<k1>3&#39;,5&#39;-Cyclic-GMP Phosphodiesterases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cyclic Nucleotide Phosphodiesterases, Type 6</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Injections</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Degeneration/enzymology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Retinal Rod Photoreceptor Cells/enzymology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To generate an animal model of retinal degeneration by using AAV-mediated ribozyme knockdown of the gamma-subunit of the rod cGMP phosphodiesterase (PDEgamma) mRNA in the retina of wild-type mice. METHODS: Two hammerhead ribozymes, HRz35 and HRz42, were designed to target the PDEgamma gene in wild-type C57BL/6 mice. The efficiency and specificity of the ribozyme cleavage was tested in vitro against three different types of target: short synthetic RNA oligomers, longer targets transcribed from clones, and full-length mRNA from total retinal RNA extracts. After in vitro validation, the ribozymes were cloned and packaged in a recombinant adenoassociated virus (rAAV) containing a proximal 472-bp murine rod opsin promoter (MOPS) to drive ribozyme synthesis. Three-week-old wild-type C57BL/6 mice were injected subretinally with the vectors. For treated versus partner control retinas, responses to light were measured by full-field electroretinography (ERG), and retinal tissues were examined by light microscopy. Messenger RNA and protein levels of PDEgamma gene were monitored by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and Western immunoblot assay. RESULTS: The ribozymes had comparable in vitro kinetic properties in multiple turnover kinetic analyses. Ribozyme HRz35 exhibited a K(cat) of 0.48 minute(-1) and a K(m) of 980 nM, and HRz42 showed a K(cat) of 0.17 minute(-1) and a K(m) of 971 nM. Both ribozymes cleaved at accessible sites in the RNA, as they digested long transcripts transcribed from clones and full-length mRNA from total retinal RNA extracts in vitro. At increasing intervals after subretinal injection with either AAV ribozyme, a 30% to 90% reduction in a- and b-wave amplitudes was observed compared with those in contralateral control eyes that were not injected. Retinal tissue analysis showed that loss of the photoreceptor cells and PDEgamma mRNA and protein paralleled the ERG results. CONCLUSIONS: Ribozyme-mediated somatic knockdown of wild-type PDEgamma mRNA in vivo can efficiently reduce the target RNA leading to a loss in rod photoreceptors and in rod-mediated ERG amplitudes, thus generating an animal model of retinal degeneration resembling human RP in an essentially normal adult retina. This vector ribozyme technique should be applicable to other genes associated with RP and perhaps also to mRNAs of phototransduction genes not yet associated with RP. Application of this approach may be age and species independent.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); EC 3.1.4.35 (3&amp;#39;,5&amp;#39;-Cyclic-GMP Phosphodiesterases); EC 3.1.4.35 (Cyclic Nucleotide Phosphodiesterases, Type 6); EC 3.1.4.35 (PDE6B protein, human); EC 3.1.4.35 (Pde6b protein, mouse); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainsville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16186371; 46/10/3836 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.04-1283</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16186371</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>248</id>
<a1>Locker,J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>The structure and organization of mitochondrial DNA from petite yeast</t1>
<jf>Plasmid</jf>
<jo>Plasmid</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>155</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Circular/analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/analysis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ethidium/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Mutagens</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Renaturation</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>RNA/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7802221; 0 (DNA, Circular); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Mutagens); 3546-21-2 (Ethidium); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); RF: 128; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0147-619X; 0147-619X</sn>
<an>PMID: 377320</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>377320</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>163</id>
<a1>Manfredsson,F. P.</a1>
<a1>Burger,C.</a1>
<a1>Rising,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Zuobi-Hasona,K.</a1>
<a1>Sullivan,L. F.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Huang,J.</a1>
<a1>Piercefield,E.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Tight Long-term dynamic doxycycline responsive nigrostriatal GDNF using a single rAAV vector</t1>
<jf>Molecular therapy : the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Mol.Ther.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1857</sp>
<op>1867</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Weight/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, High Pressure Liquid</k1>
<k1>Densitometry</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Doxycycline/blood/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Tetracycline/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF) gene transfer is being developed as a treatment for Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease (PD). Due to the potential for side effects, external transgene regulation should enhance this strategy&amp;#39;s safety profile. Here, we demonstrate dynamic control during long-term expression of GDNF using a recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV)-based bicistronic tetracycline (tet)-off construct. Nigrostriatal GDNF overexpression induces body weight alterations in rodents, enabling longitudinal in vivo tracking of GDNF expression after nigral vector delivery. Regulated GDNF expression was highly sensitive to dietary doxycycline (DOX), displaying undetectable striatal GDNF levels at serum DOX levels below those required for antimicrobial activity. However, in the absence of DOX, striatal GDNF levels exceeded levels required for efficacy in PD models. We also demonstrate the absence of a series of known GDNF-associated side effects when using direct intrastriatal vector delivery. Therefore, this single rAAV vector system meets most of the requirements for an experimental reagent for treatment of PD.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100316; GR: NS P01 36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100890581; 0 (Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor); 564-25-0 (Doxycycline); 60-54-8 (Tetracycline); OID: NLM: PMC2835027 [Available on 10/30/10]; 2009/08/25 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-0024; 1525-0016</sn>
<ad>Department of Neuroscience, Powell Gene Therapy Center, McKnight Brain Institute, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19707186; mt2009196 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/mt.2009.196</do>
<wp>20090825</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19707186</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2835027</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>177</id>
<a1>Manfredsson,F. P.</a1>
<a1>Burger,C.</a1>
<a1>Sullivan,L. F.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>rAAV-mediated nigral human parkin over-expression partially ameliorates motor deficits via enhanced dopamine neurotransmission in a rat model of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease</t1>
<jf>Experimental neurology</jf>
<jo>Exp.Neurol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>207</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>289</sp>
<op>301</op>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/physiology</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Dopamine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins/biosynthesis/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Motor Activity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Oxidopamine/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Parkinson Disease/complications/etiology/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Recovery of Function/physiology</k1>
<k1>Substantia Nigra/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sympatholytics/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases/metabolism</k1>
<ab>We hypothesized that over-expressing the E3 ligase, parkin, whose functional loss leads to Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, in the nigrostriatal tract might be protective in the unilateral 6-hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA) rat lesion model. Recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) encoding human parkin or green fluorescent protein (GFP) was injected into the rat substantia nigra 6 weeks prior to a four-site striatal 6-OHDA lesion. Vector-mediated parkin over-expression significantly ameliorated motor deficits as measured by amphetamine-induced rotational behavior and spontaneous behavior in the cylinder test but forelimb akinesia as assessed by the stepping test was unaffected. rAAV-mediated human parkin was expressed in the nigrostriatal tract, the substantia pars reticulata, and the subthalamic nucleus. However, in lesioned animals, there was no difference between nigral parkin and GFP-transduction on lesion-induced striatal tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) innervation or nigral TH positive surviving neurons. A second lesion experiment was performed to determine if striatal dopamine (DA) neurotransmission was enhanced as measured biochemically. In this second group of parkin and GFP treated rats, behavioral improvement was again observed. In addition, striatal TH and DA levels were slightly increased in the parkin-transduced group. In a third experiment, we evaluated parkin and GFP transduced rats 6 weeks after vector injection without DA depletion. When challenged with amphetamine, parkin treated rats tended to display asymmetries biased away from the treated hemisphere. Nigral parkin over-expression induced increases in both striatal TH and DA levels. Therefore, while parkin over-expression exerted no protective effect on the nigrostriatal DA system, parkin appeared to enhance the efficiency of nigrostriatal DA transmission in intact nigral DA neurons likely due to the observed increases in TH.</ab>
<no>JID: 0370712; 0 (Sympatholytics); 1199-18-4 (Oxidopamine); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases); EC 6.3.2.19 (parkin protein); 2007/04/11 [received]; 2007/06/27 [revised]; 2007/06/30 [accepted]; 2007/07/10 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0014-4886; 0014-4886</sn>
<ad>Department of Neuroscience, Powell Gene Therapy Center, McKnight Brain Institute, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17678648; S0014-4886(07)00259-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.expneurol.2007.06.019</do>
<wp>20070710</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17678648</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>188</id>
<a1>Manfredsson,F. P.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>RNA knockdown as a potential therapeutic strategy in Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease</t1>
<jf>Gene therapy</jf>
<jo>Gene Ther.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>517</sp>
<op>524</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Death/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Parkinson Disease/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA Interference</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/genetics</k1>
<ab>Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is a prevalent progressive degenerative disorder of the elderly. There is a current need for novel therapeutic strategies because the standard levodopa pharmacotherapy is only temporarily efficacious. Recently, there have been some high-profile successful preclinical results obtained in animal models of neurological disorders using small interfering RNAs delivered by viral vectors. RNA interference can theoretically be applied to Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease since over-expression of various proteins is known to kill the dopamine neurons of the substantia nigra in animal models and in familial forms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Potential RNA interfering strategies and caveats are discussed in this review.</ab>
<no>CI: Gene Therapy (2006) 13, 517-524. doi:10.1038/sj.gt.3302669; published online 3 November 2005; JID: 9421525; 0 (Proteins); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); RF: 68; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0969-7128; 0969-7128</sn>
<ad>Department of Neuroscience, McKnight Brain Institute, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0024, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16267570; 3302669 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/sj.gt.3302669</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16267570</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>241</id>
<a1>Moran,J. V.</a1>
<a1>Mecklenburg,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Sass,P.</a1>
<a1>Belcher,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Mahnke,D.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Perlman,P.</a1>
<t1>Splicing defective mutants of the COXI gene of yeast mitochondrial DNA: initial definition of the maturase domain of the group II intron aI2</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jun 11</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>2057</sp>
<op>2064</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex IV/genetics</k1>
<k1>Endoribonucleases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genetic Complementation Test</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleotidyltransferases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<ab>Six mutations blocking the function of a seven intron form of the mitochondrial gene encoding subunit I of cytochrome c oxidase (COXI) and mapping upstream of exon 3 were isolated and characterized. A cis-dominant mutant of the group IIA intron 1 defines a helical portion of the C1 substructure of domain 1 as essential for splicing. A trans-recessive mutant confirms that the intron 1 reading frame encodes a maturase function. A cis-dominant mutant in exon 2 was found to have no effect on the splicing of intron 1 or 2. A trans-recessive mutant, located in the group IIA intron 2, demonstrates for the first time that intron 2 encodes a maturase. A genetic dissection of the five missense mutations present in the intron 2 reading frame of that strain demonstrates that the maturase defect results from one or both of the missense mutations in a newly-recognized conserved sequence called domain X.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM31480/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (RNA, Fungal); EC 1.9.3.1 (Electron Transport Complex IV); EC 2.7.7.- (Nucleotidyltransferases); EC 2.7.7.- (mRNA maturase); EC 3.1.- (Endoribonucleases); OID: NLM: PMC308121; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas 75235.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8029012</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8029012</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC308121</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>252</id>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Merten,S.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Restriction Endonuclease Mapping and Analysis of Grande and Mutant Yeast Mitochondrial DNA</t1>
<yr>1976</yr>
<fd>August 2-7, 1976</fd>
<sp>519</sp>
<op>524</op>
<no>Conerence held under the auspices of the Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Mathematisch-Naturwissenschaftliche Klasse</no>
<a2>Bucher,Theodor</a2><a2> Neupert,W.</a2><a2> Sebald,W.</a2><a2>Werner,S.</a2>
<t2>Genetics and Biogenesis of Chloroplasts and Mitochondria: Interdisciplinary Conference on the Genetics and Biogenesis of Chloroplasts and Mitochondria, Munich, Germany</t2>
<pb>North-Holland Publishing Company</pb>
<pp>Amsterdam</pp>
<sn>0-7204-0604-8</sn>
<cn>QH433 I61g 1976</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>244</id>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Hsu,H. J.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<a1>Fukuhara,H.</a1>
<t1>Restriction endonuclease analysis of mitochondrial DNA from grande and genetically characterized cytoplasmic petite clones of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>3868</sp>
<op>3872</op>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/analysis</k1>
<k1>Endonucleases</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides/analysis</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/analysis</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Digestion of grande mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) BY EcoRI restriction endonuclease gives rise to nine fragments with a total molecular weight of 51.8 x 10(6). HindIII digestion yields six fragments with a similar total molecular weight. Specific restriction fragments can be detected despite the fact that yeast mtDNA consists of a heterogeneous distribution of randomly broken molecules. Digestion patterns of 10 genetically characterized petite clones containing various combinations of five antiobiotic resistance markers indicate that the petite mtDNA predominantly represents deletion of the grande genome. The petite mtDNAs contained up to seven EcoRI restriction fragments which comigrate with grande restriction fragments, and at least one fragment that did not correspond to any in the grande. Some strains contained multiple fragments with mobility different from that of grande; these fragments were usually present in less than molar concentrations. The genetic markers were associated with individual sets of restriction fragments. However, several internal inconsistencies prevent the construction of a definitive genetic fragment map. These anomalies, together with the digestion patterns, provide strong evidence that, in addition to single contiguous deletion, other changes such as multiple deletion and heterogeneity of mtDNA populations are present in some of the petite mtDNAs.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); EC 3.1.- (Endonucleases); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); OID: NLM: PMC433097; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 1105566</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1105566</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC433097</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>246</id>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Physical mapping and characterization of the mitochondrial DNA and RNA sequences from mit- mutants defective in cytochrome oxidase peptide 1 (OXI 3)</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<fd>Feb 16</fd>
<vo>170</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>9</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cytochromes/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex IV/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Agar Gel</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Linkage (Genetics)</k1>
<k1>RNA/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0125036; 0 (Cytochromes); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 1.9.3.1 (Electron Transport Complex IV); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<an>PMID: 220509</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>220509</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>247</id>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Restriction cleavage map of mitochonrial DNA from the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>2331</sp>
<op>2351</op>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides/analysis</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<ab>Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) from the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae was cleaved by restriction endonucleases Eco RI, Hpa I, Bam HI, Hind III, Pst I, and Sal I, yielding 10, 7, 5, 6, 1, and 1 fragments, respectively. A physical ordering of the restriction sites on yeast mtDNA has been derived. Yeast mtDNA cannot be isolated as intact molecules, and it contains nicks and gaps which complicate the use of conventional fragment mapping procedures. Nevertheless, the position of each of the restriction sites was obtained primarily by reciprocal redigestion of isolated restriction fragments. This procedure was supplemented by co-digestion of mtDNA with a multisite enzyme and a single-site enzyme (i.e., Sal I or Pst I) which provided a unique orientation for overlapping fragments cleaved by Sal I or Pst I. The data obtained from these approaches were confirmed by analysis of double and triple enzyme digests. Analysis of partial digest fragments was used for positioning of the smallest Eco RI fragment. A comparison of mtDNA from four grande strains (MH41-7B, 19d, TR3-15A, and MH32-12D) revealed similar, but slightly varying restriction patterns, with an identical genome size for each of approximately 5 X 10(-7) d or 75 kb. A fifth grande strain, D273-10B from S. cerevisiae, revealed restriction patterns different from those of the above strains, with a smaller genome size of 70 kb.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0411011; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); OID: NLM: PMC342570; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<an>PMID: 333388</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>333388</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC342570</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>243</id>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<a1>Merten,S.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Martin,N. C.</a1>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Physical mapping of genes on yeast mitochondrial DNA: localization of antibiotic resistance loci, and rRNA and tRNA genes</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<fd>Jul 25</fd>
<vo>163</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>241</sp>
<op>255</op>
<k1>Chloramphenicol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Microbial</k1>
<k1>Erythromycin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Linkage (Genetics)</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Paromomycin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Ribosomal/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Transfer/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<ab>We have physically mapped the loci conferring resistance to antibiotics that inhibit mitochondrial protein synthesis (erythromycin, chloramphenicol and paromomycin) or respiration (oligomycin I and II), as well as the 21s and 14s rRNA and tRNA genes on the restriction map of the mitochondrial genome of the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. The mitochondrial genes were localized by hybridization of labeled RNA probes to restriction fragments of grande (strain MH41-7B) mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) generated by endonucleases EcoRI, HpaI, BamHI, HindIII, SalI, PstI and HhaI. We have derived the HhaI restriction fragment map of MH41-7B mit DNA, to be added to our previously reported maps for the six other endonucleases. The antibiotic resistance loci (antR) were mapped by hybridization of 3H-cRNA transcribed from single marker petite mtDNA&amp;#39;s of low kinetic complexity to grande restriction fragments. We have chosen the single Sal I site as the origin of the circular physical map and have positioned the antibiotic loci as follows: C (99.5-1.Ou)--P (27-36.Ou)--OII (58.3-62u--OI (80-84u)--E (94.4-98.4u). The 21s rRNA is localized at 94.4-99.2u, and the 14s rRNA is positioned between 36.2-39.8u. The two rRNA species are separated by 36% of the genome. Total mitochondrial tRNA labeled with 125I hybridized primarily to two regions of the genome, at 99.5-11.5u and 34-44u. A third region of hybridization was occasionally detected at 70--76u, which probably corresponds to seryl and glutamyl tRNA genes, previously located to this region by petite deletion mapping.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0125036; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (RNA, Ribosomal); 114-07-8 (Erythromycin); 56-75-7 (Chloramphenicol); 7542-37-2 (Paromomycin); 9014-25-9 (RNA, Transfer); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<an>PMID: 355852</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>355852</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>212</id>
<a1>Nguyen,M. H.</a1>
<a1>Clancy,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Yu,Y. C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Potentiation of antifungal activity of amphotericin B by azithromycin against Aspergillus species</t1>
<jf>European journal of clinical microbiology &amp; infectious diseases : official publication of the European Society of Clinical Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Clin.Microbiol.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>846</sp>
<op>848</op>
<k1>Amphotericin B/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Aspergillus/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Azithromycin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Drug Synergism</k1>
<k1>Microbial Sensitivity Tests</k1>
<ab>The potential role of azithromycin in combination with amphotericin B against 25 clinical isolates of Aspergillus was assessed. The MIC of amphotericin B was 1 microg/ml for 44% of the isolates, 0.5 microg/ml for 48%, and 0.25 microg/ml for 8%. All isolates were resistant to azithromycin. Synergism, defined as a &amp;gt; or = twofold reduction in the MIC of both drugs upon combination, was demonstrated between amphotericin B and azithromycin for all 25 isolates. To prove that azithromycin exerts its antifungal effect by inhibiting protein synthesis, we studied [35S]-methionine incorporation into protein in one Aspergillus isolate. Neither amphotericin B at 0.125 microg/ml (fourfold below its MIC) nor azithromycin at 16 microg/ml (&amp;gt; or = 16-fold below its MIC) had any effect on protein synthesis when tested alone. Upon combination, however, a 68% inhibition in protein synthesis was evident by the inhibition of [35S]-methionine incorporation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20031114; JID: 8804297; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 1397-89-3 (Amphotericin B); 83905-01-5 (Azithromycin); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0934-9723; 0934-9723</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, and VA Medical Center, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9447909</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9447909</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>239</id>
<a1>Owen,R. I. V.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Peel,A.</a1>
<a1>Wang,J.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Stacpoole,P. W.</a1>
<a1>Flotte,T. R.</a1>
<t1>Recombinant adeno-associated virus vector-based gene transfer for defects in oxidative metabolism</t1>
<jf>Human Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Hum.Gene Ther.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Oct 10</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>15</is>
<sp>2067</sp>
<op>2078</op>
<k1>Acidosis, Lactic/congenital/therapy</k1>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphatases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Luminescent Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Fluorescence</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mitochondrial Proton-Translocating ATPases</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Neurons/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oxygen/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex Deficiency Disease</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transduction, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Defects in oxidative metabolism may be caused by mutations either in nuclear genes or in mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA). We tested the hypothesis that recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) could be used to complement mtDNA mutations. AAV vector constructs were designed to express the reporter gene encoding green fluorescent protein (GFP), fused to a targeting presequence that directed GFP to be translocated into mitochondria. These vectors mediated expression of mitochondrial-localized GFP, as indicated by fluorescence microscopy and electron microscopy, in respiring human embryonic kidney 293 cells and nonrespiring mtDNA-deficient (rho 0) cells. However, when sequences encoding hydrophobic segments of proteins normally encoded by mtDNA were inserted between the presequence and GFP, mitochondrial import failed to occur. In similar experiments, a fusion was created between pyruvate dehydrogenase (PDH) E1 alpha subunit, a nuclear-encoded mitochondrial gene with its own targeting presequence, and GFP. With this construct, expression of GFP was observed in mitochondria in vitro and in vivo. We conclude that the hydrophobicity of mtDNA-encoded proteins limits their ability to be transported from the cytoplasm. However, rAAV-based gene therapy may hold promise for gene therapy of PDH deficiency, the most common biochemically proven cause of congenital lactic acidosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: DK51809/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: RR 00082/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9008950; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Luminescent Proteins); 0 (Pyruvate Dehydrogenase Complex); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); 7782-44-7 (Oxygen); EC 3.6.1.- (Adenosine Triphosphatases); EC 3.6.3.- (Mitochondrial Proton-Translocating ATPases); EC 3.6.3.14 (MT-ATP6 protein, human); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1043-0342; 1043-0342</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11044909</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1089/104303400750001381</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11044909</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>222</id>
<a1>Partono,S.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>The rate and specificity of a group I ribozyme are inversely affected by choice of monovalent salt</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Feb 11</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>605</sp>
<op>609</op>
<k1>Cations, Monovalent</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Guanosine Triphosphate/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Potassium Chloride/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Solvents</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<ab>The fifth intron of the COB gene of yeast mitochondria splices autocatalytically. The rate of splicing is increased by high concentrations of monovalent salts, but the choice of both cation and anion is significant: The smaller the cation in solution, the faster the reaction (the rate in K+ greater than NH4+ greater than Na+ greater than Li+). Chloride, bromide, iodide and acetate salts enhance autocatalytic processing, but sulfate salts do not and fluoride salts are inhibitory. The choice of monovalent salt affects the KM of the intron for guanosine nucleotide, implying an alteration in the affinity of the RNA for that substrate. Under optimal conditions (1M KCl, 50 mM MgCl2) the catalytic efficiency of this intron exceeds that reported for the ribosomal intron from Tetrahymena, but several side reactions occur, including guanosine-addition within the downstream exon. The site of addition resembles the 5&amp;#39; splice junction, but selection of this site does not involve the internal guide sequence of the intron.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0411011; 0 (Cations, Monovalent); 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Solvents); 7447-40-7 (Potassium Chloride); 86-01-1 (Guanosine Triphosphate); OID: NLM: PMC333655; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2011532</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2011532</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC333655</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>235</id>
<a1>Partono,S.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Splicing of COB intron 5 requires pairing between the internal guide sequence and both flanking exons</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>8192</sp>
<op>8196</op>
<k1>Base Composition</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>RNA Precursors/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Group I introns are characterized by a set of conserved sequence elements and secondary structures. Evidence supporting the pairing of certain of these sequences has come from the comparison of intron sequences and from the analysis of mutations that disrupt splicing by interfering with pairing. One of the structures proposed for all group I introns is an internal guide sequence that base pairs with the upstream and the downstream exons, bringing them into alignment for ligation. We made specific mutations in the internal guide sequence and the flanking exons of the fifth intron in the yeast mitochondrial gene for apocytochrome b (COB). Mutations that disrupted the pairing between the internal guide sequence and the upstream exon (the P1 pairing) blocked addition of guanosine to the 5&amp;#39; end of the intron during autocatalytic reactions and prevented formation of the full-length circular intron. In contrast, transcripts containing mutations that disrupted the pairing between the guide sequence and the downstream exon (the P10 helix) initiated splicing but failed to ligate exons. Compensatory mutations that restored helices of normal stability mitigated the effects of the original mutations. These data provide direct evidence for the importance of the base pairing between the internal guide sequence and the downstream exon in the splicing of a wild-type group I intron.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (RNA Precursors); OID: NLM: PMC54921; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2236031</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2236031</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC54921</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>224</id>
<a1>Partono,S.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Autocatalytic activities of intron 5 of the cob gene of yeast mitochondria</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2562</sp>
<op>2571</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Catalysis</k1>
<k1>Cyclization</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The terminal intron of the mitochondrial cob gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae can undergo autocatalytic splicing in vitro. Efficient splicing of this intron required a high concentration of monovalent ion (1 M). We found that at a high salt concentration this intron was very active and performed many of the reactions described for other group I introns. The rate of the splicing reaction was dependent on the choice of the monovalent ion; the reaction intermediate, the intron-3&amp;#39; exon molecule, accumulated in NH4Cl but not in KCl. In addition, the intron was more reactive in KCl, accumulating in two different circular forms: one cyclized at the 5&amp;#39; intron boundary and the other at 236 nucleotides from the 5&amp;#39; end. These circular forms were able to undergo the opening and recyclization reactions previously described for the Tetrahymena rRNA intron. Cleavage of the 5&amp;#39; exon-intron boundary by the addition of GTP did not require the 3&amp;#39; terminus of the intron and the downstream exon. An anomalous guanosine addition at the 3&amp;#39; exon and at the middle of the intron was also detected. Hence, this intron, which requires a functional protein to splice in vivo, demonstrated a full spectrum of characteristic reactions in the absence of proteins.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 GM-12228-23/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); OID: NLM: PMC363457; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 3043183</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3043183</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC363457</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>167</id>
<a1>Petrs-Silva,H.</a1>
<a1>Dinculescu,A.</a1>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Min,S. H.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V.</a1>
<a1>Pang,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Zhong,L.</a1>
<a1>Zolotukhin,S.</a1>
<a1>Srivastava,A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>High-efficiency transduction of the mouse retina by tyrosine-mutant AAV serotype vectors</t1>
<jf>Molecular therapy : the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Mol.Ther.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>463</sp>
<op>471</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/classification/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ganglion Cysts</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/administration &amp; dosage/genetics</k1>
<k1>Injections</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transgenes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Tyrosine/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Vectors derived from adeno-associated viruses (AAVs) have become important gene delivery tools for the treatment of many inherited ocular diseases in well-characterized animal models. Previous studies have determined that the viral capsid plays an essential role in the cellular tropism and efficiency of transgene expression. Recently, it was shown that phosphorylation of surface-exposed tyrosine residues from AAV2 capsid targets the viral particles for ubiquitination and proteasome- mediated degradation, and mutations of these tyrosine residues lead to highly efficient vector transduction in vitro and in vivo. Because the tyrosine residues are highly conserved in other AAV serotypes, in this study we evaluated the intraocular transduction characteristics of vectors containing point mutations in surface- exposed capsid tyrosine residues in AAV serotypes 2, 8, and 9. Several of these novel AAV mutants were found to display a strong and widespread transgene expression in many retinal cells after subretinal or intravitreal delivery compared with their wild-type counterparts. For the first time, we show efficient transduction of the ganglion cell layer by AAV serotype 8 or 9 mutant vectors, thus providing additional tools besides AAV2 for targeting these cells. These enhanced AAV vectors have a great potential for future therapeutic applications for retinal degenerations and ocular neovascular diseases.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100316; GR: EY018335/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY0667/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY07132/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11087/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY13729/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100890581; 55520-40-6 (Tyrosine); OID: NLM: PMC2835095; 2008/12/16 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-0024; 1525-0016</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0284, USA. hildasilva@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19066593; mt2008269 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/mt.2008.269</do>
<wp>20081216</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19066593</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2835095</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>198</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Optic neuropathy induced by reductions in mitochondrial superoxide dismutase</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1088</sp>
<op>1096</op>
<k1>3T3 Cells</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Axons/pathology</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen Peroxide/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Membrane Potentials</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Myelin Sheath/pathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve Diseases/enzymology/etiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Phosphorylation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/pathology</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are suspected to play a pivotal role in the pathogenesis of Leber hereditary optic neuropathy (LHON), caused by mutated complex I subunit genes. It seems surprising that optic neuropathy has not been described in animals with a knockout of genes encoding critical anti-ROS defenses. If ROS have a role in the optic nerve injury of LHON, then increasing mitochondrial levels of ROS should induce optic neuropathy. METHODS: To develop an animal model system for study of oxidative injury to the optic nerve, mitochondrial defenses were decreased against ROS by designing hammerhead ribozymes to degrade SOD2 mRNA. Several potential ribozymes were analyzed in vitro. The one with the best kinetic characteristics was cloned into a recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) vector for delivery and testing in cells and animals. The effects of the AAV-expressing ribozyme on murine cell growth, SOD2 mRNA and protein, cellular ROS levels, and apoptosis were evaluated by RNase protection assay, immunoblot analysis, and ROS- and apoptosis-activated fluorescent probes. The rAAV-ribozyme was then injected into the eyes of DBA/1J mice, and the effect on the optic nerve was evaluated by ocular histopathologic examination. RESULTS: The AAV-expressing ribozyme decreased SOD2 mRNA and protein levels by as much as 85%, increased cellular superoxide, reduced mitochondrial membrane potential, and culminated in the death of infected cell lines by apoptosis without significantly altering complex I and III activity, somewhat spared in the most common LHON mutation (G11778A), although adenosine triphosphate (ATP) synthesis is markedly reduced. When inoculated into the eyes of mice, the AAV-expressing ribozyme led to loss of axons and myelin in the optic nerve and ganglion cells in the retina, the hallmarks of optic nerves examined at autopsy of patients with LHON. CONCLUSIONS: The striking similarity of the optic neuropathy to the histopathology of LHON is powerful evidence supporting ROS as a key factor in the pathogenesis of LHON.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY-11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY-12355/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); 7722-84-1 (Hydrogen Peroxide); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); EC 1.15.1.1 (superoxide dismutase 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, Center for Vision Science, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12601034</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12601034</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>199</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of complex I gene expression induces optic neuropathy</t1>
<jf>Annals of Neurology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Neurol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>198</sp>
<op>205</op>
<k1>3T3 Cells</k1>
<k1>Adenoviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex I</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kidney/cytology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>NADH, NADPH Oxidoreductases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/enzymology/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve Diseases/enzymology/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/genetics</k1>
<ab>Optic nerve degeneration is a feature common to diseases with mutations in genes that encode complex I of the respiratory chain. Vulnerability of this central nervous system tract is a mystery, because of the paucity of animal models used to investigate effects of the mutated DNA in tissues rather than isolated in cultured cells. Using a ribozyme designed to degrade the mRNA encoding a critical nuclear-encoded subunit gene of complex I (NDUFA1), we tested whether oxidative phosphorylation deficiency can recapitulate the optic neuropathy of mitochondrial disease. Injection of adenoassociated virus expressing this ribozyme led to axonal destruction and demyelination, the hallmarks of Leber hereditary optic neuropathy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: EY-12355/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7707449; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (hammerhead ribozyme); EC 1.6.- (NADH, NADPH Oxidoreductases); EC 1.6.5.3 (Electron Transport Complex I); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0364-5134; 0364-5134</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12557286</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ana.10426</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12557286</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>183</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of mitochondrial oxidative stress provides long-term neuroprotection in experimental optic neuritis</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>681</sp>
<op>691</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Culture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Encephalomyelitis, Autoimmune, Experimental/enzymology/pathology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique, Indirect</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Dyes</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Myelin Sheath/pathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/enzymology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Neuritis/enzymology/pathology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/enzymology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Axonal loss is thought to contribute to the persistence of visual loss in optic neuritis and multiple sclerosis (MS). The mechanisms of injury are poorly understood. The authors investigated the contribution of mitochondrial oxidative stress and the effects of modulating mitochondrial antioxidant gene expression in the optic nerves of mice induced with experimental allergic encephalomyelitis (EAE), with a focus on long-term neuroprotection. METHODS: Optic nerves from mice with EAE were probed for reactive oxygen species (ROS) with the use of dichlorofluorescein diacetate (DCFDA), dihydroethidium, and cerium chloride. To modulate mitochondrial oxidative stress, recombinant AAV containing the human SOD2 gene or a ribozyme targeting murine SOD2 was injected into the vitreous. Control eyes received the recombinant virus without a therapeutic gene. Mice were sensitized for EAE and were monitored by serial contrast-enhanced MRI. The effects of SOD2 modulation on the EAE optic nerve were gauged by computerized analysis of optic nerve volume, myelin fiber area, and retinal ganglion cell loss at 1, 3, and 12 months after sensitization for EAE. RESULTS: ROS were detected in the EAE optic nerve as early as 3 days after antigenic sensitization. Colocalization suggested mitochondria as the source of ROS activity in the absence of inflammation. The ribozyme suppressing SOD2 gene expression increased myelin fiber injury by 27%. Increasing SOD2 levels twofold in the optic nerve by virally mediated gene transfer ameliorated myelin fiber injury by 51% and RGC loss fourfold, limiting it to 7% in EAE at 1 year. CONCLUSIONS: Amelioration of mitochondrial oxidative stress by SOD2 gene delivery may be a therapeutic strategy for suppressing neurodegeneration in optic neuritis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: EY07982/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY12355/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (Fluorescent Dyes); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); EC 1.15.1.1 (superoxide dismutase 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17251466; 48/2/681 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.06-0553</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17251466</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>187</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Mitochondrial protein nitration primes neurodegeneration in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Oct 20</fd>
<vo>281</vo>
<is>42</is>
<sp>31950</sp>
<op>31962</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Encephalomyelitis, Autoimmune, Experimental/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Membrane Potentials</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Neurodegenerative Diseases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nitric Oxide Synthase/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Nitrogen/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species</k1>
<ab>The mechanisms of axonal and neuronal degeneration causing visual and neurologic disability in multiple sclerosis are poorly understood. Here we explored the contribution of mitochondria to neurodegeneration in the experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis animal model of multiple sclerosis. Oxidative injury to the murine mitochondrion preceded the infiltration of inflammatory cells, classically heralded as the mediators of demyelination and axonal injury by transection. Nitration of mitochondrial proteins affected key subunits of complexes I and IV of the respiratory chain and a chaperone critical to the stabilization and translocation of proteins into the organelle. Oxidative products were associated with loss of mitochondrial membrane potential and apoptotic cell death. Reductions in the rate of synthesis of adenosine triphosphate were severe and even greater than those associated with disorders caused by mutated mitochondrial DNA. Mitochondrial vacuolization, swelling, and dissolution of cristae occurred in axons as early as 3 days after sensitization for experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. Our findings implicate mitochondrial dysfunction induced by protein inactivation and mediated by oxidative stress initiates a cascade of molecular events leading to apoptosis and neurodegeneration in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis that is not mediated by inflammatory cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: EY07982/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY12355/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 7727-37-9 (Nitrogen); EC 1.14.13.39 (Nitric Oxide Synthase); 2006/08/18 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, the University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16920708; M603717200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1074/jbc.M603717200</do>
<wp>20060818</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16920708</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>240</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>SOD2 gene transfer protects against optic neuropathy induced by deficiency of complex I</t1>
<jf>Annals of Neurology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Neurol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>182</sp>
<op>191</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis/physiology</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern/methods</k1>
<k1>Cell Count/methods</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Ethidium/analogs &amp; derivatives/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Fluoresceins/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Functional Laterality</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Gene Transfer Techniques</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling/methods</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging/methods</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/deficiency/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron/methods</k1>
<k1>NADH Dehydrogenase</k1>
<k1>NIH 3T3 Cells</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/pathology/ultrastructure/virology</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve Diseases/genetics/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/pathology/virology</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>Mutations in genes encoding the NADH ubiquinone oxidoreductase, complex I of the respiratory chain, cause a diverse group of diseases. They include Leber hereditary optic neuropathy, Leigh syndrome, and mitochondrial encephalomyopathy with lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes. There is no effective treatment for these or any other mitochondrial disorder. Using a unique animal model of severe complex I deficiency induced by ribozymes targeted against a critical complex I subunit gene (NDUFA1), we attempted rescue of the optic nerve degeneration associated with Leber hereditary optic neuropathy. We used adenoassociated virus to deliver the human gene for SOD2 to the visual system of disease-induced mice. Relative to mock infection, SOD2 reduced apoptosis of retinal ganglion cells and degeneration of optic nerve fibers, the hallmarks of this disease. Rescue of this animal model supports a critical role for oxidative injury in disorders with complex I deficiency and shows that a respiratory deficit may be effectively treated in mammals, thus offering hope to patients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 2004; JID: 7707449; 0 (Fluoresceins); 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (Ndufa1 protein, mammalian); 0 (Ndufa1 protein, mouse); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 104821-25-2 (dihydroethidium); 2044-85-1 (diacetyldichlorofluorescein); 3546-21-2 (Ethidium); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); EC 1.15.1.1 (superoxide dismutase 2); EC 1.6.5.3 (NDUFA1 protein, human); EC 1.6.99.3 (NADH Dehydrogenase); CIN: Ann Neurol. 2004 Aug;56(2):171-2. PMID: 15293268; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Neurological Association</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0364-5134; 0364-5134</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15293270</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ana.20175</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15293270</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>181</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Use of mitochondrial antioxidant defenses for rescue of cells with a Leber hereditary optic neuropathy-causing mutation</t1>
<jf>Archives of Ophthalmology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Ophthalmol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>125</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>268</sp>
<op>272</op>
<k1>Antioxidants/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Fluorescence</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Optic Atrophy, Hereditary, Leber/enzymology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Superoxides/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To explore a treatment paradigm for Leber hereditary optic neuropathy (LHON), we augmented mitochondrial antioxidant defenses to rescue cells with the G11778A mutation in mitochondrial DNA. METHODS: Cells homoplasmic for the G11778A mutation in mitochondrial DNA were infected with an adeno-associated viral vector containing the human mitochondrial superoxide dismutase (SOD2) gene. Control cells were infected with an adeno-associated viral (AAV) vector expressing the green fluorescent protein (GFP). Two days later, the high-glucose culture medium was exchanged for a glucose-free medium containing galactose. After 1 or 2 days, cellular production of superoxide was assessed using the fluorescent probe dihydroethidium, and we used TUNEL (terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated biotin-deoxyuridine triphosphate nick-end labeling) staining to detect apoptotic nuclei. The effect of SOD2 on LHON cell survival was quantitated after 2 or 3 days. RESULTS: Comparisons of AAV-SOD2-infected LHON cells relative to control cells infected with AAV-green fluorescent protein showed increased expression of mitochondrial SOD that attenuated superoxide-induced fluorescence by 26% (P = .003) and suppressed TUNEL-induced fluorescence by 21% (P = .048) after 2 days of growth in galactose medium, when cell survival increased by 25% (P=.05). After 3 days in galactose medium, SOD2 increased LHON survival by 89% (P = .006) relative to controls. CONCLUSION: Protection against mitochondrial oxidative stress may be useful for treatment of LHON. CLINICAL RELEVANCE: Gene therapy with antioxidant genes may protect patients with LHON against visual loss.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: EY 12355/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7706534; 0 (Antioxidants); 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 11062-77-4 (Superoxides); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); EC 1.15.1.1 (superoxide dismutase 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-9950; 0003-9950</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17296905; 125/2/268 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archopht.125.2.268</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17296905</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>175</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>Long-term suppression of neurodegeneration in chronic experimental optic neuritis: antioxidant gene therapy</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5360</sp>
<op>5370</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antioxidants/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Atrophy</k1>
<k1>Axons/pathology</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Catalase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Encephalomyelitis, Autoimmune, Experimental/enzymology/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Injections</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Immunoelectron</k1>
<k1>Multiple Sclerosis/enzymology/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Myelin Sheath/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Neurodegenerative Diseases/enzymology/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/enzymology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Neuritis/enzymology/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To test in mice with experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) a strategy designed to treat patients at risk for axonal degeneration and persistent visual loss from optic neuritis and multiple sclerosis. METHODS: The authors cloned the human extracellular superoxide dismutase (ECSOD) or catalase (CAT) gene into recombinant adenoassociated virus (AAV). Transgene expression was evaluated by immunochemistry of infected RGC-5 cells and after intravitreal injection of AAV-ECSOD or AAV-CAT, or both, into the right eyes of DBA/1J mice. Control cells and left eyes were inoculated with AAV-GFP. Animals were sensitized for EAE, followed by serial contrast-enhanced MRI for 6 months, and then were euthanatized. The effects of ECSOD and CAT modulation on the EAE optic nerve were gauged by computerized analysis of optic nerve volume, myelin fiber area, axonal cell loss, and retinal ganglion cell (RGC) loss. RESULTS: Western blot analysis of infected RGC-5 cells revealed that expression of ECSOD increased 15-fold and that of CAT increased 3.5-fold. One month after intraocular injections, transgene expression increased 4-fold for AAV-ECSOD and 3.3-fold for AAV-CAT. Six months after intraocular injections and EAE sensitization, combination therapy with ECSOD and catalase decreased RGC loss by 29%, optic nerve demyelination by 36%, axonal loss by 44%, and cellular infiltration by 34% compared with the contralateral control eyes inoculated with AAV-GFP. Compared with the normal optic nerve, it limited RGC loss to 9%. CONCLUSIONS: Viral-mediated delivery of antioxidant genes provides long-lasting suppression against neuronal and axonal loss associated with permanent visual disability in patients with optic neuritis and multiple sclerosis.</ab>
<no>GR: EY07982/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (Antioxidants); EC 1.11.1.6 (Catalase); EC 1.15.1.1 (SOD3 protein, human); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18055782; 48/12/5360 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.07-0254</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18055782</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>184</id>
<a1>Qi,X.</a1>
<a1>Sun,L.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Guy,J.</a1>
<t1>The mutant human ND4 subunit of complex I induces optic neuropathy in the mouse</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>10</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Mitochondrial/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electron Transport Complex I/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Isoenzymes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Transmission</k1>
<k1>Optic Atrophy, Hereditary, Leber/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Optic Nerve/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Reactive Oxygen Species/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Ganglion Cells/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To produce a mouse model of Leber hereditary optic neuropathy. METHODS: A mutant ND4 subunit made compatible with the universal genetic code and containing an arginine-to-histidine substitution at residue 340, or a synthetic normal human ND4 gene was delivered to the mouse visual system. The expression and effects of the mutant ND4 gene on the optic nerve and cultured retinal ganglion cells was assessed by magnetic resonance imaging, immunohistochemistry, and light and transmission electron microscopy. RESULTS: The ATPc mitochondrial targeting sequence directed the allotopically expressed mutant human R340H and wild-type ND4FLAG polypeptides into mitochondria. Expression of normal human ND4 in murine mitochondria posed no ocular toxicity. In contrast, the mutant ND4 disrupted mitochondrial cytoarchitecture, elevated reactive oxygen species, induced swelling of the optic nerve head, and induced apoptosis, with a progressive demise of ganglion cells in the retina and their axons comprising the optic nerve. CONCLUSIONS: Allotopic expression of the mutant human R340H ND4 subunit of complex I replicated the hallmarks of human mitochondrial disease in the mouse. In contrast, ocular expression of the wild-type human ND4 subunit in lower mammals appears safe, suggesting that it may be useful for treatment of patients with Leber hereditary optic neuropathy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: EY07982/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY12335/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (DNA, Mitochondrial); 0 (Isoenzymes); 0 (Reactive Oxygen Species); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); EC 1.6.5.3 (Electron Transport Complex I); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0284, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17197509; 48/1/1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.06-0789</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17197509</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>253</id>
<a1>Rabinowitz,M.</a1>
<a1>Jacovcic,S.</a1>
<a1>Martin,N.</a1>
<a1>Hendler,F.</a1>
<a1>Halbreich,A.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Morimoto,R.</a1>
<t1>Transciprtion and organization of yeast mitochrondiral DNA.</t1>
<yr>1976</yr>
<sp>219</sp>
<op>230</op>
<a2>Saccone,C.</a2><a2> Kroon,A. M.</a2>
<t2>The Genetic Function of Mitochondrial DNA</t2>
<pb>Elsevier/North Holland Biomedical</pb>
<pp>Amsterdam</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>228</id>
<a1>Rickey,T. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Extramitochondrial citrate synthase activity in bakers&amp;#39; yeast</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>488</sp>
<op>493</op>
<k1>Citrate (si)-Synthase/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Oxo-Acid-Lyases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>We isolated the gene for citrate synthase (citrate oxaloacetate lyase; EC 4.1.3.7) from Saccharomyces cerevisiae and ablated it by inserting the yeast LEU2 gene within its reading frame. This revealed a second, nonmitochondrial citrate synthase. Like the mitochondrial enzyme, this enzyme was sensitive to glucose repression. It did not react with antibodies against mitochondrial citrate synthase. Haploid cells lacking a gene for mitochondrial citrate synthase grew somewhat slower than wild-type yeast cells, but exhibited no auxotrophic growth requirements.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 2R01 GM29387-04A1/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: S07 RR7031G/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; EC 2.3.3.1 (Citrate (si)-Synthase); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); EC 4.1.3.- (Oxo-Acid-Lyases); OID: NLM: PMC367537; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<an>PMID: 3023850</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3023850</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC367537</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>221</id>
<a1>Ritchings,B. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Mutational evidence for competition between the P1 and the P10 helices of a mitochondrial group I intron</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>May 11</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>2349</sp>
<op>2353</op>
<k1>Base Composition</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Hydrolysis</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>RNA</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<ab>A guanosine to cytosine transversion at position 2 of the fifth intron of the mitochondrial gene COB blocks the ligation step of splicing. This mutation prevents the formation of a base pair within the P1 helix of this group I intron--the RNA duplex formed between the 3&amp;#39; end of the upstream exon and the internal guide sequence. The mutation also reduces the rate of the first step of splicing (guanosine addition at the 5&amp;#39; splice junction) while stimulating hydrolysis at the 3&amp;#39; intron-exon boundary. Consequently, the ligation of exons is blocked because the 3&amp;#39; exon is removed prior to cleavage at the 5&amp;#39; splice junction. The lesion can be suppressed by second-site mutations that preserve the potential for base-pairing at this position. Because the P1 duplex and the P10 duplex (between the guide sequence and the 3&amp;#39; exon) overlap at the affected pairings represent alternative structures that do not, indeed cannot, form simultaneously.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081120; GR: R01 GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; 63231-63-0 (RNA); OID: NLM: PMC312352; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1375737</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1375737</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC312352</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>192</id>
<a1>Rodriguez-Lebron,E.</a1>
<a1>Denovan-Wright,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Nash,K.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Intrastriatal rAAV-mediated delivery of anti-huntingtin shRNAs induces partial reversal of disease progression in R6/1 Huntington&amp;#39;s disease transgenic mice</t1>
<jf>Molecular therapy : the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Mol.Ther.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>618</sp>
<op>633</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Disease Progression</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Huntington Disease/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Intranuclear Inclusion Bodies</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA Interference</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Huntington&amp;#39;s disease (HD) is a fatal neurodegenerative disorder caused by the presence of an abnormally expanded polyglutamine domain in the N-terminus of huntingtin. We developed a recombinant adeno-associated viral serotype 5 (rAAV5) gene transfer strategy to posttranscriptionally suppress the levels of striatal mutant huntingtin (mHtt) in the R6/1 HD transgenic mouse via RNA interference. Transient cotransfection of HEK293 cells with plasmids expressing a portion of human mHtt derived from R6/1 transgenic HD mice and a short-hairpin RNA directed against the 5&amp;#39; UTR of the mHtt mRNA (siHUNT-1) resulted in reduction in the levels of mHtt mRNA (-75%) and protein (-60%). Long-term in vivo rAAV5-mediated expression of siHUNT-1 in the striatum of R6/1 mice reduced the levels of mHtt mRNA (-78%) and protein (-28%) as determined by quantitative RT-PCR and Western blot analysis, respectively. The reduction in mHtt was concomitant with a reduction in the size and number of neuronal intranuclear inclusions and a small but significant normalization of the steady-state levels of preproenkephalin and dopamine- and cAMP-responsive phosphoprotein 32 kDa mRNA. Finally, bilateral expression of rAAV5-siHUNT-1 resulted in delayed onset of the rear paw clasping phenotype exhibited by the R6/1 mice. These results suggest that a reduction in the levels of striatal mHtt can ameliorate the HD phenotype of R6/1 mice.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 5 F31 NS 011182-05/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS048588-02/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100890581; 0 (Huntington protein, mouse); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); NIHMS83173; OID: NLM: NIHMS83173; OID: NLM: PMC2656966; 2005/03/30 [received]; 2005/05/11 [revised]; 2005/05/12 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-0016; 1525-0016</sn>
<ad>Department of Neuroscience, University of Florida McKnight Brain Institute, Gainesville, 32610-0244, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16019264; S1525-0016(05)00200-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ymthe.2005.05.006</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16019264</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2656966</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>225</id>
<a1>Sahota,A.</a1>
<a1>Ranjekar,P. K.</a1>
<a1>Alfonzo,J.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Taylor,M. W.</a1>
<t1>Mutants of Saccharomyces cerevisiae deficient in adenine phosphoribosyltransferase</t1>
<jf>Mutation research</jf>
<jo>Mutat.Res.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>180</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>81</sp>
<op>87</op>
<k1>Adenine/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Adenine Phosphoribosyltransferase/deficiency/genetics</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Microbial</k1>
<k1>Ethyl Methanesulfonate</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Hypoxanthine Phosphoribosyltransferase/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Pentosyltransferases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<ab>Spontaneous and ethyl methanesulfate induced mutants of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, with partial and complete deficiency of adenine phosphoribosyltransferase (APRT, EC 2.4.2.7), were isolated by selection for resistance to 8-azaadenine. Matings between totally deficient mutants and tester strain resulted in diploid heterozygotes that were sensitive to azaadenine. Upon sporulation and tetrad analysis, azaadenine resistance (and APRT deficiency) segregated as expected for a single Mendelian gene. Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (EC 2.4.2.8) activity in the mutants was similar to that in the wild-type cells. There was no detectable activity of adenine aminohydrolase (EC 3.5.4.2) in the wild-type or mutant cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AM25498/AM/NIADDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: ES CA 03501/ES/NIEHS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0400763; 1123-54-2 (8-azaadenine); 62-50-0 (Ethyl Methanesulfonate); 73-24-5 (Adenine); EC 2.4.2.- (Pentosyltransferases); EC 2.4.2.7 (Adenine Phosphoribosyltransferase); EC 2.4.2.8 (Hypoxanthine Phosphoribosyltransferase); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0027-5107; 0027-5107</sn>
<an>PMID: 3306356; 0027-5107(87)90069-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3306356</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>213</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>The Cbp2 protein stimulates the splicing of the omega intron of yeast mitochondria</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Apr 15</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1597</sp>
<op>1604</op>
<k1>Apoproteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cytochromes b</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Magnesium/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Oxygen Consumption</k1>
<k1>RNA Precursors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Ribosomal/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The Cbp2 protein is encoded in the nucleus and is required for the splicing of the terminal intron of the mitochondrial COB gene in Saccharomyces cerevisiae . Using a yeast strain that lacks this intron but contains a related group I intron in the precursor of the large ribosomal RNA, we have determined that Cbp2 protein is also required for the normal accumulation of 21S ribosomal RNA in vivo . Such strains bearing a deletion of the CBP2 gene adapt slowly to growth in glycerol/ethanol media implying a defect in derepression. At physiologic concentrations of magnesium, Cbp2 stimulates the splicing of the ribosomal RNA intron in vitro . Nevertheless, Cbp2 is not essential for splicing of this intron in mitochondria nor is it required in vitro at magnesium concentrations &amp;gt;5 mM. A similar intron exists in the large ribosomal RNA (LSU) gene of Saccharomyces douglasii . This intron does need Cbp2 for catalytic activity in physiologic magnesium. Similarities between the LSU introns and COB intron 5 suggest that Cbp2 may recognize conserved elements of the these two introns, and protein-induced UV crosslinks occur in similar sites in the substrate and catalytic domains of the RNA precursors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; 0 (Apoproteins); 0 (CBP2 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (RNA Precursors); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 0 (RNA, Ribosomal); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 7439-95-4 (Magnesium); 9035-37-4 (Cytochromes b); OID: NLM: PMC146636; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9092668; gka279 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9092668</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC146636</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>216</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Protein-induced folding of a group I intron in cytochrome b pre-mRNA</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Sep 15</fd>
<vo>270</vo>
<is>37</is>
<sp>21552</sp>
<op>21562</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Free Radicals</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Gene Products, tat/metabolism</k1>
<k1>HIV/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyl Radical</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Models, Structural</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>RNA Precursors/biosynthesis/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/biosynthesis/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Ribonuclease, Pancreatic</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>tat Gene Products, Human Immunodeficiency Virus</k1>
<ab>Some group I introns have been shown to be self-splicing in vitro, but perhaps all require proteins for splicing in vivo. Sequence differences affect the stability of secondary structures and may explain why some group I introns function efficiently without protein cofactors while others require them. The terminal intron of the cytochrome b pre-mRNA from yeast mitochondria needs a nucleus-encoded protein for splicing, even though it splices autocatalytically in high salt in vitro. This system has the advantage that the protein is specific for this intron, and yet the structure of the catalytically active RNA can be studied in its absence. We have modified the intron by chemical and enzymatic treatment in the presence and absence of the protein to determine the impact of the protein on the secondary and tertiary structures of the intron. We found protein-induced formation of secondary and tertiary structures within the intron, and the same structures also form in high salt autocatalytic conditions. We have also studied UV cross-links to determine those bases of the intron that interact directly with the protein and found that the protein contacts the intron most intimately at the structures denoted P1, L2, P4, and P6a.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; GR: R01 GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (Free Radicals); 0 (Gene Products, tat); 0 (RNA Precursors); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 0 (tat Gene Products, Human Immunodeficiency Virus); 3352-57-6 (Hydroxyl Radical); EC 3.1.27.5 (Ribonuclease, Pancreatic); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7665568</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM; X</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7665568</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>204</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Skold,A.</a1>
<a1>Wong,F.</a1>
<a1>Petters,R.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>An allele-specific hammerhead ribozyme gene therapy for a porcine model of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa</t1>
<jf>Molecular vision</jf>
<jo>Mol.Vis.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan 26</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<sp>6</sp>
<op>13</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Retinitis Pigmentosa/genetics/therapy</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Rod Opsins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To develop a hammerhead ribozyme-based gene therapy for a porcine model of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa (ADRP). METHODS: Hammerhead ribozymes were developed and assayed in vitro against RNA targets homologous to the opsin P347S mutants found in a transgenic porcine model and in humans. Both cloned and synthetic RNA oligonucleotide versions of ribozymes and targets were tested under multiple-turnover conditions using oligonucleotide RNA targets. Digestion of full-length P347S mRNA from porcine retina was performed. RESULTS: The porcine P347S hammerhead ribozyme was specific for the opsin P347S sequence. Multiple-turnover analysis yielded the following kinetic parameters: Vmax=7.3+/-0.5 nM/min, Km=2.1+/-0.6 mM, and kcat=1.5+/-0.4 min-1. The human P347S hammerhead ribozyme was substantially less active (~10,000 fold). CONCLUSIONS: We have developed a hammerhead ribozyme to use as a model for gene therapy of autosomal dominant retinitis pigmentosa in a transgenic porcine model. Based on kinetic characterization of this ribozyme compared to others used for gene therapy, this should be an effective reagent RNA. The allele specific ribozyme we tested for the human sequence, however, is not likely to be useful for gene therapy indicating that an alternative approach is necessary.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 9605351; 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (RNA, Catalytic); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Rod Opsins); epublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1090-0535; 1090-0535</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11172137; v7/a2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<wp>20010126</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11172137</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>214</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Thomas,J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>The Cbp2 protein suppresses splice site mutations in a group I intron</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Sep 1</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>3415</sp>
<op>3423</op>
<k1>Apoproteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cytochromes b</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Introns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Suppression, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The Cbp2 protein facilitates the folding of a group I intron in the COB pre-mRNA of yeast mitochondria. Based on its ability to suppress mutations affecting the auto-catalytic reaction, the protein appears to play a role in the selection of splice sites. Adding Cbp2 did not overcome the effects of mutations in P1 whose primary effect was on the first step of splicing. In contrast, most mutations affecting the ligation of exons were suppressed in vitro by Cbp2. These included mutations in P1, P9.0 and P10. In fact, a mutant transcript lacking both P9.0 and P10 ligated efficiently in the presence of Cbp2. P9.0 and P10 mutations also reduced the rate of cleavage at the 5&amp;#39; splice junction, and this effect was only partially mitigated by adding Cbp2. A competitive secondary structure near the 3&amp;#39; splice junction blocked Cbp2-stimulated splicing, but this mutation could be suppressed by co-transcriptional splicing in the presence of Cbp2. Our data underscore the importance of the interaction between the 5&amp;#39; and 3&amp;#39; splice junctions in group I introns and suggest that nucleotide-nucleotide interactions that stabilize the structure of group I introns can be superceded by protein-RNA interactions.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 GM12228/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; 0 (Apoproteins); 0 (CBP2 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 9035-37-4 (Cytochromes b); OID: NLM: PMC146108; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8811097; 6t0234 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8811097</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC146108</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>205</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Whalen,P. O.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Yan,W.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Ribozymes in treatment of inherited retinal disease</t1>
<jf>Methods in enzymology</jf>
<jo>Methods Enzymol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>316</vo>
<sp>761</sp>
<op>776</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydrolysis</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA, Catalytic/chemistry/genetics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retinal Diseases/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0212271; 0 (RNA, Catalytic); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0076-6879; 0076-6879</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10800713</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10800713</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>256</id>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Whelan,P. O.</a1>
<a1>Drenser,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Yan,W-M</a1>
<a1>Hawswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Ribozymes directed against messenger RNAs associated with autosomal dominant Retinitis pigmentosa</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<sp>267</sp>
<op>276</op>
<a2>Hollyfield,J.</a2><a2> et al.</a2>
<t2>Retinal Degeneration</t2>
<pb>Plenum Press</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>219</id>
<a1>Singh,K. K.</a1>
<a1>Small,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Alternative topogenic signals in peroxisomal citrate synthase of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5593</sp>
<op>5599</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Citrate (si)-Synthase/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Microbodies/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<ab>The tripeptide serine-lysine-leucine (SKL) occurs at the carboxyl terminus of many peroxisomal proteins and serves as a peroxisomal targeting signal. Saccharomyces cerevisiae has two isozymes of citrate synthase. The peroxisomal form, encoded by CIT2, terminates in SKL, while the mitochondrial form, encoded by CIT1, begins with an amino-terminal mitochondrial signal sequence and ends in SKN. We analyzed the importance of SKL as a topogenic signal for citrate synthase, using oleate to induce peroxisomes and density gradients to fractionate organelles. Our experiments revealed that SKL was necessary for directing citrate synthase to peroxisomes. C-terminal SKL was also sufficient to target a leaderless version of mitochondrial citrate synthase to peroxisomes. Deleting this tripeptide from the CIT2 protein caused peroxisomal citrate synthase to be missorted to mitochondria. These experiments suggest that the CIT2 protein contains a cryptic mitochondrial targeting signal.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081120; JID: 8109087; EC 2.3.3.1 (Citrate (si)-Synthase); OID: NLM: PMC360498; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32601.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1448089</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1448089</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC360498</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>185</id>
<a1>Teusner,J. T.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<t1>Down-regulation of rhodopsin gene expression by AAV-vectored short interfering RNA</t1>
<jf>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</jf>
<jo>Adv.Exp.Med.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>572</vo>
<sp>233</sp>
<op>238</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Genetic Techniques</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>RNA Interference</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<no>JID: 0121103; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0065-2598; 0065-2598</sn>
<ad>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17249579</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/0-387-32442-9_33</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17249579</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>207</id>
<a1>Tirupati,H. K.</a1>
<a1>Shaw,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>An RNA binding motif in the Cbp2 protein required for protein-stimulated RNA catalysis</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Oct 22</fd>
<vo>274</vo>
<is>43</is>
<sp>30393</sp>
<op>30401</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Substitution</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Cytochrome b Group/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Introns</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides</k1>
<k1>RNA Precursors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>RNA, Fungal/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA-Binding Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The fifth and terminal intron of yeast cytochrome b pre-mRNA (a group I intron) requires a protein encoded by the nuclear gene CBP2 for splicing. Because catalysis is intrinsic to the RNA, the protein is believed to promote formation of secondary and tertiary structure of the RNA, resulting in a catalytically competent intron. In vitro, this mitochondrial intron can be made to self-splice or undergo protein-facilitated splicing by varying the Mg(2+) and monovalent salt concentrations. This two-component system, therefore, provides a good model for understanding the role of proteins in RNA folding. A UV cross-linking experiment was initiated to identify RNA binding sites on Cbp2 and gain insights into Cbp2-intron interactions. A 12-amino acid region containing a presumptive contact site near the amino terminus was targeted for mutagenesis, and mutant proteins were characterized for RNA binding and stimulation of splicing. Mutations in this region resulted in partial or complete loss of function, demonstrating the importance of this determinant for stimulation of RNA splicing. Several of the mutations that severely reduced splicing did not significantly shift the overall binding isotherm of Cbp2 for the precursor RNA, suggesting that contacts critical for activity are not necessarily reflected in the dissociation constant. This analysis has identified a unique RNA binding motif of alternating basic and aromatic residues that is essential for protein facilitated splicing.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081029; JID: 2985121R; 0 (CBP2 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Cytochrome b Group); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (RNA Precursors); 0 (RNA, Fungal); 0 (RNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32605, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10521416</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10521416</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>218</id>
<a1>Tuttle,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,W. A.,Jr</a1>
<t1>Selective autophagy of peroxisomes in methylotrophic yeasts</t1>
<jf>European journal of cell biology</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Cell Biol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>283</sp>
<op>290</op>
<k1>Alcohol Oxidoreductases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Autophagy/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Glucose/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Methanol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Microbodies/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Pichia/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Vacuoles/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The methylotrophic yeasts Pichia pastoris and Hansenula polymorpha respond to a methanol substrate by synthesizing peroxisomal enzymes resulting in the formation of large peroxisomes. When the carbon source was changed from methanol to glucose, we observed a rapid loss of peroxisomes. In this comparative study, we utilized biochemical and morphological techniques to characterize the loss of peroxisomes in these yeasts. We used metabolic labeling and chase procedures to evaluate whether this loss was due to suppressed synthesis or enhanced degradation. The synthesis of alcohol oxidase was depressed 10-fold when cultures grown in methanol attained stationary growth. However, no further reduction of synthesis was observed upon transfer of these cultures to glucose medium. In stationary phase cultures maintained in methanol, two peroxisomal proteins, alcohol oxidase and dihydroxyacetone synthase, were degraded with a half-life of over 3 h. However, within 3 h of glucose repression, as much as 80% of the radiolabeled peroxisomal proteins were lost from both yeasts. This glucose-mediated degradative event appeared to be specific for peroxisomal proteins, since mitochondrial proteins were stable. Ultrastructural examination of both yeasts revealed that glucose induced the sequestration of peroxisomes into the yeast vacuole, the presumed site of degradation. These results suggest that peroxisome loss during glucose repression is due to a selective, enhanced degradation of whole peroxisomes by autophagic mechanisms.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: DK33326/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7906240; 50-99-7 (Glucose); 67-56-1 (Methanol); EC 1.1.- (Alcohol Oxidoreductases); EC 1.1.3.13 (alcohol oxidase); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0171-9335; 0171-9335</sn>
<ad>University of Florida College of Medicine, Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, Gainesville 32610-0235.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8330626</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8330626</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>220</id>
<a1>Wang,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Small,G. M.</a1>
<t1>A negative regulating element controlling transcription of the gene encoding acyl-CoA oxidase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Jul 11</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>13</is>
<sp>3495</sp>
<op>3500</op>
<k1>Acyl-CoA Oxidase</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oxidoreductases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic/genetics</k1>
<ab>Peroxisomes are induced in Saccharomyces cerevisiae when this yeast is grown in the presence of oleate, and are repressed when glucose is supplied as the carbon source. Concomitant with this is an induction/repression of peroxisomal beta-oxidation enzymes. We are investigating the transcriptional control of acyl-CoA oxidase, the first and rate-limiting enzyme in the peroxisomal beta-oxidation cycle. The promoter region of POX1 from S. cerevisiae has been analyzed in POX1/lacZ fusions. Expression of the POX1/lacZ fusion protein underwent glucose repression and oleate induction. By deletion, DNA band shift and DNase I footprinting analyses we have identified a region that is involved in transcriptional repression of POX1. Elimination of this DNA sequence results in constitutive expression of POX1 when S. cerevisiae is grown on a fermentable carbon source or glycerol.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0411011; 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); EC 1.- (Oxidoreductases); EC 1.3.3.6 (Acyl-CoA Oxidase); EC 1.3.3.6 (POX1 protein, S cerevisiae); OID: NLM: PMC312507; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1630920</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1630920</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC312507</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>179</id>
<a1>White,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Fritz,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Kaushal,S.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A. S.</a1>
<t1>Increased sensitivity to light-induced damage in a mouse model of autosomal dominant retinal disease</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1942</sp>
<op>1951</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Dependovirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electroretinography</k1>
<k1>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy</k1>
<k1>Genes, Dominant</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling</k1>
<k1>Light/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Photoreceptor Cells, Vertebrate/pathology</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries, Experimental/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Retina/pathology/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Retinal Degeneration/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Rhodopsin/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transgenes</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To describe a sensitivity to light-induced damage associated with expression of a T17M mutant human rhodopsin (hT17M) transgene in mice, with the goal of minimizing retinal injury during the subretinal delivery of rAAV-mediated gene therapy. METHODS: Mice were bred to express the hT17M rhodopsin transgene in a line that was hemizygous null for wild-type mouse rhodopsin (mrho(+/-)), and the eyes of transgenic mice and nontransgenic littermates were exposed for 2.5 minutes to unilateral illumination with fiber-optic light ranging from 5,000 to 10,000 lux. Funduscopic images were made with a handheld camera (Genesis; Kowa Company, Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). Full-field scotopic electroretinographic analysis (ERG) was performed to measure loss of retinal function. Morphometry in the light microscope was used to measure loss of rod photoreceptors. TUNEL staining and a nucleosome release assay were used to measure levels of apoptosis in retinal specimens. RESULTS: mrho(+/-);hT17M mice exhibited a sensitivity to light-induced damage that caused severe loss of a- and b-wave ERG responses. hT17M transgenic mice on the mrho(+/+) background were equally sensitive to light-induced damage. Histologic analysis showed a concomitant loss of photoreceptors and TUNEL labeling of fragmented DNA in rod photoreceptor cells, demonstrating that the damage occurred via an apoptotic pathway. Nontransgenic littermate mice were not affected by this exposure to light. Mice expressing an hP23H mutant human rhodopsin transgene were minimally sensitive to light-induced damage at these intensities, in comparison to hT17M mice. Treating the hT17M mice with an equivalent regimen of exposure to red light was less damaging to the retina, as measured by ERG and histology. CONCLUSIONS: Expression of a human hT17M mutant rhodopsin transgene in mice is associated with photoreceptor apoptosis in response to moderate exposure to light. This phenotype was not observed in nontransgenic littermates or in mice expressing an hP23H mutant human rhodopsin transgene. The results suggest that elimination of the glycosylation site at N15 is associated with increased sensitivity to light-induced damage.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: R01 EY11596/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 EY07132/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 9009-81-8 (Rhodopsin); EIN: Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2007 Aug;48(8):3436. Fritz, Jason J [added]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17460245; 48/5/1942 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1167/iovs.06-1131</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17460245</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>238</id>
<a1>Yan,W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,A.</a1>
<a1>Hauswirth,W.</a1>
<t1>Selective degradation of nonsense beta-phosphodiesterase mRNA in the heterozygous rd mouse</t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>13</is>
<sp>2529</sp>
<op>2536</op>
<k1>3&#39;,5&#39;-Cyclic-GMP Phosphodiesterases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cyclic Nucleotide Phosphodiesterases, Type 6</k1>
<k1>DNA/analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Eye Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Dosage</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>RNA/analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retina/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Retinal Degeneration/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To investigate the molecular mechanism relating phenotype and genotype in the rd mouse, mRNA and pre-mRNA levels derived from the wild-type and position-347 nonsense mutant beta-phosphodiesterase (beta-PDE) genes were determined and compared with the corresponding gene copy ratios. METHODS: Total RNA and genomic DNA was isolated from the retinas of three heterozygous rd/+ mouse strains. For each, quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was used to determine the ratio of wild-type and rd beta-phosphodiesterase pre-mRNA and mature mRNA. The gene copy ratio between wild-type and rd beta-PDE was also determined by quantitative PCR. RESULTS: The pre-mRNA ratio of wild-type versus nonsense mutant was close to 1:1, whereas the corresponding mRNA ratio was greater than 3:1, even though the gene copy ratio was confirmed to be 1:1. CONCLUSIONS: The equivalence of pre-mRNA ratio level for wild-type and nonsense mutant in the rd/+ retina indicates that both genes were transcribed at similar levels. Thus, neither the nonsense mutation at position 347 nor the intron 1 retroviral insertion also present in the rd gene seem to have affected gene transcription. In contrast, the strain-independent bias favoring wild-type mature mRNA in vivo suggests a specific degradation of mutant transcript during or after pre-mRNA splicing. This allele-specific degradation serves to decrease mutant transcript levels dramatically in all rd strains, and suggests that photoreceptor cells have the capacity to reduce the level of an mRNA containing a nonsense mutation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; GR: EY07864/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY08571/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; GR: EY11123/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (Eye Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 63231-63-0 (RNA); 9007-49-2 (DNA); EC 3.1.4.35 (3&amp;#39;,5&amp;#39;-Cyclic-GMP Phosphodiesterases); EC 3.1.4.35 (Cyclic Nucleotide Phosphodiesterases, Type 6); EC 3.1.4.35 (Pde6b protein, mouse); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9856762</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9856762</pmid></reference></refworks>
