
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3600</id>
<a1>Amarasekare,Kaushalya G.</a1>
<a1>Chong,Juang-Horng</a1>
<a1>Epsky,Nancy D.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Temperature on the Life History of the Mealybug Paracoccus marginatus (Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1798</sp>
<op>1804</op>
<ab>Effect of temperature on the life history of the mealybug Paracoccus marginatus Williams &amp;amp; Granara de Willink (Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae) was investigated in the laboratory. P. marginatus was able to develop and complete its life cycle at 18, 20, 25, and 30 +/- 1 degrees C. At 15, 34, and 35 degrees C, the eggs hatched after 27.5, 5.9, and 5.5 d of incubation, respectively, but further development of the first-instar nymphs was arrested. No eggs hatched at 37 degrees C. The developmental time for egg to adult was the longest at 18 degrees C for both males and females. Approximately 80-90% of the eggs survived between 20 and 30 degrees C. The highest fecundity was at 25 degrees C with each female producing an average of 300 eggs. Adult longevity, and preoviposition and oviposition periods increased with decreasing temperature up to 25 degrees C. The proportion of females was approximate to 42% at 25 degrees C and was between 70 and 80% at 18, 20, and 30 degrees C. Adult males and females required 303.0 and 294.1 degree-days (DD), respectively, to complete their development. The estimated minimum temperature thresholds for the adult males and females were 14.5 and 13.9 degrees C, respectively. For adult males, the estimated optimum and maximum temperature thresholds were 28.7 and 31.9 degrees C; and for adult females, they were 28.4 and 32.1 degrees C, respectively. The ability of P. marginatus to develop, survive, and reproduce successfully between 18 and 30 degrees C suggests that it has the capability to develop and establish in areas within this temperature range.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000261430700012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3598</id>
<a1>Amarasekare,Kaushalya G.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,Nancy D.</a1>
<t1>Efficiency and establishment of three introduced parasitoids of the mealybug Paracoccus marginatus (Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae)</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>51</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>91</sp>
<op>95</op>
<ab>Three introduced parasitoids Acerophagus papayae, Anagyrus loecki, and Pseudleptomastix mexicana of the mealybug Paracoccus marginatus have been released in Miami-Dade and Broward counties (Florida) in 2003. Efficiency and establishment of these previously introduced parasitoids to control P. marginatus were measured in 2005 and 2006, at three locations in Homestead (Miami-Dade). Mealybug populations were initially established on three branches (per plant) of 10 hibiscus plants inside closed-sleeve cages. The three treatments, closed, open, and no-cage environments were applied to the three established mealybug populations on each plant. The number of mealybugs and natural enemies was monitored in all treatments. After 72 h, the number of P. marginatus in the open-sleeve cage was higher than in the no-cage treatment but both were lower than the number in the closed-sleeve cage. Efficiency of parasitoids was evaluated by their percentage parasitism. Percentage parasitism (=recovery) was also used as an indicator for parasitoid establishment. Two of the three previously released parasitoids (A. papayae and A. loecki) were recovered in this study. Acerophagus papayae had a higher percentage parasitism than A. loecki in both the open-sleeve cage (31.0% vs 2.3%) and the no-cage treatments (21.4% vs 1.6%) and caused the most mortality of P. marginatus. There was no recovery of P. mexicana in either of the treatments. Although both A. papayae and A. loecki were established in tested areas, A. papayae was more efficient in controlling P. marginatus than A. loecki. The reasons for not recovering P. mexicana in release areas is yet unknown. (C) 2009 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000273889800012</an>
<do>10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.07.005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3603</id>
<a1>Amarasekare,Kaushalya G.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<a1>Osborne,Lance S.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,Nancy D.</a1>
<t1>Life history of Paracoccus marginatus (Hemiptera : pseudococcidae) on four host plant species under laboratory conditions</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>630</sp>
<op>635</op>
<ab>Life history of the mealybug, Paracoccus marginatus Williams and Granara de Willink, on three ornamental plants [Hibiscus rosa-sinensis L., Acalypha wilkesiana (Muell.-Arg.), and Plumeria rubra L.] and one weed species (Parthenium hysterophorus L.) was studied under laboratory conditions. Mealybugs were able to develop, survive, and reproduce on all four hosts; however, there were differences in the life history parameters. Adult females that developed on acalypha and parthenium emerged approximate to 1 d earlier than those that developed on hibiscus and plumeria. Adult males had a longer developmental time on plumeria than on the other hosts. Survival of first- and second-instar nymphs and cumulative adult survival were lowest on plumeria. Longevity was not affected by hosts for males and females and averaged 2.3 +/- 0.1 and 21.2 +/- 0.1 d, respectively. On plumeria, 58.9 1.7% of the adults were females, which was a higher female percentage than on the other hosts. No egg production occurred in virgin females. Prereproductive and reproductive periods of the females were not affected by hosts and averaged 6.3 +/- 0.1 and 11.2 +/- 0.1 d, respectively. Mean fecundity of 186.3 +/- 1.8 eggs on plumeria was lower than on the other three plant species. Life history parameters of P. marginatus on hibiscus, acalypha, plumeria, and parthenium show its ability to develop, survive, and reproduce on a wide variety of plant species.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000258342500002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3602</id>
<a1>Chong,Juang-Horng</a1>
<a1>Roda,Amy L.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<t1>Life history of the mealybug, Maconellicoccus hirsutus (Hemiptera : Pseudococcidae), at constant temperatures</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>323</sp>
<op>332</op>
<ab>Important life history parameters of the mealybug, Maconellicoccus hirsutus (Green), were characterized on hibiscus (Hibiscus rosa-sinensis L.) cuttings at six constant temperatures between 15 and 35 degrees C. The development of M. hirsutus was the fastest at 27 degrees C, where the mealybugs completed development in approximate to 29 d. The lower (T-min) and upper (T-max) developmental thresholds and the optimal developmental temperature (T-opt) for the development of female mealybugs were estimated as 14.5, 35, and 29 degrees C, respectively. The thermal constant (K), which is the number of temperature-day or degree-day units required for development, of the-females was 347 DD. The original distribution range prediction (based on T-min = 17.5 degrees C and K = 300 DD) indicated that M. hirsutus could complete at least one generation in all of the continental United States. However, results of this study suggested that the distribution range of M. hirsutus may expand northward because of the lower T-min, and the predicted number of generations in a year may be lower because of the higher K required to complete each generation. The average cumulative survival rate of M. hirsutus at 25 and 27 degrees C was 72%, which was significantly higher than 51 and 62% at 20 and 30 degrees C, respectively. M. hirsutus reproduced sexually, with each mated female producing 260-300 eggs between 20 and 27 degrees C but only approximate to 100 eggs at 30 degrees C. Female longevity was reduced from 28 d it 20 degrees C to 19-21 d at 25-30 degrees C. At 27 degrees C, the net reproductive rate (R-o) was estimated at 165 female/female, the intrinsic rate of population increase (r(m)) was 0.119 (female/female/d), the generation time (T-G) was 43 d, and the doubling time (DT) was 5.8 d. The life table statistics suggested that the currently released biological control agents, which have higher r(m), than M. hirsutus, will be able to complete more generations than the mealybug within the tested temperature range; thus, they are effective against M. hirsutus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000258342400006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3601</id>
<a1>Chong,Juang-Horng</a1>
<a1>Roda,Amy L.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<t1>Mortality of the Lobate Lac Scale, Paratachardina Pseudolobata (Hemiptera: Kerriidae), at Near Or Below Freezing Temperatures</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>674</sp>
<op>678</op>
<ab>The ability of the invasive lobate lac scale, Paratachardina pseudolobata Kondo &amp;amp; Gullan, to survive exposure to near or below freezing temperatures (-25, -15, -10, -5, 0, 5, and 10 degrees C) for extended durations (6, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h) was assessed in the laboratory. Exposure at 10 degrees C for 6 to 72 h did not cause significant mortality in immature and adult lobate lac scales. All nymphs and adults were killed after exposure to very low temperatures (-25 to -10 degrees C) for 6 h. All nymphs were killed within 24 h at -5, 0, and 5 degrees C, while about 2% of adults were still alive after 72 h at 0 and 5 degrees C. Results suggested that the range expansion of the lobate lac scale in the United States will be limited by winter temperature. The lobate lac scale may have a higher potential to invade areas where the average winter temperature do not drop below freezing for an extended duration (3 or more consecutive days), such as southern Florida, Rio Grande Valley in Texas, and Colorado river Delta between California and Arizona.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000261564100023</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3599</id>
<a1>Chong,Juang-Horng</a1>
<a1>Tefel,Jeffrey J.</a1>
<a1>Roda,Amy L.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Beetle Density and Time of Day on the Dispersal of Gratiana Boliviana (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>99</sp>
<op>106</op>
<ab>The leaf beetle, Gratiana boliviana Spaeth, is a biological control agent of tropical soda apple (Solanum viarum Dunal), a noxious weed invading the rangeland and agricultural fields of Florida and other southeastern states. In caged experiments, we examined the influence of beetle density and the time of day on the dispersal of the leaf beetle. Increasing beetle density from 2 to 100 beetles per plant did not increase G. boliviana dispersal, as long as the host plants were not severely defoliated. An increase in beetle density from 10 to 100 beetles per plant significantly reduced the per capita fecundity from 0.3 to 0.02 eggs over a 24-h period. Thus, a mass rearing method for G. boliviana should consider the potential detrimental effect of increasing density on the fecundity of the leaf beetle. When the dispersal activity of the leaf beetle was observed between 8:00 and 18:00 h, the proportion of beetles dispersing from a given plant increased throughout the morning hours and peaked at noon. A monitoring or sampling program of G. boliviana should be conducted in the early morning or late afternoon when the beetles&amp;#39; tendency to disperse is the lowest in order to more accurately sample for the population density in a certain area. Beetle density and the time of day interacted to influence the proportion of G. boliviana dispersing from a given plant. The proportions of beetles that dispersed were not different among the different time periods at densities of less than 40 beetles per plant. At or above 40 beetles per plant, the proportion of beetles that dispersed peaked at noon. This study suggests that a myriad of factors, including density, feeding damage, photoperiod and host plant quality, interact to determine the dispersal pattern of G. boliviana.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000264161900016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3606</id>
<a1>Epsky,Nancy D.</a1>
<a1>Amalin,Divina</a1>
<a1>Kendra,Paul E.</a1>
<a1>Puche,Helena</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<t1>Temporal and spatial characterization of an infestation of Paratachardina lobata lobata (Hemiptera : Kerriidae), a new invasive pest in Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>367</sp>
<op>374</op>
<ab>The lobate lac scale, Paratachardina lobata lobata (Chamberlin) was first found in south Florida in 1999. Reported hosts are present in the germplasm collection located at the USDA/ARS Subtropical Horticulture Research Station in Miami, and the scale was first found there in the summer of 2002. A study was initiated to determine the spatio-temporal dynamics of a lobate lac scale infestation at SHRS from Jul 2003 to Jul 2005. Numbers and percentages of viable adults, and reproductive success as indicated by ratio of nymphs to viable adults (= 100 scales per 30 cm branch) were found on only seven host plants. Among plants located in areas of high infestation probabilities, individual host susceptibility appeared to be the primary factor regulating infestation level.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000240526900012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3613</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Carpenter,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Gross,H. R.</a1>
<t1>Integration of inherited sterility and a parasitoid, Archytas marmoratus (Diptera: Tachinidae), for managing Helicoverpa zea (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae): Acceptability and suitability of hosts</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1679</sp>
<op>1684</op>
<ab>One of the factors important to the successful integration of inherited sterility and biological control is the suitability of hosts from irradiated parents. In this study corn earworm, Helicoverpa zea (Boddie), larvae from irradiated parents were compared with larvae from normal parents as to their acceptance by and suitability for Archytas marmoratus (Townsend). Normal larvae and larvae from crosses of irradiated males with normal females were placed in whorl-stage corn and subsequently exposed to maggots of A. marmoratus. Host and parasitoid emergence was approximately equal from both the normal and the irradiation treatment; however, parasitism was greater in the normal hosts. In field-cage studies in which adult A. marmoratus were released and allowed to larviposit, percentage parasitism and emergence of H. zea and A. marmoratus were equal between the normal treatment and the irradiation treatment. When maggots were applied to caged plants, emergence of H. zee and A. marmoratus were both low. Significantly more H. zee emerged in the normal treatment than in the irradiation treatment and the application of maggots did not affect emergence of H. zea. There were no significant differences in emergence of A. marmoratus between the normal and irradiation treatments. In a concurrent laboratory study, emergence of H. zea did not differ between normal and irradiation treatment but was greatly reduced when exposed to maggots. Similarly, emergence of A. marmoratus was not affected by irradiation treatment. Larvae from a cross of irradiated males and normal females appear to be both acceptable and suitable for development and subsequent emergence of A. marmoratus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1995TL69600040</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3615</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Carpenter,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Gross,H. R.</a1>
<t1>Potential of the Combined use of Inherited Sterility and a Parasitoid, Archytas-Marmoratus (Diptera, Tachinidae), for Managing Helicoverpa-Zea (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>41</sp>
<op>46</op>
<ab>The potential for combining inherited sterility with Archytas marmoratus (Townsend) (Diptera: Tachinidae) to manage the corn earworm, Helicoverpa zea (Boddie) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae), was examined in the laboratory and in the field. Larvae from crosses of irradiated males with normal females, irradiated females with normal males, and normal males with normal females were exposed to maggots of A. marmoratus in the laboratory and the field. Emergence of parasitoids from larvae of irradiated female and normal male crosses was significantly less than that of larvae from normal parents and of larvae from irradiated male and normal female crosses, but there were no differences between emergence from larvae from normal crosses and irradiated male by normal female crosses. Mortality of unparasitized larvae was greater when male or female parents were irradiated, than when they were unirradiated. Larvae of irradiated parents developed more slowly than did larvae of normal parents; at the time of collection from the field, larvae resulting from irradiated male by normal female crosses were predominantly fourth and early fifth instars, while larvae resulting from normal male by normal female crosses were predominantly late fifth instars. Among larvae resulting from normal crosses, parasitoid emergence was greater from hosts collected as fifth instars than from hosts collected as fourth and early fifth instars. Combining inherited sterility and A. marmoratus may be feasible for managing the early season population of H. zea.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1994NM71100006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3614</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Carpenter,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Wiseman,B. R.</a1>
<a1>Gross,H. R.</a1>
<t1>Host Corn-Earworm (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) Reared on Meridic Diet Containing Silks from a Resistant Corn Genotype on Archytas-Marmoratus (Diptera, Tachinidae) and Ichneumon-Promissorius (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>837</sp>
<op>845</op>
<ab>Larvae of Helicoverpa zea (Boddie) fed on a meridic diet containing silks of a resistant com genotype, &amp;#39;Zapalote Chico 2451# (PC3)&amp;#39;, were examined as suitable hosts for a larval-pupal parasitoid, Archytas marmoratus (Townsend), and a pupal parasitoid, Ichneumon promissorius (Erich). Host pupal weight, parasitoid weight, and developmental time were significantly reduced when host larvae were reared on a diet containing resistant silks compared with diet without resistant silks. Weight of A. marmoratus was strongly correlated with host weight for both host diets. Parasitoid developmental time for both parasitoids was also correlated with host pupal weight for hosts fed on a diet containing resistant silks. Fecundity of both parasitoids was not affected by host diet. Adult longevity of I. promissorius was significantly reduced when reared from hosts fed the diet containing resistant silks compared with hosts reared on the diet without resistant silks. Longevity of female A. marmoratus was not affected by host diet, but male A. marmoratus lived longer when reared from hosts fed the resistant diet. Despite a few negative effects (lower percentage emergence of A. marmoratus) of a resistant host diet on the parasitoids, these strategies could be compatible because the negative effects did not result in lower parasitoid fecundity or increased parasitoid developmental time.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1994PC62800008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3616</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<t1>Within-Root Mortality of Cylas-Formicarius (Coleoptera, Apionidae) by Entomopathogenic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>722</sp>
<op>729</op>
<ab>Within-root mortality of sweetpotato weevil, Cylas formicarius (F.), by six strains of entomopathogenic nematodes in the families Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae (Steinernema carpocapsae [Weiser] [=Neoaplectana carpocapsae, Steinernema feltiae] All and Mexican strains; Steinernema feltiae [Filipjev] [=Steinernema bibionis] N-27 strain; Steinernema glaseri [Steiner]; Heterorhabditis bacteriophora Poinar [=Heterorhabditis heliothidis] HP88 strain; and Heterorhabditis sp. FL2122 strain [an undescribed nematode isolated in Florida]) was tested in several buried-root bioassays. The ability of nematodes to locate and kill weevils, and the location within the root where infection occurred, were measured. In addition, mortality of the weevils in roots that were artificially infested in the laboratory was compared with mortality in naturally infested roots from the field using two concentrations of one nematode (S. carpocapsae Mexican strain). In general, the heterorhabditid nematodes caused higher levels of mortality within the root than the steinernematids. Heterorhabditis sp. FL2122 strain killed the highest proportion of weevils in the shortest period of time. Similar differences among nematodes were seen in the inner portion (1/2 radius) of the storage roots, as well as in the outer portion. Although weevil mortality in the artificially infested roots was greater than in the naturally infested roots, the trends in mortality were similar; we observed increased mortality in the nematode treatments compared with the control and no difference in mortality between the two nematode concentrations.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1993MA89500013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3617</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of 10 Entomopathogenic Nematodes for Control of Sweet-Potato Weevil (Coleoptera, Apionidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1642</sp>
<op>1650</op>
<ab>Ten entomopathogenic nematode species or strains in the families Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae-Steinernema carpocapsae (Weiser), Agriotos, All, Breton, Italian, and Mexican strains; Steinernema feltiae (Filipjev), N27 strain; Steinernema intermedia (Poinar); Heterorhabditis bacteriophora, Poinar, HP88, and North Carolina strains; and an unidentified Heterorhabditis sp. FL2122 strain-were compared in the laboratory against the sweetpotato weevil, Cylas formicarius (F.). Although all nematodes tested could kill sweetpotato weevils, there were differences among the nematodes. Larval LC50s were low for most nematodes tested (&amp;lt;10 infective juveniles per insect). The heterorhabditid nematodes included the most virulent nematode (unidentified Heterorhabditis sp. FL2122 strain), and the least virulent nematode (H. bacteriophora North Carolina strain). Heterorhabditid nematodes were more pathogenic to pupae than were steinernematid nematodes. Weevil adults were the least susceptible stage to nematode infection. With the exception of S. carpocapsae All strain, adult mortality was &amp;lt;6% for all nematodes. Adult mortality by All strain ranged from 25 to 60% depending on the nematode concentration applied. Male weevils accounted for 96-100% of the adult mortality by All strain. Larval mortality from nematode infection increased significantly over a 4-d period for all nematodes with the exception of S. feltiae, which caused high mortality within 24 h. Heterorhabditid nematodes produced significantly more infective juveniles per cadaver than did steinernematid nematodes. The importance of these data for selecting suitable nematodes for biological control of the sweetpotato weevil is discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1992JQ98200017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3611</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>McLane,W.</a1>
<a1>Klein,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Moyseenko,J.</a1>
<a1>Oliver,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Cowan,D.</a1>
<t1>Management of early-instar Japanese beetle (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae) in field-grown nursery crops</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1151</sp>
<op>1161</op>
<ab>Numerous fleld studies were conducted in commercial nurseries in Tennessee from 1996 through 1999 to evaluate chemical and biological treatments, application timing and rates, and method of application for control of early instars of Japanese beetle, Popillia japonica Newman. Insecticide treatments included bifenthrin, bendiocarb, chlorpyrifos, carbaryl, fipronil, halofenozide, imidacloprid, permethrin, tefluthrin, thiamethoxam, and trichlorfon. Biological treatments included entomopathogenic nematodes (Heterorhabditis bacteriophora HP88 or H. marelatus), Bacillus thuringiensis Berliner subspecies japonensis Buibui strain, and Beauveria bassiana (Balsamo) Vuillemin, All treatments were applied on the soil surface or injected into the soil around the base of each tree. Tree type and size varied among and within tests, however, the sampling unit (61-cm-diameter root ball) remained the same throughout all tests. The biological treatments provided poor-to-moderate control (0-75%) of Japanese beetle larvae. Imidacloprid was the most frequently evaluated insecticide and achieved 91-100, 87-100, 83-100, and 41-100% control with applications in May, June, July, and August, respectively. Halofenozide treatments were not sig nificantly different from imiducloprid treatments with one exception. Halofenozide provided 60-87, 85-100, and 82-92 control with applications made in June, July, and August, respectively. Fipronil and thiamethoxam were evaluated to a lesser extent but both performed similarly to imidacloprid. Most other insecticide treatments were less successful in reducing numbers of Japanese beetle larvae and with few exceptions achieved &amp;lt; 50% control.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000171545000020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3612</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Winkler,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,D. I.</a1>
<a1>Gibb,T.</a1>
<t1>Interaction between halofenozide and the entomopathogenic nematode Heterorhabditis marelatus for control of Japanese beetle (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae) larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>48</sp>
<op>53</op>
<ab>Japanese beetle, Popillia japonica Newman is a major pest of turf and ornamentals. Laboratory bioassays were conducted to evaluate the potential interactions between a biological control agent, Heterorhabditis marelatus (Nematoda: Heterorhabditidae) IN strain and the insecticide halofenozide against both overwintered and nonoverwintered 3rd instars of Japanese beetle. Treatments consisted of all combinations of 2 rates of halofenozid with H. marelatus nematodes Imidacloprid was used as a standard. Percentage larval mortality was evaluated at 7, 14, and 21 d after treatment No deleterious effects were observed. The nematode treatments generally produced significantly greater larval mortality relative to both chemical treatments. Twenty-one clays after treatment, both rates of nematodes resulted in 100% mortality, whereas insecticide treatments did not surpass 60% mortality. No synergism was detected in any of the combination treatments. There were no significant differences in nematode reproduction in larvae exposed to halofenozide and nematodes versus larvae exposed to only nematodes.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000088598600009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3618</id>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,Richard K.</a1>
<t1>Movement and Postinfection Emergence of Entomopathogenic Nematodes from Sweetpotato Weevil, Cylas formicarius (F.) (Coleoptera: Apionidae)</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>297</sp>
<op>305</op>
<ab>Emergence and movement of five entomopathogenic nematode species [Steinernema carpocapsae (Weiser) All strain; S. feltiae (Filipjev) (= S. bibionis) N-27 strain; S. glaseri (Steiner); Heterorhabditis bacteriophora Poinar HP88 strain; Heterorhabditis sp. FL2122 strain (an undescribed nematode isolated in Florida)] from sweetpotato weevil cadavers, Cylas formicarius (F.), within sweet potato, Ipomoea batatas (L.) Lam., storage roots, was measured using a Galleria mellonella (L.) baiting technique. Weevil-infested storage roots were exposed to the nematodes and then buried in sand or soil in the laboratory and in the field. In both sand and soil environments (laboratory and field), all nematode species tested were recovered, with the heterorhabditid species causing more mortality of the bait insect than the steinernematid species. All nematode species were capable of moving horizontally at least 15 cm from the weevil cadavers within the swollen root in a soil environment in the laboratory. The heterorhabditid nematodes and to a lesser extent, S. feltiae and S. glaseri, were capable of locating and infecting weevils within swollen roots placed 15 cm away from the swollen root from which they exited. Steinernema carpocapsae was not capable of infecting weevils within these roots. All nematode species mentioned above and S. carpocapsae Mexican strain were applied to the field as a point-source inoculation and were recovered 60 cm horizontally from the point of application with the heterorhabditid nematodes and S. glaseri causing the most mortality of the bait insect. (c) 1992 Academic Press, Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000207173600007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3610</id>
<a1>Oliver,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<t1>Ambrosia beetle (Coleoptera : Scolytidae) species attacking chestnut and captured in ethanol-baited traps in middle Tennessee</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>909</sp>
<op>918</op>
<ab>Ambrosia beetles can be important pests of nursery production. The beetles are difficult to control with insecticides, requiring that pesticides be closely timed before tree attack, applied repeatedly, or have long residual activity. The goal of this project was to improve management decisions for ambrosia beetle control in nurseries. This study used ethanol-baited traps, field observations of tree attacks, and emergence cages over beetle galleries to determine the following: (1) composition of ambrosia beetle fauna in middle Tennessee, (2) species responsible for attacks on chestnut (Castanea mollissima Blume), a susceptible tree species, (3) timing of tree attacks and progeny emergence, and (4) the relationship between tree attacks, progeny emergence, and beetle collections in ethanol-baited traps. Ambrosia beetles were surveyed using ethanol-baited Lindgren traps at the Tennessee State University Nursery Crop Research Station in McMinnville, TN, and at two commercial nurseries near Dibrell and Tarlton, TN, during 1998 and 1999. At the Nursery Station, species composition of ambrosia beetles attacking chestnut trees was determined in 1999. Xyleborinus saxeseni Ratzeburg, Xylosandrus crassiusculus Motschulsky, and Monarthrum fasciatum Say were the dominant ambrosia beetle species collected in traps. Xyleborinus saxeseni was the dominant species at all three locations when both 1998 and 1999 collections were totaled. Other commonly trapped species included Monarthrum mali Fitch, Xyleborus atratus Eichhoff, and Xyleborus pelliculosus Eichhoff. Tree attacks began on 2 April before trees broke dormancy. The majority of chestnut attacks occurred in April and May. Progeny emerged from 48% of the caged galleries, including 35.9, 10.3, 3.3, and 1.1% X. germanus, X. crassiusculus, Hypothenemus spp., and X. saxeseni, respectively. Beetles exhibited several unusual behaviors during this study, including emergence of female X. germanus from trees the following spring, emergence of live male X. germanus and X. crassiusculus,a staggered chronology of progeny emergence, and presence of multiple beetle species emerging from the same gallery. Xylosandrus crassiusculus and X. germanus were the dominant species attacking chestnut, but total trap collections of X. germanus were small (less than or equal to 1.7%). Several findings from this study have significance to the nursery industry. The timing of peak trap collections during April (particularly collections of X. crassiusculus and X. saxeseni) coincided with peak tree attacks. The factors responsible for chestnut susceptibility to attack were not measured in this study, but since the majority of trees were attacked before dormancy break, tree phenological state probably is an important determinant of tree vulnerability. The collection of some species like X. germanus in trap collections may be a more important indicator of tree attack than abundance in the trap. Progeny emergence from chestnut trees during June and July did not coincide with increased trap collections or renewed attacks on chestnut. Therefore, traps may not always indicate ambrosia beetle abundance. Several new state records were collected during this study, including X. crasiusculus, a species capable of serious economic damage to nursery stock.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000171801700017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3609</id>
<a1>Oliver,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Klein,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Moyseenko,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Bishop,B.</a1>
<t1>Effect of insecticides on Tiphia vernalis (Hymenoptera : Tiphiidae) oviposition and survival of progeny to cocoon stage when parasitizing Popillia japonica (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae) larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>694</sp>
<op>703</op>
<ab>The effect of insecticides on oviposition of Tiphia vernalis Rohwer and subsequent survival of parasitoid progeny to the cocoon stage was determined in the laboratory by using larval Japanese beetle, Popillia japonica Newman, as the host. Insecticides tested were imidacloprid thiamethoxam, halofenozide, chlorpyrifos, and carbaryl at labeled rates. Female T. vernalis were allowed 2 d to parasitize P. japonica larvae after the parasitoids had received a 4-d exposure to insecticide-treated soil. Another group of female T. vernalis were allowed 2 d to parasitize P. japonica larvae that bad been exposed to insecticide-treated soil for 3-4 d. Percentage of parasitism of P. japonica larvae in these trials after exposure of adult parasitoids to carbaryl, chlorpyrifos, halofenozide, or imidacloprid-treated soil (23.3-50.0%) or adult parasitoids to chlorpyrifos, halofenozide, or imidacloprid-treated grubs (33.0-56.7%) was not negatively affected relative to the control treatment (21.7-54.2%). A third group of adult T. vernalis and P. japonica larvae were simultaneously exposed to chlorpyrifos or carbaryl treatments. Percentage parasitism in these trials was lower for T. vernalis adults exposed to the chlorpyrifos and carbaryl (15.0-25.0%) relative to the control (57.5-62.5%) with the exception of one trial with carbaryl (40.0%). However, exposure of the parasitoid and P. japonica to chlorpyrifos 0.5X, carbaryl 0.5X, imidacloprid, halofenozide, or thiamethoxam in several trials resulted in parasitism that was equivalent or greater than (45.0-80.0%) the untreated control (57.5-62.5%). Japanese beetle larval mortality in these trials was greater in the insecticide and parasitoid combination (97.5-100.0%) than with insecticides alone (45.0-100.0%). Percentage of survival of T. vernalis progeny to the cocoon stage was not negatively affected by a 4-d adult parasitoid exposure to carbaryl and chlorpyrifos treated soil (11.7-16.7% versus 18.3% control) or a 2-d exposure to P. japonica-treated larvae (16.7-18.3% versus 28.3% control). However, simultaneous exposure of T. vernalis progeny and P. japonica larvae to chlorpyrifos- and carbaryl-treated soil resulted in no parasitoids surviving to the cocoon stage. Between neonicotinoids, thiamethoxam had more adverse impact on percentage parasitism (52.5%) and survival to the cocoon stage (10.0%) than imidacloprid (80.0 and 32.5%, respectively). Results of this study indicate soil incorporation of imidacloprid and halofenozide had minimal effect on the number of P. japonica. larvae parasitized by T. vernalis or survival of T. vernalis progeny to the cocoon stage; therefore, they are more suitable for use with T. vernalis. In contrast, chlorpyrifos, carbaryl, and thiamethoxam lowered the number of T. vernalis progeny surviving to the cocoon stage, and carbaryl and chlorpyrifos reduced the number of P. japonica larvae parasitized. The soil incorporation of insecticides is discussed as one explanation for the minimal effects of some insecticides on T. vernalis.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000229652600010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3608</id>
<a1>Oliver,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Reding,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Moyseenko,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Klein,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Bishop,B.</a1>
<t1>Survival of adult Tiphia vernalis (Hymenoptera : Tiphiidae) after insecticide, fungicide, and herbicide exposure in laboratory bioassays</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>288</sp>
<op>294</op>
<ab>Tiphia vernalis Rohwer is a hymenopteran ectoparasitoid of Japanese beetle, Popillia japonica Newman, larvae. The adult wasps feed on nectar or honeydew between mid-April and late June. Adults may contact pesticides when landing on foliage or when females hunt for grubs in the soil. The lethal effect of nursery, turf, and landscape pesticides was determined by exposing wasps to treated foliage in the laboratory. Pesticides tested at labeled rates were the insecticides bifenthrin, carbaryl, chlorpyrifos, halofenozide, and imidacloprid; the herbicides oryzalin, pendimethalin, and a combination product with 2,4-D, dicamba, and mecoprop (multiherbicide); and the fungicides chlorothalonil and thiophanate-methyl. During 2001 and 2002, male and female T. vernalis were exposed to pesticides by using turf cores. For both years, bifenthrin, chlorpyrifos, and imidacloprid treatments lowered adult survival relative to the control, but halofenozide had minimal effect on mortality of males and females. More males than females died after exposure to carbaryl treatments. Survival of females was not reduced by exposure to herbicides or fungicides. Females were apparently more tolerant of pesticides than males. Mortality of males in response to herbicides and fungicides was more variable than for females; in 2002 trials, male mortality was higher after exposure to multiherbicide, oryzalin, pendimethalin, and thiophanate-methyl than the control. The fungicide chlorothalonil did not increase mortality of males or females in either year. Sublethal effects were not evaluated. The study indicates the choice of pesticide may be important for conserving T. vernalis in nursery, landscape, and turf settings.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000236813800005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3604</id>
<a1>Oliver,Jason B.</a1>
<a1>Reding,Michael E.</a1>
<a1>Klein,Michael G.</a1>
<a1>Youssef,Nadeer N.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catharine M.</a1>
<a1>Bishop,Bert</a1>
<a1>James,Shannon S.</a1>
<a1>Callcott,Anne-Marie</a1>
<t1>Chlorpyrifos immersion to eliminate third instars of Japanese beetle (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae) in balled and burlapped trees and subsequent treatment effects on red maple</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>307</sp>
<op>314</op>
<ab>This study examined chlorpyrifos immersion of balled and burlapped (B&amp;amp;B) nursery trees for elimination of third instars of Japanese beetle, Popillia japonica Newman (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae), and for phytotoxicity on red maple, Acer rubrum L. Trees were harvested as 45- and 60-cm-diameter B&amp;amp;B and immersed in chlorpyrifos at U.S. Domestic Japanese Beetle Harmonization Plan rate (0.24 kg active ingredient [AI]/100 liters) or lower rates of 0.015, 0.03, 0.06, and 0.12 kg (AI)/100 liters. The 0.03, 0.06, and 0.24 kg (AI) rates provided 100% control of Japanese beetle grubs in both 45- and 60-cm B&amp;amp;B. The 0.015 and 0.12 kg (AI) chlorpyrifos rates were 100% effective in three tests. However, in another test, 0.015 and 0.12 kg (AI) chlorpyrifos treatments had four (93% control) and one (98% control) grubs recovered, respectively. Root ball soils consisted of loam, silt loam, or clay loam texture classifications. Trunk diameter and internode growth of red maple harvested as 45-cm B&amp;amp;B decreased linearly with increasing chlorpyrifos dip rate during the first year, but effects were unapparent in the second year. Chlorpyrifos rates had no measurable impact on growth of red maples harvested as 60-cm B&amp;amp;B. No visual phytotoxicity symptoms were detected for chlorpyrifos rate or root ball size treatments. In conclusion, results support lowering the U.S. Domestic Japanese Beetle Harmonization Plan chlorpyrifos dip rate for category 2 states to at least 0.03 kg (AI) for B&amp;amp;B diameters :560 cm. Chlorpyrifos rates &amp;lt; 0.24 kg (AI) will lower cost, reduce worker exposure, and lessen potential environmental contamination.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000245454700009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3607</id>
<a1>Pena,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Ulmer,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Halbert,S. E.</a1>
<t1>Jackfruit, Artocarpus heterophylus, is not a host of Diaphorina citri (Homoptera : Psyllidae) in Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>412</sp>
<op>413</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000240526900022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3605</id>
<a1>Robbins,Paul S.</a1>
<a1>Alm,Steven R.</a1>
<a1>Armstrong,Charles D.</a1>
<a1>Averill,Anne L.</a1>
<a1>Baker,Thomas C.</a1>
<a1>Bauernfiend,Robert J.</a1>
<a1>Baxendale,Frederick P.</a1>
<a1>Braman,S. Kris</a1>
<a1>Brandenburg,Rick L.</a1>
<a1>Cash,Daniel B.</a1>
<a1>Couch,Gary J.</a1>
<a1>Cowles,Richard S.</a1>
<a1>Crocker,Robert L.</a1>
<a1>DeLamar,Zandra D.</a1>
<a1>Dittl,Timothy G.</a1>
<a1>Fitzpatrick,Sheila M.</a1>
<a1>Flanders,Kathy L.</a1>
<a1>Forgatsch,Tom</a1>
<a1>Gibb,Timothy J.</a1>
<a1>Gill,Bruce D.</a1>
<a1>Gilrein,Daniel O.</a1>
<a1>Gorsuch,Clyde S.</a1>
<a1>Hammond,Abner M.</a1>
<a1>Hastings,Patricia D.</a1>
<a1>Held,David W.</a1>
<a1>Heller,Paul R.</a1>
<a1>Hiskes,Rose T.</a1>
<a1>Holliman,James L.</a1>
<a1>Hudson,William G.</a1>
<a1>Klein,Michael G.</a1>
<a1>Krischik,Vera L.</a1>
<a1>Lee,David J.</a1>
<a1>Linn,Charles E., Jr.</a1>
<a1>Luce,Nancy J.</a1>
<a1>MacKenzie,Kenna E.</a1>
<a1>Mannion,Catherine M.</a1>
<a1>Polavarapu,Sridhar</a1>
<a1>Potter,Daniel A.</a1>
<a1>Roelofs,Wendell L.</a1>
<a1>Royals,Brian M.</a1>
<a1>Salsbury,Glenn A.</a1>
<a1>Schiff,Nathan M.</a1>
<a1>Shetlar,David J.</a1>
<a1>Skinner,Margaret</a1>
<a1>Sparks,Beverly L.</a1>
<a1>Sutschek,Jessica A.</a1>
<a1>Sutschek,Timothy P.</a1>
<a1>Swier,Stanley R.</a1>
<a1>Sylvia,Martha M.</a1>
<a1>Vickers,Neil J.</a1>
<a1>Vittum,Patricia J.</a1>
<a1>Weidman,Richard</a1>
<a1>Weber,Donald C.</a1>
<a1>Williamson,R. Chris</a1>
<a1>Villani,Michael G.</a1>
<t1>Trapping Phyllophaga spp. (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae : Melolonthinae) in the United States and Canada using sex attractants</t1>
<jf>Journal of Insect Science</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Sci.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>NOV 15</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<sp>39</sp>
<op>39</op>
<ab>The sex pheromone of the scarab beetle, Phyllophaga anxia, is a blend of the methyl esters of two amino acids, L-valine and L-isoleucine. A field trapping study was conducted, deploying different blends of the two compounds at 59 locations in the United States and Canada. More than 57,000 males of 61 Phyllophaga species ( Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Melolonthinae) were captured and identified. Three major findings included: ( 1) widespread use of the two compounds [ of the 147 Phyllophaga ( sensu stricto) species found in the United States and Canada, males of nearly 40% were captured]; ( 2) in most species intraspecific male response to the pheromone blends was stable between years and over geography; and ( 3) an unusual pheromone polymorphism was described from P. anxia. Populations at some locations were captured with L-valine methyl ester alone, whereas populations at other locations were captured with L-isoleucine methyl ester alone. At additional locations, the L-valine methyl ester-responding populations and the L-isoleucine methyl ester-responding populations were both present, producing a bimodal capture curve. In southeastern Massachusetts and in Rhode Island, in the United States, P. anxia males were captured with blends of L-valine methyl ester and L-isoleucine methyl ester.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1536-2442</sn>
<an>000243274200001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
