
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2498</id>
<a1>Abbas,M. S. T.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Interaction between Nuclear Polyhedrosis Virus-Infected Anticarsia-Gematalis (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) Larvae and Predator Podisus-Maculiventris (Say) (Hemiptera, Pentatomidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>599</sp>
<op>602</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1984ST28600049</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2398</id>
<a1>Abd-Alla,Adly M. M.</a1>
<a1>Vlak,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Bergoin,M.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Parker,A.</a1>
<a1>Burand,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Jehle,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>ICTV</a1>
<t1>Hytrosaviridae: a proposal for classification and nomenclature of a new insect virus family</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>154</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>909</sp>
<op>918</op>
<ab>Salivary gland hypertrophy viruses (SGHVs) have been identified from different dipteran species, such as the tsetse fly Glossina pallidipes (GpSGHV), the housefly Musca domestica (MdSGHV) and the narcissus bulbfly Merodon equestris (MeSGHV). These viruses share the following characteristics: (i) they produce non-occluded, enveloped, rod-shaped virions that measure 500-1,000 nm in length and 50-100 nm in diameter; (ii) they possess a large circular double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) genome ranging in size from 120 to 190 kbp and having G + C ratios ranging from 28 to 44%; (iii) they cause overt salivary gland hypertrophy (SGH) symptoms in dipteran adults and partial to complete sterility. The available information on the complete genome sequence of GpSGHV and MdSGHV indicates significant co-linearity between the two viral genomes, whereas no co-linearity was observed with baculoviruses, ascoviruses, entomopoxviruses, iridoviruses and nudiviruses, other large invertebrate DNA viruses. The DNA polymerases encoded by the SGHVs are of the type B and closely related, but they are phylogenetically distant from DNA polymerases encoded by other large dsDNA viruses. The great majority of SGHV ORFs could not be assigned by sequence comparison. Phylogenetic analysis of conserved genes clustered both SGHVs, but distantly from the nudiviruses and baculoviruses. On the basis of the available morphological, (patho)biological, genomic and phylogenetic data, we propose that the two viruses are members of a new virus family named Hytrosaviridae. This proposed family currently comprises two unassigned species, G. pallidipes salivary gland hypertrophy virus and M. domestica salivary gland hypertrophy virus, and a tentative unassigned species, M. equestris salivary gland hypertrophy virus. Here, we present the characteristics and the justification for establishing this new virus family.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0304-8608</sn>
<an>000267028500001</an>
<do>10.1007/s00705-009-0398-5</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2404</id>
<a1>Benda,Nicole D.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion</a1>
<a1>Torto,Baldwyn</a1>
<a1>Teal,Peter</a1>
<t1>Detection and characterization of Kodamaea ohmeri associated with small hive beetle Aethina tumida infesting honey bee hives</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>194</sp>
<op>201</op>
<ab>Honey bee colony infestation by the small hive beetle (SHB) is associated with fermentation of hive materials. Pollen, beetles, and robbing bees (ten of each) were collected from hives infested with SHB in both Florida and Kenya. Plating of homogenized bodies of beetles and bees and comb swabs resulted in smooth cream-colored yeast colonies that formed pseudomycelial cells as they aged. Fatty acid profiles of yeast isolates from Florida and Kenya most closely matched the profiles of Candida krusei and C. sake, respectively. However the DNA sequence of the 28S and 5.8S-ITS2 of both the Florida and Kenya isolates were, 99-100 % homologous to Kodamaea ohmeri. The ITS1 region differed between the two geographic strains. The two strains produced similar volatile profiles which were attractive to SHB and contained compounds also found in honey bee alarm pheromone.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000258938700007</an>
<do>10.3827/IBRA.1.47.3.07</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2429</id>
<a1>Blaske,V. U.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Helicosporidium spp. (Chlorophyta : Trebouxiophyceae) infection on the development and survival of three noctuid species</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>54</sp>
<op>61</op>
<ab>A new Helicosporidium spp. isolate recently purified from an aquatic weevil, Cyrtobagus salviniae Calder &amp;amp; Sands, was capable of infecting and reproducing in three heterologous noctuid hosts. Regardless of host species, oral treatment of Heliocoverpa zea (Boddie), Spodoptera exigua (Hubner), or Trichoplusia ni (Hubner) early instars with cyst preparations of Helicosporidium spp. resulted in approximate to50% infection of the challenged larvae. The sex ratio did not differ between infected and control groups, suggesting the existence of a natural, nonsex-related resistance to the disease. Injection of Helicosporidium spp. into the hemocoels of late instars resulted in virtually 100% infection, indicating that resistance is related to the ingestion of the pathogen and therefore affiliated with midgut-mediated barriers. The pathogen&amp;#39;s development was not interrupted by metamorphosis; likewise, the infection did not necessarily interrupt the insects&amp;#39; development. When treated as early instars, 50-90% of the infected larvae formed pupae, of which 20-30% emerged as adults. However, a high proportion of the infected adults (62-86%) had malformed wings, and their longevity was reduced compared with that of healthy adults. Infected S. exigua adults that seemed to be morphologically healthy were able to mate and produce viable offspring. The disease was detected in five of 12 groups of progeny produced by infected adults. However, the relative infection rate in the filial generation was low (2-5%). To our knowledge, this is the first evidence for a vertical transmission of helicosporidial infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000189311200007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2420</id>
<a1>Blaske-Lietze,V. U.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Pathogenesis of Helicosporidium sp (Chlorophyta : Trebouxiophyceae) in susceptible noctuid larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>161</sp>
<op>168</op>
<ab>Helicosporidium sp. is a unique, achlorophyllous green alga that has been reported to infect various insect orders, including Lepidoptera, Diptera, and Coleoptera. The infectious cyst stage is ingested by the host, ruptures in the midgut lumen, and releases a filamentous cell. Histopathological examinations using larvae of a susceptible noctuid host, Spodoptera exigua, showed both cysts and filamentous cells affiliated with the microvillar lining of the midgut epithelium. A considerable proportion of the ingested cysts (22-39%) were recovered in feces collected 24h after ingestion. A small number of filamentous cells passed the midgut epithelium and entered the hemocoel within 4-24 h after cyst ingestion. After 48 h, vegetative cell stages were detected in the hemolymph followed by a 4- to 5-day period of increasing multiplication. Cyst differentiation in the colonized hemolymph began 6-7 days after the treatment. (c) 2005 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000233916900003</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2005.09.002</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2417</id>
<a1>Blaske-Lietze,V. U.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Denton,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Botts,M.</a1>
<a1>Becnel,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Development of the insect pathogenic alga Helicosporidium</t1>
<jf>Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Eukaryot.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>MAY-JUN</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>165</sp>
<op>176</op>
<ab>This study examined the morphogenesis and replication dynamics of the different life stages (cysts, filamentous cells, vegetative cells) of Helicosporidium sp., a non-photosynthetic, entomopathogenic alga. The isolate (SjHe) used originated from an infected black fly larva. Filamentous cell transformation into vegetative cells and autosporulation during vegetative cell replication were observed under controlled in vitro conditions. The transformation process was initiated by a partial swelling of the filamentous cell along with the reorganization of the nuclear material. Two subsequent nuclear and cell divisions resulted in the release of 4 rod-shaped daughter cells, which divided into oval to spherical vegetative cells. These underwent several cycles of autosporogenic cell division. Multiple-passaged vegetative cell cultures formed non-motile, adherent cell clusters (palmelloid colonies). Vegetative replication dynamics were also observed in 2 experimental noctuid hosts, Spodoptera exigua and Helicoverpa zea. The average density of helicosporidial cells produced per microliter hemolymph exceeded cell concentrations obtained in vitro by 15- and 46-fold in S. exigua and H. zea, respectively. Cyst morphogenesis was only observed in the hemolymph, whereas no cysts differentiated at various in vitro conditions.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1066-5234</sn>
<an>000237182600002</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1550-7408.2006.00090.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2439</id>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<a1>Stokes,G.</a1>
<a1>Suazo,A.</a1>
<a1>Funderburk,J.</a1>
<t1>AFLP analysis of the entomopathogen Nomuraea rileyi</t1>
<jf>Mycologia</jf>
<jo>Mycologia</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>JUL-AUG</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>638</sp>
<op>648</op>
<ab>The dimorphic, asexual entomopathogen Nomuraea rileyi is a well known mortality agent of noctuid insects in subtropical and temperate agricultural systems. Genomic DNA was extracted from N. rileyi isolates collected from Anticarsia gemmatalis velvetbean caterpillar in Florida, Brazil, and Argentina as well as from non-Anticarsia hosts and subjected to a modified single-step AFLP analysis. Compared to RAPDs, the employed AFLP method provided a reliable and sensitive method for detecting genomic differences among N. rileyi populations. All ten AFLP primers produced polymorphic bands when used to amplify the different Nomuraea DNA samples. Approximately 65% (141 bands) of the total scorable bands (216) detected with ethidium bromide were polymorphic and ranged 400-3000 bp. A total of 43 haplotypes were found among the 73 N. rileyi isolates. Analysis of the AFLP data revealed extensive polymorphism among different N. rileyi isolates derived from both homologous and heterologous noctuid host species. For example, the dominant haplotype isolated from the Florida A. gemmatalis population was detected in diseased Pseudoplusia includens soybean looper and Plathypena scabra green cloverworm. Cluster analysis demonstrated that the AFLP polymorphisms observed among the N. rileyi isolates were associated with geographical location and/or with local insect population(s). Examination of this entomopathogen from a single field over a multiseasonal time frame demonstrated that the N. rileyi population is stable and can probably overwinter and initiate the disease cycle the following year.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-5514</sn>
<an>000088424000005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2445</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Imidacloprid - Chemical synergist for microbial control agents of termites.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of Papers of the American Chemical Society</jf>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>AUG 25</fd>
<vo>212</vo>
<sp>19</sp>
<op>AGRO</op>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 1</no>
<sn>0065-7727</sn>
<an>A1996VA91500155</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2486</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Abbas,M. S. T.</a1>
<a1>Rathbone,L.</a1>
<a1>Hostettler,N.</a1>
<t1>Predators as Potential Dispersal Agents of the Nuclear Polyhedrosis-Virus of Anticarsia Gemmatalis [Lep, Noctuidae] in Soybean</t1>
<jf>Entomophaga</jf>
<jo>Entomophaga</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>108</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8959</sn>
<an>A1987H369700011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2437</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Becnel,J. J.</a1>
<a1>White,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Bott,M.</a1>
<t1>In vivo and in vitro development of the protist Helicosporidium sp.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Eukaryot.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>JUL-AUG</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>460</sp>
<op>470</op>
<ab>We describe the discovery and developmental features of a Helicosporidium sp. isolated from the black fly Simulium jonesi. Morphologically, the helicosporidia are characterized by a distinct cyst stage that encloses three ovoid cells and a single elongate filamentous cell. Bioassays have demonstrated that the cysts of this isolate infect various insect species, including the lepidopterans, Helicoverpa zea, Galleria mellonella, and Manduca sexta, and the dipterans, Musca domestica, Aedes taeniorhynchus, Anopheles albimanus, and An. quadrimaculatus. The cysts attach to the insect peritrophic matrix prior to dehiscence, which releases the filamentous cell and the three ovoid cells. The ovoid cells are short-lived in the insect gut with infection mediated by the penetration of the filamentous cell into the host. Furthermore. these filamentous cells are covered with projections that anchor them to the midgut lining. Unlike most entomopathogenic protozoa, this Helicosporidium sp. can be propagated in simple nutritional media under defined in vitro conditions, providing a system to conduct detailed analysis of the developmental biology of this poorly known taxon. The morphology and development of the in vitro produced cells are similar to that reported for the achorophyllic algae belonging to the genus Prototheca.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1066-5234</sn>
<an>000169799400008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2500</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Bradford,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Barfield,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of the Velvetbean Caterpillar and Soybean Looper (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) to Nomuraea-Rileyi - Effects of Pathotype, Dosage, Temperature, and Host Age</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>253</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1984SL88100053</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2502</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Brasaemle,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Nation,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Lipid-Composition of the Entomopathogenic Fungus Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>254</sp>
<op>258</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1984SG55700016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2491</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Cherry,R. H.</a1>
<a1>Anderson,D. L.</a1>
<t1>Incidence of Bacillus-Popilliae in Ligyrus-Subtropicus and Cyclocephala-Parallela (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae) in Florida Sugarcane Fields</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>703</sp>
<op>705</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1986C744100046</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2441</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Farmerie,W. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Cloning and sequencing of cDNA of the insecticidal toxin Hirsutellin A</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>258</sp>
<op>261</op>
<ab>The hyphomycete Hirsutella thompsonii produces an extracellular insecticidal protein, Hirsutellin A. This basic protein, cytolytic against insect cells and capable of inhibiting protein translation, possesses biological features similar to the well-characterized ribosomal-inhibiting proteins (RIPs) alpha-sarcin, mitogellin, and restrictocin. Cloning and DNA sequencing analysis of the 3&amp;#39; and 5&amp;#39; RACE products of HtA cDNA identifies a consensus DNA sequence which encompasses the complete open reading frame of the HtA gene. This gene codes for a precursor of 164 aa which includes a 34-aa leader sequence. The leader sequence of HtA, like those found in RIPs, contains a signal and a pro sequence. The mature 130-aa HtA, having a calculated M-r = 14,159 and pI = 9.21, is considered a stable hydrophilic protein. HtA does not possess the characteristic RNase motif of fungal RIPs but does possess a series of consensus phosphorylation and myristoylation sites and a putative ATP/GTP binding site. The sequence of HtA is unique and does not produce the secondary or tertiary structures characteristic of other fungal RIPs. (C) 1998 Academic Press.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000076835800011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2458</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Mazet,I.</a1>
<a1>Azbell,J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of the Fungal Pathogen, Beauveria-Bassiana, on the Lysozyme Activity in Spodoptera-Exigua Larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of insect physiology</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>385</sp>
<op>391</op>
<ab>The beet armyworm, Spodoptera exigua, injected with the bacterial endotoxin (LPS), can be induced to produce relatively high titer (approx. 1 mg lysozyme/ml) of lysozyme activity. This enzyme, like other insect lysozyme is heat stable under acid conditions and has a M(r) of 15 kDa. Infection of S. exigua by Beauveria Bassiana, disrupts the host cellular defense but does not induce lysozyme activity nor interfere with the ability of S. exigua to synthesize lysozyme in response to LPS challenge. The S. exigua humoral components induced by LPS challenge, although possessing antibacterial activity, do not have any observable effect on the in vivo development of B. bassiana.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-1910</sn>
<an>A1994NL09500003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2517</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Allen,G. E.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Host Age, Virus Dosage, and Temperature on the Infectivity of a Nucleopolyhedrosis Virus Against Velvetbean Caterpillar, Anticarsia-Gemmatalis, Larvae</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>59</sp>
<op>61</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1980JF83800016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2482</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Nonspecific Induction of Germination of Conidiobolus-Obscurus and Nomuraea-Rileyi with Host and Non-Host Cuticle Extracts</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>51</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>168</sp>
<op>171</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1988M166400013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2475</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of a Non-Occluded Baculovirus (Subgroup-C) from the Field Cricket, Gryllus-Rubens</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>106</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>93</sp>
<op>102</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0304-8608</sn>
<an>A1989AL45500009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2483</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of an Iridovirus Isolated from the Southern Mole Cricket, Scapteriscus-Vicinus</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>238</sp>
<op>245</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1987K690200010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2452</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Mazet,I.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J.</a1>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<t1>Comparative-Analysis of the In-Vivo and In-Vitro Metabolites Produced by the Entomopathogen Beauveria-Bassiana</t1>
<jf>Canadian Journal of Botany-Revue Canadienne De Botanique</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>73</vo>
<sp>S1092</sp>
<op>S1099</op>
<ab>Beauveria bassiana, like other insect mycopathogens, has evolved mechanisms to penetrate the insect exoskeleton via germ tubes and to replicate in the host hemocoel. Our initial studies have shown that biologically active metabolites released in the hemolymph during the vegetative growth phase of B. bassiana disrupt the host immune response and metamorphosis. These components cause an immediate reduction in filopodial-producing hemocytes and an increase in the level of serum phenoloxidase. Radiolabeling of tissues explanted from healthy versus infected larvae has demonstrated both the induction and repression of polypeptides in B. bassiana infected hemolymph. None of the polypeptides detected with S-35 pulse labeling were responsible for the cytotoxic and insecticidal activities detected in infected hemolymph. Western blots of SDS gels containing chromatographic fractions from healthy and infected sera probed with both antibodies against B. bassiana cell homogenates and culture filtrates contained a complex of antigens. The results of lectin labeling and sodium periodate treatments suggested that carbohydrates were the major epitopes being recognized by both monoclonal and polyclonal probes.</ab>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. 1 E-H</no>
<sn>0008-4026</sn>
<an>A1995TC46300057</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2510</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Joslyn,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Isoenzyme Differentiation among 17-Geographical Isolates of Hirsutella-Thompsonii</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>329</sp>
<op>337</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1982NP94300009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2516</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Comparative-Analysis of the Alkali-Liberated Components of the Hyphantria-Cunea and the Diacrisia-Virginica Granulosis Viruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>264</sp>
<op>272</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1980KM49200015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2520</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Cytoplasmic Polyhedrosis-Virus Isolated from Banded Woolly Bear, Isia-Isabella</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>131</sp>
<op>133</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1978EG76900021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2519</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Scanning Electron-Microscope Study of Hyphantria-Cunea Cpv-Infected Midgut Tissue</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>229</sp>
<op>233</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1978FT17300018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2518</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Hyphantria-Cunea Infected with Diacrisia Granulosis Virus to its Homologous Baculoviruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>341</sp>
<op>347</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1978GB86600014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2522</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Granulosis Virus from Diacrisia-Virginica (Lepidoptera-Arctiidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>434</sp>
<op>435</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1977EB54500022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2523</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Interinstar Susceptibility of Fall Webworm, Hyphantria-Cunea, to its Nucleopolyhedrosis and Granulosis Viruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>68</sp>
<op>75</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1977DK66000009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2521</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nordin,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Hyphantria-Cunea to a Granulosis Virus Isolated from Diacrisia-Virginica</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>377</sp>
<op>380</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1977EB54500014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2464</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>The Galactose Binding Lectin from the Beet Armyworm, Spodoptera-Exigua - Distribution and Site of Synthesis</t1>
<jf>Insect biochemistry and molecular biology</jf>
<jo>Insect Biochem.Mol.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>233</sp>
<op>242</op>
<ab>The Spodoptera exigua galactose binding lectin, extracted from hemolymph by affinity chromatography, was comprised of large molecular weight aggregates (100-700 kDa). SDS-PAGE of this lectin preparation revealed it to contain 2 subunits of 33.2 and 34.4 kDa in equimolar concentrations. These subunits had similar amino acid profiles, possessed identical N-terminal sequences and reacted equally to a bank of antilectin monoclonal antibodies. By staining Western blots with various lectin conjugate probes, we demonstrated that the 34.4 kDa subunit contains complex mannose residues, suggesting that this subunit is the glycosylated form of the 33.2 kDa subunit. The N-terminal sequence of the S. exigua lectin was distinct from other invertebrate galactose binding lectins. Light microscopy in combination with immunoelectron microscopy was used to localize the S. exigua lectin in the granules of the granulocyte class of hemocytes. Degranulation of these cells resulted in the release of the lectin. Isotope incorporation studies followed by immunoprecipitation with a S. exigua monoclonal antibody demonstrated that the fat body was the major site of lectin synthesis. Similar studies with hemocyte monolayers did not result in the production of detectable levels of S-35-labeled S. exigua lectin.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0965-1748</sn>
<an>A1993KV20200004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2487</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Detection of Protease Inhibitors in the Hemolymph of Resistant Anticarsia-Gemmatalis which are Inhibitory to the Entomopathogenic Fungus, Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Experientia</jf>
<jo>Experientia</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>MAR 15</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>336</sp>
<op>339</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0014-4754</sn>
<an>A1987G802000033</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2504</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Nutritional-Requirements for Conidial Germination of several Host Range Pathotypes of the Entomopathogenic Fungus Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>288</sp>
<op>292</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1984SG55700024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2511</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructural Studies on the Fungus, Nomuraea-Rileyi, Infecting the Velvetbean Caterpillar, Anticarsia-Gemmatalis</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>338</sp>
<op>345</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1982NP94300010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2479</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Nonspecific Factors Involved in Attachment of Entomopathogenic Deuteromycetes to Host Insect Cuticle</t1>
<jf>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1795</sp>
<op>1805</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0099-2240</sn>
<an>A1988P186700028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2512</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Schoborg,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Allen,G. E.</a1>
<t1>The Relative Susceptibility of 6 Noctuid Species to Infection by Nomuraea-Rileyi Isolated from Anticarsa-Gemmatalis</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>238</sp>
<op>240</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1982NG98100017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2438</id>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Tigano,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Sosa-Gomez,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Glare,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Inglis,P. W.</a1>
<t1>Genotypic properties of the entomopathogenic fungus Nomuraea rileyi</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>124</sp>
<op>138</op>
<ab>The dimorphic entomopathogenic fungus Nomuraea rileyi, an important biological control agent of various noctuid defoliators, is known to regulate Anticarsia gemmatalis, the key soybean pest in South America and the southeastern United States. At present, very little is known about the isolates that are associated with the endemic or epizootic phases of this disease agent. The development of molecular markers capable of delineating N. rileyi pathotypes is essential for such an analysis. In this study, various molecular techniques, including internal transcribed spacer (ITS) sequence analysis, randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD), amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP), and telomeric fingerprinting methods, were employed to identify genotypes. Analysis of the ITS-5.8s and 28s regions of N. rileyi isolates suggested that this species was more closely related to Metarhizium anisopliae and M. flavoviride than to Nomuraea atypicola and N. anemonoides. These findings and comparisons with other studies suggest that the systematics of the genus Nomuraea needs reexamination. Analysis of the telomeric fingerprinting, RAPD, and AFLP data produced very similar associations among different Nomuraea. In all cases, the non-rileyi isolates (N. anemonoides and N. atypicola) appeared unrelated to the N. rileyi. The N. rileyi isolates, mainly isolated from A. gemmatalis, were grouped into two clusters: one contained the Florida isolates and the other consisted of a diffuse group of South American isolates. Calculated genetic distances among the different N. rileyi isolates corresponded to geographical isolation. (C) 2000 Academic Press.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000089920000004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2414</id>
<a1>Boucias,Drion Garth</a1>
<a1>Scharf,Dansia W.</a1>
<a1>Breaux,Samuel E.</a1>
<a1>Purcell,Dusty H.</a1>
<a1>Mizell,Russell E.</a1>
<t1>Studies on the fungi associated with the glassy-winged sharpshooter Homalodisca coagulata with emphasis on a new species Hirsutella homalodiscae nom. prov.</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>231</sp>
<op>258</op>
<ab>The glassy-winged sharpshooter (GWSS), Homalodisca coagulata (Say), is an efficient vector of the phytopathogenic bacterium Xyllela fastidiosa. Native to the Southeast US, it was introduced to California, where its presence has caused a sharp increase in X. fastidiosa-based disease. Here are described three fungi associated with GWSS in its native range, including a Hirsutella species that is the predominant mycopathogen detected in sampled GWSS populations. Also described are potentially novel species of Pseudogibellula and Sporothrix. Data garnered from examination of in situ and in vitro morphological characters were compared to published keys and type specimen descriptions to achieve morphology-based identification. ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 and partial sequences of the large subunit (LSU)-rDNA, actin, and beta-tubulin genes of several GWSS Hirsutella isolates were sequenced and analyzed. Phylogenetic analysis of the LSU-rDNA and tubulin of the GWSS Hirsutella in combination with sequence data generated from other Hirsutella species defined the GWSS isolates to belong to subgroup II within this genus. The combination of phenotypic and genotypic data demonstrated GWSS Hirsutella to be a new species and as such, has been designated Hirsutella homalodiscae nom. prov. Species-specific PCR primers, designed from intron and exon regions of the actin and tubulin genes, were used in a multiplex reaction for the in situ identification of H. homalodiscae. A total of 246 mummified GWSS collected from sites in the southeastern US were subjected to multiplex PCR analysis. More than 70% of these samples tested positive for the presence of H. homalodiscae demonstrating it to be the major mycopathogen distributed throughout the native range of GWSS.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>000244684300006</an>
<do>10.1007/s10526-006-9019-3</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2506</id>
<a1>Buckingham,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<a1>Theriot,R. F.</a1>
<t1>Reintroduction of the Alligatorweed Flea Beetle (Agasicles-Hygrophila Selman and Vogt) into the United-States from Argentina</t1>
<jf>Journal of Aquatic Plant Management</jf>
<jo>J.Aquat.Plant Manage.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>101</sp>
<op>102</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0146-6623</sn>
<an>A1983RP54400014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2474</id>
<a1>Cherry,R. H.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Incidence of Bacillus-Popilliae in Different Life Stages of Florida Sugarcane Grubs (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Entomological Science</jf>
<jo>J.Entomol.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>526</sp>
<op>530</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0749-8004</sn>
<an>A1989CA73100018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2416</id>
<a1>Cho,Eun-Min</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion</a1>
<a1>Keyhani,Nennat O.</a1>
<t1>EST analysis of cDNA libraries from the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria (Cordyceps) bassiana. II. Fungal cells sporulating on chitin and producing oosporein</t1>
<jf>Microbiology-Sgm</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>152</vo>
<sp>2855</sp>
<op>2864</op>
<ab>In the accompanying paper [Cho, E.-M., Liu, L., Farmerie, W. &amp;amp; Keyhani, N. O. (2006). Microbiology 152, 2843-2854], the analysis of expressed sequence tag (EST) libraries derived from homogeneous single-cell populations of aerial conidia, in vitro blastospores and submerged conidia of the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria (Cordyceps) bassiana has been reported. Here an extended EST analysis is presented of complex cell mixtures derived from fungal cells sporulating on chitin or grown under culture conditions inducing the production of the B. bassiana secondary metabolite, oosporein. Fungal material used for the construction of the libraries included germinating conidia and blastospores, mycelia, as well as cells in various developmental stages. Approximately 2500 5&amp;#39; end sequences were determined from random sequencing of clones from each library, and were clustered into 277 contigs with 1069 singlets, and 306 contigs with 1064 singlets, for the chitin and oosporein libraries, respectively. Almost half (45-50%) of the sequences in each library displayed either no significant similarity (e value &amp;gt; 10(-4)) or similarity to hypothetical proteins found in the NCBI database. Approximately 20-25% of the sequences in each library could be annotated by gene ontology terms. A comparative analysis between the two libraries, as well as the libraries in the accompanying paper, is presented. A set of 4360 clustered and unique sequences was characterized. The data are indicative of a highly plastic gene expression repertoire being available to B. bassiana for growth during different environmental and developmental conditions, and provides a dataset for gene discovery and genome annotation.</ab>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 9</no>
<sn>1350-0872</sn>
<an>000240693600034</an>
<do>10.1099/mic.0.28845-0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2462</id>
<a1>Coler,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Frank,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Garciacanedo,A.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Characterization and Description of a Virus Causing Salivary-Gland Hyperplasia in the Housefly, Musca-Domestica</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>275</sp>
<op>282</op>
<ab>A double-stranded DNA virus was isolated from hyperplasic salivary glands of male and female houseflies, Musca domestica L. (Diptera: Muscidae), collected from a dairy in Alachua County, Florida, U.S.A. Sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS)-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) of this housefly salivary gland hyperplasia (SGH) virus revealed the presence of two major and eight minor structural polypeptides. Restriction endonuclease analysis indicated that the c. 137 kilobase pair DNA was double-stranded. Weekly sweep-net sampling of the fly population throughout the season (May-October, 1991) showed that 1.5-18.5% of the dissected flies possessed hyperplasic salivary glands. The virus replicated within the nuclei of the salivary gland cells and was transmitted per os to newly-emerged healthy adult flies.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>A1993LM80400012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2419</id>
<a1>Conklin,T.</a1>
<a1>Blaske-Lietze,V. U.</a1>
<a1>Becnel,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Infectivity of two isolates of Helicosporidium spp. (Chlorophyta : Trebouxiophyceae) in heterologous host insects</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>431</sp>
<op>440</op>
<ab>Members of the genus Helicosporidium are the first described algal insect pathogens. They have a close affinity to the non-photosynthetic algae of the genus Prototheca, and have a wide host range, infecting many species of aquatic and terrestrial insects. In this study the infectivity of two Helicosporidium spp. isolates, originating from a black fly (SjHe) and an aquatic weevil (CsHe), was tested against a weevil Diaprepes abbreviatus (L.) and three mosquito species Anopheles quadrimaculatus Say, Culex quinquefasciatus Say, and Aedes aegypti (L.). The weevil constitutes a new experimental host record for helicosporidia. The CsHe isolate was more virulent than the SjHe isolate in D. abbreviatus. Anopheles quadrimaculatus was the most susceptible mosquito species measured by infection rate and mortality. The infectivity and virulence of SjHe and CsHe isolates did not differ in any of the mosquito species.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000234928700012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2423</id>
<a1>de Koning,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Keeling,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Expressed sequence tag (EST) survey of the highly adapted green algal parasite, Helicosporidium</t1>
<jf>Protist</jf>
<jo>Protist</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>156</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>190</op>
<ab>Helicosporidia are obligate invertebrate pathogens with a unique and highly adapted mode of infection. The evolutionary history of Helicosporidia has been uncertain, but several recent molecular phylogenetic studies have shown an unexpectedly close relationship to green algae, and specifically to the opportunistic pathogen Prototheca. To date, molecular sequences from Helicosporidia are restricted to those genes used for phylogenetic reconstruction and genes related to the existence and function of its cryptic plastid. We have therefore conducted a small expressed sequence tag (EST) project on Helicosporidium sp., yielding about 700 unique sequences. We have examined the functional distribution of known genes, the distribution of EST abundance, and the prevalence of previously unknown gene sequences. To demonstrate the potential utility of large amounts of data, we have used ribosomal proteins to test whether the phylogenetic position of Helicosporidium inferred from a small number of genes is broadly supported by a large number of genes. We conducted phylogenetic analyses on 69 ribosomal proteins and found that 98% supported the green algal origin of Helicosporidia and 80% support a specific relationship with Prototheca. Overall, these data multiply the available molecular information from Helicosporidium 100-fold, which should provide the basis for new insights into these unusual but interesting parasites. (c) 2005 Elsevier GmbH. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1434-4610</sn>
<an>000231228900004</an>
<do>10.1016/j.protis.2005.02.005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2451</id>
<a1>Debeaupuis,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Sarfati,J.</a1>
<a1>Kobayashi,H.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Gumowski,P.</a1>
<a1>Beauvais,A.</a1>
<a1>Paris,S.</a1>
<a1>Monod,M.</a1>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Antigens of Aspergillus-Fumigatus Expressed during Infection</t1>
<jf>Canadian Journal of Botany-Revue Canadienne De Botanique</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>73</vo>
<sp>S1087</sp>
<op>S1091</op>
<ab>Aspergillus fumigatus secretes an array of antigenic molecules in vitro and in vivo. Recent progresses have been made in the characterization and standardization of A. fumigatus antigens useful for the serodiagnosis of aspergillosis. The chymotrypsin antigen has been purified and can be utilized for the diagnosis of aspergillosis occurring in patients with an immunocompetent B cell population. In the case of immunosuppressed patients suffering from invasive aspergillosis, new methods have been developed to detect the galactofuran containing antigen in the serum. The chemical configuration of this molecule is now known. In contrast to their potential in diagnosis, very little progress has been made on the study of the biochemical and pathoimmunological role of these antigens during the infection process. Two reasons can be advanced for this lack of understanding of the virulence determinants. First of all, antigens studied have been produced in vitro in a dextrose rich medium where pH reaches a value below 5 at maximal growth. These culture conditions are very different from the nutritional environment of the lung, which is a protein-based medium with a slightly basic pH. Antigens expressed under these nutritional conditions are very different from the ones detected in vitro. Second, A. fumigatus is an opportunistic fungus which is characterized by a multifactorial virulence. Gene disruption strategy is not adequate to discriminate the role of a factor in the virulence of the fungus. In contrast, as shown by the studies on two toxins of A. fumigatus, a direct effect of an antigen can be seen directly when several fungal molecules are tested in conjunction on host cells.</ab>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. 1 E-H</no>
<sn>0008-4026</sn>
<an>A1995TC46300056</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2396</id>
<a1>Denton,John S. S.</a1>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-Ulrike</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Host age and pathogen dosage impact cyst morphogenesis in the invertebrate pathogenic alga Helicosporidium sp (Chlorophyta: Trebouxiophyceae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>36</sp>
<op>39</op>
<ab>Helicosporidium sp. is a pathogenic alga that replicates in the hemolymph of various invertebrate hosts. Morphogenesis of the infectious life stage, the cyst, occurs in the infected host, but to date cannot be induced in vitro. Using larvae of the heterologous host Helicoverpa zea, we examined potential factors influencing pathogenicity and in vivo cyst production of the alga and the impact of infection on host survival. Factors tested were cyst dosage administered per os (ranging from 10(2) to 10(5) cysts per larva) and host age at exposure (third, fourth. and fifth larval instar). Cyst production occurred between 7 and 13 days after treatment, regardless of host age at treatment. Increasing dosage increased both percent infection and mortality, but cyst production did not track the total infection response. Increasing host age at exposure mitigated dosage effects on infection and mortality and also elevated cyst production in later-treated larvae. Only the highest dosage produced a significant decrease in the overall time to death. Moderate cyst dosages and later host ages were most effective at regenerating Helicosporidium cysts. (C) 2009 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000269228100006</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2009.06.003</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2477</id>
<a1>Eller,F. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Tumlinson,J. H.</a1>
<t1>Interactions between Microplitis-Croceipes (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) and a Nuclear Polyhedrosis-Virus of Heliothis-Zea (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>977</sp>
<op>982</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1988R217100012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2495</id>
<a1>Funderburk,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Herzog,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Sprenkel,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Lynch,R. E.</a1>
<t1>Parasitoids and Pathogens of Larval Lesser Cornstalk Borers (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) in Northern Florida</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1319</sp>
<op>1323</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1984TU20900030</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2401</id>
<a1>Garcia-Maruniak,Alejandra</a1>
<a1>Abd-Alla,Adly M. M.</a1>
<a1>Salem,Tamer Z.</a1>
<a1>Parker,Andrew G.</a1>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-Ulrike</a1>
<a1>van Oers,Monique M.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<a1>Kim,Woojin</a1>
<a1>Burand,John P.</a1>
<a1>Cousserans,Francois</a1>
<a1>Robinson,Alan S.</a1>
<a1>Vlak,Just M.</a1>
<a1>Bergoin,Max</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Two viruses that cause salivary gland hypertrophy in Glossina pallidipes and Musca domestica are related and form a distinct phylogenetic clade</t1>
<jf>Journal of General Virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<sp>334</sp>
<op>346</op>
<ab>Glossina pallidipes and Musca domestica salivary gland hypertrophy viruses (GpSGHV and MdSGHV) replicate in the nucleus of salivary gland cells causing distinct tissue hypertrophy and reduction of host fertility. They share general characteristics with the non-occluded insect nudiviruses, such as being insect-pathogenic, having enveloped, rod-shaped virions, and large circular double-stranded DNA genomes. MdSGHV measures 65x550 nm and contains a 124 279 bp genome (similar to 44 mol% G+C content) that codes for 108 putative open reading frames (ORFs). GpSGHV, measuring 50x1000 nm, contains a 190 032 bp genome (28 mol% G+C content) with 160 putative ORFs. Comparative genomic analysis demonstrates that 37 MdSGHV ORFs have homology to 42 GpSGHV ORFs, as some MdSGHV ORFs have homology to two different GpSGHV ORFs. Nine genes with known functions (dnapol, ts, pif-1, pif-2, pif-3, mmp, p74, odv-e66 and helicase-2), a homologue of the conserved baculovirus gene Ac81 and at least 13 virion proteins are present in both SGHVs. The amino acid identity ranged from 19 to 39 % among ORFs. An (A/T/G)TAAG motif similar to the baculovirus late promoter motif, was enriched 100 bp upstream of the ORF transcription initiation sites of both viruses. Six and seven putative microRNA sequences were found in MdSGHV and GpSGHV genomes, respectively. There was genome. Collinearity between the two SGHVs, but not between the SGHVs and the nudiviruses. Phylogenetic analysis of conserved genes clustered both SGHVs in a single clade separated from the nudiviruses and baculoviruses. Although MdSGHV and GpSGHV are different viruses, their pathology, host range and genome composition indicate that they are related.</ab>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 2</no>
<sn>0022-1317</sn>
<an>000263075200007</an>
<do>10.1099/vir.0.006783-0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2405</id>
<a1>Garcia-Maruniak,Alejandra</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<a1>Farmerie,William</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Sequence analysis of a non-classified, non-occluded DNA virus that causes salivary gland hypertrophy of Musca domestica, MdSGHV</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JUL 20</fd>
<vo>377</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>184</sp>
<op>196</op>
<ab>The genome of the virus that causes salivary gland hypertrophy in Musca domestica (MdSGHV) was sequenced. This non-classified, enveloped, double stranded, circular DNA virus had a 124,279bp genome. The G + C content was 43.5% with 108 putative methionine-initiated open reading frames (ORFs). Thirty ORFs had homology to database proteins: eleven to proteins coded by both baculoviruses and nudiviruses (p74, pif-1, pif-2, pif-3, odv-e66, rr1, rr2, iap, dUTPase, MMP, and Ac81-like), seven to nudiviruses (mcp, dhfr, ts, tk and three unknown proteins), one to baculovirus (Ac150-like), one to herpesvirus (dna pol), and ten to cellular proteins. Mass spectrum analysis of the viral particles&amp;#39; protein components identified 29 structural ORFs, with only p74 and odv-e66 previously characterized as baculovirus structural proteins. Although most of the homology observed was to nudiviruses, phylogenetic analysis showed that MdSGHV was not closely related to them or to the baculoviruses. (c) 2008 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0042-6822</sn>
<an>000257040700021</an>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2008.04.010</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2408</id>
<a1>Geden,Christopher J.</a1>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-Ulrike</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal prevalence and transmission of salivary gland hypertrophy virus of house flies (Diptera : Muscidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>42</sp>
<op>51</op>
<ab>A survey (2005-2006) of housefly, Musca domestica L. (Diptera: Muscidae) populations on four Florida dairy farms demonstrated the presence of flies with acute symptoms of infection with salivary gland hypertrophy (SGH) virus on all farms. Disease incidence varied among farms (farm averages, 0.5-10.1%) throughout the year, and it showed a strong positive correlation with fly density. Infections were most common among flies that were collected in a feed barn on one of the farms, especially among flies feeding on wet brewers grains (maximum 34% SGH). No infections were observed among adult flies reared from larvae collected on the farms, nor among adults reared from larvae that had fed on macerated salivary glands from infected flies. Infected female flies produced either no or small numbers of progeny, none of which displayed SGH when they emerged as adults. Healthy flies became infected after they fed on solid food (a mixture of powdered milk, egg, and sugar) that had been contaminated by infected flies (42%) or after they were held in cages that had previously housed infected flies (38.6%). Healthy flies also became infected after they fed on samples of brewers grains (6.8%) or calf feed (2%) that were collected from areas of high fly visitation on the farms. Infection rates of field-collected flies increased from 6 to 40% when they fed exclusively on air-dried cloth strips soaked in a suspension of powdered egg and whole milk. Rates of virus deposition by infected flies on food were estimated by quantitative polymerase chain reaction at similar to 100 million virus copies per fly per hour. Electron microscopy revealed the presence on enveloped virus particles in the lumen of salivary glands and on the external mouthparts of infected flies.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000252635500007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2471</id>
<a1>Haag,K. H.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Infectivity of Insect Pathogens Against Neochetina-Eichhorniae, a Biological-Control Agent of Water-Hyacinth</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>74</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>128</sp>
<op>133</op>
<ab>Several insect pathogens were tested for infectivity against Neochetina eichhorniae Warner (Coleoptera:Curculionidae), a biological control agent for waterhyacinth, Eichhornia crassipes (Mart.) Solms. No mortality resulted from exposure to 21 strains of Bacillus thuringiensis. No significant mortality resulted from exposure to 2 strains of Metarhizium anisopliae. Although treatment of adult weevils with 6 strains of Beauvaria bassiana produced no significant mortality, 2 strains (BbAFA - 35%, Bb 5647 - 65%) did result in statistically significant mortality. Exposure to 2 strains of Steinernema carpocapsae resulted in 60-70% mortality. Our results indicate limited potential for these insect pathogens to control N. eichhorniae in resource recovery or wastewater treatment facilities.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1991FE55000016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2431</id>
<a1>Hay-Roe,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Becriel,J. J.</a1>
<t1>A newly discovered baculovirus induces reflex bleeding in the butterfly Heliconius himera (Nymphalidae : Heliconiinae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>59</sp>
<op>62</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000185607300009</an>
<do>10.1016/S0022-2011(03)00105-8</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2406</id>
<a1>Herrero-Galan,Elias</a1>
<a1>Lacadena,Javier</a1>
<a1>Martinez del Pozo,Alvaro</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<a1>Olmo,Nieves</a1>
<a1>Onaderra,Mercedes</a1>
<a1>Gavilanes,Jose G.</a1>
<t1>The insecticidal protein hirsutellin A from the mite fungal pathogen Hirsutella thompsonii is a ribotoxin</t1>
<jf>Proteins-Structure Function and Bioinformatics</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>217</sp>
<op>228</op>
<ab>The mite fungal pathogen Hirsutella thompsonii produces a single polypeptide chain, insecticidal protein named hirsutellin A (HtA) that is composed of 130 amino acid residues. This protein has been purified from its natural source and produced as a recombinant protein in Escherichia coli Spectroscopic analysis has determined that the two protein forms are indistinguishable. HtA specifically inactivates ribosomes and produces the alpha-fragment characteristic of ribotoxin activity on rRNA. Behaving as a cyclizing ribonuclease, HtA specifically cleaves oligonucleotides that mimick the sarcin/ricin loop of the ribosome, as well as selected polynucleotides and dinucleosides. HtA interacts with phospholipid membranes as do other ribotoxins. As a consequence of its ribonuclease activity and its ability to interact with cell membranes, HtA exhibits cytotoxic activity on human tumor cells. On the basis of these results, HtA is considered to be a member of the ribotoxin group of proteins, although it is significantly smaller (130 aa) than all known ribotoxins that are composed of 1491 150 amino acids. Ribotoxins are members of a larger family of fungal ribonucleases whose members of smaller size (100/110 aa) are not cytotoxic. Thus, the characterization of the fungal ribotoxin HtA represents an important milestone in the study of the diversity and the function of fungal ribonucleases.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0887-3585</sn>
<an>000256609800018</an>
<do>10.1002/prot.21910</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2449</id>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Phenoloxidase activity in Hemolymph of naive and Beauveria bassiana-infected Spodoptera exigua larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>35</sp>
<op>40</op>
<ab>The majority of Spodoptera exigua hemolymph phenoloxidase (PO) activity is localized in the hemocytes of naive larvae. Mid sixth instar larvae possessed 0.2 +/- 0.5 and 3.4 +/- 2.6 units (1 unit = Delta 0.001 Angstrom/min at 490 nm) of PO activity/mu l of hemolymph equivalent in the plasma and hemocyte lysate (HL) fractions, respectively. The S. exigua HL PO had a pH optimum of 7.0 when assayed against DL-Dopa. This enzyme is present in hemocytes as a proenzyme: activation of PO could be inhibited with either 10 mM diisopropyl fluorophosphate or soybean trypsin inhibitor (1 mg/ml). The relative activity of HL PO was not inhibited by the addition of EGTA or EDTA. The PO titers in HL and plasma fractions sampled from sixth instar larvae during the feeding period (0-60 hr) of the sixth larval instar were not significantly different, However, a 10 x increase in PO activity was observed in plasma sampled from the wandering and prepupal stages. A series of assays was conducted to monitor the PO activity in Beauveria bassiana-infected S. exigua larvae. At 24 hr postchallenge the PO titers in plasma and HL fractions from infected larvae were comparable to PO titers in fractions from saline controls. Analysis of PO activities revealed that by 48-60 hr postchallenge the PO titers in the HL sampled from infected larvae decreased sevenfold, whereas plasma PO titers increased. The increased titer of PO in the plasma did not inhibit fungal development. (C) 1996 Academic Press, Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1996TX60500006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2466</id>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Beauveria-Bassiana on the Cellular Defense Response of the Beet Armyworm, Spodoptera-Exigua</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>152</sp>
<op>158</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1992JK79100008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2465</id>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Vey,A. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Beauveria-Bassiana and Candida-Albicans on the Cellular Defense Response of Spodoptera-Exigua</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>187</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1993KQ34200011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2468</id>
<a1>Ignoffo,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Relative Activity of Geographical Isolates of Nomuraea Bioassayed Against the Cabbage-Looper and Velvetbean Caterpillar</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>59</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>215</sp>
<op>217</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1992HG55900019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2435</id>
<a1>Jackson,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Thaler,J. O.</a1>
<t1>Pathobiology of amber disease, caused by Serratia spp., in the New Zealand grass grub, Costelytra zealandica</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>232</sp>
<op>243</op>
<ab>Amber disease in the New Zealand grass grub (Costelytra zealandica) is caused by some strains of Serratia entomophila or Serratia proteamaculans (Enterobacteriaceae). When treated with pathogenic isolates, larvae ceased feeding within 48 h, developed an amber coloration after 72 h, and entered a long chronic phase without feeding. Am acute dose of 2-4 x 10(4) pathogenic bacteria was sufficient to produce disease in 50% of treated larvae. Time to death was directly related to temperature. At 15degreesC, infected larvae remained in a chronic, nonfeeding state for more than 4 months prior to death. Nonpathogenic isolates, lacking the disease-causing plasmid (pADAP), had no effect on either feeding or disease. Twenty-four hours after ingestion, bacteria were found predominantly in the hindgut and growth occurred primarily within the fermentation chamber and in the head section of the larvae. Nonpathogenic strains did not multiply in treated larvae. Treatment of diseased larvae with antibiotic eliminated Serratia cells from the insects but did not result in restoration of feeding or the dark gut characteristic of the healthy larva. (C) 2001 Elsevier Science (USA).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000175343300008</an>
<do>10.1006/jipa.2002.5078</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2509</id>
<a1>Johnson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Barfield,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Allen,G. E.</a1>
<t1>A Temperature-Dependent Developmental Model for a Nucleopolyhedrosis Virus of the Velvetbean Caterpillar, Anticarsia-Gemmatalis (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>292</sp>
<op>298</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1982PL34500019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2515</id>
<a1>Joslyn,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Isoenzyme Differentiation among 3 Pathotypes of the Entomogenous Fungus Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Canadian journal of microbiology</jf>
<jo>Can.J.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>364</sp>
<op>366</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0008-4166</sn>
<an>A1981LG53100015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2418</id>
<a1>Kalkar,O.</a1>
<a1>Carner,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Scharf,D.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of an Indonesian Isolate of Paecilomyces reniformis</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>161</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>109</sp>
<op>118</op>
<ab>An entomopathogenic fungus (IndGH 96), identified as Paecilomyces reniformis, was isolated from long-horned grasshoppers (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae) in Sulawesi, Indonesia. The phenotypic and molecular data identified the IndGH 96 as a P. reniformis. We present the first comprehensive characterization of this species using morphological features, sequencing of the ITS1-5.8s-ITS2 region, D1/D2 region of 28S of rDNA, and a portion of the tubulin gene, and laboratory bioassays. Distinguishing features include a hyphal body stage during vegetative growth and the production of distinctly curved, light-green conidia. High dosage bioassays showed that IndGH 96 was infectious to both long-horned and short-horned grasshoppers but not to the house cricket, Acheta domestica, or to the lepidopterans velvetbean caterpillar, Anticarsia gemmatalis or fall armyworm, Spodoptera frugiperda. Phenotypic and genetic analyses suggest that IndGH 96 and other isolates of P. reniformis are more closely related to Nomuraea rileyi than to other species of Paecilomyces.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>000235202200007</an>
<do>10.1007/s11046-005-0133-z</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2006</id>
<a1>Kanga,LHB</a1>
<a1>James,RR</a1>
<a1>Boucias,DG</a1>
<t1>Hirsutella thompsonii and Metarhizium anisopliae as potential microbial control agents of Varroa destructor, a honey bee parasite</t1>
<jf>Journal of Invertebrate Pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>175</sp>
<op>184</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2433</id>
<a1>Kanga,L. H. B.</a1>
<a1>James,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Hirsutella thompsonii and Metarhizium anisopliae as potential microbial control agents of Varroa destructor, a honey bee parasite</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>175</sp>
<op>184</op>
<ab>The potential of Hirsutella thompsonii Fisher and Metarhizium anisopliae (Metschinkoff) as biological control agents of the parasitic mite, Varroa destructor Anderson and Trueman was evaluated in the laboratory and in observation hives. In the laboratory, time required for 90% cumulative mortality of mites (LT90) was 4.16 (3.98-4.42) days for H. thompsonii and 5.85 (5.48-7.43) days for M. anisopliae at 1.1 X 10(3) conidia mm(-2). At a temperature (34 +/- 1 degreesC) similar to that of the broodnest in a honey bee colony, Apis mellifera L., H. thompsonii [LC90 = 9.90 x 10(1) (5.86-19.35) conidia mm(-2) at Day 7] and M. anisopliae [LC90 = 7.13 X 10(3) (2.80-23.45) conidia mm(-2) at Day 7] both showed significant virulence against V destructor. The applications of H. thompsonii to observation hives resulted in significant mortality of mites, and reduction of the number of mites per bee 21 and 42 days post-treatments. The treatments did not significantly affect the mite population in sealed brood. However, the fungus must have persisted because infected mites were still observed [82.97 +/- (0.6)%] 42 days post-treatment. In addition, the fungus was found to sporulate on the host. A small percentage [2.86 +/- (0.2)%] of dead mites found in the control hives also showed fungal infection, suggesting that adult bees drifted between hives and disseminated the fungus. H. thompsonii was harmless to the honey bees at the concentrations applied and did not have any deleterious effects on the fecundity of the queens. Microbial control with fungal pathogens provides promising new avenues for control of V. destructor and could be a useful component of an integrated pest management program for the honey bee industry. Published by Elsevier Science (USA).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000180541500005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2455</id>
<a1>Lastra,C. C. L.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Soares,G. G.</a1>
<t1>Bacillus-Thuringiensis Endotoxin Effects on Spodoptera-Exigua and S-Frugiperda Larva Infected with Baculoviruses</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>239</sp>
<op>242</op>
<ab>The objective of this study was to examine the effects of the B. thuringiensis-based MVP biopesticide on the development of baculoviruses in Spodoptera larvae. The sensitivity of both the beet armyworm, Spodoptera exigua (Hubner) and the fall armyworm, S. frugiperda (J. E. Smith), to the CryIA(c) toxin present in MW was temporary; upon reaching the third instar, both species were much less susceptible to the CryIA(c) toxin. The sublethal effects of MVP on Spodoptera, reflected by a delay in larvae development, did not alter the dose response of these insects to their respective nuclear polyhedrosis virus. However, feeding the virus infected Spodoptera larvae MVP amended diet (10 mg/ml) did increase the number of second instars succumbing to viral infection. Microscopic examination of the larva killed by the MW baculovirus demonstrated normal virus inclusion formation. In summary, our laboratory bioassays suggested that B. thuringiensis delta endotoxins, applied at rates that are sublethal, should not interfere with baculovirus development in B. thuringiensis tolerant hosts such as S. exigua and S. frugiperda.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1995RH34800008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2497</id>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Intraspecific Variability in Conidiobolus-Obscurus</t1>
<jf>Journal of General and Applied Microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Appl.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>135</sp>
<op>150</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-1260</sn>
<an>A1984TL76400001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2478</id>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Fournet,B.</a1>
<t1>Structure of the Exocellular Polysaccharide Produced by the Fungus, Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Carbohydrate research</jf>
<jo>Carbohydr.Res.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>OCT 1</fd>
<vo>181</vo>
<sp>282</sp>
<op>286</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0008-6215</sn>
<an>A1988Q734200032</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2490</id>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Rosas,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Aggressiveness of Conidiobolus-Obscurus Against the Pea Aphid .4. Electrophoretic and Immunoelectrophoretic Characterization of Aggressive Strains</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>159</sp>
<op>166</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1986D768100005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2400</id>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-U</a1>
<a1>Sims,Kelly R.</a1>
<a1>Salem,Tamer Z.</a1>
<a1>Geden,Christopher J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Transmission of MdSGHV among adult house flies, Musca domestica (Diptera: Muscidae), occurs via oral secretions and excreta</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>49</sp>
<op>55</op>
<ab>The MdSGHV is a double-stranded DNA virus that replicates in the salivary glands of infected adult house flies. Transmission of this non-occluded, enveloped virus is believed to be mediated orally via deposition and consumption of oral secretions composed of salivary gland secretions and crop contents. In this study, transmission electron micrographs of crops from infected flies showed numerous enveloped virions in the crop lumen adjacent to the Cuticular intima, as well as on the hemocoel side in close vicinity to muscle cells. Oral treatments of newly emerged flies with viremic salivary gland homogenates, crop homogenates. or gradient-purified virus resulted in an average 44% infection. Virus released via oral secretion was infectious when ingested by newly emerged adult flies, resulting in an average 66% infection. Using quantitative real-time PCR, MdSGHV DNA was quantified in oral secretions and excreta obtained from viremic flies. Between 2 and 4 days post-infection (dpi), viral copy numbers in oral secretions increased exponentially and from 5 to 21 dpi each infected fly released an average 106 MdSGHV copies per feeding event. Excreta samples collected overnight from individual infected flies at 5 dpi contained an average 6.5 x 10(5) viral copies. Low but detectable infection rates were produced when newly emerged flies were challenged with excreta samples. In summary, evaluation of the quantity and infectivity of MdSGHV released by individual infected house flies clearly showed that deposition of oral secretions and excreta onto a shared food substrate is the main route of natural MdSGHV transmission among adult house flies. (c) 2009 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000265420200007</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2009.02.007</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2409</id>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-Ulrike</a1>
<a1>Geden,Christopher J.</a1>
<a1>Blackburn,Patrick</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Effects of salivary gland hypertrophy virus on the reproductive behavior of the housefly, Musca domestica</t1>
<jf>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>6811</sp>
<op>6818</op>
<ab>Pathological studies demonstrated that the salivary gland hypertrophy virus of houseflies (MdSGHV) shuts down reproduction in infected females. The mechanism that underlay the disruption of reproduction functioned on several levels. Females infected at the previtellogenic stage did not produce eggs, reflecting a block in the gonadotropic cycle. Sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and Western blot analysis of hemolymph samples demonstrated that MdSGHV infection reduced the levels of both the female-specific hexamerin and egg yolk proteins. Furthermore, reverse transcriptase quantitative real-time PCR data demonstrated that infection blocked hexamerin and yolk protein gene transcription. When females were allowed to develop eggs prior to infection (postvitellogenic stage), the outcome of mating attempts depended upon when mating took place. If egg-containing, virus-infected females were mated within 24 It of infection, they copulated and deposited a single batch of fertilized eggs. However, if mating was delayed for a longer period, the egg-containing females refused to copulate with healthy males. Both of these results suggested that a virus-induced signal influenced the central nervous system, shutting down female receptivity and egg production. All experiments demonstrated that MdSGHV-infected males did not display azoospermia and were fertile. Both healthy females mated with infected males, and the resulting F1 progeny were free of salivary gland hypertrophy symptoms, which suggests that the virus is not sexually or vertically transmitted.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0099-2240</sn>
<an>000250700600013</an>
<do>10.1128/AEM.02694-06</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2447</id>
<a1>Liu,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Liu,W. Z.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J.</a1>
<t1>The mode of action of hirsutellin A on eukaryotic cells</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>224</sp>
<op>228</op>
<ab>A 16-kDa protein toxin was purified from Hirsutella thompsonii var thompsonii and named hirsutellin A (HtA). At 0.5 and 5.0 mu M concentrations, HtA caused detectable cytopathic effects on Spodoptera frugiperda cells (Sf-9) within 2-4 hr and completely inhibited Sf-9 cell growth at 4 days posttreatment. Electron microscope data showed that the HtA treated Sf-9 cells became hypotrophied and internal organelles and cell membranes were disrupted. At the same concentration, HtA effectively inhibited Brome mosaic virus protein synthesis of both rabbit reticulocyte and wheat germ in vitro translation systems. The ribosomal RNA extracted from HtA treated Sf-9 cells produced a smaller RNA (approximately 528 bases) than untreated Sf-9 cells. In summary, HtA is the first mycotoxin of a invertebrate mycopathogen determined to possess ribosomal inhibiting activity and appears to possess some specificity to invertebrate cells. (C) 1996 Academic Press, Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1996UM68400005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2450</id>
<a1>Liu,W. Z.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>McCoy,C. W.</a1>
<t1>Extraction and characterization of the insecticidal toxin Hirsutellin A produced by Hirsutella thompsonii var thompsonii</t1>
<jf>Experimental mycology</jf>
<jo>Exp.Mycol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>254</sp>
<op>262</op>
<ab>Hirsutellin A (HtA) produced by Hirsutella thompsonii var. thompsonii (strain JAB-04) was extracted and purified using a combination of ion-exchange, gel-permeation, and immunoaffinity chromatography. The identity of the purified HtA was confirmed by amino acid analysis and N-terminal sequencing. Monoclonal antibodies prepared against HtA were capable of detecting 25-50 ng of HtA by direct sandwich ELISA. In addition, utilizing Western blot methods, the antibodies were shown to be specific to HtA. The production of HtA was monitored during submerged fermentation. The peak level of exocellular HtA (13-14 mu g/ml) was during the late exponential growth phase (39-45 h), determined by utilizing a combination of densitometric analysis of the 16.3-kDa bands on SDS-PAGE gels and ELISA. HtA production was directly correlated with mycelial growth. Twenty-one-hour culture filtrates were highly toxic re, larvae of the greater wax moth. Pure HtA at a final concentration of 40 pmol was highly toxic to Galleria mellonella larvae. (C) 1995 Academic Press, Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0147-5975</sn>
<an>A1995TM69400003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2460</id>
<a1>Lopezlastra,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Studies on the Cellular Reactions of Spodoptera-Exigua Larvae Infected with the Fungus Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>101</sp>
<op>102</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1994MQ69300019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2505</id>
<a1>Lynn,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Nuclear Polyhedrosis-Virus Replication in Epithelial-Cell Cultures of Lepidoptera</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>424</sp>
<op>426</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1983RQ05500026</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2507</id>
<a1>Madore,C. D.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Dimond,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Reduction of Reproductive Potential in Spruce Budworm (Lepidoptera, Tortricidae) by a Chitin-Inhibiting Insect Growth-Regulator</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>708</sp>
<op>710</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1983RB80000007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2424</id>
<a1>Magalhaes,B. P.</a1>
<a1>Rodrigues,J. C. V.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Childers,C. C.</a1>
<t1>Pathogenicity of Metarhizium anisopliae var. acridum to the false spider mite Brevipalpus phoenicis (Acari : Tenuipalpidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>195</sp>
<op>198</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000230583300013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2434</id>
<a1>Maimala,S.</a1>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<a1>Chandrapatya,A.</a1>
<t1>Detection of the toxin Hirsutellin A from Hirsutella thompsonii</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>80</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>112</sp>
<op>126</op>
<ab>A total of 162 strains of Hirsutella thompsonii, isolated from infected mites collected worldwide, were examined for the production of Hirsutellin A (HtA). More than half of the broth filtrates exhibited mortality rates superior to 50% when assayed against Galleria mellonella. The presence of the gene coding for HtA, a previously characterized H. thompsonii protein exotoxin, was determined by PCR amplification using gene-specific primers. Most isolates (100 out of 162) were shown to possess the HtA gene. However, the presence of the gene could not be associated with enhanced insecticidal activity. Both isolate groups (with or without an amplifiable HtA gene) produced filtrates that caused the same average mortality rate (65%) when assayed against G. mellonella. The production and secretion of the HtA toxin were estimated by probing broth filtrates with an anti-HtA monoclonal antibody. Again, the detection of the HtA protein was poorly correlated with subsequent mortality rates induced by the broth filtrates of the various H. thompsonii strains. This study suggests that HtA is requisite for neither survival nor pathogenicity, and that H. thompsonii strains are likely to secrete other toxins that have yet to be characterized. Sequencing of a limited number of HtA genes showed that, when present, the gene is highly conserved, and it displays an interesting intronic polymorphism. (C) 2002 Elsevier Science (USA). All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000178680000005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2407</id>
<a1>Marshall,S. D. G.</a1>
<a1>Gatehouse,L. N.</a1>
<a1>Becher,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Christeller,J. T.</a1>
<a1>Gatehouse,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Hurst,M. R. H.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Jackson,T. A.</a1>
<t1>Serine proteases identified from a Costelytra zealandica (White) (Coleoptera : Scarabaeidae) midgut EST library and their expression through insect development</t1>
<jf>Insect molecular biology</jf>
<jo>Insect Mol.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>259</op>
<ab>Costelytra zealandica larvae are pests of New Zealand pastures causing damage by feeding on the roots of grasses and clovers. The major larval protein digestive enzymes are serine proteases (SPs), which are targets for disruption in pest control. An expressed sequence tag (EST) library from healthy, third instar larval midgut tissue was constructed and analysed to determine the composition and regulation of proteases in the C. zealandica larval midgut. Gene mining identified three trypsin-like and 11 chymotrypsin-like SPs spread among four major subgroups. Representative SPs were examined by quantitative PCR and enzyme activity assayed across developmental stages. The serine protease genes examined were expressed throughout feeding stages and downregulated in nonfeeding stages. The study will improve targeting of protease inhibitors and bacterial disruptors of SP synthesis.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0962-1075</sn>
<an>000255753400006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2448</id>
<a1>Mazet,I.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Effects of the fungal pathogen, Beauveria bassiana on protein biosynthesis of infected Spodoptera exigua larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of insect physiology</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>91</sp>
<op>99</op>
<ab>Vegetative development of Beauveria bassiana in the hemocoel of the beet armyworm, Spodoptera exigua did not cause significant alterations in the profile of hemolymph proteins. Pulse-labeling tissue explants revealed that vegetative growth of B. bassiana hyphal bodies did not impact the biosynthetic capability of either the fat body or cuticle epidermis, both major sites of host protein synthesis. Even at the late stage of hyphal body development, when concentrations reached 3 x 10(4) fungal cells per mu l of hemolymph, both fat body and cuticle explants were capable of synthesizing and secreting the majority of proteins detected in naive samples. Hemocyte cultures were found to secrete significantly fewer labeled proteins than either fat body or cuticle explants. Replication of hyphal bodies in hemocyte cultures established from infected larvae induced the synthesis and secretion of 3 peptides having M(r) of 31, 32 and 40 kDa, Interestingly, peptides having identical M(r)s were detected in infected cell free hemolymph samples. These peptides did not correspond to proteins induced in response to heat shock suggesting that they may represent in vivo produced fungal metabolites. At the very late vegetative growth stage, the hyphal bodies produced germ tubes which invaded host tissues, Unlike the hyphal bodies, the mycelial tissue invasion phase inhibited host protein biosynthesis and produced a range of exocellular peptides.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-1910</sn>
<an>A1996TX64800001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2459</id>
<a1>Mazet,I.</a1>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Detection of Toxic Metabolites in the Hemolymph of Beauveria-Bassiana Infected Spodoptera-Exigua Larvae</t1>
<jf>Experientia</jf>
<jo>Experientia</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>FEB 15</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>142</sp>
<op>147</op>
<ab>Highly active metabolites have been detected in the hemolymph of the lepidopteran Spodoptera exigua infected with the mycopathogen, Beauveria bassiana. A combination of phenyl sepharose and CM ion exchange chromatography was utilized to extract the active metabolites from infected hemolymph samples. The active in vivo metabolites, having a molecular mass greater than 10 KDa, were thermolabile and were inactivated by proteinase K. These metabolites were characterized by their ability to disrupt metamorphosis, killing treated larvae at the wandering or pupal stage. Additionally, injection of S. exigua larvae with &amp;#39;active&amp;#39; samples caused a reduction in the number of filopodial-producing hemocytes. The biological activities and biochemical properties suggest that novel compounds are produced during B. bassiana mycosis.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0014-4754</sn>
<an>A1994MW47600015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2454</id>
<a1>Mazet,I.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<t1>Comparative-Analysis of Phagocytosis of Fungal Cells by Insect Hemocytes Versus Horse Neutrophils</t1>
<jf>Developmental and comparative immunology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Comp.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>NOV-DEC</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>455</sp>
<op>466</op>
<ab>In this study, the phagocytic ability Of Spodoptera exigua hemocytes was compared to horse neutrophils. In vitro assays showed that the insect granulocytes and horse neutrophils actively phagocytose FITC-labeled Paecilomyces farinosus blastospores opsonized with S. exigua hemolymph lectin or horse serum, respectively. Killing of fungal cells by the neutrophils and hemocytes was analyzed under in vitro conditions. Neutrophils reduced the growth of P. farinosus up to 65% whereas no fungicidal activity was observed with hemocyte monolayers. The production of oxygen metabolites by both phagocytic cells incubated with various elicitors (fungal cells, bacteria, phorbol myristate acetate) was examined using luminol-enhanced chemiluminescence. Phagocytosis of opsonized microbes by horse neutrophils resulted in marked increase of chemiluminescence activity whereas no chemiluminescence was detected in similarly challenged phagocytic insect hemocytes. Electron microscopy was used to examine phagocytic events and confirmed that insect phagocytes were unable to kill tested microbes.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0145-305X</sn>
<an>A1994RT49400001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2473</id>
<a1>Mccoy,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Selection of Beauveria-Bassiana Pathotypes as Potential Microbial Control Agents of Soil-Inhabiting Citrus Weevils</t1>
<jf>Memorias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</jf>
<jo>Mem.Inst.Oswaldo Cruz</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>84</vo>
<sp>75</sp>
<op>80</op>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. 3</no>
<sn>0074-0276</sn>
<an>A1989CE24300015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2472</id>
<a1>Mcdowell,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Funderburk,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Lynch,R. E.</a1>
<t1>Biological-Activity of Beauveria-Bassiana Against Elasmopalpus-Lignosellus (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) on Leaf Substrates and Soil</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>137</sp>
<op>141</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1990CM72000022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2403</id>
<a1>Meyer,Jason M.</a1>
<a1>Hoy,Marjorie A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and characterization of an Isaria fumosorosea isolate infecting the Asian citrus psyllid in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>96</sp>
<op>102</op>
<ab>A fungal pathogen that killed adult Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Asian citrus psyllid) (Hemiptera: Psyllidae) in Florida Citrus groves during the fall of 2005 was identified and characterized. investigation of this pathogen is important because D. citri vectors citrus greening disease (Huanglongbing), which was reported in Florida in 2005. The morphological and genetic data generated herein support identification of the fungus as Isaria fumosorosea Wize (lfr) (=Paecilomyces fumosoroseus) (Hypocreales: Cordycipitaceae) from the Asian citrus psyllid (Ifr-AsCP). Koch&amp;#39;s postulates were fulfilled after the fungus was isolated in vitro and transmitted to healthy psyllids, which then exhibited a diseased-phenotype similar to that observed in the field. Both in vitro growth characteristics and two lfr AsCP-specific molecular markers discriminated the psyllid pathogen from another local lfr isolate. lfr 97 Apopka. These molecular markers will be useful to track the dynamics of this disease in D. citri populations. The potential for utilizing lfr to complement existing psyllid pest management strategies is discussed. (C) 2008 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000259131400015</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2008.03.007</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2412</id>
<a1>Meyer,Jason M.</a1>
<a1>Hoy,Marjorie A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Morphological and molecular characterization of a Hirsutella species infecting the Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemiptera : Psyllidae), in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>95</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>101</sp>
<op>109</op>
<ab>The Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayania, is an invasive pest that vectors citrus greening disease, which recently was detected in Florida. Mycosed adult D. citri were collected at four sites in central Florida between September 2005 and February 2006. Observation of the cadavers using scanning electron microscopy revealed that the pathogen had branched synnemata supporting monophiladic conidiogenous cells. A high-fidelity polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay was used to amplify the 18S rRNA, 28S rRNA and beta-tubulin genes of the pathogen for phylogenetic analysis. The morphological and genetic data indicated that the pathogen was a novel isolate related to Hirsittella citriformis Speare. PCR assays using isolate-specific primers designed from the unique putative intron region of the beta-tubulin sequence distinguished the psyllid pathogen from five related Hirsittella species. The pathogen was maintained in vivo by exposing healthy D. citri to the synnemata borne on field-collected cadavers. Infected psyllids had an abundance of septate hyphal bodies in their hemolymph and exhibited behavioral symptoms of disease. Ill vitro cultures of the pathogen were slow-growing and produced synnemata similar to those found on mycosed D. citri. In laboratory bioassays, high levels of mortality were observed in D. citri that were exposed to the conidia-bearing synnemata produced ill vivo and ill vitro. (c) 2007 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000247153400005</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2007.01.005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2481</id>
<a1>Morrow,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Comparative-Analysis of the Invitro Growth of the Hyphal Body and Mycelial Stage of the Entomopathogenic Fungus, Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>51</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>197</sp>
<op>206</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1988N141100003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2476</id>
<a1>Morrow,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Heath,M. A.</a1>
<t1>Loss of Virulence in an Isolate of an Entomopathogenic Fungus, Nomuraea-Rileyi, After Serial Invitro Passage</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>404</sp>
<op>407</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1989U088000014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2484</id>
<a1>Morrow,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Entomophaga-Aulicae in Tomato Hornworm, Manduca-Quinquemaculata</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>330</sp>
<op>332</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1987K690200024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2492</id>
<a1>Osborne,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>A Review of Chemical Antagonists to Mycopathogens of Citrus Root Weevils</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>409</sp>
<op>416</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1985ARB1800009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2493</id>
<a1>Osborne,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Lindquist,R. K.</a1>
<t1>Activity of Bacillus-Thuringiensis Var Israelensis on Bradysia-Coprophila (Diptera, Sciaridae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>922</sp>
<op>925</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1985AQD0700042</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2514</id>
<a1>Pavan,O. H.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>The Effects of Serial Passage of a Nucleopolyhedrosis Virus through an Alternate Host System</t1>
<jf>Entomophaga</jf>
<jo>Entomophaga</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>99</sp>
<op>108</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8959</sn>
<an>A1981LX96400010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2440</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Comparative analysis of the binding of antibodies prepared against the insect Spodoptera exigua and against the mycopathogen Nomuraea rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>107</sp>
<op>116</op>
<ab>Polyclonal antibodies were produced in mice against Spodoptera exigua (beet armyworm) larval hemolymph and hemocytes and against cell wall surfaces of hyphal bodies and hyphae of the entomopathogenic hyphomycete Nomuraea rileyi. In addition to exhibiting strong activity against their original antigenic substrates, all of the antibodies cross-react extensively with other substrates, The hemolymph antibody binds to hemocytes and vice verse, and both antibodies cross-react to the insect fat body basement membrane (extracellular matrix (ECM) and to N. rileyi and Beauveria bassiana (another entomopathogenic fungus) cell wall surfaces (ECM), Likewise, the anti-fungal antibodies cross-react with S. exigua hemolymph and hemocytes, especially the granules that may contain ECM components, and with fat body basement membrane. These cross-reactivities are specific as indicated by negative controls in the microscopy and Western blotting assays. Parallel labeling experiments using Con A suggest that the reactive epitopes contain mannose; however, none of the antibodies bind to mannose residues of nonentomopathogenic Candida albicans or Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeast cells. Thus, these cross-reactivities suggest that the host mimicry expressed by surface components of entomopathogenic fungi represents an important pathogenic determinant. (C) 2000 Academic Press.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000086206600002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2442</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of monoclonal antibodies against cell wall epitopes of the insect pathogenic fungus, Nomuraea rileyi: differential binding to fungal surfaces and cross-reactivity with host hemocytes and basement membrane components</t1>
<jf>European journal of cell biology</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Cell Biol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>118</sp>
<op>127</op>
<ab>Monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) were generated against epitopes on yeast-like hyphal bodies and hyphae of the entomopathogenic hyphomycete, Nomuraea rileyi. Two MAbs (4C10, 2H4) bind to epitopes common to both hyphal bodies and hyphae, whereas MAb 4E9 binds only to hyphal surfaces. 4C10 and 2H4 appear to be directed towards carbohydrate portions of cell surface mannoproteins, as evidenced by similarities in staining patterns between these MAbs and Concanavalin A on Western blots of N. rileyi cell wall extracts. These MAbs crossreact with antigens on blastospore and hyphal surfaces of two other entomopathogenic fungi, Beauveria bassiana and Paecilomyces farinosus in fluorescence microscopy assays, but do not cross-react with a non-entomopathogenic strain of Candida albicans or with Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeasts. MAb 4C10 also cross-reacts with immunocompetent granular hemocytes from Spodoptera exigua (beet armyworm) and Trichoplusia ni (cabbage looper) larvae and with S. exigua plasmatocytes. Electron microscopy revealed that this MAb binds to a component in cytoplasmic granules in the hemocytes, and that surface labeling may be due to the release of this MAb-positive component upon degranulation. MAb 2H4 does not cross-react with granular hemocytes, but does bind to plasmatocytes and hemocytes that tightly adhere to the substrate in monolayer assays. Additionally MAb 4C10 specifically labels a basement membrane epitope on S. exigua fat body suggesting that this antibody binds to mannose residues on extracellular matrix glycoproteins. Cross-reactivity of these N. rileyi MAbs with insect hemocyte and tissue components indicates that fungal surface epitopes ran mimic host surface molecules, which could explain why N. rileyi hyphal bodies are not recognized by granulocytes and are able to circulate freely in the hemolymph without binding to basement membranes lining the hemocoel.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0171-9335</sn>
<an>000072606100004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2444</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>In vitro growth of the entomopathogenic hyphomycete Nomuraea rileyi</t1>
<jf>Mycologia</jf>
<jo>Mycologia</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>JAN-FEB</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>66</sp>
<op>71</op>
<ab>The entomopathogen Nomuraea rileyi is a dimorphic hyphomycete having invasive hyphal stages and a yeastlike vegetative stage. Each phenotype has unique characteristics that contribute to pathogenicity of the fungus towards insects. Growth both in vivo and in vitro is highly synchronous. In vitro, conidial germ tubes produce hyphal bodies (yeastlike cells) in complex mycological medium and, if transferred to a less complex medium (Vogel&amp;#39;s), the hyphal bodies synchronously convert to mycelia. This transition can be reversed by transferring the mycelia back to the original medium. The hyphal body phase can be by-passed by placing germ tubes directly into Vogel&amp;#39;s. The ability to regulate fungal development provides a means of comparing characteristics (e.g., cell surface epitopes, enzyme production) which differ according to phenotype, and to identify genes associated with phase transitions.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-5514</sn>
<an>A1997WH03000006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2446</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Phagocytosis of lectin-opsonized fungal cells and endocytosis of the ligand by insect Spodoptera exigua granular hemocytes: An ultrastructural and immunocytochemical study</t1>
<jf>Cell and tissue research</jf>
<jo>Cell Tissue Res.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>285</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>57</sp>
<op>67</op>
<ab>Phagocytosis of blastospores of the fungal entomopathogen Paecilomyces farinosus by granular hemocytes from larvae of Spodoptera exigua (beet army-worm) was studied. Blastospores were opsonized with a galactose-specific lectin purified from S. exigua hemolymph or with peanut agglutinin prior to incubation with hemocytes. Observations of thin sections revealed that pseudopodia extending from granulocytes attached to ligands (lectins, lectin conjugates) on the blastospores, and that the ligands became detached from the fungal surfaces and were endocytosed by granulocytes via coated pits on the plasma membrane. Coated vesicles bearing the endocytosed molecules appeared to be transported to the hemocytic granules. In other cases, ligand still coated the blastospores after phagocytosis and may have later concentrated within the phagosome along with digested fungal cell wall components. Phagocytosis of blastospores and clustering of a biotinylated lectin conjugate on or within the granulocytes were inhibited by drugs targeting cytoskeletal elements. Actin was concentrated in the pseudopodia of phagocytic granulocytes and may be directly associated with lectin receptor(s). Microtubules were abundant in the granulocytes, sometimes in specific regions.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0302-766X</sn>
<an>A1996UW98300007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2463</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Variations in the Ability of Galactose and Mannose-Specific Lectins to Bind to Cell-Wall Surfaces during Growth of the Insect Pathogenic Fungus Paecilomyces-Farinosus</t1>
<jf>European journal of cell biology</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Cell Biol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>330</op>
<ab>The arrangement of carbohydrate molecules on surfaces of fungal cells may play an important role in nonself recognition of these microorganisms by potential invertebrate hosts. Changes in the ability of various galactose and mannose-specific lectins to bind to surface components on cell walls of the insect pathogen Paecilomyces farinosus were therefore examined during growth and differentiation of the fungus. Fluorescein isothiocyanate conjugates of concanavalin A (Con A, specific for alpha-D-mannose) and peanut agglutinin (PNA, beta-D-galaclose) bound inconsistently to blastospores and weakly to mycelia except at apical regions where strong fluorescence was observed. Labeling patterns were similar on cells tested with a galactose-specific lectin purified from Spodoptera exigua (beet armyworm) hemolymph, but Bandeiraea simplicifolia lectin (BS-I alpha-D-galactose) bound only to mycelia. Electron microscopy using ferritin and gold probes showed that the galactomannans are located in a loosely bound coating on the cell wall surface. Variations in lectin binding patterns are apparently due to absence (e.g., by shedding) of the coat or to rearrangement of carbohydrate components in the coat. Staining of Western blots of dithiothreitol (DTT) cell wall extracts further indicated that the BS-I-binding entity is a unique component of the mycelial surface since, as in the fluorescence studies, blastospore preparations were not labeled. Staining of blastospore blots with other galactose-specific probes (e.g., PNA) was comparable to staining of mycelial blots. Shedding or changes in the galactomannan coat on blastospores may prevent opsonization of these cells by host (e.g., S. exigua) lectins therefore preventing recognition by potentially phagocytic hemocytes; in addition, the presentation of receptor molecules (possibly mannoproteins) unique to the mycelial stage may allow these cells to be recognized without prior opsonization.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0171-9335</sn>
<an>A1993LA86000014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2467</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructural-Localization of Carbohydrate in Cell-Walls of the Entomogenous Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Canadian journal of microbiology</jf>
<jo>Can.J.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>377</sp>
<op>386</op>
<ab>Several probes were used in this ultrastructural study to localize polysaccharides in cell walls on conidial germ tubes, hyphal bodies, and mycelia of the entomogenous hyphomycete Nomuraea rileyi. With the exception of galactose, labelling patterns did not vary from one morphological stage to another. Galactose, which was localized by using a monoclonal antibody to a galactose-specific lectin purified from insect larval hemolymph, was absent from cell walls of hyphal bodies and conidia but was present on germ-tube and mycelial surfaces. Chitin (N-acetylglucosamine), labelled with a wheat-germ agglutinin-ferritin conjugate, was present in the middle regions of lateral walls and septa, and beta-1-4 glucans were located in the middle and inner regions, as indicated by binding of a cellulase-gold conjugate. An anti-laminaribiose antibody was used to label beta-1-3 glucans present in the outer wall areas and inner regions near the plasmalemma. The location of mannose residues as indicated by concanavalin A - ferritin binding was similar to that of the beta-1-3 glucans; vesicle-like structures were also labelled. None of the probes labelled the outer conidial pellicle or exocellular sheath surrounding germ tubes, and labelling of mycelial sheath was inconsistent. The absence of galactose from Nomuraea hal body walls is discussed in terms of host-parasite interaction.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0008-4166</sn>
<an>A1992JD66900004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2469</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Physicochemical Properties of Cell-Surfaces from the Different Developmental Stages of the Entomopathogenic Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Mycologia</jf>
<jo>Mycologia</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>MAY-JUN</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>264</sp>
<op>272</op>
<ab>Physicochemical properties of cell wall surfaces of conidia, conidial germ tubes, hyphal bodies and mycelia of the entomogenous hyphomycete Nomuraea rileyi were studied. Hydrophobicity was determined using a polystyrene microsphere adhesion assay. Microspheres bound to conidial germ tube and mycelial walls indicating that these surfaces are hydrophobic. Microspheres did not bind to hyphal body walls except at polar areas. Results from these experiments were confirmed using phase exclusion methods. Electrostatic charge characteristics of fungal surfaces were examined using DEAE (positively charged) and CM (negatively charged) beads. Cells from all growth phases adhered to DEAE but not CM beads indicating the presence of negatively charged sites on the surfaces. Degree of electronegativity as shown by FITC-poly-L-lysine binding is greatest on hyphal bodies and at the proximal end of germ tubes. Fluorescence was faint on conidia and mycelia. Cationized ferritin formed a thick capsule around hyphal body cells and a thinner but continuous layer on sheath material surrounding germ tubes; labeling of mycelial sheath was more random possibly due to the dispersed nature of this material. Areas of germ tubes or mycelium not covered by sheath were sparsely labeled as were conidial surfaces. Neutralization of hydrophobicity or electronegativity did not affect passive binding of conidial or mycelial cells to monolayers of insect hemocytes.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-5514</sn>
<an>A1991FU07600003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2485</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>The Hyphomycete Sorosporella - Syngliocladium from Mole Cricket, Scapteriscus-Vicinus</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>25</sp>
<op>30</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>A1987J118300005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2488</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Characteristics of a Galactose-Binding Hemagglutinin (Lectin) from Hemolymph of Spodoptera-Exigua Larvae</t1>
<jf>Developmental and comparative immunology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Comp.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>FAL</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>477</sp>
<op>487</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0145-305X</sn>
<an>A1986F693200002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2489</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Lectin Binding Characteristics of several Entomogenous Hyphomycetes - Possible Relationship to Insect Hemagglutinins</t1>
<jf>Mycologia</jf>
<jo>Mycologia</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>SEP-OCT</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>818</sp>
<op>824</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-5514</sn>
<an>A1986E452500018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2494</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Hemagglutinin Activity in the Hemolymph of Anticarsia-Gemmatalis Larvae Infected with the Fungus Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Developmental and comparative immunology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Comp.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>21</sp>
<op>30</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0145-305X</sn>
<an>A1985AGE2800003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2503</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Production and Regeneration of Protoplasts in the Entomogenous Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>285</sp>
<op>287</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1984SG55700023</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2499</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructure of Conidial Germination in the Entomopathogenic Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>432</sp>
<op>434</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1984SR06600018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2496</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Use of Labeled Lectins to Investigate Cell-Wall Surfaces of the Entomogenous Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>141</sp>
<op>148</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>A1984TT94700003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2508</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Lectins as Probes for the Investigation of Surface-Properties of the Entomogenous Hyphomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of Cell Biology</jf>
<jo>J.Cell Biol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>95</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>A136</sp>
<op>A136</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-9525</sn>
<an>A1982PN30200522</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2513</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructural Aspects of Conidiogenesis in the Entomogenous Hyhomycete Nomuraea-Rileyi</t1>
<jf>Canadian Journal of Botany-Revue Canadienne De Botanique</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>26</sp>
<op>33</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0008-4026</sn>
<an>A1982MZ93300004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2480</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Heath,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Function of a Galactose-Binding Lectin from Spodoptera-Exigua Larval Hemolymph - Opsonization of Blastospores from Entomogenous Hyphomycetes</t1>
<jf>Journal of insect physiology</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>533</sp>
<op>540</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-1910</sn>
<an>A1988N891100013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2453</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<t1>In-Vivo Development of the Entomogeneous Hyphomycete Paecilomyces-Farinosus in Host Spodoptera-Exigua (Beet Armyworm) Larvae</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>130</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>158</op>
<ab>The in vivo development of the entomogenous hyphomycete Paecilomyces farinosus in Spodoptera exigua (beet armyworm) larvae was examined using light and electron microscopic techniques. Blastospores injected into larval hemocoels (500 blastospores/larva) were immediately ingested by phagocytic hemocytes, and no fungal cells were detected in the hemolymph until similar to 36 h post-injection. As indicated by immunocytochemical methods, the in vivo-produced blastosopres, in contrast to in vitro blastospores, lacked a galacto-mannan surface layer required for opsonization by a S. exigua humoral lectin. Therefore, these in vivo cells were not recognized by phagocytic granulocytes and were freely-circulating in the hemolymph, Hyphae differentiating from the blastospores were recognized by the hemocytes and induced formation of multicellular hemocytic nodules. By 72 h post-injection, mycelia were observed emerging from the nodules and by 96 h, larvae had become mummified due to extensive proliferation of the fungus throughout host tissues, Neither phagocytosis of the initially injected in vitro-produced blastospores nor nodule formation around hyphal cells later in the infection process was effective in stopping fungal growth. The in vivo development of P. farinosus was similar to that of another hyphomycete, Beauveria bassiana except that in the latter case, extensive nodule formation was inhibited by the production of fungal metabolites.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>A1995RW02800005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2461</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Hung,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Evasion of Host-Defense by In-Vivo-Produced Protoplast-Like Cells of the Insect Mycopathogen Beauveria-Bassiana</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>175</vo>
<is>18</is>
<sp>5962</sp>
<op>5969</op>
<ab>In vivo cells (hyphal bodies) of the hyphomycetous insect pathogen Beauveria bassiana collected from host Spodoptera exigua larval hemolymph were osmotically sensitive and lacked a well-defined cell wall. In light and electron microscope studies, a galactose-specific lectin purified from S. exigua hemolymph, concanavalin A (specific for alpha-mannose), and a polyclonal antibody to B. bassiana cell walls all bound to surfaces of in vitro-produced B. bassiana blastospores; however, none of these probes labelled the thin layer of extracellular material covering the plasma membranes of hyphal bodies. These cells were observed freely circulating in S. exigua hemolymph at 36 h postinfection, although immunocompetent hemocytes were known to be present. Additionally, association of hyphal bodies with hemocytes in monolayers was significantly less than for opsonized in vitro blastospores or submerked conidia. The absence of antigenically important galactomannan components on in vivo cells may therefore allow these cells to escape recognition and phagocytosis. Lack of structural components (e.g., chitin, as evidenced by the absence of binding of wheat germ agglutinin) may also be important with respect to evasion of host cellular defense mechanisms. Production of wall material resumed 48 to 60 h postinfection and therefore may coincide with loss of phagocytic capabilities of the hemocytes due to immunosuppressive effects of fungal metabolites. The protoplast-like cells may be formed by the action of hydrolytic enzymes in the hemocytes or by inhibition of fungal cell wall synthetases.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-9193</sn>
<an>A1993LX11600027</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2457</id>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Lopezlastra,C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Laminin-Binding Sites on Cell-Walls of the Entomopathogen Nomuraea-Rileyi Associated with Growth and Adherence to Host Tissues</t1>
<jf>Mycologia</jf>
<jo>Mycologia</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>MAY-JUN</fd>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>327</sp>
<op>335</op>
<ab>The entomogenous hyphomycete Nomuraea rileyi replicates by budding or septation of yeast-like hyphal bodies in the hemocoels of host Spodoptera exigua (beet armyworm) larvae. Hyphal bodies are not recognized by host hemocytes and circulate freely in the hemolymph. Approximately 88 hours postinjection with 5 x 10(3) hyphal bodies per larva, the hyphal bodies begin to form germ tubes which have the ability to attach to hemocytes and other host tissues, e.g., fat body. Immunofluorescence studies showed that laminin, a common component of the extracellular matrix in vertebrates and invertebrates, binds to germ tubes but not to hyphal bodies. Binding to germ tubes is saturable, and the major binding site, as indicated by Western blots of cell wall extracts, is apparently a mannoprotein with a molecular mass of 76 kilodaltons. Immunoelectron microscopy revealed that laminin binds to the fibrillar sheath covering the germ tube wall. Laminin also binds to conidia but not to conidial germ tubes. The significance of the differential binding of laminin to N. rileyi surfaces during morphogenesis of the fungus as related to recognition by host hemocytes and attachment to host tissues is discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-5514</sn>
<an>A1994NZ04600002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2402</id>
<a1>Prompiboon,Pannipa</a1>
<a1>Bhumiratana,Amaret</a1>
<a1>Ruchirawat,Somsak</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<a1>Wiwat,Chanpen</a1>
<t1>Isolation of ergosterol peroxide from Nomuraea rileyi infected larvae of tobacco cutworm</t1>
<jf>World Journal of Microbiology &amp; Biotechnology</jf>
<jo>World J.Microbiol.Biotechnol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2909</sp>
<op>2917</op>
<ab>In the search for potential cytotoxic substances produced by Nomuraea rileyi, an active compound was isolated from mycosed insects through an activity guided fractionation process. The compound, cytotoxic against the Sf9 insect cell line, was identified to be ergosterol peroxide (5 alpha, 8 alpha-epidioxy-24(R)-methylcholesta-6, 22-dien-3 beta-ol) using nuclear magnetic resonance techniques, infrared spectrometry, and mass spectroscopy. Anticancer screens demonstrated that ergosterol peroxide at micromolar concentrations inhibited the growth of hormone-dependent breast cancer cell line (T47D), hormone-independent breast cancer cell line (MDA-MB-231), human epidermoid carcinoma in mouth cell line (KB), human cervical carcinoma cell line (HeLa), lung cancer cell line (H69AR) and human cholangiocarcinoma cell line (HuCCA-1). Ergosterol peroxide showed moderate effects against Spodoptera litura larvae; 46.7% mortality via topical application after 7 day post-treatment whereas the insect&amp;#39;s death was not found in per os application. The amounts of ergosterol peroxide produced by N. rileyi cultures under in vitro and in vivo were determined. The physiological levels of ergosterol peroxide detected in mycosed and mummified cadavers were very low (0.011 and 0.386 mu g/larva) less then levels that either inhibited insect cell proliferation or caused insecticidal activity.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0959-3993</sn>
<an>000260319900021</an>
<do>10.1007/s11274-008-9830-3</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2394</id>
<a1>Prompiboon,Pannipa</a1>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-Ulrike</a1>
<a1>Denton,John S. S.</a1>
<a1>Geden,Christopher J.</a1>
<a1>Steenberg,Tove</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Musca domestica Salivary Gland Hypertrophy Virus, a Globally Distributed Insect Virus That Infects and Sterilizes Female Houseflies</t1>
<jf>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>994</sp>
<op>998</op>
<ab>The housefly, Musca domestica, is a cosmopolitan pest of livestock and poultry and is of economic, veterinary, and public health importance. Populations of M. domestica are naturally infected with M. domestica salivary gland hypertrophy virus (MdSGHV), a nonoccluded double-stranded DNA virus that inhibits egg production in infected females and is characterized by salivary gland hypertrophy (SGH) symptoms. MdSGHV has been detected in housefly samples from North America, Europe, Asia, the Caribbean, and the southwestern Pacific. In this study, houseflies were collected from various locations and dissected to observe SGH symptoms, and infected gland pairs were collected for MdSGHV isolation and amplification in laboratory-reared houseflies. Differences among the MdSGHV isolates were examined by using molecular and bioassay approaches. Approximately 600-bp nucleotide sequences from each of five open reading frames having homology to genes encoding DNA polymerase and partial homology to the genes encoding four per os infectivity factor proteins (p74, pif-1, pif-2, and pif-3) were selected for phylogenetic analyses. Nucleotide sequences from 16 different geographic isolates were highly homologous, and the polymorphism detected was correlated with geographic source. The virulence of the geographic MdSGHV isolates was evaluated by per os treatment of newly emerged and 24-h-old houseflies with homogenates of infected salivary glands. In all cases, 24-h-old flies displayed a resistance to oral infection that was significantly greater than that displayed by newly eclosed adults. Regardless of the MdSGHV isolate tested, all susceptible insects displayed similar degrees of SGH and complete suppression of oogenesis.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0099-2240</sn>
<an>000274328900002</an>
<do>10.1128/AEM.02424-09</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2432</id>
<a1>Rosas-Acevedo,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Lezama,R.</a1>
<a1>Sims,K.</a1>
<a1>Pescador,A.</a1>
<t1>Exudate from sporulating cultures of Hirsutella thompsonii inhibit oviposition by the two-spotted spider mite Tetranychus urticae</t1>
<jf>Experimental and Applied Acarology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3-4</is>
<sp>213</sp>
<op>225</op>
<ab>The acaricidal mycopathogen Hirsutella thompsonii has been found to secrete metabolites that are active against female Tetranychus urticae. Specifically, the rose-colored exudate produced on sporulating cultures of Mexican HtM120I strain sterilized female spider mites in a dose-dependent fashion. Topical application of the exudate resulted in a 100% reduction in mite fecundity over the initial six days of experimentation. Depending upon the exudate dosage, mites partially recovered within 3 and 6 d post-treatment and produced a limited number of eggs. The spider mite active HtM120I exudate contained less detectable HtA toxin than the HtM120I broth filtrate, and it was innocuous when injected into the greater wax moth Galleria mellonella L. larvae. Broth filtrates of HtM120I cultures, although toxic to assayed G. mellonella larvae, did not inhibit mite oviposition to the degree or duration of the exudate preparations. These findings suggest that the factor responsible for suppressing oviposition in female spider mites is linked to the sporulation process and is distinct from the well-characterized HtA produced by vegetative cells.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0168-8162</sn>
<an>000185514700003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2399</id>
<a1>Salem,Tamer Z.</a1>
<a1>Garcia-Maruniak,Alejandra</a1>
<a1>Lietze,Verena-U</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of transcripts from predicted open reading frames of Musca domestica salivary gland hypertrophy virus</t1>
<jf>Journal of General Virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<sp>1270</sp>
<op>1280</op>
<ab>The Musca domestica salivary gland hypertrophy virus (MdSGHV) is a large dsDNA virus that infects and sterilizes adult houseflies. The transcriptome of this newly described virus was analysed by rapid amplification of cDNA 3&amp;#39;-ends (3&amp;#39;-RACE) and RT-PCR. Direct sequencing of 3&amp;#39;-RACE products revealed 78 poly(A) transcripts containing 95 of the 108 putative ORFs. An additional six ORFs not amplified by 3&amp;#39;-RACE were detected by RT-PCR. Only seven of the 108 putative ORFs were not amplified by either 3&amp;#39;-RACE or RT-PCR. A series of 5&amp;#39;-RACE reactions were conducted on selected ORFs that were identified by 3&amp;#39;-RACE to be transcribed in tandem (tandem transcripts). In the majority of cases, the downstream ORFs were detected as single transcripts as well as components of the tandem transcripts, whereas the upstream ORFs were found only in tandem transcripts. The only exception was the upstream ORF MdSGHV084, which was differentially transcribed as a single transcript at 1 and 2 days post-infection (days p.i.) and as a tandem transcript (MdSGHV084/085) at 2 days p.i. Transcriptome analysis of MdSGHV detected splicing in the 3&amp;#39; untranslated region (3&amp;#39;-UTR) and extensive heterogeneity in the polyadenylation signals and cleavage sites. In addition, 23 overlapping antisense transcripts were found. In conclusion, sequencing the 3&amp;#39;-RACE products without cloning served as an alternative approach to detect both 3&amp;#39;-UTRs and transcript variants of this large DNA virus.</ab>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 5</no>
<sn>0022-1317</sn>
<an>000266019700025</an>
<do>10.1099/vir.0.009613-0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2456</id>
<a1>Sarfati,J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Latge,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Antigens of Aspergillus-Fumigatus Produced In-Vivo</t1>
<jf>Journal of Medical and Veterinary Mycology</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>JAN-FEB</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>9</sp>
<op>14</op>
<ab>Immunoblots of extracts from kidneys of mice infected intravenously with Aspergillus fumigatus were probed with human sera from patients with aspergilloma. A limited number of antigens were detected with molecular masses of 31, 36, 56, 84, 88 and 200 kDa. These antigens can be clustered into two classes: (i) galactomannan and/or galactofuran-containing glycoproteins; and (ii) antigenic proteins (31, 36 and 88 kDa) exempt of the galactofuran epitope. Antigens belonging to this second class were also produced in vitro but were not the major proteins expressed by A. fumigatus in a glucose-asparagin medium.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0268-1218</sn>
<an>A1995QZ83200002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2393</id>
<a1>Scharf,Michael E.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>Potential of termite-based biomass pre-treatment strategies for use in bioethanol production</t1>
<jf>Insect Science</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>166</sp>
<op>174</op>
<ab>When considering the current state of the biorefinery industry, it is readily apparent that industrial cellulose and hemicellulose digestion processes are relatively advanced, whereas enzymatic pre-treatment strategies for biomass delignification and cellulose solubilization are not well developed. The need for efficient biomass pre-treatment strategies presents a significant opportunity for researchers studying lignocellulose digestion in termites and other insects. With an emphasis on industrial biomass pre-treatment, this review provides an overview of: (i) industrial biorefining operations (feedstocks, processing, and economics); (ii) recent findings from termite research that have revealed candidate enzymes; and (iii) research needs and opportunities for consideration by entomologists working in this area. With respect to research findings, recently identified candidate lignases (laccases, catalases, peroxidases, esterases), other potentially important detoxification enzymes (cytochrome P450, superoxide dismutase), and phenolic acid esterases (carboxylesterases) that may assist in hemicellulose solubilization are overviewed. Regarding research needs and opportunities, several approaches for identification of candidate pre-treatment enzymes from upstream, symbiont-free gut regions are also described.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1672-9609</sn>
<an>000278345200002</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1744-7917.2009.01309.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2425</id>
<a1>Sims,K.</a1>
<a1>Funderburk,J.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D.</a1>
<t1>Host-parasite biology of Thripinema fuscum (Tylenchida : Allantonematidae) and Franklinielia fusca (Thysanoptera : Thripidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>4</sp>
<op>11</op>
<ab>Thripinema fuscum is a natural enemy of Frankliniella fusca in peanut. Laboratory experiments were conducted to determine the reproductive biology of T. fuscum as affected by gender and stage of development of the host and to determine the effects of parasitism on host longevity, Fecundity, and mortality. The adult females of F. fusca were the most readily parasitized (P &amp;lt; 0.001) in the laboratory experiments followed by the second instars, the first instars, and the adult males. One generation of T. fascum developed within the parasitized larvae and adults, with the males and females emerging only during the adult stage of the host. Parasitism did not cause mortality of the host. Parasitism affected male longevity (P &amp;lt; 0.001) but not female longevity. The adult female thrips that were parasitized as first or second instars did not Jay eggs, and the adult females stopped laying eggs within 3 days of being parasitized. The fernale-to-male sex ratio of T fuscum? emerging from parasitized male and female E fusca was 22 and 18 to 1, respectively. More T. fuscum emerged from female hosts than from male hosts (P &amp;lt; 0.001). More emerged from hosts parasitized as larvae compared with hosts parasitized as adults (P &amp;lt; 0.05). The intrinsic capacity of increase of T. fascum ranged between 0 29 . and 0.37 when parasitizing the adult males and females and between 0.18 and 0.21 when parasitizing the larval males and females. Percent parasitism of E fusca was estimated in peanut fields. The flowers were the primary site for aggregation of the adults of F. fusca and for the free-living females of T. fuscum to parasitize new hosts. As under laboratory conditions, field parasitism of adult males was less than parasitism of adult females in 2001 and 2002 (P &amp;lt; 0.01 and 0.001, respectively). Our study indicates that T. fuscum is a potential biological control agent capable Of Suppressing F. fusca populations in peanut.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<an>000230220000002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2397</id>
<a1>Sims,Kelly R.</a1>
<a1>Funderburk,Joe E.</a1>
<a1>Reitz,Stuart R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<t1>The impact of a parasitic nematode, Thripinema fuscum, on the feeding behavior and vector competence of Frankliniella fusca</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>200</sp>
<op>208</op>
<ab>Frankliniella fusca (Hinds) (Thysanoptera: Thripidae) is the predominant thrips species found inhabiting and reproducing in peanut, Arachis hypogaea L. (Fabaceae), and is one of at least seven thrips species reported to transmit Tomato spotted wilt virus (TSWV). The entomogenous nematode Thripinema fuscum Tipping &amp;amp; Nguyen (Tylenchida: Allantonematidae), a natural enemy of F. fusca, parasitizes larval and adult populations under field conditions. All known Thripinema species render the host female thrips sterile and have the potential to suppress pest populations to near extinction. As a result, secondary spread of TSWV in peanut is reduced. Reduction of the virus under field conditions may also be due to lower transmission rates caused by parasite-induced alterations in host feeding behavior. Therefore, the feeding rates of healthy and parasitized F. fusca male and female cohorts on leaf discs were recorded daily for 10 days and digital images were subjected to image analysis and viral transmission rates were compared daily using double antibody sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Thripinema fuscum reduced the feeding of female F. fusca by nearly 65%, and the ability of females to transmit TSWV by 50%. Potential mechanisms underlying the parasite-induced alterations in feeding behavior and transmission are discussed. Parasitism by T. fuscum significantly reduced male longevity, but female longevity was not affected. These results provide further evidence that T. fuscum aids in regulating viruliferous F. fusca pest populations and suggests its potential as a biological control agent for inoculative release in peanut.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8703</sn>
<an>000267949300012</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1570-7458.2009.00884.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2443</id>
<a1>SosaGomez,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Nation,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Attachment of Metarhizium anisopliae to the southern green stink bug Nezara viridula cuticle and fungistatic effect of cuticular lipids and aldehydes</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>31</sp>
<op>39</op>
<ab>In this paper we examined the conidial attachment of Metarhizium anisopliae on the southern green stink bug, Nezara viridula, using the exuvia and nymphal stage of the host as a substrate for M. anisopliae conidiospores. Initial studies using fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-labeled conidia examined the differential binding of conidia to various sites on the cuticle. Both the topography and the chemistry of the cuticle affected conidial adhesion. Conidia were trapped in areas containing large numbers of setae (e.g., antennal tips, apical portions of tibia and tarsi). Chemical treatments to remove the cuticle proteins did not affect conidial adhesion, but solvent extraction of cuticular lipids significantly reduced the adhesion of IM. anisopliae spores. Germination of M. anisopliae conidia attached to N. viridula cuticle was much less than conidia attached to other insect cuticle substrates. After a 24-hr incubation, only 5-20% of the conidia produced detectable germ tubes. The aldehyde (E)-2-decenal, a primary component of the stink bug scent gland, was detected in cuticle extracts and found to be selectively fungistatic to certain entomopathogenic fungi, including M. anisopliae. The hydrocarbon fraction (nC13 and nC21 to nC31 hydrocarbon series) served as a binding substrate for M. anisopliae, but conidia did not degrade these hydrocarbons and did not use them as a carbon source. (C) 1997 Academic Press.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1997WJ83700005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2470</id>
<a1>Storey,G. K.</a1>
<a1>Vandermeer,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,C. W.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Fire Ant (Solenopsis-Invicta) Venom Alkaloids on the Invitro Germination and Development of Selected Entomogenous Fungi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>58</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>88</sp>
<op>95</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1991FU16600012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2421</id>
<a1>Suwannakut,S.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Wiwat,C.</a1>
<t1>Genotypic analysis of Nomuraea rileyi collected from various noctuid hosts</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>169</sp>
<op>176</op>
<ab>The genetic diversity of 79 Nomuraea rileyi isolates from various lepidopteran hosts in Asia, North America, and South America was evaluated using amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) analysis. Cluster analysis separated the X rileyi isolates into two major groups and seven subgroups. The resulting dendrogram generally classified the N. rileyi isolates based on insect host and geographical region. The haplotypic diversity index of N. rileyi subpopulations from each location and host origin was ranging from 0.8788 to 1.000. However, analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) demonstrated no significant differences (p = 0.3421) among N. rileyi isolates from different continents. Whereas the genetic variation among the N. rileyi populations from the different host insects within each continent was significantly different (p &amp;lt; 0.0001). (c) 2005 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000233916900004</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2005.08.010</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2427</id>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>The non-photo synthetic, pathogenic green alga Helicosporidium sp has retained a modified, functional plastid genome</t1>
<jf>FEMS microbiology letters</jf>
<jo>FEMS Microbiol.Lett.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>APR 1</fd>
<vo>233</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>153</sp>
<op>157</op>
<ab>A fragment of the Helicosporidium sp. (Chlorophyta: Trebouxiophyceae) plastid genome has been sequenced. The genome architecture was compared to that of both a non-photosynthetic relative (Prototheca wickerhamii) and a photosynthetic relative (Chlorella vulgaris). Comparative genomic analysis indicated that Helicosporidium and Prototheca are closely related genera. The analyses also revealed that the Helicosporidium sp. plastid genome has been rearranged. In particular, two ribosomal protein-encoding genes (rpl19 and rps23) appeared to have been transposed, or lost from the Helicosporidium sp. plastid genome. RT-PCR reactions demonstrated that the retained plastid genes were transcribed, suggesting that, despite rearrangement(s), the Helicosporidium sp. plastid genome has remained functional. The modified plastid genome architecture is a novel apomorphy that indicates that the Helicosporidia are highly derived green algae, more so than Prototheca spp. As such, they represent a promising model to study organellar genome reorganizations in parasitic protists. (C) 2004 Federation of European Microbiological Societies. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0378-1097</sn>
<an>000220630200021</an>
<do>10.1016/j.femsle.2004.02.006</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2426</id>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>A pilot-scale Expressed Sequence Tag analysis of Beauveria bassiana gene expression reveals a tripeptidyl peptidase that is differentially expressed in vivo</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>158</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>209</op>
<ab>The entomopathogen Beauveria bassiana is a dimorphic fungus that displays an in vivo-specific, yeast-like parasitic phase. In order to study the transcriptome of B. bassiana during this unique developmental phase, we developed a method to harvest in vivo B. bassiana cells from infected Manduca sexta larvae. The infected hemolymph was collected just prior to insect death and subjected to gradient centrifugation, which allowed for separation of the B. bassiana in vivo-produced cells from remaining insect hemocytes. Total RNA was extracted from the harvested fungal cells and used to construct a cDNA library that is representative of B. bassiana gene expression in vivo. Expressed Sequence Tags (ESTs) were generated and led to the cloning of two protease genes. One of these proteases was identified as a tripeptidyl peptidase (Bb TPP). The Bb TPP protease was shown to be up-regulated during infection, and identification of a signal peptide suggested that the enzyme is secreted in the host hemolymph. Although its activity and role have yet to be characterized, the Bb TPP protease appears as a likely candidate for being involved in B. bassiana pathogenesis. The identification of this novel, up-regulated protease also suggests that random sequencing from our in vivo cDNA library may be a valuable step towards identifying biologically active metabolites produced in vivo by B. bassiana.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>000223918600009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2436</id>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Adams,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Becnel,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Phylogenetic analysis identifies the invertebrate pathogen Helicosporidium sp as a green alga (Chlorophyta)</t1>
<jf>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Syst.Evol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>52</vo>
<sp>273</sp>
<op>279</op>
<ab>Historically, the invertebrate pathogens of the genus Helicosporidium were considered to be either protozoa or fungi, but the taxonomic position of this group has not been considered since 1931. Recently, a Helicosporidium sp., isolated from the blackfly Simulium jonesi Stone &amp;amp; Snoddy (Diptera: Simuliidae), has been amplified in the heterologous host Helicoverpa zea. Genomic DNA has been extracted from gradient-purified cysts. The 18S, 28S and 5.8S regions of the Helicosporidium rDNA, as well as partial sequences of the actin and beta-tubulin genes, were amplified by PCR and sequenced. Comparative analysis of these nucleotide sequences was performed using neighbour-joining and maximum-parsimony methods. All inferred phylogenetic trees placed Helicosporidium sp. among the green algae (Chlorophyta), and this association was supported by bootstrap and parsimony jackknife values. Phylogenetic analysis focused on the green algae depicted Helicosporidium sp. as a close relative of Prototheca wickerhamii and Prototheca zopfii (Chlorophyta, Trebouxiophyceae), two achlorophylous, pathogenic green algae. On the basis of this phylogenetic analysis, Helicosporidium sp. is clearly neither a protist nor a fungus, but appears to be the first described algal invertebrate pathogen. These conclusions lead us to propose the transfer of the genus Helicosporidium to Chlorophyta, Trebouxiophyceae.</ab>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 1</no>
<sn>1466-5026</sn>
<an>000173464200028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2430</id>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Becnel,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Adams,B. J.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of plastid 16S rRNA (rrn 16) genes from Helicosporidium spp.: evidence supporting the reclassification of Helicosporidia as green algae (Chlorophyta)</t1>
<jf>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Syst.Evol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<sp>1719</sp>
<op>1723</op>
<ab>The Helicosporidia are invertebrate pathogens that have recently been identified as non-photosynthetic green algae (Chlorophyta). In order to confirm the algal nature of the genus Helicosporidium, the presence of a retained chloroplast genome in Helicosporidia cells was investigated. Fragments homologous to plastid 16S rRNA (rrn 16) genes were amplified successfully from cellular DNA extracted from two different Helicosporidium isolates. The fragment sequences are 1269 and 1266 by long, are very AT-rich (60.7 %) and are similar to homologous genes sequenced from non-photosynthetic green algae. Maximum-parsimony, maximum-likelihood and neighbour-joining methods were used to infer phylogenetic trees from an rrn16 sequence alignment. All trees depicted the Helicosporidia as sister taxa to the non-photosynthetic, pathogenic alga Prototheca zopfii. Moreover, the trees identified Helicosporidium spp. as members of a clade that included the heterotrophic species Prototheca spp. and the mesotrophic species Chlorella protothecoides. The clade is always strongly supported by bootstrap values, suggesting that all these organisms share a most recent common ancestor. Phylogenetic analyses inferred from plastid 16S rRNA genes confirmed that the Helicosporidia are non-photosynthetic green algae, close relatives of the genus Prototheca (Chlorophyta, Trebouxiophyceae). Such phylogenetic affinities suggest that Helicosporidium spp. are likely to possess Prototheca-like organelles and organelle genomes.</ab>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 6</no>
<sn>1466-5026</sn>
<an>000186918500003</an>
<do>10.1099/ijs.0.02559-0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2422</id>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Scharf,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Differential expression of chitin synthase (CHS) and glucan synthase (FKS) genes correlates with the formation of a modified, thinner cell wall in in vivo-produced Beauveria bassiana cells</t1>
<jf>Mycopathologia</jf>
<jo>Mycopathologia</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>160</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>303</sp>
<op>314</op>
<ab>During infection (in vivo), the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana produces yeast-like cells that are surrounded by modified cell walls. These modifications have been related to the fungus ability to limit recognition by the host defense system. The composition of the in vivo cell wall was analyzed using a combination of cytochemical and molecular techniques. The in vivo cell walls still contained both chitin and 1,3-beta-glucan, but they were significantly thinner than in vitro cell walls (50-60 nm versus 100-160 nm, respectively). The difference in cell wall thickness was correlated with transcriptional regulation of cell wall-related genes: quantitative RT-PCR reactions demonstrated that B. bassiana chitin synthase (CHS) and glucan synthase (FKS) genes are down regulated in vivo. These analyses indicate that in vivo-triggered phenotypic modifications, including cell wall adjustments, are controlled by molecular mechanisms that include regulation of gene expression at the transcriptional level.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0301-486X</sn>
<an>000232794800007</an>
<do>10.1007/s11046-005-0134-y</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2395</id>
<a1>Tartar,Aurelian</a1>
<a1>Wheeler,Marsha M.</a1>
<a1>Zhou,Xuguo</a1>
<a1>Coy,Monique R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<a1>Scharf,Michael E.</a1>
<t1>Parallel metatranscriptome analyses of host and symbiont gene expression in the gut of the termite Reticulitermes flavipes</t1>
<jf>Biotechnology for Biofuels</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>OCT 15</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<sp>25</sp>
<op>25</op>
<ab>Background: Termite lignocellulose digestion is achieved through a collaboration of host plus prokaryotic and eukaryotic symbionts. In the present work, we took a combined host and symbiont metatranscriptomic approach for investigating the digestive contributions of host and symbiont in the lower termite Reticulitermes flavipes. Our approach consisted of parallel high-throughput sequencing from (i) a host gut cDNA library and (ii) a hindgut symbiont cDNA library. Subsequently, we undertook functional analyses of newly identified phenoloxidases with potential importance as pretreatment enzymes in industrial lignocellulose processing. Results: Over 10,000 expressed sequence tags (ESTs) were sequenced from the 2 libraries that aligned into 6,555 putative transcripts, including 171 putative lignocellulase genes. Sequence analyses provided insights in two areas. First, a non-overlapping complement of host and symbiont (prokaryotic plus protist) glycohydrolase gene families known to participate in cellulose, hemicellulose, alpha carbohydrate, and chitin degradation were identified. Of these, cellulases are contributed by host plus symbiont genomes, whereas hemicellulases are contributed exclusively by symbiont genomes. Second, a diverse complement of previously unknown genes that encode proteins with homology to lignase, antioxidant, and detoxification enzymes were identified exclusively from the host library (laccase, catalase, peroxidase, superoxide dismutase, carboxylesterase, cytochrome P450). Subsequently, functional analyses of phenoloxidase activity provided results that were strongly consistent with patterns of laccase gene expression. In particular, phenoloxidase activity and laccase gene expression are mostly restricted to symbiont-free foregut plus salivary gland tissues, and phenoloxidase activity is inducible by lignin feeding. Conclusion: To our knowledge, this is the first time that a dual host-symbiont transcriptome sequencing effort has been conducted in a single termite species. This sequence database represents an important new genomic resource for use in further studies of collaborative host-symbiont termite digestion, as well as development of coevolved host and symbiont-derived biocatalysts for use in industrial biomass-to-bioethanol applications. Additionally, this study demonstrates that: (i) phenoloxidase activities are prominent in the R. flavipes gut and are not symbiont derived, (ii) expands the known number of host and symbiont glycosyl hydrolase families in Reticulitermes, and (iii) supports previous models of lignin degradation and host-symbiont collaboration in cellulose/hemicellulose digestion in the termite gut. All sequences in this paper are available publicly with the accession numbers FL634956-FL640828 (Termite Gut library) and FL641015-FL645753 (Symbiont library).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1754-6834</sn>
<an>000272095400001</an>
<do>10.1186/1754-6834-2-25</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2501</id>
<a1>Temerak,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Whitcomb,W. H.</a1>
<t1>A Singly-Embedded Nuclear Polyhedrosis-Virus and Entomophagous Insects Associated with Populations of the Bean Leafroller Urbanus-Proteus L (Lepid, Hesperiidae)</t1>
<jf>Zeitschrift Fur Angewandte Entomologie-Journal of Applied Entomology</jf>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>97</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>187</sp>
<op>191</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-2240</sn>
<an>A1984SJ17700013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2415</id>
<a1>Tigano,Myrian S.</a1>
<a1>Adams,Byron</a1>
<a1>Maimala,Saowanit</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion</a1>
<t1>Genetic diversity of Hirsutella thompsonii isolates from Thailand based on AFLP analysis and partial beta-tubulin gene sequences</t1>
<jf>Genetics and Molecular Biology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>715</sp>
<op>721</op>
<ab>Amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) was used to investigate polymorphism among 43 Hirsutella thompsonii isolates (33 from Thailand) obtained from various mite species. The outgroups were an unidentified Hirsutella isolate along with Hirsutella nodulosa and Hirsutella kirchneri. Phylogenetic analyses of the AFLP data showed significant variation among isolates and the existence of three H. thompsonii clades. We also investigated the isolates using PCR with specific primers for the Hirsutella exotoxin gene Hirsutelin A (HtA) and 18 of these isolates were used for sequencing of the partial beta-tubulin gene. Phylogenetic analyses of beta-tubulin sequences showed two distinct H. thompsonii clades, one of which included AFLP clades I and II. For both markers grouping of the H. thompsonii isolates was not related to either host mite species or geographical origin, although for the HtA gene one clade contained only isolates with no detectable HtA band. These results confirm the high intraspecific polymorphism of H. thompsonii, and maximum likelihood analysis showed no monophyletic group within this species. To refine the taxonomy of this genus other studies should be undertaken using additional molecular markers and several other Hirsutella isolates.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1415-4757</sn>
<an>000242662800022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2411</id>
<a1>Torto,Baldwyn</a1>
<a1>Arbogast,Richard T.</a1>
<a1>Alborn,Hans</a1>
<a1>Suazo,Alonso</a1>
<a1>van Engelsdorp,Dennis</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion</a1>
<a1>Tumlinson,James H.</a1>
<a1>Teal,Peter E. A.</a1>
<t1>Composition of volatiles from fermenting pollen dough and attractiveness to the small hive beetle Aethina tumida, a parasite of the honeybee Apis mellifera</t1>
<jf>Apidologie</jf>
<jo>Apidologie</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>JUL-AUG</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>380</sp>
<op>389</op>
<ab>The response of the small hive beetle ( SHB), Aethina tumida Murray, to volatiles from a pollen-based diet conditioned by the feeding of 100 adult virgin female or male SHBs ( 4-8 weeks old) for 1, 3, 7 or 14 days is described and compared to that of the same diet inoculated with the yeast Kodamaea ohmeri ( NRRL Y-30722), isolated from the beetle. In a wind tunnel, volatiles from pollen dough conditioned by beetles of either sex for 3 or 7 days lured significantly more beetles into traps than volatiles from unconditioned dough. In contrast, trap captures with volatiles from dough conditioned for 1 and 14 days were weakly attractive. In cage bioassays, when naive, unfed, virgin, SHBs ( 3-4 days old) were given a choice between yeast-inoculated pollen dough and non-inoculated dough, the responses were similar to those obtained in the wind tunnel with dough conditioned by SHBs for 3 and 7 days. Chemical analysis revealed high levels of fermentation-related products in volatiles that attracted the beetle.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-8435</sn>
<an>000250083400008</an>
<do>10.1051/apido:2007024</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2410</id>
<a1>Torto,Baldwyn</a1>
<a1>Arbogast,Richard T.</a1>
<a1>Van Engelsdorp,Dennis</a1>
<a1>Willms,Steven</a1>
<a1>Purcell,Dusti</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion</a1>
<a1>Tumlinson,James H.</a1>
<a1>Teal,Peter E. A.</a1>
<t1>Trapping of Aethina tumida Murray (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae) from Apis mellifera L. (Hymenoptera : Apidae) colonies with an in-hive baited trap</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1018</sp>
<op>1024</op>
<ab>The effectiveness of two lures for trapping the small hive beetle, Aethina tumida, by means of in-hive traps was tested by field trials in apiaries located in Florida, Delaware, and Pennsylvania during 2003-2005. Both lures included a mixture (pollen dough) consisting of bee pollen and commercial pollen substitute formulated with or without glycerol and honey. Before it was used in the traps, the dough was conditioned either by the feeding of adult small hive beetles or by inoculation with the yeast Kodamaea ohmeri (NRRL Y-30722). Traps baited with conditioned dough captured significantly more beetles than unbaited traps, and traps positioned under the bottom board of a hive captured significantly more beetles than traps located at the top of a hive. In fact, baited in-hive bottom board traps nearly eliminated the beetles from colonies at a pollination site in Florida. However, when these honey bee colonies were moved to an apiary, trap catch increased markedly over time, indicating a resurgence of the beetle population produced by immigration of beetles from nearby hives or emerging from the soil. In tests at three Florida apiaries during 2006, yeast-inoculated dough baited bottom board traps captured significantly more beetles than unbaited traps, showing the effectiveness of yeast-inoculated dough as a lure and its potential as a tool in managing the small hive beetle.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000250128900005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2413</id>
<a1>Torto,Baldwyn</a1>
<a1>Boucias,Drion G.</a1>
<a1>Arbogast,Richard T.</a1>
<a1>Tumlinson,James H.</a1>
<a1>Teal,Peter E. A.</a1>
<t1>Multitrophic interaction facilitates parasite-host relationship between an invasive beetle and the honey bee</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>MAY 15</fd>
<vo>104</vo>
<is>20</is>
<sp>8374</sp>
<op>8378</op>
<ab>Colony defense by honey bees, Apis mellifera, is associated with stinging and mass attack, fueled by the release of alarm pheromones. Thus, alarm pheromones are critically important to survival of honey bee colonies. Here we report that in the parasitic relationship between the European honey bee and the small hive beetle, Aethina tumida, the honey bee&amp;#39;s alarm pheromones serve a negative function because they are potent attractants for the beetle. Furthermore, we discovered that the beetles from both Africa and the United States vector a strain of Kodamaea ohmeri yeast, which produces these same honey bee alarm pheromones when grown on pollen in hives. The beetle is not a pest of African honey bees because African bees have evolved effective methods to mitigate beetle infestation. However, European honey bees, faced with disease and pest management stresses different from those experienced by African bees,are unable to effectively inhibit beetle infestation. Therefore, the environment of the European honey bee colony provides optimal conditions to promote the unique bee-beetle-yeast-pollen multitrophic interaction that facilitates effective infestation of hives at the expense of the European honey bee.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0027-8424</sn>
<an>000246599900034</an>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0702813104</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2428</id>
<a1>Wattanalai,R.</a1>
<a1>Wiwat,C.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Tartar,A.</a1>
<t1>Chitinase gene of the dimorphic mycopathogen, Nomuraea rileyi</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>54</sp>
<op>57</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>000220097100008</an>
<do>10.1016/j.jip.2003.12.007</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
