<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1745</id>
<a1>Gross,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Weissman,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Veenker,E.</a1>
<a1>Cohen,J. I.</a1>
<t1>The diagnostic utility of computed tomography for preoperative localization in surgery for hyperparathyroidism</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>114</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>227</sp>
<op>231</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hyperparathyroidism/radiography/radionuclide imaging/surgery/ultrasonography</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Successful unilateral or minimal-access parathyroid exploration and reoperative surgery of the parathyroid glands requires accurate preoperative localization of parathyroid disease. Although ultrasound and nuclear imaging techniques have an established role in this regard, the use of computed tomography (CT) for parathyroid exploration is not well understood. The purpose of the present study was to better define the diagnostic utility of CT in preoperative localization of the abnormal gland in surgery for hyperparathyroidism. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective cohort study. METHODS: All parathyroid explorations performed at Oregon Health and Science University (Portland, OR) between 2000 and 2002 were reviewed. The study group was limited to patients with hyperparathyroidism in whom localization failed preoperatively using ultrasound and/or sestamibi scanning and subsequent investigation using CT imaging was performed. Operative, pathological, and imaging reports were then analyzed to assess the accuracy of CT imaging for localizing parathyroid disease. RESULTS: Twenty-two patients with hyperparathyroidism were investigated preoperatively using CT imaging. Parathyroid exploration was successful in all but one patient, leaving 21 patients in all in the cohort. The majority of cases (67%) were reoperative, and all patients had previously undergone inconclusive ultrasound and/or sestamibi scanning. Computed tomography correctly localized parathyroid disease in 18 (86%) of the 21 patients who underwent successful extirpation of parathyroid disease and was able to identify abnormal glands with equal utility in the neck and the chest. CONCLUSION: When ultrasound or sestamibi are unsuccessful, CT imaging can provide valuable preoperative localizing information before surgery for hyperparathyroidism, particularly in patients with recurrent or persistent disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Oregon Health and Science University, 3181 Southwest Sam Jackson Park Road, Portland, OR 97239, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14755195</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200402000-00010</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14755195</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1744</id>
<a1>Leon,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Catalanotto,F. A.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Retronasal and orthonasal olfactory ability after laryngectomy</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>133</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>36</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngectomy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nose</k1>
<k1>Olfaction Disorders/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Self Assessment (Psychology)</k1>
<k1>Smell/physiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To characterize orthonasal and retronasal olfactory ability in patients who have had a total laryngectomy (TL). DESIGN: Prospective psychophysical evaluation of orthonasal and retronasal olfactory function. SETTING: Academic center outpatient clinic. PATIENTS: Volunteer sample of 36 subjects who underwent laryngectomy 0.5 to 25.0 years after TL (median, 3.5 years) and 36 age-, sex-, and smoking history-matched controls. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Scores on established psychophysical tests of orthonasal and retronasal olfaction and self-rating scores of smell assessed with a visual analog scale. RESULTS: Assessment of orthonasal olfactory ability yielded a mean composite score of 4.3 (maximum score, 7) for the TL group and 5.3 for the control group (P = .002). Evaluation of retronasal olfactory ability resulted in a mean score of 11.0 (maximum score, 20) for the TL group vs 14.3 for the control group (P&amp;lt;.001). The mean self-rating scores of smell were 2.9 and 6.6 (maximum score, 10) for the TL and control groups, respectively (P&amp;lt;.001). Self-ratings of smell positively correlated with orthonasal (r(S) = 0.42; P&amp;lt;.001) and retronasal (r(S) = 0.50; P&amp;lt;.001) olfactory ability. CONCLUSIONS: Laryngectomy is associated with measurable decreases in olfactory function that are also subjectively perceived. Quantification of decrements in orthonasal and retronasal olfactory function can be used to characterize the severity of hyposmia and to assess the potential for, and efficacy of, olfactory rehabilitation. Although self-assessment with a simple visual analog scale successfully identifies many laryngectomy patients who have objective evidence of olfactory dysfunction, further investigation is necessary to evaluate and compare its validity and reliability with other available survey instruments that purport to measure olfaction.</ab>
<no>JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology and Community Dentistry and Behavioral Science, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17224519; 133/1/32 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archotol.133.1.32</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17224519</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1746</id>
<a1>Veenker,E.</a1>
<a1>Cohen,J. I.</a1>
<t1>Current trends in management of Zenker diverticulum</t1>
<jf>Current Opinion in Otolaryngology &amp; Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Curr.Opin.Otolaryngol.Head Neck Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>160</sp>
<op>165</op>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Physician&#39;s Practice Patterns/trends</k1>
<k1>Zenker Diverticulum/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<ab>Zenker&amp;#39;s diverticulum is a relatively common problem encountered by head and neck surgeons. Careful review of the available literature regarding its pathogenesis indicates that Zenker diverticulum likely occurs as a result of increased intrabolus pressures during swallowing secondary to cricopharyngeal spasm. Rational treatment for Zenker diverticulum therefore addresses cricopharyngeal spasm. The traditional approach to diagnosis and management of Zenker diverticulum has been based on standard techniques and principles. For example, diverticulectomy with concurrent cricopharyngeal myotomy is an acceptable form of treatment with a high success rate. However, recent advances in endoscopic stapling and carbon dioxide laser technologies have added new options to the therapeutic armament of the otolaryngologist. For appropriately selected patients, endoscopic staple-assisted diverticulostomy is a minimally invasive, safe, and effective procedure associated with shorter hospital stays, more rapid postoperative recovery, decreased time to resumption of oral intake, and high levels of patient satisfaction.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 9417024; RF: 16; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1068-9508; 1068-9508</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology/Head and Neck Surgery, Division of Head and Neck Surgery/Oncology, Oregon Health and Sciences University, Portland, Oregon, USA. cohenj@ohsu.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12923356</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12923356</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1747</id>
<a1>Veenker,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Andersen,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Cohen,J. I.</a1>
<t1>Cricopharyngeal spasm and Zenker&amp;#39;s diverticulum</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>681</sp>
<op>694</op>
<k1>Algorithms</k1>
<k1>Deglutition/physiology</k1>
<k1>Deglutition Disorders/complications/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Diverticulitis/complications/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Gastroesophageal Reflux/complications/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Pharyngeal Muscles/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Spasm/complications/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Zenker Diverticulum/complications/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<ab>Cricopharyngeal spasm and Zenker&amp;#39;s diverticulum represent disorders of the pharyngoesophageal junction for which a unifying theory of etiology has yet to be established. There is, however, a large body of evidence that supports an association with gastroesophageal reflux. Cricopharyngeal myotomy is the key to successful management of both disorders. Newer transoral endoscopic techniques of management have a lower overall morbidity than traditional open approaches in appropriately selected patients and are therefore gaining popularity as the preferred method of treatment.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2003; JID: 8902541; RF: 101; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Oregon Health and Sciences University, Department of Otolaryngology/Head and Neck Surgery, 3181 SW Sam Jackson Park Rd, Portland, Oregon 97201-3098, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12884352</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.10268</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12884352</pmid></reference></refworks>
