<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3970</id>
<a1>Gourdine,J. S.</a1>
<a1>McCutcheon,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Simmons,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Kale floral nectar and honey as food sources for enhancing longevity and parasitism of Diadegma insulare (Hymenoptera : Ichneumonidae), a parasitoid of the diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella (Lepidoptera : Plutellidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Agricultural and Urban Entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Agric.Urban Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>6</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>1523-5475 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000220646800001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3980</id>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Sanchez,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Lecrone,S. H.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Nitrogen and Foliar Biomass on Population Parameters of Cabbage Insects</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>7</sp>
<op>16</op>
<ab>The effects of different nitrogen (N) fertilization rates (0, 45, 90, and 168 kg N/ha), plant nitrogen concentration, and plant biomass on abundance and population growth of diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella (L.), cabbage looper, Trichoplusia ni (Hubner), cabbage budworm, Hellula phidilealis (Walker), imported cabbageworm, Artogeia rapae (L.), and cross-striped cabbageworm, Evergestis rimosalis (Guenee), were investigated in Homestead and Sanford, Florida in 1987. The effects of these factors on the parasitization of P. xylostella were also examined. In Homestead, abundance of most insect pests and parasitized P. xylostella increased with an increase in the level of N applied and with an increase in plant biomass. Similar results were found in Sanford, although results were not consistently significant. Abundance of most insect pests was significantly positively correlated with plant N concentration. Multiple regression analyses indicated that foliar biomass was significantly more important than N fertilization rate and subsequent plant N concentration at predicting abundance of insect pests and parasitized P. xylostella on cabbage.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 11</no>
<sn>0013-8703 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1991GR52400002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3968</id>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Heimpel,G. E.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Comparing floral nectar and aphid honeydew diets on the longevity and nutrient levels of a parasitoid wasp</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>111</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>189</sp>
<op>199</op>
<ab>We compared the effects of floral nectar from buckwheat, Fagopyrum esculentum Moench, and honeydew produced by the soybean aphid, Aphis glycines Matsumura (Homoptera: Aphididae), on longevity, nutrient levels, and egg loads of the parasitoid Diadegma insulare Cresson (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae). Diadegma insulare lived for 2 days in control treatments of water or clean soybean leaves, for 6-7 days with honeydew, and in excess of 2 weeks with buckwheat nectar. Potential reasons for the superiority of buckwheat nectar over soybean aphid honeydew for extending the longevity of parasitoids include: (i) parasitoids ingest more sugars from floral sources, (ii) oligosaccharides in honeydew have a lower nutritional value than nectar sugars, and (iii) honeydew has antagonistic compounds. Overall sugar levels were lower in honeydew- vs. nectar-fed female wasps, suggesting a lower feeding rate, but other explanations cannot be excluded. Diadegma insulare eclosed with high levels of lipids and glycogen, and low levels of gut and storage sugars. All carbohydrates increased over the life of both nectar- and honeydew-fed wasps, but remained low or decreased in starved wasps. Lipid levels declined over the lifespan of female wasps, but females fed floral nectar showed the slowest rate of lipid decline. Diet did not affect egg load, probably because the females were not given hosts in the experiment.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 45</no>
<sn>0013-8703 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000221739000005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3965</id>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Heimpel,G. E.</a1>
<t1>Broken wing fringe setae as a relative estimate of parasitoid age</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>87</sp>
<op>92</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0013-8703 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000240402500010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3981</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Toxicity of Abamectin to Liriomyza-Trifolii (Burgess) (Diptera, Agromyzidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>738</sp>
<op>740</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1988M805800056</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3982</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Light on the Pupariation of Liriomyza-Trifolii (Diptera, Agromyzidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>758</sp>
<op>759</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1986F364000020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3983</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Storage at 1.1-Degrees-C on the Mortality of Liriomyza-Trifolii (Burgess) (Diptera, Agromyzidae) Life Stages in Celery</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>407</sp>
<op>411</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1985AFT0300024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3984</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Temperature on Development and Fecundity of Liriomyza-Trifolii (Burgess) (Diptera, Agromyzidae) on Celery</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>497</sp>
<op>501</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 32</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1984ST28600031</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3976</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Pesticide Resistance in Florida Insects Limits Management Options</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>386</sp>
<op>399</op>
<ab>Pesticide resistance in Florida was characterized through a survey and literature review The survey was conducted in 1994 among public-sector entomologists to determine the current and future status, extent, context, pattern, and instances of pesticide (insecticide and acaricide) resistance in Florida. Results attested to the impact of pesticide resistance on the management of numerous arthropods in Florida. Twenty-five examples of insecticide and acaricide resistance were cited by survey respondents in agricultural, ornamental and landscape, medical and veterinary, or household and structural pests. It remains possible to manage most arthropods by using chemical pesticides, but the current and anticipated lack of efficacious materials threatens current practices in some areas. Trends in extent, context, or patterns of resistance were noted as follows: high value crops, frequently treated arthropods, smaller arthropods, and pyrethroids were all considered factors associated with resistance. Insecticide resistance and its management were reviewed in depth for the leafminer Liriomyza trifolii and the diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella, two major insect pests in Florida for which management options have become severely limited because of insecticide resistance. Both cultural practices (continuous cropping, isolation, transport of infested seedlings) and pesticide use patterns (frequent application of broad spectrum pesticides) contributed to L. trifolii and P. xylostella I resistance development. The history of pesticide resistance in these two insects is probably typical of pest resistance in Florida and may portend similar future problems unless dependency on pesticides for pest suppression is reduced through adoption of IPM philosophy and practices.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1995RX01300002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3985</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Chalfant,R. B.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Workman,R. B.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Visual Damage Thresholds for Management of Cabbage Caterpillars in Florida and Georgia</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1008</sp>
<op>1011</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1984TK74600037</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3988</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Horn,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Tillage on Survivorship of Cereal Leaf Beetle Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae and its Larval Parasites, Tetrastichus-Julis Hymenoptera, Eulophidae and Lemophagus-Curtus Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>485</sp>
<op>486</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979HA23800024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3975</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Nuessly,G.</a1>
<a1>Taylor,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of Emamectin Benzoate and Bacillus-Thuringiensis at Controlling Diamondback Moth (Lepidoptera, Plutellidae) Populations on Cabbage in Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>82</sp>
<op>96</op>
<ab>Emamectin benzoate (MK-244; Merck &amp;amp; Co., Rahway, NJ), used alone and alternated with Bacillus thuringiensis (Berliner) ssp. aizawai (Bta), Bta alone, and B. thuringiensis ssp. hurstaki (Btk) alone, were evaluated for control of diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella (L.), in head cabbage at three locations in Florida. Additional treatments unique to each location were also evaluated. Emamectin benzoate alone, Bta alone, emamectin benzoate alternated with Bta, and mevinphos were shown to be effective. Btk was less efficacious than Bta at two locations.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 16</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1995QP11900011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3972</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Osborne,L. S.</a1>
<t1>Chemical control of Cactoblastis cactorum (Lepidoptera : Pyralidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>510</sp>
<op>512</op>
<ab>Chemical control of Cactoblastis cactorum is hampered by the lack of data to support usage of many available pesticides. The application of pesticides to infested cacti is severely limited by the fact that these infested plants occur on sites in urban habitats, on public lands or in areas that are difficult to access. The use of such materials is governed by the United States: Environmental Protection Agency and pesticide usage patterns, including allowable sites, must be specified on the pesticide label. There are an array of materials that could potentially be used to manage this insect with minimal impact on the environment and non-target organisms. However, there is very little research being conducted to determine the efficacy and safety of these pesticides.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: Workshop on Cactoblastis Cactorum in North America; CY: SEP, 2000; CL: TAMPA, FLORIDA; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000173025300009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3986</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Pass,B. C.</a1>
<a1>Yeargan,K. V.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal Abundance and Activity of Sitona-Hispidulus Adults in Kentucky</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>27</sp>
<op>30</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1981LN96300006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3987</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Pass,B. C.</a1>
<a1>Yeargan,K. V.</a1>
<t1>Developmental Rates of Patasson Lameerei [Hym - Mymaridae] and the Effect of Host Egg Age on Parasitism</t1>
<jf>Entomophaga</jf>
<jo>Entomophaga</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>345</sp>
<op>348</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 12</no>
<sn>0013-8959 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979JM29000002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3978</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Savage,K. E.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Selected Insecticides for Control of Diamondback Moth and Cabbage-Looper in Cabbage in Central Florida with Observations on Insecticide Resistance in the Diamondback Moth</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>585</sp>
<op>591</op>
<ab>A field study was conducted to evaluate selected insecticides for the control of P. xylostella and cabbage looper, Trichoplusia ni (Hubner), in cabbage, Brassica oleracea L. (Capitata group). Chlorpyrifos, endosulfan, mevinphos, and Bacillus thuringiensis subsp. kurstaki were considerably more effective at controlling P. xylostella than cypermethrin, permethrin, methomyl, and thiodicarb. Cypermethrin, permethrin, thiodicarb, and endosulfan were the most effective at controlling T. ni. Mixtures of two insecticides improved efficacy apparently due to one component controlling T. ni. and not P. xylostella and the other component controlling P. xylostella and not T. ni. Laboratory examination of selected populations from the field study indicated that poor efficacy of the pyrethroids and carbamates on P. xylostella was probably due to insecticide resistance.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: WORKSHOP ON IMPORTANT ARTHROPOD PESTS OF THE CARIBBEAN BASIN AMENABLE TO BIOLOGICAL CONTROL : HOMOPTERA, COLEOPTERA, LEPIDOPTERA; CY: APR 08-10, 1991; CL: ORLANDO, FL; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992KH68100022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3977</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Savage,K. E.</a1>
<t1>Insecticide Resistance in Diamondback Moth in Florida</t1>
<jf>Diamondback Moth and Other Crucifer Pests</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<sp>427</sp>
<op>435</op>
<no>PT: J; CT: 2ND INTERNATIONAL WORKSHOP ON DIAMONDBACK MOTH AND OTHER CRUCIFER PESTS; CY: DEC 10-14, 1990; CL: TAINAN, TAIWAN; TC: 1</no>
<a2>Talekar,N. S.</a2>
<an>BIOSIS:PREV199344027621</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3979</id>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Savage,K. E.</a1>
<t1>Toxicity of Selected Insecticides to 2 Laboratory Strains of Insecticide-Resistant Diamondback Moth (Lepidoptera, Plutellidae) from Central Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2073</sp>
<op>2076</op>
<ab>Topical application and leaf residue bioassays were done to determine the toxicity of selected insecticides to two laboratory strains (A and B) of the diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella (L.), from central Florida. Both strains were started in the spring of 1987 with individuals from a field population. Strain A was isolated before insecticide application. Strain B was isolated after five weekly applications of fenvalerate. Both strains were maintained in the laboratory for 27 (strain B) and 29 (strain A) generations without exposure to insecticides. Results indicated that strain B was 38.3 times more resistant to fenvalerate than strain A based on topical application, but leaf residue bioassays indicated no difference. The toxicities of chlorpyrifos and methamidophos were similar in both strains based on topical application. Leaf residue bioassays with concentrations of insecticides representing field rates indicated both strains were resistant to fenvalerate and methomyl but were susceptible to chlorpyrifos, acephate, endosulfan, and thiodicarb.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992KB23700005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3966</id>
<a1>Pluke,R. W. H.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Host Preferences of Trichogramma pretiosum and the influence of prior ovipositional experience on the parasitism of Plutella xylostella and Pseudoplusia includens eggs</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>51</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>569</sp>
<op>583</op>
<ab>Trichogramma wasps are generalist egg parasitoids used in biological control efforts. In a multi host situation they may preferentially parasitize a non-target host species to the detriment of the control program. Plutella xylostella Linnaeus (Lepidoptera: Plutellidae) is a very serious pest of cabbage, but is only one in a number of species in the &amp;#39;cabbageworm&amp;#39; complex. We investigated the host preferences of Trichogramma pretiosum Riley (Hymenoptera: Chalcidoidea) when offered the eggs of Plutella xylostella and the eggs of Pseudoplusia includens Hubner (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae), another species in the &amp;#39;cabbageworm&amp;#39; complex. Trichogramma pretiosum reared on the eggs of the factitious host Ephestia kuehniella Zeller (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae) parasitized both Plutella xylostella and Pseudoplusia includens eggs under laboratory conditions. For both choice and no-choice experiments, T. pretiosum parasitized significantly more P. xylostella eggs than P. includens eggs. Prior ovipositional experience with one or other of the two host species had no effect on the subsequent parasitism levels of the two host species. The preference for P. xylostella eggs was also not affected by this prior ovipositional experience.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>WOS:000241010000002</an>
<do>10.1007/s10526-005-1033-3 ER</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3967</id>
<a1>Pluke,R. W. H.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Polyvinyl alcohol film as an oviposition substrate for diamondback moth (Lepidoptera : Plutellidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>535</sp>
<op>535</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000234928700021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3973</id>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Evans,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Bennett,F. D.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Webb,S. E.</a1>
<t1>A survey of parasitoids of Bemisia spp. whiteflies in Florida, the Caribbean, and Central and South America</t1>
<jf>International Journal of Pest Management</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Pest Manage.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>255</sp>
<op>260</op>
<ab>Wild and cultivated plants were surveyed in Florida, the Caribbean, and Latin America for parasitoids of Bemisia spp. whiteflies. Foliage samples containing late instar Bemisia nymphs were collected and held in the laboratory for emergence of adult parasitoids. Florida collections were made weekly, biweekly or monthly depending upon the time of year and location. Samples also were collected on an irregular basis in Caribbean and Latin American countries including Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Fl Salvador, Grenada, Guadeloupe, Guatemala, Honduras, Jamaica, Mexico, Puerto Rico and Venezuela. At least 20 species of parasitoids and one species of hyperparasitoid were reared from Bemisia. Encarsia pergandiella Howard (which may be a complex of species including the sympatric species E. tabacivora Viggiani), E. nigricephala Dozier and Eretmocerus sop. were the most abundant parasitoids, accounting for 59%, 16% and 13%, respectively, of the total reared from Bemisia. Encarsia meritoria Gahan, which is a complex of species but which may be mostly E. hispida De Santis in the New World, was rarely collected in Florida but was abundant at some sites in the Caribbean and Latin America.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 12</no>
<sn>0967-0874 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000078178400011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3971</id>
<a1>Seal,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Toxicity of Bacillus thuringiensis CRY1-type insecticidal toxin to geographically distant populations of tomato pinworm</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>222</sp>
<op>224</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000183972900020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3974</id>
<a1>Wolfenbarger,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Riley,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Staetz,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Herzog,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Gage,E. V.</a1>
<t1>Response of silverleaf whitefly (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) to bifenthrin and endosulfan by vial bioassay in Florida, Georgia and Texas</t1>
<jf>Journal of Entomological Science</jf>
<jo>J.Entomol.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>412</sp>
<op>420</op>
<ab>Median lethal concentration (LC50) values of bifenthrin and endosulfan were determined for dead and moribund + dead categories for adults of the silverleaf whitefly, Bemisia argentifolii (Bellows and Perring) (formerly sweetpotato whitefly, B. tabaci (Gennadius), strain B), in 3-h vial bioassays in Florida, Georgia, and Texas in 1991 and 1992. For the moribund + dead category in Florida, LC50 values for bifenthrin ranged from 0.00076 to 1.48 mu g/vial, a 1,947-fold difference. An LC50 as high as 128.1 mu g bifenthrin/vial for adults from cabbage in Texas was determined for the dead category. For endosulfan in Florida, LC50 values of the moribund plus dead categories for endosulfan ranged from 0.04 to 35.6 mu g/vial, an 890-fold difference. An LC50 as high as 119.7 mu g endosulfan/vial was determined for adults from cotton in Texas for the dead category. The wide ranges of LC50 values for both insecticides suggest the presence of resistant and susceptible whiteflies in all three dates.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0749-8004 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000076780800010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3969</id>
<a1>Xu,Y. Y.</a1>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Jones,W. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of selected insecticides on Diadegma insulare (Hymenoptera : Ichneumonidae), a parasitoid of Plutella xylostella (Lepidoptera : Plutellidae)</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol Science and Technology</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol Sci.Technol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>713</sp>
<op>723</op>
<ab>Effects of eight insecticides on Diadegma insulare (Cresson), a parasitoid of the diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella L., were evaluated under the laboratory conditions. The insecticides were three azadirachtin-based products (Ecozin, Agroneem and Neemix), two Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt) products (Xentari and Crymax), indoxacarb, spinosad, and lambda-cyhalothrin. When D . insulare pupae were treated, none of the insecticide treatments except lambda-cyhalothrin significantly reduced adult emergence, with 76-90% adults emerged from the treated pupae. In the lambda-cyhalothrin treatment, only 10% D . insulare pupae produced adult wasps. Indoxacarb, spinosad, and lambda-cyhalothrin caused 100% D . insulare adult mortality in 24 h in Petri dishes sprayed with insecticides in the contact bioassays, and 95.8, 100 and 95.8% adult mortality in 24 h in the ingestion bioassays, respectively. In contrast, all three azadirachtin-based insecticides and the two Bt-insecticides caused only 0-10.4% mortality of D . insulare adults after ingestion. The surviving D . insulare from ingestion treatments with Bt- and azadirachtin-insecticides parasitized 50.8-67.6% of P. xylostella larvae, respectively, compare to 72.1% for the water control. After ingesting indoxacarb, spinosad and lambda-cyhalothrin mixed in honey-water, both the females and the males lived significantly shorter than those ingesting Bt- and azadirachtin-insecticides and the non-insecticide honey-water. Effects of leaf residues of indoxacarb, spinosad and lambda-cyhalothrin varied significantly. The leaf residues of spinosad had the least effects on D . insulare adults, and 7- and 10-day-old residue only caused 5.6 and 7.4% mortality in 24 h, whereas 10-day-old leaf residues of indoxacarb and lambda-cyhalothrin caused 40.7 and 57.4% mortality in 24 h, respectively.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 16</no>
<sn>0958-3157</sn>
<an>WOS:000222179400007</an>
<do>10.1080/09583150410001682395 ER</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
