<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1372</id>
<a1>Abranches,J.</a1>
<a1>Candella,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Wen,Z. T.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Different roles of EIIABMan and EIIGlc in regulation of energy metabolism, biofilm development, and competence in Streptococcus mutans </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>188</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3748</sp>
<op>3756</op>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Biological Transport</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Energy Metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Glucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mannose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Phosphoenolpyruvate Sugar Phosphotransferase System/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus mutans/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The phosphoenolpyruvate:sugar phosphotransferase system (PTS) is the major carbohydrate transport system in oral streptococci. The mannose-PTS of Streptococcus mutans, which transports mannose and glucose, is involved in carbon catabolite repression (CCR) and regulates the expression of known virulence genes. In this study, we investigated the role of EII(Glc) and EIIAB(Man) in sugar metabolism, gene regulation, biofilm formation, and competence. The results demonstrate that the inactivation of ptsG, encoding a putative EII(Glc), did not lead to major changes in sugar metabolism or affect the phenotypes of interest. However, the loss of EII(Glc) was shown to have a significant impact on the proteome and to affect the expression of a known virulence factor, fructan hydrolase (fruA). JAM1, a mutant strain lacking EIIAB(Man), had an impaired capacity to form biofilms in the presence of glucose and displayed a decreased ability to be transformed with exogenous DNA. Also, the lactose- and cellobiose-PTSs were positively and negatively regulated by EIIAB(Man), respectively. Microarrays were used to investigate the profound phenotypic changes displayed by JAM1, revealing that EIIAB(Man) of S. mutans has a key regulatory role in energy metabolism, possibly by sensing the energy levels of the cells or the carbohydrate availability and, in response, regulating the activity of transcription factors and carbohydrate transporters. </ab>
<no>id: 5; LR: 20091118; GR: DE 12236/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (Transcription Factors); 31103-86-3 (Mannose); 50-99-7 (Glucose); EC 2.7.1.- (Phosphoenolpyruvate Sugar Phosphotransferase System); OID: NLM: PMC1482907; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology, University of Florida College of Dentistry, P.O. Box 100424, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16707667; 188/11/3748 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.00169-06</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16707667</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1482907</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1411</id>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>GCR1 of Saccharomyces cerevisiae encodes a DNA binding protein whose binding is abolished by mutations in the CTTCC sequence motif </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Nov 1</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>9443</sp>
<op>9447</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>GTP-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotides/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins</k1>
<k1>Regulatory Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>rap GTP-Binding Proteins</k1>
<ab>In Saccharomyces cerevisiae, glycolysis enzymes constitute 30-60% of the soluble protein. GCR1 gene function is required for high-level glycolytic gene expression. In gcr1 mutant strains the levels of most glycolytic enzymes are between 2% and 10% of wild type. Binding sites for the global regulatory protein known as repressor activator protein 1 (RAP1)/general regulatory factor 1 (GRF1)/translation upstream factor (TUF) are found in close proximity to one or more CTTCC sequence motifs in the controlling region of GCR1-dependent genes. RAP1/GRF1/TUF-binding sites are known to be essential elements of upstream activating sequences that control expression of many glycolytic genes. In this report, I demonstrate that GCR1 encodes a DNA binding protein whose ability to bind DNA is dependent on the CTTCC sequence motif. This finding, in addition to the work of others, suggests that the GCR1 gene product and the RAP1/GRF1/TUF gene product act in concert to mediate high-level glycolytic gene expression. </ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20091118; GR: GM-4133/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Oligonucleotides); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); EC 3.6.1.- (GTP-Binding Proteins); EC 3.6.5.2 (rap GTP-Binding Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC52734; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1946357</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1946357</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC52734</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1413</id>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Glycolytic gene expression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae: nucleotide sequence of GCR1, null mutants, and evidence for expression </t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3774</sp>
<op>3784</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Deletion</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>Enzymes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>In Saccharomyces cerevisiae, the gcr mutation is known to have a profound effect on the levels of most glycolytic enzymes, reducing them to 5% of normal or less in growth on noncarbohydrates. Here I report the preparation of chromosomal gcr insertion and deletion mutations. The null mutations were recessive, were not lethal, and caused a pattern of glycolytic enzyme deficiency similar to that seen earlier for the gcr1-1 allele, including the partial inducibility by glucose of the residual enzyme activities. DNA sequence analysis showed that GCR1 encoded a protein of molecular weight 94,414, with a very low codon bias index, characteristic of several S. cerevisiae regulatory genes; adjacent 5&amp;#39; and 3&amp;#39; sequences contained elements suggesting that it was transcribed, polyadenylated, and translated. RNA gel transfer hybridization experiments with purified polyadenylated RNA and a probe complementary to the 5&amp;#39; portion of the open reading frame showed that Ger was expressed as a polyadenylated transcript. Together with previous work, the present results suggest that the Gcr product may be a transcriptional factor necessary specifically for the high-level transcription of a limited set of genes whose products, the enzymes of glycolysis, constitute a substantial fraction of cell proteins and are responsible for the primary metabolic flux in many cells. </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20091118; GENBANK/M14145; GR: 1U41 RR01685-02/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA-07995/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM-21098/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); 0 (Enzymes); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); OID: NLM: PMC367138; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<an>PMID: 3025612</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3025612</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC367138</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1414</id>
<a1>Baker,H. V.,2nd</a1>
<a1>Wolf,R. E.,Jr</a1>
<t1>Essential site for growth rate-dependent regulation within the Escherichia coli gnd structural gene </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>24</is>
<sp>7669</sp>
<op>7673</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/genetics</k1>
<ab>Expression of gnd of Escherichia coli, which encodes the hexose monophosphate shunt enzyme, 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase (6PGD; EC 1.1.1.44), is subject to growth rate-dependent regulation: the level of the enzyme is directly proportional to growth rate under a variety of growth conditions. Previous results obtained with strains carrying transcriptional fusions of gnd to the structural genes of the lactose operon suggested that the growth rate-dependent regulation of gnd expression is at the post-transcriptional level. To characterize the regulation further, we prepared with phage MudII a set of eight independent gnd-lac gene (protein) fusions. We showed through genetic analysis and DNA sequencing that each fusion joint was located within the 6PGD-coding sequence between the first and second base pair of a codon, the reading frame required for production of a hybrid 6PGD-beta-galactosidase. Strains harboring the gnd-lac fusion plasmids produced proteins whose mobility in a NaDodSO4/polyacrylamide gel agreed with the molecular weights predicted from the DNA sequence for the respective hybrid proteins. The level of beta-galactosidase was high and relatively growth rate-independent in the fusion whose fusion joint was at codon 48. The level of beta-galactosidase in the other seven fusion strains whose fusion joints were located further downstream in the 6PGD-coding sequence showed the same dependence on growth rate as 6PGD in a normal strain. beta-Galactosidase levels were not affected by the presence of a gnd+ gene in trans to any of the fusions. The results suggest that all sites necessary for growth rate-dependent regulation of 6PGD level lie in gnd upstream from codon 118 and that an essential site of negative control lies within the coding sequence, between codons 48 and 118. </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20091118; GENBANK/K02072; GR: GM27113/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; EC 1.1.1.43 (Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); OID: NLM: PMC392213; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 6440141</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6440141</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC392213</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1416</id>
<a1>Baker,H. V.,2nd</a1>
<a1>Wolf,R. E.,Jr</a1>
<t1>Growth rate-dependent regulation of 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase level in Escherichia coli K-12: beta-galactosidase expression in gnd-lac operon fusion strains </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>153</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>771</sp>
<op>781</op>
<k1>DNA, Recombinant</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The level of 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase is positively correlated with the cellular growth rate. To determine whether growth rate-dependent regulation of expression of gnd, which encodes this enzyme, is carried out by a transcriptional mechanism, the structural genes of the lactose operon were fused to and brought under the control of the gnd promoter through the use of phage Mu d1(Apr lac). Four independent gnd::Mu d1(Apr lac) operon fusion strains were isolated. After the Mu d1 prophage was replaced with lambda p1(209), Lac+ specialized transducing phages carrying the gnd-lac fusions were prepared. These phages were used to demonstrate that the lac genes were fused to the gnd promoter by crossing them with gnd promoter deletion mutants and with polar phage Mu cts-induced gnd mutants. A genetic map of the fusion joints was deduced. The level of beta-galactosidase in each fusion strain was the same in cells growing on acetate as in cells growing on glucose (with specific growth rate constants of 0.1 and 0.55 h-1, respectively) and was unaffected by the presence of a gnd+ gene in trans. Our results suggest that a post-transcriptional mechanism mediates growth rate-dependent regulation of gnd and that this regulation is not autogenous. Models for regulation are discussed with respect to these results and the physiology and DNA sequence of gnd. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20091118; GR: GM27113/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (DNA, Recombinant); EC 1.1.1.43 (Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase); OID: NLM: PMC221696; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<an>PMID: 6337127</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6337127</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC221696</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1356</id>
<a1>Bartee,E.</a1>
<a1>Mohamed,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<t1>The addition of tumor necrosis factor plus beta interferon induces a novel synergistic antiviral state against poxviruses in primary human fibroblasts </t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>498</sp>
<op>511</op>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Drug Synergism</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts/immunology/virology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunologic Factors/immunology/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Interferon-beta/immunology/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/immunology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha/immunology/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/immunology</k1>
<k1>Yatapoxvirus/immunology</k1>
<ab>Tumor necrosis factor (TNF) and members of the interferon (IFN) family have been shown to independently inhibit the replication of a variety of viruses. In addition, previous reports have shown that treatment with various combinations of these antiviral cytokines induces a synergistic antiviral state that can be significantly more potent than addition of any of these cytokines alone. The mechanism of this cytokine synergy and its effects on global gene expression, however, are not well characterized. Here, we use DNA microarray analysis to demonstrate that treatment of uninfected primary human fibroblasts with TNF plus IFN-beta induces a distinct synergistic state characterized by significant perturbations of several hundred genes which are coinduced by the individual cytokines alone, as well as the induction of more than 850 novel host cell genes. This synergy is mediated directly by the two ligands, not by intermediate secreted factors, and is necessary and sufficient to completely block the productive replication and spread of myxoma virus in human fibroblasts. In contrast, the replication of two other poxviruses, vaccinia virus and tanapox virus, are only partially inhibited in these cells by the synergistic antiviral state, whereas the spread of both of these viruses to neighboring cells was efficiently blocked. Taken together, our data indicate that the combination of TNF and IFN-beta induces a novel synergistic antiviral state that is highly distinct from that induced by either cytokine alone. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (Immunologic Factors); 0 (Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha); 77238-31-4 (Interferon-beta); OID: NLM: PMC2612348; 2008/10/29 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5514; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18971273; JVI.01376-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.01376-08</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20081029</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18971273</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2612348</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1380</id>
<a1>Biberthaler,P.</a1>
<a1>Bogner,V.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Neth,P.</a1>
<a1>Kanz,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Mutschler,W.</a1>
<a1>Jochum,M.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Genome-wide monocytic mRNA expression in polytrauma patients for identification of clinical outcome </t1>
<jf>Shock (Augusta, Ga.)</jf>
<jo>Shock</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>11</sp>
<op>19</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Cluster Analysis</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genome, Human</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Monocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>Immune activation in multiple trauma is closely linked to the development of multiple organ dysfunction and failure, and consequently, has a profound influence on patient outcome. Although peripheral blood monocytes play a critical role in this immune response, the biological significance of changes in genome-wide expression immediately after traumatic injury have not been explored previously. Thirteen patients presenting with multiple blunt trauma were studied. Peripheral blood monocytes were obtained within 90 min and at 6, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h after trauma. Apparent genome-wide expression was determined with Affymetrix U133A microarrays. Supervised analysis identified 698 probe sets that were differentially expressed in the 13 trauma subjects (P </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20071114; GR: U54-GM-62119-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9421564; 0 (RNA, Messenger); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1073-2322; 1073-2322</sn>
<ad>Chirurgische Klinik und Poliklinik-Innenstadt, Klinikum Innenstadt, Ludwig-Maximilians Universitaet, Munich, 80336 Munich, Germany.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15988315; 00024382-200507000-00003 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15988315</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1352</id>
<a1>Bogner,V.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Kanz,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Mutschler,W.</a1>
<a1>Biberthaler,P.</a1>
<t1>Hemorrhage and subsequent allogenic red blood cell transfusion are associated with characteristic monocyte messenger RNA expression patterns in patients after multiple injury-a genome wide view </t1>
<jf>The Journal of trauma</jf>
<jo>J.Trauma</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>792</sp>
<op>801</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Erythrocyte Transfusion</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genome, Human</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>I-kappa B Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Injury Severity Score</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Monocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Multiple Organ Failure/genetics</k1>
<k1>Multiple Trauma/genetics</k1>
<k1>NF-kappa B/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Protein Array Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin C/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Up-Regulation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Wounds, Nonpenetrating/genetics</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>INTRODUCTION: As outcome to severe trauma is frequently affected by massive blood loss and consecutive hemorrhagic shock, replacement of red blood cell (RBC) units remains indispensable. Administration of RBC units is an independent risk factor for adverse outcome in patients with trauma. The impact of massive blood transfusion or uncrossmatched blood transfusion on the patients&amp;#39; immune response in the early posttraumatic period remains unclear. MATERIAL: Thirteen patients presenting with blunt multiple injuries (Injury Severity Score &amp;gt;16) were studied. Monocytes were obtained on admission and at 6, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours after trauma. Biotinylated complementary RNA targets were hybridized to Affymetrix HG U 133A microarrays. The data were analyzed by a supervised analysis based on whether the patients received massive blood transfusions, and then subsequently, by hierarchical clustering, and by Ingenuity pathway analysis. RESULTS: Supervised analysis identified 224 probe sets to be differentially expressed (p </ab>
<no>id: 5; JID: 0376373; 0 (I-kappa B Proteins); 0 (NF-kappa B); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Ubiquitin C); 139874-52-5 (NF-kappaB inhibitor alpha); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1529-8809; 0022-5282</sn>
<ad>Chirurgische Klinik und Poliklinik-Innenstadt, Ludwig-Maximilians University, Munich, Munich, Germany. Viktoria.Bogner@med.uni-muenchen.de</ad>
<an>PMID: 19820587; 00005373-200910000-00020 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/TA.0b013e31819d9c04</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19820587</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1367</id>
<a1>Bogner,V.</a1>
<a1>Kirchhoff,C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Stegmaier,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Mutschler,W.</a1>
<a1>Biberthaler,P.</a1>
<t1>Gene expression profiles are influenced by ISS, MOF, and clinical outcome in multiple injured patients: a genome-wide comparative analysis </t1>
<jf>Langenbeck&#39;s archives of surgery / Deutsche Gesellschaft fur Chirurgie</jf>
<jo>Langenbecks Arch.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>392</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>255</sp>
<op>265</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genome, Human</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Monocytes</k1>
<k1>Multiple Organ Failure/genetics</k1>
<k1>Multiple Trauma/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Trauma Severity Indices</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Posttraumatic immune system activation in major trauma patients is linked to systemic inflammatory response syndrome, multiple organ failure (MOF), and mortality. Recent studies suggest that genome-wide expression is altered in response to distinct clinical parameters; however, the functional allocation of theses genes remains unclear. PATIENTS AND METHODS: Thirteen patients after major trauma (Injury Severity Score </ab>
<no>id: 10; GR: U54-GM-62119-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9808285; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 2007/02/15 [received]; 2007/02/16 [accepted]; 2007/04/03 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>1435-2443; 1435-2443</sn>
<ad>Chirurgische Klinik und Poliklinik-Innenstadt, Ludwig-Maximilians University, Nussbaumstrasse 20, 80336 Munich, Germany. Viktoria.Bogner@med.uni-muenchen.de</ad>
<an>PMID: 17404753</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00423-007-0182-5</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20070403</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17404753</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1374</id>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Logvinenko,T.</a1>
<a1>Lederer,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Hubbard,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Chaudry,I. H.</a1>
<a1>Remick,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Mannick,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Commonality and differences in leukocyte gene expression patterns among three models of inflammation and injury </t1>
<jf>Physiological genomics</jf>
<jo>Physiol.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb 14</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>298</sp>
<op>309</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/blood/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/administration &amp; dosage/blood/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Microarray Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA/analysis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<k1>Spleen/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/blood/complications/immunology</k1>
<ab>The aim of this study was to compare gene expression profiles of leukocytes from blood (white blood cells; WBCs) and spleen harvested at an early time point after injury or sham injury in mice subjected to trauma/hemorrhage, burn injury, or lipopolysaccharide (LPS) infusion at three experimental sites. Groups of injured or LPS-infused animals and sham controls were killed at 2 h after injury and resuscitation, blood and spleen were harvested, and leukocyte populations were recovered after erythrocyte lysis. RNA was extracted from postlysis leukocyte populations. Complementary RNA was synthesized from each RNA sample and hybridized to microarrays. A large number (500-1,400) of genes were differentially expressed at the 2-h time point in injured or LPS-infused vs. sham animals. Thirteen of the differentially expressed genes in blood, and 46 in the spleen, were upregulated or downregulated in common among all three animal models and may represent a common, early transcriptional response to systemic inflammation from a variety of causes. The majority of these genes could be assigned to pathways involved in the immune response and cell death. The up- or downregulation of a cohort of 23 of these genes was validated by RT-PCR. This large-scale microarray analysis shows that, at the 2-h time point, there is marked alteration in leukocyte gene expression in three animal models of injury and inflammation. Although there is some commonality among the models, the majority of the differentially expressed genes appear to be uniquely associated with the type of injury and/or the inflammatory stimulus. </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20071114; GR: 1U54-GM-62119-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9815683; 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 63231-63-0 (RNA); 2005/12/20 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-2267; 1094-8341</sn>
<ad>Department of Genetics, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16478828; 00213.2005 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1152/physiolgenomics.00213.2005</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20051220</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16478828</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1394</id>
<a1>Brum,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Varela,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Microarray analysis of A549 cells infected with rabbitpox virus (RPV): a comparison of wild-type RPV and RPV deleted for the host range gene, SPI-1 </t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Oct 25</fd>
<vo>315</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>334</op>
<k1>Actins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>HSP70 Heat-Shock Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Histones/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Peptides/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>A documented consequence of poxvirus infections is global inhibition of host protein synthesis and reduction in mRNA levels. We examined this mRNA decrease by infecting A549 cells, derived from a human lung carcinoma, with rabbitpox virus (RPV), or RPV deleted for the serine protease inhibitor SPI-1 (RPVDeltaSPI-1), which exhibits a growth defect on A549 cells. At various times postinfection, mRNA profiles were analyzed using Affymetrix U95AV2 microarrays. There was a decline in overall cellular mRNA levels beginning at 2.5 hpi, and by 5 hpi, mRNA levels were drastically reduced for the majority of genes. However, several mRNAs increased, including those of heat-shock genes. Finally, a comparison of host mRNA profiles of RPV- to RPVDeltaSPI-1-infected cells revealed subtle differences in mRNA levels at 5 and 12 hpi. In summary, while there was a global decrease of host mRNA levels, the induction of selected mRNAs may be required for a successful poxvirus infection. </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20071114; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Actins); 0 (HSP70 Heat-Shock Proteins); 0 (Histones); 0 (Peptides); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 129712-62-5 (lambda Spi-1); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology and The Genetics Institute, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14585335; S0042682203005324 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14585335</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1361</id>
<a1>Burger,C.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<t1>Genome-wide analysis of aging and learning-related genes in the hippocampal dentate gyrus </t1>
<jf>Neurobiology of learning and memory</jf>
<jo>Neurobiol.Learn.Mem.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>379</sp>
<op>396</op>
<k1>Aging/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Death/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Division/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement/genetics</k1>
<k1>Dentate Gyrus/cytology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Maze Learning/physiology</k1>
<k1>Memory/physiology</k1>
<k1>Neurons/physiology</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred F344</k1>
<ab>We have previously described the transcriptional changes that occur in the hippocampal CA1 field of aged rats following a Morris Water Maze (MWM) training paradigm. In this report we proceed with the analysis of the dentate region from the same animals. Animals were first identified as age learning-impaired or age-superior learners when compared to young rats based on their performance in the MWM. Messenger RNA was isolated from the dentate gyrus of each animal to interrogate Affymetrix RAE 230A rat genome microarrays. Microarray profiling identified 1129 genes that were differentially expressed between aged and young rats as a result of aging, and independent of their behavioral training (p</ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20091118; GR: P01 NS036302-07/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: P01 NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9508166; NIHMS56779; OID: NLM: NIHMS56779; OID: NLM: PMC2530823; 2007/02/18 [received]; 2007/11/20 [revised]; 2007/11/23 [accepted]; 2008/01/29 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1095-9564; 1074-7427</sn>
<ad>Department of Neurology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. burger@neurology.wisc.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18234529; S1074-7427(07)00190-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.nlm.2007.11.006</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20080129</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18234529</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2530823</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1371</id>
<a1>Burger,C.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Feller,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<a1>Mandel,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Changes in transcription within the CA1 field of the hippocampus are associated with age-related spatial learning impairments </t1>
<jf>Neurobiology of learning and memory</jf>
<jo>Neurobiol.Learn.Mem.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>21</sp>
<op>41</op>
<k1>Aging/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cognition Disorders/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Hippocampus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Maze Learning/physiology</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Problem Solving/physiology</k1>
<k1>Protein Array Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred F344</k1>
<k1>Space Perception/physiology</k1>
<k1>Statistics, Nonparametric</k1>
<k1>Synapses/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Aged rats display a broad range of behavioral performance in spatial learning. The aim of this study was to identify candidate genes that are associated with learning and memory impairments. We first categorized aged-superior learners and age learning-impaired rats based on their performance in the Morris water maze (MWM) and then isolated messenger RNA from the CA1 hippocampal region of each animal to interrogate Affymetrix microarrays. Microarray analysis identified a set of 50 genes that was transcribed differently in aged-superior learners that had successfully learned the spatial strategy in the MWM compared to aged learning-impaired animals that were unable to learn and a variety of groups designed to control for all non-learning aspects of exposure to the water maze paradigm. A detailed analysis of the navigation patterns of the different groups of animals during acquisition and probe trials of the MWM task was performed. Young animals used predominantly an allocentric (spatial) search strategy and aged-superior learners appeared to use a combination of allocentric and egocentric (response) strategies, whereas aged-learning impaired animals displayed thigmotactic behavior. The significant 50 genes that we identified were tentatively classified into four groups based on their putative role in learning: transcription, synaptic morphology, ion conductivity and protein modification. Thus, this study has potentially identified a set of genes that are responsible for the learning impairments in aged rats. The role of these genes in the learning impairments associated with aging will ultimately have to be validated by manipulating gene expression in aged rats. Finally, these 50 genes were functioning in the context of an aging CA1 region where over 200 genes was found to be differentially expressed compared to a young CA1. </ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20071114; GR: NS PO136302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9508166; 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 2005/11/17 [received]; 2006/05/04 [revised]; 2006/05/20 [accepted]; 2006/07/10 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1074-7427; 1074-7427</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. cburger@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16829144; S1074-7427(06)00073-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.nlm.2006.05.003</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20060710</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16829144</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1378</id>
<a1>Calvano,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Richards,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Felciano,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Cho,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Chen,R. O.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Tschoeke,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<a1>Lowry,S. F.</a1>
<a1>Inflamm and Host Response to Injury Large Scale Collab. Res. Program</a1>
<t1>A network-based analysis of systemic inflammation in humans </t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct 13</fd>
<vo>437</vo>
<is>7061</is>
<sp>1032</sp>
<op>1037</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Computational Biology</k1>
<k1>Endotoxins/blood/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunity, Innate/drug effects/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/blood/chemically induced/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/drug effects/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<ab>Oligonucleotide and complementary DNA microarrays are being used to subclassify histologically similar tumours, monitor disease progress, and individualize treatment regimens. However, extracting new biological insight from high-throughput genomic studies of human diseases is a challenge, limited by difficulties in recognizing and evaluating relevant biological processes from huge quantities of experimental data. Here we present a structured network knowledge-base approach to analyse genome-wide transcriptional responses in the context of known functional interrelationships among proteins, small molecules and phenotypes. This approach was used to analyse changes in blood leukocyte gene expression patterns in human subjects receiving an inflammatory stimulus (bacterial endotoxin). We explore the known genome-wide interaction network to identify significant functional modules perturbed in response to this stimulus. Our analysis reveals that the human blood leukocyte response to acute systemic inflammation includes the transient dysregulation of leukocyte bioenergetics and modulation of translational machinery. These findings provide insight into the regulation of global leukocyte activities as they relate to innate immune system tolerance and increased susceptibility to infection in humans. </ab>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20081121; JID: 0410462; 0 (Endotoxins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); EIN: Nature. 2005 Dec 1;438(7068):696; 2005/05/17 [received]; 2005/07/04 [accepted]; 2005/08/31 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1476-4687; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, UMDNJ-Robert Wood Johnson Medical School, New Brunswick, New Jersey 08903, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16136080; nature03985 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/nature03985</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20050831</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16136080</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1383</id>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C.</a1>
<a1>Calvano,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Laudanski,K.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Elson,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Hayden,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Herndon,D. N.</a1>
<a1>Lowry,S. F.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Schoenfeld,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Bankey,P.</a1>
<a1>Billiar,T.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Calvano,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Camp,D.</a1>
<a1>Chaudry,I.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Elson,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Freeman,B.</a1>
<a1>Gamelli,R.</a1>
<a1>Gibran,N.</a1>
<a1>Harbrecht,B.</a1>
<a1>Hayden,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Heagy,W.</a1>
<a1>Heimbach,D.</a1>
<a1>Herndon,D. N.</a1>
<a1>Horton,J.</a1>
<a1>Hunt,J.</a1>
<a1>Laudanski,K.</a1>
<a1>Lederer,J.</a1>
<a1>Lowry,S. F.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Mannick,J.</a1>
<a1>McKinley,B.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Minei,J.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Moore,E.</a1>
<a1>Moore,F.</a1>
<a1>Munford,R.</a1>
<a1>Nathens,A.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;keefe,G.</a1>
<a1>Purdue,G.</a1>
<a1>Rahme,L.</a1>
<a1>Remick,D.</a1>
<a1>Sailors,M.</a1>
<a1>Schoenfeld,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,M.</a1>
<a1>Silver,G.</a1>
<a1>Smith,R.</a1>
<a1>Stephanopoulos,G.</a1>
<a1>Stormo,G.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<a1>Toner,M.</a1>
<a1>Warren,S.</a1>
<a1>West,M.</a1>
<a1>Wolfe,S.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Young,V.</a1>
<a1>Inflammation and Host Response to Injury Large-Scale Collaborative Research Program</a1>
<t1>Application of genome-wide expression analysis to human health and disease </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar 29</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>13</is>
<sp>4801</sp>
<op>4806</op>
<k1>Cluster Analysis</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genome, Human</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Multicenter Studies as Topic/methods</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis/methods/standards</k1>
<k1>Patient Selection</k1>
<k1>Principal Component Analysis</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Specimen Handling/methods</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The application of genome-wide expression analysis to a large-scale, multicentered program in critically ill patients poses a number of theoretical and technical challenges. We describe here an analytical and organizational approach to a systematic evaluation of the variance associated with genome-wide expression analysis specifically tailored to study human disease. We analyzed sources of variance in genome-wide expression analyses performed with commercial oligonucleotide arrays. In addition, variance in gene expression in human blood leukocytes caused by repeated sampling in the same subject, among different healthy subjects, among different leukocyte subpopulations, and the effect of traumatic injury, were also explored. We report that analytical variance caused by sample processing was acceptably small. Blood leukocyte gene expression in the same individual over a 24-h period was remarkably constant. In contrast, genome-wide expression varied significantly among different subjects and leukocyte subpopulations. Expectedly, traumatic injury induced dramatic changes in apparent gene expression that were greater in magnitude than the analytical noise and interindividual variance. We demonstrate that the development of a nation-wide program for gene expression analysis with careful attention to analytical details can reduce the variance in the clinical setting to a level where patterns of gene expression are informative among different healthy human subjects, and can be studied with confidence in human disease. </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20091118; GR: U54 GM-62119-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC555033; 2005/03/21 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Washington University, St. Louis, MO 63130, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15781863; 0409768102 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0409768102</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20050321</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15781863</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC555033</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1386</id>
<a1>Coberley,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Kohler,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Brown,J. N.</a1>
<a1>Oshier,J. T.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Popp,M. P.</a1>
<a1>Sleasman,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Goodenow,M. M.</a1>
<t1>Impact on genetic networks in human macrophages by a CCR5 strain of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 </t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>11477</sp>
<op>11486</op>
<k1>CDC2 Protein Kinase/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Cycle</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>HIV-1/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymphocytes/metabolism/virology</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/metabolism/virology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, CCR5/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) impacts multiple lineages of hematopoietic cells, including lymphocytes and macrophages, either by direct infection or indirectly by perturbations of cell networks, leading to generalized immune deficiency. We designed a study to discover, in primary human macrophages, sentinel genetic targets that are impacted during replication over the course of 7 days by a CCR5-using virus. Expression of mRNA and proteins in virus- or mock-treated macrophages from multiple donors was evaluated. Hierarchical agglomerative cluster analysis grouped into distinct temporal expression patterns &amp;gt;900 known human genes that were induced or repressed at least fourfold by virus. Expression of more than one-third of the genes was induced rapidly by day 2 of infection, while other genes were induced at intermediate (day 4) or late (day 7) time points. More than 200 genes were expressed exclusively in either virus- or mock-treated macrophage cultures, independent of the donor, providing an unequivocal basis to distinguish an effect by virus. HIV-1 altered levels of mRNA and/or protein for diverse cellular programs in macrophages, including multiple genes that can contribute to a transition in the cell cycle from G(1) to G(2)/M, in contrast to expression in mock-treated macrophages of genes that maintain G(0)/G(1). Virus treatment activated mediators of cell cycling, including PP2A, which is impacted by Vpr, as well as GADD45 and BRCA1, potentially novel targets for HIV-1. The results identify interrelated programs conducive to optimal HIV-1 replication and expression of genes that can contribute to macrophage dysfunction. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20091119; GR: AI28571/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI47723/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: HL58005/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD32259/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AR07603/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 CA09126/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Receptors, CCR5); EC 2.7.11.22 (CDC2 Protein Kinase); OID: NLM: PMC523249; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Pathology, Immunology, and Laboratory Medicine, Box 100275, University of Florida College of Medicine, 1600 S.W. Archer Rd., Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15479790; 78/21/11477 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.78.21.11477-11486.2004</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15479790</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC523249</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1404</id>
<a1>Drazinic,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Smerage,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Activation mechanism of the multifunctional transcription factor repressor-activator protein 1 (Rap1p) </t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>3187</sp>
<op>3196</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation</k1>
<ab>Transcriptional activation in eukaryotic organisms normally requires combinatorial interactions of multiple transcription factors. In most cases, the precise role played by each transcription factor is not known. The upstream activating sequence (UAS) elements of glycolytic enzyme genes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae are excellent model systems for the study of combinatorial interactions. The yeast protein known as Rap1p acts as both a transcriptional repressor and an activator, depending on sequence context. Rap1p-binding sites are found adjacent to Gcr1p-binding sites in the UAS elements of glycolytic enzyme genes. These UAS elements constitute some of the strongest activating sequences known in S. cerevisiae. In this study, we have investigated the relationship between Rap1p- and Gcr1p-binding sites and the proteins that bind them. In vivo DNA-binding studies with rap1ts mutant strains demonstrated that the inability of Rap1p to bind at its site resulted in the inability of Gcr1p to bind at adjacent binding sites. Synthetic oligonucleotides, modeled on the UAS element of PYK1, in which the relative positions of the Rap1p- and Gcr1p-binding sites were varied prepared and tested for their ability to function as UAS elements. The ability of the oligonucleotides to function as UAS elements was dependent not only on the presence of both binding sites but also on the relative distance between the binding sites. In vivo DNA-binding studies showed that the ability of Rap1p bind its site was independent of Gcr1p but that the ability of Gcr1p to bind its site was dependent on the presence of an appropriately spaced and bound Rap1p-binding site. In vitro binding studies showed Rap1p-enhanced binding of Gcr1p on oligonucleotides modeled after the native PYK1 UAS element but not when the Rap1p- and Gcr1p-binding sites were displaced by 5 nucleotides. This work demonstrates that the role of the Rap1p in the activation of glycolytic enzyme genes is to bind in their UAS elements and to facilitate the binding of Gcr1p at adjacent binding sites. </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20091119; JID: 8109087; 0 (ABF1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (REB1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); OID: NLM: PMC231312; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8649429</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8649429</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC231312</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1381</id>
<a1>Efron,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Tsujimoto,H.</a1>
<a1>Bahjat,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Ungaro,R.</a1>
<a1>Debernardis,J.</a1>
<a1>Tannahill,C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Edwards,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Differential maturation of murine bone-marrow derived dendritic cells with lipopolysaccharide and tumor necrosis factor-alpha </t1>
<jf>Journal of endotoxin research</jf>
<jo>J.Endotoxin Res.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>145</sp>
<op>160</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens</k1>
<k1>Bone Marrow Cells</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Dendritic Cells/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha/physiology</k1>
<ab>Dendritic cells (DCs) play a key role in the interface between the innate and acquired immune systems. In response to both exogenous as well as endogenous signals, DCs undergo a programmed maturation to become an efficient, antigen-presenting cell. Yet little is known regarding the differential responses by endogenous versus exogenous stimuli on DC maturation. In the present report, we have compared the phenotypic, functional, and genome-wide expression responses associated with maturation by bone marrow derived DCs to either an endogenous danger signal, tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha), or a microbial product, bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS). Examination of the cell surface expression of DCs as well as cytokine production demonstrated that patterns of DC maturation varied dramatically depending upon the stimulus. Whereas LPS was highly effective in terms of inducing phenotypic and functional maturation, TNF-alpha exposure produced a phenotypically distinct DC. Gene expression patterns in DCs 6 and 24 h after LPS and TNF-alpha exposure revealed that these activation signals produce fundamentally different genomic responses. Supervised analysis revealed that the expression of 929 probe sets discriminated among the treatment groups, and the patterns of gene expression in TNF-alpha stimulated DCs were more similar to unstimulated cells at both 6 and 24 h post-stimulation than to LPS-stimulated cells at the same time points. These findings reveal that DCs are capable of a varying phenotypic response to different antigens and endogenous signals. </ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20071114; GR: R01 GM63041-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37 GM-40561-15/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08721-04/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9433350; 0 (Antigens); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 0 (Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha); ppublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0968-0519; 0968-0519</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15949143</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1179/096805105X46583</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15949143</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1365</id>
<a1>Escobar,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Cheng,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Moore,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Tannahill,C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Banerjee,A.</a1>
<t1>Stored packed red blood cell transfusion up-regulates inflammatory gene expression in circulating leukocytes </t1>
<jf>Annals of Surgery</jf>
<jo>Ann.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>246</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>129</sp>
<op>134</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Biological Markers/blood</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cyclooxygenase 2/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Erythrocyte Transfusion</k1>
<k1>Heparin Lyase/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Probes</k1>
<k1>RNA/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Toll-Like Receptor 4/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Up-Regulation</k1>
<ab>SUMMARY BACKGROUND DATA: The transfusion of more than 6 units of packed red blood cells (PRBCs) within the first 12 hours of injury is the strongest independent predictor of multiple organ failure (MOF). This suggests that stored blood contains bioactive factors that may modify the immunoinflammatory response. METHODS: To simulate postinjury major transfusions ex vivo, we obtained whole blood from 4 healthy adults and divided it into four 7-mL groups (I-IV). Group I was not diluted. Group II had 7 mL of 0.9% sterile saline (SS) added. Group III received 3.5 mL each of leuko-reduced stored PRBC and SS (simulating a major transfusion). Group IV received 3.5 mL each of SS and a hemoglobin-based oxygen carrier (PolyHeme) to evaluate the effects of hemoglobin alone. The hemoglobin content in groups III and IV was measured to be equal. Total leukocyte RNA was purified, and its gene array profiles were obtained. RESULTS: Of the 56,475 oligonucleotide probe sets interrogated, 415 were statistically different (P </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20091118; GR: P50GM049222/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32GM08315/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: U54GM62119/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372354; 0 (Biological Markers); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Interleukin-8); 0 (Membrane Proteins); 0 (NLRP3 protein, human); 0 (Oligonucleotide Probes); 0 (Toll-Like Receptor 4); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 1.14.99.1 (Cyclooxygenase 2); EC 1.14.99.1 (PTGS2 protein, human); EC 4.2.2.7 (Heparin Lyase); OID: NLM: PMC1899205; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-4932; 0003-4932</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Colorado Health Science Center/Denver Health Medical Center, Denver, CO 80204, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17592301; 00000658-200707000-00020 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.sla.0000264507.79859.f9</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17592301</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1899205</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1417</id>
<a1>Farrish,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.,2nd</a1>
<a1>Wolf,R. E.,Jr</a1>
<t1>Different control circuits for growth rate-dependent regulation of 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase and protein components of the translational machinery in Escherichia coli </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>152</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>584</sp>
<op>594</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Previous studies showed that the level of 6-phosphogluconate (6PG) dehydrogenase increases about fourfold with increasing growth rate when the growth rate is varied by varying the carbon source. When the growth rate was reduced by anaerobic growth or by using mutations to divert metabolism to less efficient pathways, the level of 6PG dehydrogenase was the same as in a wild-type strain growing aerobically on other carbon sources that yielded the same growth rate. Thus, expression of gnd, which encodes 6PG dehydrogenase, is regulated by the cellular growth rate and not by specific nutrients in the medium. Growth rate-dependent regulation was independent of temperature. After a nutritional shift-up, 6PG dehydrogenase and total protein did not attain the postshift rate of accumulation for 30 min, whereas RNA accumulation increased immediately. The kinetics of accumulation of 6PG dehydrogenase and RNA were coincident after a nutritional shift-down. Partial amino acid starvation of a strain that controls RNA synthesis stringently (rel+) had no effect on the differential rate of accumulation of the enzyme. The level of 6PG dehydrogenase in cells harboring a gnd+ multicopy plasmid was in approximate proportion to gene dosage and somewhat higher at faster growth rates. Growth rate control of chromosomal gnd was normal in strains carrying multiple copies of the promoter-proximal and promoter-distal portions of gnd. These results show that gnd is not part of the same regulatory network as components of the translational apparatus since gnd shows a delayed response to a nutritional shift-up, is not autoregulated, and is not subject to stringent control. Models to account for growth rate-dependent regulation of gnd are discussed. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20091118; GR: GM27113/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (RNA, Bacterial); EC 1.1.1.43 (Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase); OID: NLM: PMC221505; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<an>PMID: 6182137</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6182137</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC221505</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1384</id>
<a1>Feezor,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M.</a1>
<a1>Hayden,D.</a1>
<a1>Tannahill,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Fay,A.</a1>
<a1>MacMillan,S.</a1>
<a1>Laramie,J.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Laudanski,K.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Schoenfeld,D.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<a1>Inflammation and Host Response to Injury,Large-Scale Collaborative Research Program</a1>
<t1>Whole blood and leukocyte RNA isolation for gene expression analyses </t1>
<jf>Physiological genomics</jf>
<jo>Physiol.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov 17</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>254</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Blood Specimen Collection/standards</k1>
<k1>Cluster Analysis</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling/methods/standards/statistics &amp; numerical data</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis/methods/standards/statistics &amp; numerical data</k1>
<k1>RNA/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Research Design/standards</k1>
<k1>Specimen Handling/standards</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/blood</k1>
<ab>The analysis of gene expression data in clinical medicine has been plagued by the lack of a critical evaluation of accepted methodologies for the collection, processing, and labeling of RNA. In the present report, the reliability of two commonly used techniques to isolate RNA from whole blood or its leukocyte compartment was compared by examining their reproducibility, variance, and signal-to-noise ratios. Whole blood was obtained from healthy subjects and was either untreated or stimulated ex vivo with Staphylococcus enterotoxin B (SEB). Blood samples were also obtained from trauma patients but were not stimulated with SEB ex vivo. Total RNA was isolated from whole blood with the PAXgene proprietary blood collection system or from isolated leukocytes. Biotin-labeled cRNA was hybridized to Affymetrix GeneChips. The Pearson correlation coefficient for gene expression measurements in replicates from healthy subjects with both techniques was excellent, exceeding 0.985. Unsupervised analyses, including hierarchical cluster analysis, however, revealed that the RNA isolation method resulted in greater differences in gene expression than stimulation with SEB or among different trauma patients. The intraclass correlation, a measure of signal-to-noise ratio, of the difference between SEB-stimulated and unstimulated blood from healthy subjects was significantly higher in leukocyte-derived samples than in whole blood: 0.75 vs. 0.46 (P = 0.002). At the P </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20091215; GR: U54-GM-62119-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9815683; 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Enterotoxins); 39424-53-8 (enterotoxin B, staphylococcal); 63231-63-0 (RNA); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-2267; 1094-8341</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15548831; 19/3/247 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1152/physiolgenomics.00020.2004</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15548831</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1391</id>
<a1>Feezor,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Lee,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Huber,T. S.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M.</a1>
<a1>Kim,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Ruiz-Taylor,L.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Seeger,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Genomic and proteomic determinants of outcome in patients undergoing thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysm repair </t1>
<jf>Journal of immunology (Baltimore, Md.: 1950)</jf>
<jo>J.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>172</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>7103</sp>
<op>7109</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Aortic Aneurysm, Abdominal/surgery</k1>
<k1>Aortic Aneurysm, Thoracic/surgery</k1>
<k1>Blood Proteins/analysis</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genome</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Multiple Organ Failure/etiology</k1>
<k1>Proteomics</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>Thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysm repair, with its requisite intraoperative mesenteric ischemia-reperfusion, often results in the development of systemic inflammatory response syndrome, multiorgan dysfunction syndrome (MODS), and death. In the present study, an adverse clinical outcome following thoracoabdominal aortic aneurysm repair was identified by blood leukocyte genomic and plasma proteomic responses. Time-dependent changes in the expression of 146 genes from blood leukocytes were observed (p </ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20071114; GR: R37 GM-40586/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08721/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985117R; 0 (Blood Proteins); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-1767; 0022-1767</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15153533</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15153533</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1377</id>
<a1>Feezor,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Cheng,A.</a1>
<a1>Paddock,H. N.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Functional genomics and gene expression profiling in sepsis: beyond class prediction </t1>
<jf>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</jf>
<jo>Clin.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Nov 15</fd>
<vo>41 Suppl 7</vo>
<sp>S427</sp>
<op>35</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Burns/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Cluster Analysis</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sepsis/genetics/immunology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>Functional genomics involving genome-wide expression analyses is rapidly finding applications in clinical medicine. New technologies now permit the simultaneous analysis of mRNA levels for the entire human transcriptome from as few as 1000 cells. This approach is dramatically changing the way we define health and disease, allowing, for the first time, an unbiased view of the global changes in gene expression that are occurring. For the study of trauma biology and sepsis, this technology offers a powerful tool to develop molecular signatures for inflamed tissues and specific cell populations. At present, functional genomics is being used to classify the progress of disease and survival in response to traumatic and burn injury, sepsis and visceral ischemia, and reperfusion injury, as well as to describe patterns of gene expression in response to varying microbial pathogens. As the number of bioinformatics tools increases, functional genomics is beginning to reveal the underlying complexity of the biological response to a variety of inflammatory diseases and is providing new approaches for their exploration. Functional genomics is becoming a standard tool in inflammation research as a means to unravel the basic biological processes. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20071203; GR: R01 GM-63213/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37 GM-40586/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08721/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9203213; RF: 38; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-6591; 1058-4838</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16237642; CID36069 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1086/431993</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16237642</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1395</id>
<a1>Feezor,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Oberholzer,C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Novick,D.</a1>
<a1>Rubinstein,M.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Pribble,J.</a1>
<a1>Souza,S.</a1>
<a1>Dinarello,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Ertel,W.</a1>
<a1>Oberholzer,A.</a1>
<t1>Molecular characterization of the acute inflammatory response to infections with gram-negative versus gram-positive bacteria </t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>5803</sp>
<op>5813</op>
<k1>Cytokines/blood/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/immunology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gram-Negative Bacterial Infections/etiology/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Gram-Positive Bacterial Infections/etiology/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/etiology/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Inflammation Mediators/blood</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/immunology</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/immunology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Sepsis/etiology/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/immunology</k1>
<ab>Sepsis caused by gram-negative bacteria and that caused by gram-positive bacteria often manifest similar clinical features. We investigated plasma proinflammatory cytokine profiles in patients with sepsis due to gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria and studied the cytokine production and differential gene regulation of leukocytes stimulated ex vivo with Escherichia coli lipopolysaccharide or heat-killed Staphylococcus aureus. Concentrations of tumor necrosis factor alpha, interleukin 1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), IL-8, IL-10, IL-18 binding protein, procalcitonin, and protein C in plasma did not differ between patients with sepsis due to gram-negative and gram-positive bacteria. However, plasma IL-1beta, IL-6, and IL-18 concentrations were significantly higher in patients with sepsis due to gram-positive bacteria. Ex vivo stimulation of whole blood with heat-killed S. aureus markedly increased IL-1beta and IL-18 levels more than E. coli lipopolysaccharide stimulation. Microarray analysis revealed at least 359 cross-validated probe sets (genes) significant at the P </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20091118; GR: AI 15614/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM 40586/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: HL 68743/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM 80721/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Cytokines); 0 (Inflammation Mediators); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); OID: NLM: PMC201043; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Shands Hospital, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14500502</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14500502</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC201043</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1392</id>
<a1>Feezor,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Paddock,H. N.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Varela,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Barreda,J.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Mozingo,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Temporal patterns of gene expression in murine cutaneous burn wound healing </t1>
<jf>Physiological genomics</jf>
<jo>Physiol.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Feb 13</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>341</sp>
<op>348</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Burns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cluster Analysis</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Skin Diseases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Wound Healing/genetics</k1>
<ab>The global changes in gene expression in injured murine skin were characterized following a second-degree scald burn. Dorsal skin was harvested from uninjured and from burned mice at 2 h and at 3 and 14 days following immersion in 65 degrees C water for 45 s. Gene expression was surveyed using an Affymetrix U74Av2 GeneChip, and patterns of gene expression were analyzed using hierarchical clustering and supervised analysis. Burn injury produced significant alterations in the expression of a number of genes, with the greatest changes seen 3 and 14 days after the scald burn. Using a supervised analysis with a false discovery rate of 1% or 5%, differences in the expression of 192 or 1,116 genes, respectively, discriminated among the unburned skin and the three time points after the burn injury. Gene expression was primarily a transient and time-dependent upregulation. The expression of only 24 of the 192 discriminating genes was downregulated after the burn injury. No gene exhibited a sustained increase in expression over the entire 14 days following the burn injury. Gene ontologies revealed an integrated upregulation of inflammatory and protease genes at acute time intervals, and a diminution of cytoskeletal and muscle contractile genes at 3 or 14 days after the injury. Following a second-degree scald burn, global patterns of gene expression in the burn wound change dramatically over several weeks in a time-dependent manner, and these changes can be categorized based on the biological relevance of the genes. </ab>
<no>id: 5; LR: 20071114; GR: R37-GM-40586-14/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-GM-08721-05/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9815683; 0 (RNA, Messenger); epublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-2267; 1094-8341</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14966252; 16/3/341 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1152/physiolgenomics.00101.2003</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20040213</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14966252</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1387</id>
<a1>Ha,U. H.</a1>
<a1>Kim,J.</a1>
<a1>Badrane,H.</a1>
<a1>Jia,J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Wu,D.</a1>
<a1>Jin,S.</a1>
<t1>An in vivo inducible gene of Pseudomonas aeruginosa encodes an anti-ExsA to suppress the type III secretion system </t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>307</sp>
<op>320</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Copper/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Two-Hybrid System Techniques</k1>
<ab>We have previously reported on the isolation of in vivo inducible genes of Pseudomonas aeruginosa using IVET system. One of such genes isolated from burn mouse infection model encodes a short open reading frame with unknown function. In this study, we demonstrate that this gene product specifically suppresses the expression of type III secretion genes in P. aeruginosa, thus named PtrA (Pseudomonas type III repressor A). A direct interaction between the PtrA and type III transcriptional activator ExsA was demonstrated, suggesting that its repressor function is probably realized through inhibition of the ExsA protein function. Indeed, an elevated expression of the exsA compensates the repressor effect of the PtrA. Interestingly, expression of the ptrA is highly and specifically induced by copper cation. A copper- responsive two-component regulatory system, copR-copS, has also been identified and shown to be essential for the copper resistance in P. aeruginosa as well as the activation of ptrA in response to the copper signal. Elevated expression of the ptrA during the infection of mouse burn wound suggests that P. aeruginosa has evolved tight regulatory systems to shut down energy-expensive type III secretion apparatus in response to specific environmental signals, such as copper stress. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20080627; JID: 8712028; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (ExsA protein, bacteria); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 7440-50-8 (Copper); ppublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, PO Box 100266, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15469505; MMI4282 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04282.x</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15469505</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1375</id>
<a1>Handayani,R.</a1>
<a1>Rice,L.</a1>
<a1>Cui,Y.</a1>
<a1>Medrano,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Samedi,V. G.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Szabo,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Shiverick,K. T.</a1>
<t1>Soy isoflavones alter expression of genes associated with cancer progression, including interleukin-8, in androgen-independent PC-3 human prostate cancer cells </t1>
<jf>The Journal of nutrition</jf>
<jo>J.Nutr.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>75</sp>
<op>82</op>
<k1>DNA/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genistein/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Isoflavones/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Phytoestrogens/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Prostatic Neoplasms/drug therapy/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Soybean Proteins/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>High consumption of soy isoflavones in Asian diets has been correlated with a lower incidence of clinically important cases of prostate cancer. The chemopreventive properties of these diets may result from an interaction of several types of isoflavones, including genistein and daidzein. The present study investigated the effects of a soy isoflavone concentrate (ISF) on growth and gene expression profiles of PC-3 human prostate cancer cells. Trypan blue exclusion and [3H]-thymidine incorporation assays showed that ISF decreased cell viability and caused a dose-dependent inhibition of DNA synthesis, respectively, with 50% inhibition (IC50) of DNA synthesis at 52 mg/L (P = 0.05). The glucoside conjugates of genistein and daidzein in ISF were converted to bioactive free aglycones in cell culture in association with the inhibition of DNA synthesis. Flow cytometry and Western immunoblot analyses showed that ISF at 200 mg/L caused an accumulation of cells in the G2/M phase of the cell cycle (P </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20071114; GR: CA91231/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: P42 ES07375/ES/NIEHS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0404243; 0 (Interleukin-8); 0 (Isoflavones); 0 (Phytoestrogens); 0 (Soybean Proteins); 446-72-0 (Genistein); 486-66-8 (daidzein); 9007-49-2 (DNA); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-3166; 0022-3166</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacology, College of Medicine, Univerisity of Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16365062; 136/1/75 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16365062</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1360</id>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Beyond good and evil in the oral cavity: insights into host-microbe relationships derived from transcriptional profiling of gingival cells </t1>
<jf>Journal of dental research</jf>
<jo>J.Dent.Res.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>203</sp>
<op>223</op>
<k1>Bacteria/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Physiological Phenomena</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gingiva/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Host-Pathogen Interactions/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microarray Analysis</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic/genetics</k1>
<ab>In many instances, the encounter between host and microbial cells, through a long-standing evolutionary association, can be a balanced interaction whereby both cell types co-exist and inflict a minimal degree of harm on each other. In the oral cavity, despite the presence of large numbers of diverse organisms, health is the most frequent status. Disease will ensue only when the host-microbe balance is disrupted on a cellular and molecular level. With the advent of microarrays, it is now possible to monitor the responses of host cells to bacterial challenge on a global scale. However, microarray data are known to be inherently noisy, which is caused in part by their great sensitivity. Hence, we will address several important general considerations required to maximize the significance of microarray analysis in depicting relevant host-microbe interactions faithfully. Several advantages and limitations of microarray analysis that may have a direct impact on the significance of array data are highlighted and discussed. Further, this review revisits and contextualizes recent transcriptional profiles that were originally generated for the specific study of intricate cellular interactions between gingival cells and 4 important plaque micro-organisms. To our knowledge, this is the first report that systematically investigates the cellular responses of a cell line to challenge by 4 different micro-organisms. Of particular relevance to the oral cavity, the model bacteria span the entire spectrum of documented pathogenic potential, from commensal to opportunistic to overtly pathogenic. These studies provide a molecular basis for the complex and dynamic interaction between the oral microflora and its host, which may lead, ultimately, to the development of novel, rational, and practical therapeutic, prophylactic, and diagnostic applications. </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20091118; GR: DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE13523/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE14955/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE16715/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE011111-15/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE016715-04/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE007200-18/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: U01 DE014955-04/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0354343; RF: 241; NIHMS89336; OID: NLM: NIHMS89336; OID: NLM: PMC2633067; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0345; 0022-0345</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology, College of Dentistry, Box 100424 JHMHSC, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0424, USA. mhandfield@dental.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18296603; 87/3/203 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Review; D; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18296603</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2633067</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1382</id>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Mans,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Zheng,G.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Mao,S.</a1>
<a1>Progulske-Fox,A.</a1>
<a1>Narasimhan,G.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Distinct transcriptional profiles characterize oral epithelium-microbiota interactions </t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>811</sp>
<op>823</op>
<k1>Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Coculture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Ecosystem</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Gingiva/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mouth Mucosa/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Porphyromonas gingivalis/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Tumor Suppressor Protein p53/physiology</k1>
<ab>Transcriptional profiling, bioinformatics, statistical and ontology tools were used to uncover and dissect genes and pathways of human gingival epithelial cells that are modulated upon interaction with the periodontal pathogens Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans and Porphyromonas gingivalis. Consistent with their biological and clinical differences, the common core transcriptional response of epithelial cells to both organisms was very limited, and organism-specific responses predominated. A large number of differentially regulated genes linked to the P53 apoptotic network were found with both organisms, which was consistent with the pro-apoptotic phenotype observed with A. actinomycetemcomitans and anti-apoptotic phenotype of P. gingivalis. Furthermore, with A. actinomycetemcomitans, the induction of apoptosis did not appear to be Fas- or TNF(alpha)-mediated. Linkage of specific bacterial components to host pathways and networks provided additional insight into the pathogenic process. Comparison of the transcriptional responses of epithelial cells challenged with parental P. gingivalis or with a mutant of P. gingivalis deficient in production of major fimbriae, which are required for optimal invasion, showed major expression differences that reverberated throughout the host cell transcriptome. In contrast, gene ORF859 in A. actinomycetemcomitans, which may play a role in intracellular homeostasis, had a more subtle effect on the transcriptome. These studies help unravel the complex and dynamic interactions between host epithelial cells and endogenous bacteria that can cause opportunistic infections. </ab>
<no>id: 5; LR: 20071114; GR: DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE13523/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE14955/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE13545/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100883691; 0 (Tumor Suppressor Protein p53); 0 (fimbrillin); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5814; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0424, USA. mhandfield@dental.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15888084; CMI513 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-5822.2005.00513.x</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15888084</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1368</id>
<a1>Hasegawa,Y.</a1>
<a1>Mans,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Mao,S.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Gingival epithelial cell transcriptional responses to commensal and opportunistic oral microbial species </t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>2540</sp>
<op>2547</op>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fusobacterium nucleatum/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gingiva/cytology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase Kinases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Proteome</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus/classification/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Transcriptional profiling and ontology tools were utilized to define the biological pathways of gingival epithelial cells modulated by coculture with the oral commensal Streptococcus gordonii and the opportunistic commensal Fusobacterium nucleatum. Overall, F. nucleatum and S. gordonii perturbed the gingival epithelial cell transcriptome much less significantly than the oral pathogens Porphyromonas gingivalis and Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans perturbed the transcriptome, indicating that there was a greater degree of host adaptation by the commensal species (M. Handfield, J. J. Mans, G. Zheng, M. C. Lopez, S. Mao, A. Progulske-Fox, G. Narasimhan, H. V. Baker, and R. J. Lamont, Cell. Microbiol. 7:811-823, 2005). The biological pathways significantly impacted by F. nucleatum and S. gordonii included the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) and Toll-like receptor signaling pathways. Differential regulation of GADD45 and DUSP4, key components of the MAPK pathway, was confirmed at the protein level by Western blotting. Modulation of the MAPK pathway is likely to affect host cell proliferation and differentiation. In addition, both the MAPK and Toll-like receptor pathways ultimately converge on cytokine gene expression. An enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay of secreted interleukin-6 (IL-6) and IL-8 demonstrated that F. nucleatum induced production of these cytokines, whereas S. gordonii inhibited secretion from the epithelial cells. Stimulation of secretion of proinflammatory cytokines from epithelial cells may reflect the invasive phenotype of F. nucleatum and contribute to the greater pathogenic potential of F. nucleatum than of S. gordonii. </ab>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20091119; GEO/GSE6927; GEO/GSM159477; GEO/GSM159478; GEO/GSM159479; GEO/GSM159480; GEO/GSM159481; GEO/GSM159482; GEO/GSM159483; GEO/GSM159484; GEO/GSM159485; GEO/GSM159486; GEO/GSM159487; GEO/GSM159488; GR: DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE16715/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE7200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Proteins); 0 (Proteome); EC 2.7.12.2 (Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase Kinases); OID: NLM: PMC1865734; 2007/02/16 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology and Center for Molecular Microbiology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0424, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17307939; IAI.01957-06 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/IAI.01957-06</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20070216</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17307939</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1865734</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1358</id>
<a1>Hasegawa,Y.</a1>
<a1>Tribble,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Mans,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Role of Porphyromonas gingivalis SerB in gingival epithelial cell cytoskeletal remodeling and cytokine production </t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2420</sp>
<op>2427</op>
<k1>Actins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytokines/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytoskeleton/physiology</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/immunology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gingiva/cytology/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Keratinocytes/cytology/immunology</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Phosphoric Monoester Hydrolases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Porphyromonas gingivalis/enzymology/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The SerB protein of Porphyromonas gingivalis is a HAD family serine phosphatase that plays a critical role in entry and survival of the organism in gingival epithelial cells. SerB is secreted by P. gingivalis upon contact with epithelial cells. Here it is shown by microarray analysis that SerB impacts the transcriptional profile of gingival epithelial cells, with pathways involving the actin cytoskeleton and cytokine production among those significantly overpopulated with differentially regulated genes. Consistent with the transcriptional profile, a SerB mutant of P. gingivalis exhibited defective remodeling of actin in epithelial cells. Interaction between gingival epithelial cells and isolated SerB protein resulted in actin rearrangement and an increase in the F/G actin ratio. SerB protein was also required for P. gingivalis to antagonize interleukin-8 accumulation following stimulation of epithelial cells with Fusobacterium nucleatum. SerB is thus capable of modulating host cell signal transduction that impacts the actin cytoskeleton and cytokine production. </ab>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20091118; GEO/GSE10526; GR: DE 16715/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Actins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Cytokines); 0 (Interleukin-8); EC 3.1.3.- (Phosphoric Monoester Hydrolases); EC 3.1.3.3 (phosphoserine phosphatase); OID: NLM: PMC2423092; 2008/04/07 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5522; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology and Center for Molecular Microbiology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0424, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18391005; IAI.00156-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/IAI.00156-08</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20080407</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18391005</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2423092</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1357</id>
<a1>Haskell-Luevano,C.</a1>
<a1>Schaub,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Andreasen,A.</a1>
<a1>Haskell,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Moore,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Koerper,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Rouzaud,F.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Millard,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Walter,G.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Xiang,Z.</a1>
<t1>Voluntary exercise prevents the obese and diabetic metabolic syndrome of the melanocortin-4 receptor knockout mouse </t1>
<jf>The FASEB journal : official publication of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology</jf>
<jo>FASEB J.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>642</sp>
<op>655</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blood Glucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Body Weight</k1>
<k1>Cholesterol/blood</k1>
<k1>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2/genetics/metabolism/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Insulin/blood</k1>
<k1>Leptin/blood</k1>
<k1>Liver/anatomy &amp; histology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Obesity/genetics/metabolism/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Organ Size</k1>
<k1>Pancreas/anatomy &amp; histology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Physical Conditioning, Animal/physiology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Melanocortin, Type 4/deficiency/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<ab>Exercise is a mechanism for maintenance of body weight in humans. Morbidly obese human patients have been shown to possess single nucleotide polymorphisms in the melanocortin-4 receptor (MC4R). MC4R knockout mice have been well characterized as a genetic model that possesses phenotypic metabolic disorders, including obesity, hyperphagia, hyperinsulinemia, and hyperleptinemia, similar to those observed in humans possessing dysfunctional hMC4Rs. Using this model, we examined the effect of voluntary exercise of MC4R knockout mice that were allowed access to a running wheel for a duration of 8 wk. Physiological parameters that were measured included body weight, body composition of fat and lean mass, food consumption, body length, and blood levels of cholesterol and nonfasted glucose, insulin, and leptin. At the termination of the experiment, hypothalamic mRNA expression levels of neuropeptide Y (NPY), agouti-related protein (AGRP), proopiomelanocortin (POMC), cocaine- and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART), orexin, brain-derived neurotropic factor (BDNF), phosphatase with tensin homology (Pten), melanocortin-3 receptor (MC3R), and NPY-Y1R were determined. In addition, islet cell distribution and function in the pancreas were examined. In the exercising MC4R knockout mice, the pancreatic islet cell morphology and other physiological parameters resembled those observed in the wild-type littermate controls. Gene expression profiles identified exercise as having a significant effect on hypothalamic POMC, orexin, and MC3R levels. Genotype had a significant effect on AGRP, POMC, CART, and NPY-Y1R, with an exercise and genotype interaction effect on NPY gene expression. These data support the hypothesis that voluntary exercise can prevent the genetic predisposition of melanocortin-4 receptor-associated obesity and diabetes. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20100202; GR: R01DK057080/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8804484; 0 (Blood Glucose); 0 (Leptin); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Receptor, Melanocortin, Type 4); 11061-68-0 (Insulin); 57-88-5 (Cholesterol); OID: NLM: PMC2630780; 2008/10/29 [aheadofprint]; 2008/10/31 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1530-6860; 0892-6638</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacodynamics, University of Florida, PO Box 100487, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. carrie@cop.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18971258; fj.08-109686 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1096/fj.08-109686</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20081029</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18971258</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2630780</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1406</id>
<a1>Henry,Y. A.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Gibbs,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Chambers,A.</a1>
<a1>Kingsman,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Stanway,C. A.</a1>
<t1>The yeast protein Gcr1p binds to the PGK UAS and contributes to the activation of transcription of the PGK gene </t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Nov 15</fd>
<vo>245</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>506</sp>
<op>511</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>GTP-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phosphoglycerate Kinase/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation</k1>
<k1>rap GTP-Binding Proteins</k1>
<ab>Analysis of the upstream activation sequence (UAS) of the yeast phosphoglycerate kinase gene (PGK) has demonstrated that a number of sequence elements are involved in its activity and two of these sequences are bound by the multifunctional factors Rap1p and Abf1p. In this report we show by in vivo footprinting that the regulatory factor encoded by GCR1 binds to two elements in the 3&amp;#39; half of the PGK UAS. These elements contain the sequence CTTCC, which was previously suggested to be important for the activity of the PGK UAS and has been shown to be able to bind Gcr1p in vitro. Furthermore, we find that Gcr1p positively influences PGK transcription, although it is not responsible for the carbon source dependent regulation of PGK mRNA synthesis. In order to mediate its transcriptional influence we find that Gcr1p requires the Rap1p binding site, in addition to its own, but not the Abf1p site. As neither a Rap1p nor a Gcr1p binding site alone is able to activate transcription, we propose that Gcr1p and Rap1p interact in an interdependent fashion to activate PGK transcription. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20091119; GR: GM-41330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0125036; 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); EC 2.7.2.3 (Phosphoglycerate Kinase); EC 3.6.1.- (GTP-Binding Proteins); EC 3.6.5.2 (rap GTP-Binding Proteins); ppublish </no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, Oxford University, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7808400</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7808400</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1405</id>
<a1>Huie,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>DNA-binding properties of the yeast transcriptional activator, Gcr1p </t1>
<jf>Yeast (Chichester, England)</jf>
<jo>Yeast</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Mar 30</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>307</sp>
<op>317</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<ab>In Saccharomyces cerevisiae the GCRI gene product is required for high-level expression of genes encoding glycolytic enzymes. In this communication, we extend our analysis of the DNA binding properties of Gcr1p. The DNA-binding domain of Gcr1p binds DNA with high affinity. The apparent dissociation constant of the Gcr1p DNA-binding domain for one of its specific binding sites (TTTCAGCTTCCTCTAT) is 2.9 x 10(-10) M. However, competition experiments showed that Gcr1p binds this site in vitro with a low degree of specificity. We measured a 33-fold difference between the ability of specific competitor and DNA of random sequence to inhibit the formation of nucleoprotein complexes between Gcr1p and a radiolabeled DNA probe containing its binding site. DNA band-shift experiments, utilizing probes of constant length in which the positions of Gcr1p-binding sites are varied relative to the ends, indicated that Gcr1p-DNA nucleoprotein complexes contain bent DNA. The implications of these findings in terms of the combinatorial interactions that occur at the upstream activating sequence elements of genes encoding glycolytic enzymes are discussed. </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20091119; JID: 8607637; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Transcription Factors); 9007-49-2 (DNA); ppublish </no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0749-503X; 0749-503X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8701604; 10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(19960330)12:4&lt;307::AID-YEA912&gt;3.0.CO;2-C [pii]; 10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(19960330)12:4&lt;307::AID-YEA912&gt;3.0.CO</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>2-C</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8701604</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1410</id>
<a1>Huie,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Scott,E. W.</a1>
<a1>Drazinic,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Hornstra,I. K.</a1>
<a1>Yang,T. P.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of the DNA-binding activity of GCR1: in vivo evidence for two GCR1-binding sites in the upstream activating sequence of TPI of Saccharomyces cerevisiae </t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2690</sp>
<op>2700</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis</k1>
<k1>Methylation</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Regulatory Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Triose-Phosphate Isomerase/genetics</k1>
<ab>GCR1 gene function is required for high-level glycolytic gene expression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Recently, we suggested that the CTTCC sequence motif found in front of many genes encoding glycolytic enzymes lay at the core of the GCR1-binding site. Here we mapped the DNA-binding domain of GCR1 to the carboxy-terminal 154 amino acids of the polypeptide. DNase I protection studies showed that a hybrid MBP-GCR1 fusion protein protected a region of the upstream activating sequence of TPI (UASTPI), which harbored the CTTCC sequence motif, and suggested that the fusion protein might also interact with a region of the UAS that contained the related sequence CATCC. A series of in vivo G methylation protection experiments of the native TPI promoter were carried out with wild-type and gcr1 deletion mutant strains. The G doublets that correspond to the C doublets in each site were protected in the wild-type strain but not in the gcr1 mutant strain. These data demonstrate that the UAS of TPI contains two GCR1-binding sites which are occupied in vivo. Furthermore, adjacent RAP1/GRF1/TUF- and REB1/GRF2/QBP/Y-binding sites in UASTPI were occupied in the backgrounds of both strains. In addition, DNA band-shift assays were used to show that the MBP-GCR1 fusion protein was able to form nucleoprotein complexes with oligonucleotides that contained CTTCC sequence elements found in front of other glycolytic genes, namely, PGK, ENO1, PYK, and ADH1, all of which are dependent on GCR1 gene function for full expression. However, we were unable to detect specific interactions with CTTCC sequence elements found in front of the translational component genes TEF1, TEF2, and CRY1. Taken together, these experiments have allowed us to propose a consensus GCR1-binding site which is 5&amp;#39;-(T/A)N(T/C)N(G/A)NC(T/A)TCC(T/A)N(T/A)(T/A)(T/G)-3&amp;#39;. </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20091118; GR: GM-4133/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); EC 5.3.1.1 (Triose-Phosphate Isomerase); OID: NLM: PMC364463; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1588965</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1588965</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC364463</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1369</id>
<a1>Laudanski,K.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Richards,D. R.</a1>
<a1>De,A.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Bankey,P.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Calvano,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<t1>Cell-specific expression and pathway analyses reveal alterations in trauma-related human T cell and monocyte pathways </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Oct 17</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>42</is>
<sp>15564</sp>
<op>15569</op>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genome, Human</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Monocytes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Multiple Organ Failure/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocytes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Wounds and Injuries/immunology</k1>
<ab>Monitoring genome-wide, cell-specific responses to human disease, although challenging, holds great promise for the future of medicine. Patients with injuries severe enough to develop multiple organ dysfunction syndrome have multiple immune derangements, including T cell apoptosis and anergy combined with depressed monocyte antigen presentation. Genome-wide expression analysis of highly enriched circulating leukocyte subpopulations, combined with cell-specific pathway analyses, offers an opportunity to discover leukocyte regulatory networks in critically injured patients. Severe injury induced significant changes in T cell (5,693 genes), monocyte (2,801 genes), and total leukocyte (3,437 genes) transcriptomes, with only 911 of these genes common to all three cell populations (12%). T cell-specific pathway analyses identified increased gene expression of several inhibitory receptors (PD-1, CD152, NRP-1, and Lag3) and concomitant decreases in stimulatory receptors (CD28, CD4, and IL-2Ralpha). Functional analysis of T cells and monocytes confirmed reduced T cell proliferation and increased cell surface expression of negative signaling receptors paired with decreased monocyte costimulation ligands. Thus, genome-wide expression from highly enriched cell populations combined with knowledge-based pathway analyses leads to the identification of regulatory networks differentially expressed in injured patients. Importantly, application of cell separation, genome-wide expression, and cell-specific pathway analyses can be used to discover pathway alterations in human disease. </ab>
<no>id: 2; LR: 20091118; GR: 5R01 GM-65237/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: U54 GM-62119/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC1592643; 2006/10/10 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Rochester School of Medicine, Rochester, NY 14642, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17032758; 0607028103 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0607028103</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20061010</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17032758</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1592643</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1362</id>
<a1>Lederer,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B. H.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Macmillan,S.</a1>
<a1>Delisle,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Macconmara,M. P.</a1>
<a1>Choudhry,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Lekousi,S.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Mannick,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Chaudry,I. H.</a1>
<a1>Inflammation and the Host Response to Injury Collaborative Research Program Participants</a1>
<t1>Comparison of longitudinal leukocyte gene expression after burn injury or trauma-hemorrhage in mice </t1>
<jf>Physiological genomics</jf>
<jo>Physiol.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Feb 19</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>299</sp>
<op>310</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blood Loss, Surgical</k1>
<k1>Burns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Regulatory Networks/genetics</k1>
<k1>Hemorrhage/genetics</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Spleen/pathology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>A primary objective of the large collaborative project entitled &amp;quot;Inflammation and the Host Response to Injury&amp;quot; was to identify leukocyte genes that are differentially expressed after two different types of injury in mouse models and to test the hypothesis that both forms of injury would induce similar changes in gene expression. We report here the genes that are expressed in white blood cells (WBCs) and in splenocytes at 2 h, 1 day, 3 days, and 7 days after burn and sham injury or trauma-hemorrhage (T-H) and sham T-H. Affymetrix Mouse Genome 430 2.0 GeneChips were used to profile gene expression, and the results were analyzed by dCHIP, BRB Array Tools, and Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (IPA) software. We found that the highest number of genes differentially expressed following burn injury were at day 1 for both WBCs (4,989) and for splenocytes (4,715) and at day 1 for WBCs (1,167) and at day 3 for splenocytes (1,117) following T-H. The maximum overlap of genes that were expressed after both forms of injury were at day 1 in WBCs (136 genes) and at day 7 in splenocytes (433 genes). IPA revealed that the cell-to-cell signaling, cell death, immune response, antiapoptosis, and cell cycle control pathways were affected most significantly. In summary, this report provides a database of genes that are modulated in WBCs and splenocytes at sequential time points after burn or T-H in mice and reveals that relatively few leukocyte genes are expressed in common after these two forms of injury. </ab>
<no>id: 5; GR: 1U54-GM-62119-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9815683; 2007/11/06 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-2267; 1094-8341</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital/Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts 02115, USA. jlederer@rics.bwh.harvard.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17986522; 00086.2007 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1152/physiolgenomics.00086.2007</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20071106</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17986522</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1388</id>
<a1>Lian,W.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Badrane,H.</a1>
<a1>Tan,W.</a1>
<a1>Wu,D.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Lim,D. V.</a1>
<a1>Jin,S.</a1>
<t1>Ultrasensitive detection of biomolecules with fluorescent dye-doped nanoparticles </t1>
<jf>Analytical Biochemistry</jf>
<jo>Anal.Biochem.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov 1</fd>
<vo>334</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>135</sp>
<op>144</op>
<k1>Fluorescent Dyes</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Luminescent Measurements</k1>
<k1>Molecular Probe Techniques</k1>
<k1>Nanostructures/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Protein Array Analysis</k1>
<k1>Silicon Dioxide</k1>
<ab>Fluorescent-labeled molecules have been used extensively for a wide range of applications in biological detection and diagnosis. A new form of highly luminescent and photostable nanoparticles was generated by doping the fluorescent dye tris(2&amp;#39;2-bipyridyl)dichlororuthenium(II)hexahydrate (Rubpy) inside silica material. Because thousands of fluorescent dye molecules are encapsulated in the silica matrix that also serves to protect Rubpy dye from photodamaging oxidation, the Rubpy-dye-doped nanoparticles are extremely bright and photostable. We have used these nanoparticles successfully in various fluorescence labeling techniques, including fluorescent-linked immunosorbent assay, immunocytochemistry, immunohistochemistry, DNA microarray, and protein microarray. By combining the high-intensity luminescent nanoparticles with the specificity of antibody-mediated recognition, ultrasensitive target detection has been achieved. In all cases, assay results clearly demonstrated the superiority of the nanoparticles over organic fluorescent dye molecules and quantum dots in probe labeling for sensitive target detection. These results demonstrate the potential to apply these newly developed fluorescent nanoparticles in various biodetection systems. </ab>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20071114; GR: K01 DK02947/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0370535; 0 (Fluorescent Dyes); 7631-86-9 (Silicon Dioxide); 2004/05/11 [received]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-2697; 0003-2697</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15464962; S0003-2697(04)00655-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ab.2004.08.005</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15464962</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1399</id>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Understanding the growth phenotype of the yeast gcr1 mutant in terms of global genomic expression patterns </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>182</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>4970</sp>
<op>4978</op>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genome, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Ribosomal Proteins</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<ab>The phenotype of an organism is the manifestation of its expressed genome. The gcr1 mutant of yeast grows at near wild-type rates on nonfermentable carbon sources but exhibits a severe growth defect when grown in the presence of glucose, even when nonfermentable carbon sources are available. Using DNA microarrays, the genomic expression patterns of wild-type and gcr1 mutant yeast growing on various media, with and without glucose, were compared. A total of 53 open reading frames (ORFs) were identified as GCR1 dependent based on the criterion that their expression was reduced twofold or greater in mutant versus wild-type cultures grown in permissive medium consisting of YP supplemented with glycerol and lactate. The GCR1-dependent genes, so defined, fell into three classes: (i) glycolytic enzyme genes, (ii) ORFs carried by Ty elements, and (iii) genes not previously known to be GCR1 dependent. In wild-type cultures, GCR1-dependent genes accounted for 27% of the total hybridization signal, whereas in mutant cultures, they accounted for 6% of the total. Glucose addition to the growth medium resulted in a reprogramming of gene expression in both wild-type and mutant yeasts. In both strains, glycolytic enzyme gene expression was induced by the addition of glucose, although the expression of these genes was still impaired in the mutant compared to the wild type. By contrast, glucose resulted in a strong induction of Ty-borne genes in the mutant background but did not greatly affect their already high expression in the wild-type background. Both strains responded to glucose by repressing the expression of genes involved in respiration and the metabolism of alternative carbon sources. Thus, the severe growth inhibition observed in gcr1 mutants in the presence of glucose is the result of normal signal transduction pathways and glucose repression mechanisms operating without sufficient glycolytic enzyme gene expression to support growth via glycolysis alone. </ab>
<no>id: 2; LR: 20091119; JID: 2985120R; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Ribosomal Proteins); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); 50-99-7 (Glucose); OID: NLM: PMC111378; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10940042</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10940042</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC111378</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1401</id>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Smerage,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Multiple domains of repressor activator protein 1 contribute to facilitated binding of glycolysis regulatory protein 1 </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Nov 24</fd>
<vo>95</vo>
<is>24</is>
<sp>14112</sp>
<op>14117</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Peptide Fragments/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Structure-Activity Relationship</k1>
<k1>Telomere-Binding Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<ab>The function of repressor activator protein 1 (Rap1p) at glycolytic enzyme gene upstream activating sequence (UAS) elements in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is to facilitate binding of glycolysis regulatory protein 1 (Gcr1p) at adjacent sites. Rap1p has a modular domain structure. In its amino terminus there is an asymmetric DNA-bending domain, which is distinct from its DNA-binding domain, which resides in the middle of the protein. In the carboxyl terminus of Rap1p lie its silencing and putative activation domains. We carried out a molecular dissection of Rap1p to identify domains contributing to its ability to facilitate binding of Gcr1p. We prepared full-length and three truncated versions of Rap1p and tested their ability to facilitate binding of Gcr1p by gel shift assay. The ability to detect ternary complexes containing Rap1p.DNA. Gcr1p depended on the presence of binding sites for both proteins in the probe DNA. The DNA-binding domain of Rap1p, although competent to bind DNA, was unable to facilitate binding of Gcr1p. Full-length Rap1p and the amino- and carboxyl-truncated versions of Rap1p were each able to facilitate binding of Gcr1p at an appropriately spaced binding site. Under these conditions, Gcr1p displayed an approximately 4-fold greater affinity for Rap1p-bound DNA than for otherwise identical free DNA. When spacing between Rap1p- and Gcr1p-binding sites was altered by insertion of five nucleotides, the ability to form ternary Rap1p.DNA.Gcr1p complexes was inhibited by all but the DNA-binding domain of Rap1p itself; however, the ability of each individual protein to bind the DNA probe was unaffected. </ab>
<no>id: 4; LR: 20091119; JID: 7505876; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (Peptide Fragments); 0 (RAP1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Telomere-Binding Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); 9007-49-2 (DNA); OID: NLM: PMC24335; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Box 100266, JHMHC, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9826662</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9826662</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC24335</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1408</id>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Smerage,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>A simplified vacuum blotting method for genomic sequencing and in vivo footprinting </t1>
<jf>BioTechniques</jf>
<jo>BioTechniques</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>362</sp>
<op>363</op>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA/methods</k1>
<k1>Vacuum</k1>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20071114; GR: GM-41330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8306785; 0 (DNA, Fungal); ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0736-6205; 0736-6205</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8217138</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8217138</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1370</id>
<a1>Mans,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Oda,D.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<t1>Distinctive characteristics of transcriptional profiles from two epithelial cell lines upon interaction with Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans </t1>
<jf>Oral microbiology and immunology</jf>
<jo>Oral Microbiol.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>261</sp>
<op>267</op>
<k1>Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans/genetics</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Biological Transport/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chemotaxis/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA Damage/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Enzymologic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>KB Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Keratinocytes/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Neovascularization, Physiologic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acids/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nucleosides/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein-Tyrosine Kinases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA/genetics</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic/genetics</k1>
<ab>Transcriptional profiling and gene ontology analyses were performed to investigate the unique responses of two different epithelial cell lines to an Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans challenge. A total of 2867 genes were differentially regulated among all experimental conditions. The analysis of these 2867 genes revealed that the predominant specific response to infection in HeLa cells was associated with the regulation of enzyme activity, RNA metabolism, nucleoside and nucleic acid transport and protein modification. The predominant specific response in immortalized human gingival keratinocytes (IHGK) was associated with the regulation of angiogenesis, chemotaxis, transmembrane receptor protein tyrosine kinase signaling, cell differentiation, apoptosis and response to stress. Of particular interest, stress response genes were significantly - yet differently - affected in both cell lines. In HeLa cells, only three regulated genes impacted the response to stress, and the response to unfolded protein was the only term that passed the ontology filters. This strikingly contrasted with the profiles obtained for IHGK, in which 61 regulated genes impacted the response to stress and constituted an extensive network of cell responses to A. actinomycetemcomitans interaction (response to pathogens, oxidative stress, unfolded proteins, DNA damage, starvation and wounding). Hence, while extensive similarities were found in the transcriptional profiles of these two epithelial cell lines, significant differences were highlighted. These differences were predominantly found in pathways that are associated with host-pathogen interactions. </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20091119; GR: DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE13523/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE14955/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 DE07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8707451; 0 (Nucleic Acids); 0 (Nucleosides); 0 (Proteins); 63231-63-0 (RNA); EC 2.7.10.1 (Protein-Tyrosine Kinases); ppublish </no>
<pp>Denmark</pp>
<sn>0902-0055; 0902-0055</sn>
<ad>Center for Molecular Microbiology, Department of Oral Biology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16842512; OMI281 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; D</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1399-302X.2006.00281.x</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16842512</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1353</id>
<a1>Mans,J. J.</a1>
<a1>von Lackum,K.</a1>
<a1>Dorsey,C.</a1>
<a1>Willis,S.</a1>
<a1>Wallet,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<t1>The degree of microbiome complexity influences the epithelial response to infection </t1>
<jf>BMC genomics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genomics</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug 18</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<sp>380</sp>
<k1>Bacteroidaceae Infections/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Coculture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gingiva/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Host-Pathogen Interactions</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Keratinocytes/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Metagenome</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Porphyromonas gingivalis/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Streptococcal Infections/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus gordonii/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The human microflora is known to be extremely complex, yet most pathogenesis research is conducted in mono-species models of infection. Consequently, it remains unclear whether the level of complexity of a host&amp;#39;s indigenous flora can affect the virulence potential of pathogenic species. Furthermore, it remains unclear whether the colonization by commensal species affects a host cell&amp;#39;s response to pathogenic species beyond the direct physical saturation of surface receptors, the sequestration of nutrients, the modulation of the physico-chemical environment in the oral cavity, or the production of bacteriocins. Using oral epithelial cells as a model, we hypothesized that the virulence of pathogenic species may vary depending on the complexity of the flora that interacts with host cells. RESULTS: This is the first report that determines the global epithelial transcriptional response to co-culture with defined complex microbiota. In our model, human immortalized gingival keratinocytes (HIGK) were infected with mono- and mixed cultures of commensal and pathogenic species. The global transcriptional response of infected cells was validated and confirmed phenotypically. In our model, commensal species were able to modulate the expression of host genes with a broad diversity of physiological functions and antagonize the effect of pathogenic species at the cellular level. Unexpectedly, the inhibitory effect of commensal species was not correlated with its ability to inhibit adhesion or invasion by pathogenic species. CONCLUSION: Studying the global transcriptome of epithelial cells to single and complex microbial challenges offers clues towards a better understanding of how bacteria-bacteria interactions and bacteria-host interactions impact the overall host response. This work provides evidence that the degree of complexity of a mixed microbiota does influence the transcriptional response to infection of host epithelial cells, and challenges the current dogma regarding the potential versus the actual pathogenicity of bacterial species. These findings support the concept that members of the commensal oral flora have evolved cellular mechanisms that directly modulate the host cell&amp;#39;s response to pathogenic species and dampen their relative pathogenicity. </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20091119; GR: DE07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE11111/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE16715/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100965258; OID: NLM: PMC2736203; 2008/11/13 [received]; 2009/08/18 [accepted]; 2009/08/18 [aheadofprint]; epublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2164; 1471-2164</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA. jmans@dental.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19689803; 1471-2164-10-380 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1471-2164-10-380</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20090818</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19689803</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2736203</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1349</id>
<a1>Meka,A.</a1>
<a1>Bakthavatchalu,V.</a1>
<a1>Sathishkumar,S.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Verma,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Wallet,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Bhattacharyya,I.</a1>
<a1>Boyce,B. F.</a1>
<a1>Handfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Lamont,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Ebersole,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Kesavalu,L.</a1>
<t1>Porphyromonas gingivalis infection-induced tissue and bone transcriptional profiles </t1>
<jf>Molecular oral microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Oral Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>61</sp>
<op>74</op>
<ab>Porphyromonas gingivalis has been associated with subgingival biofilms in adult periodontitis. However, the molecular mechanisms of its contribution to chronic gingival inflammation and loss of periodontal structural integrity remain unclear. This investigation aimed to examine changes in the host transcriptional profiles during a P. gingivalis infection using a murine calvarial model of inflammation and bone resorption. P. gingivalis FDC 381 was injected into the subcutaneous soft tissue over the calvaria of BALB/c mice for 3 days, after which the soft tissues and calvarial bones were excised. RNA was isolated from infected soft tissues and calvarial bones and was analysed for transcript profiles using Murine GeneChip((R)) arrays to provide a molecular profile of the events that occur following infection of these tissues. After P. gingivalis infection, 6452 and 2341 probe sets in the infected soft tissues and calvarial bone, respectively, were differentially expressed (P </ab>
<no>id: 2; GR: AR43510/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE015720/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101524770; ppublish </no>
<pp>Denmark</pp>
<sn>2041-1014</sn>
<ad>Department of Periodontology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20331794; OMI555 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; D</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.2041-1014.2009.00555.x</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20331794</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1355</id>
<a1>Moreb,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Chang,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Amaya,M.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Ostmark,B.</a1>
<a1>Chou,W.</a1>
<t1>ALDH isozymes downregulation affects cell growth, cell motility and gene expression in lung cancer cells </t1>
<jf>Molecular cancer</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cancer.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Nov 24</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<sp>87</sp>
<k1>Aldehyde Dehydrogenase/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Human/genetics</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Isoenzymes/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms/enzymology/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Interfering</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Aldehyde dehydrogenase isozymes ALDH1A1 and ALDH3A1 are highly expressed in non small cell lung cancer. Neither the mechanisms nor the biologic significance for such over expression have been studied. METHODS: We have employed oligonucleotide microarrays to analyze changes in gene profiles in A549 lung cancer cell line in which ALDH activity was reduced by up to 95% using lentiviral mediated expression of siRNA against both isozymes (Lenti 1+3). Stringent analysis methods were used to identify gene expression patterns that are specific to the knock down of ALDH activity and significantly different in comparison to wild type A549 cells (WT) or cells similarly transduced with green fluorescent protein (GFP) siRNA. RESULTS: We confirmed significant and specific down regulation of ALDH1A1 and ALDH3A1 in Lenti 1+3 cells and in comparison to 12 other ALDH genes detected. The results of the microarray analysis were validated by real time RT-PCR on RNA obtained from Lenti 1+3 or WT cells treated with ALDH activity inhibitors. Detailed functional analysis was performed on 101 genes that were significantly different (P or = 2 folds in the Lenti 1+3 group versus the control groups. There were 75 down regulated and 26 up regulated genes. Protein binding, organ development, signal transduction, transcription, lipid metabolism, and cell migration and adhesion were among the most affected pathways. CONCLUSION: These molecular effects of the ALDH knock-down are associated with in vitro functional changes in the proliferation and motility of these cells and demonstrate the significance of ALDH enzymes in cell homeostasis with a potentially significant impact on the treatment of lung cancer. </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20091118; JID: 101147698; 0 (Enzyme Inhibitors); 0 (Isoenzymes); 0 (RNA, Small Interfering); EC 1.2.1.3 (ALDH3A1 protein, human); EC 1.2.1.3 (Aldehyde Dehydrogenase); EC 1.2.1.3.- (ALDH1A1 protein, human); OID: NLM: PMC2605459; 2008/06/19 [received]; 2008/11/24 [accepted]; 2008/11/24 [aheadofprint]; epublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1476-4598; 1476-4598</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA. morebjs@medicine.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19025616; 1476-4598-7-87 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1476-4598-7-87</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20081124</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19025616</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2605459</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1415</id>
<a1>Nasoff,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.,2nd</a1>
<a1>Wolf,R. E.,Jr</a1>
<t1>DNA sequence of the Escherichia coli gene, gnd, for 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase </t1>
<jf>Gene</jf>
<jo>Gene</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>264</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Codon</k1>
<k1>Endonucleases/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Single-Strand Specific DNA and RNA Endonucleases</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Expression of gnd of Escherichia coli, which encodes 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase, an enzyme of the hexose monophosphate shunt, is subject to growth rate-dependent regulation and is gene dosage-dependent: the level of the enzyme increases in direct proportion to the cellular growth rate at both low and high gene copy numbers. We have determined the nucleotide sequence of gnd and flanking control regions, the 5&amp;#39;-end of in vivo gnd mRNA, and the start codon of the structural gene. Analysis of the sequence indicated that: (i) the gnd promoter is typical of other E. coli promoters and the structural gene is followed by a rho-independent transcription termination signal; (ii) the 56-nucleotide leader of gnd mRNA does not contain a rho-independent transcription termination signal, so growth rate-dependent regulation of 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase level is not carried out by an attenuation mechanism analogous to the one that controls expression of the E. coli ampC gene; (iii) the codon composition of the structural gene resembles that of other highly expressed E. coli genes and thus is not responsible for the regulation either; (iv) the structural gene is preceded at an optimal distance by a strong Shine-Dalgarno (SD) sequence, AGGAG ; (v) the leader region of the mRNA contains regions of dyad symmetry that have the potential to sequester the SD sequence and the start codon. This latter feature of the gene suggests that growth rate-dependent regulation may involve regulation of translation initiation frequency. </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20081121; GENBANK/K02072; GR: GM27113/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7706761; 0 (Codon); 0 (RNA, Messenger); EC 1.1.1.43 (Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase); EC 3.1.- (Endonucleases); EC 3.1.30.1 (Single-Strand Specific DNA and RNA Endonucleases); ppublish </no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0378-1119; 0378-1119</sn>
<an>PMID: 6329905</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6329905</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1393</id>
<a1>Paddock,H. N.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Varela,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Beierle,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Mozingo,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of gene expression patterns in human postburn hypertrophic scars </t1>
<jf>The Journal of burn care &amp; rehabilitation</jf>
<jo>J.Burn Care Rehabil.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Nov-Dec</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>371</sp>
<op>377</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Biopsy</k1>
<k1>Burns/complications</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cicatrix, Hypertrophic/genetics/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>DNA Probes</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>Hypertrophic scars cause cosmetic disfigurement and limited mobility in burn patients. To better understand the molecular pathophysiology of hypertrophic scar formation, microarray analyses were performed on normal skin and hypertrophic scars from four burn patients. Microarray analyses were determined in an effort to identify genes whose expression discriminated between normal skin and mature, hypertrophic scars. Surgical biopsies were obtained from two pediatric and two adult patients 6 to 15 months after burn injury. Total RNA was isolated from the samples and subjected to microarray analysis using the Affymetrix U95Av2 GeneChip. Results from this analysis revealed 31 probe sets representing genes that were consistently up-regulated at least two-fold in hypertrophic scar specimens from all four patients and four probe sets that were down-regulated. The significance analysis of microarrays algorithm also identified 35 probe sets whose increased expression resulted in the hierarchal clustering of the hypertrophic scar and normal tissue, seven of which were identical to the six genes identified by paired analyses. These six genes all displayed elevated levels of expression in the scar tissue. Proteins encoded by the genes identified included germline oligometric matrix protein, matrix metalloproteinase-16, collagen type 1alpha, pleiotrophin, and thrombospondin-4. Although the results presented here suggest that there may be unique patterns of gene expression in hypertrophic scars that may be important in the evaluation and treatment of hypertrophic scarring, the results must be confirmed with larger datasets. </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20071114; GR: R37-GM-40586-14/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08721-03/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8110188; 0 (DNA Probes); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0273-8481; 0273-8481</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Institute for Wound Research, University of Florida Genetics Institute, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0286, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14610421</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.BCR.0000095508.96754.E0</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14610421</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1397</id>
<a1>Rice,L.</a1>
<a1>Samedi,V. G.</a1>
<a1>Medrano,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Sweeney,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Stenstrom,A.</a1>
<a1>Furman,J.</a1>
<a1>Shiverick,K. T.</a1>
<t1>Mechanisms of the growth inhibitory effects of the isoflavonoid biochanin A on LNCaP cells and xenografts </t1>
<jf>The Prostate</jf>
<jo>Prostate</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Aug 1</fd>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>212</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anticarcinogenic Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cell Cycle Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Division/drug effects</k1>
<k1>DNA, Complementary/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genistein/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Nude</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Transplantation</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Prostatic Neoplasms/genetics/metabolism/pathology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Transplantation, Heterologous</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Isoflavones inhibit the growth of some types of tumor cells, including prostate adenocarcinoma. This study used LNCaP cells and xenografts to investigate the mechanisms of the antiproliferative effects of biochanin A, a major isoflavone present in red clover but not soy-derived products. METHODS: LNCaP cells were exposed to varying doses of biochanin A to evaluate viability, DNA synthesis, and DNA fragmentation (TUNEL) analysis. Regulation of gene expression was determined by using Western immunoblotting and cDNA microarrays. Anti-tumorigenic effects were evaluated by using athymic mice with LNCaP flank tumors. RESULTS: Biochanin A induced a dose-dependent inhibition of proliferation and [(3)H]thymidine incorporation that correlated with increased DNA fragmentation, indicative of apoptosis. Western blot analyses of cell cycle regulatory proteins revealed that biochanin A significantly decreased expression of cyclin B and p21, whereas flow cytometry showed that cells were accumulating in the G(0)/G(1) phase. cDNA microarray analyses identified 29 down-regulated genes with six reduced below assay detection limits. Eleven genes were up-regulated, including 9 that were undetectable in controls. In mice with LNCaP xenografts, biochanin A significantly reduced tumor size and incidence. CONCLUSION: These results indicate that biochanin A inhibits prostate cancer cell growth through induction of cell cycle arrest and apoptosis. Biochanin A-regulated genes suggest multiple pathways of action. Biochanin A inhibits the incidence and growth of LNCaP xenograft tumors in athymic mice. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20071114; CI: Copyright 2002; GR: CA099126-25/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: P42 ES07375/ES/NIEHS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8101368; 0 (Anticarcinogenic Agents); 0 (Cell Cycle Proteins); 0 (DNA, Complementary); 446-72-0 (Genistein); 491-80-5 (biochanin A); ppublish </no>
<pb>Wiley-Liss, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0270-4137; 0270-4137</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Division of Urology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12111696</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/pros.10100</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12111696</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1363</id>
<a1>Rock,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Harfe,B. D.</a1>
<t1>Identification of genes expressed in the mouse limb using a novel ZPA microarray approach </t1>
<jf>Gene expression patterns : GEP</jf>
<jo>Gene Expr.Patterns</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>19</sp>
<op>26</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Intercellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factor AP-2/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics</k1>
<ab>One well-studied signaling center in the developing vertebrate limb, the zone of polarizing activity (ZPA), produces the morphogen sonic hedgehog that is necessary for normal growth and pattern formation. To identify additional factors expressed in the ZPA of the mouse limb bud, the Shhgfpcre allele was used to purify ZPA cells using fluorescence-activated cell sorting. Microarray technology was then used to identify genes whose expression was elevated in the ZPA compared to the rest of the limb. In situ hybridization confirmed the expression of two known transcription factors, Hlxb9 and Tcfap2b, an uncharacterized EST, and a transmembrane protein of unknown function in domains overlapping the ZPA. The expression of two other genes was confirmed by rtPCR. The methods described in this report will be applicable for identifying genes enriched in Shh-expressing cells throughout development. </ab>
<no>id: 6; JID: 101167473; 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); 0 (Intercellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins); 0 (SHH protein, human); 0 (Tcfap2b protein, mouse); 0 (Transcription Factor AP-2); 0 (Transcription Factors); 140115-73-7 (Hb9 protein, mouse); 2007/07/05 [received]; 2007/08/22 [revised]; 2007/08/24 [accepted]; 2007/09/02 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>1567-133X; 1567-133X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Cancer and Genetics Research Complex, 1376 Mowry Road, Gainesville, FL 32610, United States.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17911046; S1567-133X(07)00089-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.modgep.2007.08.004</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20070902</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17911046</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1359</id>
<a1>Russom,A.</a1>
<a1>Sethu,P.</a1>
<a1>Irimia,D.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Calvano,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Garcia,I.</a1>
<a1>Finnerty,C.</a1>
<a1>Tannahill,C.</a1>
<a1>Abouhamze,A.</a1>
<a1>Wilhelmy,J.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Herndon,D. N.</a1>
<a1>Lowry,S. F.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R. G.</a1>
<a1>Toner,M.</a1>
<a1>Inflammation and Host Response to Injury Large Scale Collaborative Research Program</a1>
<t1>Microfluidic leukocyte isolation for gene expression analysis in critically ill hospitalized patients </t1>
<jf>Clinical chemistry</jf>
<jo>Clin.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>891</sp>
<op>900</op>
<k1>Burns/pathology</k1>
<k1>Cell Separation</k1>
<k1>Critical Illness</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Hospitalization</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/chemistry/cytology</k1>
<k1>Microfluidic Analytical Techniques</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Wounds, Nonpenetrating/pathology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Microarray technology is becoming a powerful tool for diagnostic, therapeutic, and prognostic applications. There is at present no consensus regarding the optimal technique to isolate nucleic acids from blood leukocyte populations for subsequent expression analyses. Current collection and processing techniques pose significant challenges in the clinical setting. Here, we report the clinical validation of a novel microfluidic leukocyte nucleic acid isolation technique for gene expression analysis from critically ill, hospitalized patients that can be readily used on small volumes of blood. METHODS: We processed whole blood from hospitalized patients after burn injury and severe blunt trauma according to the microfluidic and standard macroscale leukocyte isolation protocol. Side-by-side comparison of RNA quantity, quality, and genome-wide expression patterns was used to clinically validate the microfluidic technique. RESULTS: When the microfluidic protocol was used for processing, sufficient amounts of total RNA were obtained for genome-wide expression analysis from 0.5 mL whole blood. We found that the leukocyte expression patterns from samples processed using the 2 protocols were concordant, and there was less variability introduced as a result of harvesting method than there existed between individuals. CONCLUSIONS: The novel microfluidic approach achieves leukocyte isolation in </ab>
<no>id: 2; GR: P41 EB 002503/EB/NIBIB NIH HHS/United States; GR: U54 GM 062119/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9421549; 63231-63-0 (RNA); 2008/03/28 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0009-9147; 0009-9147</sn>
<ad>Surgical Services and Center for Engineering in Medicine, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School and Shriners Hospital for Children, Boston, MA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18375483; clinchem.2007.099150 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Multicenter Study; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1373/clinchem.2007.099150</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20080328</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18375483</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1366</id>
<a1>Samols,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Skalsky,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Maldonado,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Riva,A.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Renne,R.</a1>
<t1>Identification of cellular genes targeted by KSHV-encoded microRNAs </t1>
<jf>PLoS pathogens</jf>
<jo>PLoS Pathog.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May 11</fd>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>e65</sp>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 8, Human/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kidney/metabolism</k1>
<k1>MicroRNAs/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Sarcoma, Kaposi/genetics/virology</k1>
<k1>Thrombospondin 1/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transforming Growth Factor beta/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are 19 to 23 nucleotide-long RNAs that post-transcriptionally regulate gene expression. Human cells express several hundred miRNAs which regulate important biological pathways such as development, proliferation, and apoptosis. Recently, 12 miRNA genes have been identified within the genome of Kaposi sarcoma-associated herpesvirus; however, their functions are still unknown. To identify host cellular genes that may be targeted by these novel viral regulators, we performed gene expression profiling in cells stably expressing KSHV-encoded miRNAs. Data analysis revealed a set of 81 genes whose expression was significantly changed in the presence of miRNAs. While the majority of changes were below 2-fold, eight genes were down-regulated between 4- and 20-fold. We confirmed miRNA-dependent regulation for three of these genes and found that protein levels of thrombospondin 1 (THBS1) were decreased &amp;gt;10-fold. THBS1 has previously been reported to be down-regulated in Kaposi sarcoma lesions and has known activity as a strong tumor suppressor and anti-angiogenic factor, exerting its anti-angiogenic effect in part by activating the latent form of TGF-beta. We show that reduced THBS1 expression in the presence of viral miRNAs translates into decreased TGF-beta activity. These data suggest that KSHV-encoded miRNAs may contribute directly to pathogenesis by down-regulation of THBS1, a major regulator of cell adhesion, migration, and angiogenesis. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20100429; GENBANK/AY973824; GEO/GSE7554; GR: 5T32CA009126-30/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM07250/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101238921; 0 (MicroRNAs); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Thrombospondin 1); 0 (Transforming Growth Factor beta); OID: NLM: PMC1876501; 2006/12/14 [received]; 2007/03/20 [accepted]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1553-7374; 1553-7366</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17500590; 06-PLPA-RA-0547R2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1371/journal.ppat.0030065</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17500590</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1876501</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1400</id>
<a1>Sato,T.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Sugioka,S.</a1>
<a1>Jigami,Y.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Uemura,H.</a1>
<t1>The E-box DNA binding protein Sgc1p suppresses the gcr2 mutation, which is involved in transcriptional activation of glycolytic genes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae </t1>
<jf>FEBS letters</jf>
<jo>FEBS Lett.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec 17</fd>
<vo>463</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>307</sp>
<op>311</op>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Suppressor</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation</k1>
<ab>Glycolytic gene expression is mediated by the Gcr1p-Gcr2p transcriptional activation complex. A screen for multicopy suppressors of gcr2 yielded SGC1. SGC1&amp;#39;s suppression activity was specific to gcr2, it did not extend to gcr1. Disruption of SGC1 moderately affected glycolytic enzyme activities, although no growth defect was evident. Sgc1p exhibits a bHLH motif which is characteristic of E-box DNA-binding proteins. DNA footprinting experiments demonstrated Sgc1p&amp;#39;s ability to bind at an E-box. However, its binding specificity was less than 10-fold, which is also characteristic of E-box binding proteins. LexA fusion experiments demonstrated that Sgc1p has weak intrinsic activating activity independent of GCR1 and GCR2. We propose that Sgc1p binds at E-boxes of glycolytic genes and contributes to their activation. </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20090518; JID: 0155157; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR2 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (TYE7 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Transcription Factors); ppublish </no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0014-5793; 0014-5793</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Biology, National Institute of Bioscience and Human-Technology, Tsukuba Research Center (MITI), Higashi 1-1, Tsukuba, Ibaraki, Japan.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10606743; S0014-5793(99)01654-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10606743</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1418</id>
<a1>Schultz,E. W.</a1>
<a1>Hall,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Repair of the Liver following the Injection of Chloroform into the Portal System </t1>
<jf>The Journal of medical research</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Res.</jo>
<yr>1923</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>207</sp>
<op>230.11</op>
<no>id: 1; JID: 17920120R; ppublish </no>
<sn>0097-3599</sn>
<an>PMID: 19972596</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19972596</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2041760</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1412</id>
<a1>Scott,E. W.</a1>
<a1>Allison,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of TPI gene expression in isogeneic wild-type and gcr1-deletion mutant strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae </t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Dec 11</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>7099</sp>
<op>7107</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding, Competitive</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Deletion</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Triose-Phosphate Isomerase/genetics</k1>
<ab>In Saccharomyces cerevisiae the enzymes of glycolysis constitute 30-60 percent of the soluble protein. GCR1 gene function is required for high level glycolytic gene expression. We have undertaken a biochemical and genetic characterization of TPI, a gene affected by gcr1 lesions. Northern analysis showed that steady-state levels of TPI transcripts are severely reduced in gcr1 mutant strains. However, primer extension experiments revealed that TPI transcripts isolated from wild-type and gcr1 mutant strains have identical 5&amp;#39; ends. To map the 5&amp;#39; boundary of TPI controlling region, we employed a TPI::lacZ gene fusion carrying 3.5 kb 5&amp;#39; to the translational start of the TPI structural gene. Nuclease Bal31 deletion analysis demonstrated that sequences sufficient for high level expression of TPI reside within 392 nucleotides preceding the start of the structural gene. We have identified GRF1/RAPI/TUF-binding site positioned 339 to 349 bp 5&amp;#39; to the translation start of TPI. DNA band shift assays were carried out with wild-type and gcr1 deletion mutant strains, and similar patterns of band shifting were observed. </ab>
<no>id: 5; LR: 20091118; GR: GM-41330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; EC 5.3.1.1 (Triose-Phosphate Isomerase); OID: NLM: PMC332775; ppublish </no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, JHMHC, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2263469</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2263469</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC332775</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1409</id>
<a1>Scott,E. W.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Concerted action of the transcriptional activators REB1, RAP1, and GCR1 in the high-level expression of the glycolytic gene TPI </t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>543</sp>
<op>550</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Regulatory Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation</k1>
<k1>Triose-Phosphate Isomerase/genetics</k1>
<ab>In Saccharomyces cerevisiae, the TPI gene product, triosephosphate isomerase, makes up about 2% of the soluble cellular protein. Using in vitro and in vivo footprinting techniques, we have identified four binding sites for three factors in the 5&amp;#39; noncoding region of TPI: a REB1-binding site located at positions -401 to -392, two GCR1-binding sites located at positions -381 to -366 and -341 to -326, and a RAP1-binding site located at positions -358 to -346. We tested the effects of mutations at each of these binding sites on the expression of a TPI::lacZ gene fusion which carried 853 bp of the TPI 5&amp;#39; noncoding region integrated at the URA3 locus. The REB1-binding site is dispensable when material 5&amp;#39; to it is deleted; however, if the sequence 5&amp;#39; to the REB1-binding site is from the TPI locus, expression is reduced fivefold when the site is mutated. Because REB1 blocks nucleosome formation, the most likely function of its binding site in the TPI controlling region is to prevent the formation of nucleosomes over the TPI upstream activation sequence. Mutations in the RAP1-binding site resulted in a 10-fold reduction in expression of the reporter gene. Mutating either GCR1-binding site alone had a modest effect on expression of the fusion. However, mutating both GCR1-binding sites resulted in a 68-fold reduction in the level of expression of the reporter gene. A LexA-GCR1 fusion protein containing the DNA-binding domain of LexA fused to the amino terminus of GCR1 was able to activate expression of a lex operator::GAL1::lacZ reporter gene 116-fold over background levels. From this experiment, we conclude that GCR1 is able to activate gene expression in the absence of REB1 or RAP1 bound at adjacent binding sites. On the basis of these results, we suggest that GCR1 binding is required for activation of TPI and other GCR1-dependent genes and that the primary role of other factors which bind adjacent to GCR1-binding sites is to facilitate of modulate GCR1 binding in vivo. </ab>
<no>id: 2; LR: 20091118; GR: GM-41330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI-07113/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8109087; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); EC 5.3.1.1 (Triose-Phosphate Isomerase); OID: NLM: PMC358933; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8417350</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8417350</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC358933</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1350</id>
<a1>Shan,J.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Kilberg,M. S.</a1>
<t1>Expression profiling after activation of the amino acid deprivation response in HepG2 human hepatoma cells </t1>
<jf>Physiological genomics</jf>
<jo>Physiol.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar 9</fd>
<ab>Dietary protein malnutrition is manifested as amino acid deprivation of individual cells, which activates an amino acid response (AAR) that alters cellular functions, in part, by regulating transcriptional and post-transcriptional mechanisms. The AAR was activated in HepG2 human hepatoma cells and the changes in mRNA content were analyzed by microarray expression profiling. The results documented that 1507 known genes were differentially regulated by p </ab>
<no>id: 3; JID: 9815683; aheadofprint </no>
<sn>1531-2267; 1094-8341</sn>
<ad>University of Florida College of Medicine.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20215415; 00217.2009 [pii]</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1152/physiolgenomics.00217.2009</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20100309</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20215415</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2869104</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1364</id>
<a1>Skalsky,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Samols,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Plaisance,K. B.</a1>
<a1>Boss,I. W.</a1>
<a1>Riva,A.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Renne,R.</a1>
<t1>Kaposi&amp;#39;s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus encodes an ortholog of miR-155 </t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>12836</sp>
<op>12845</op>
<k1>3&#39; Untranslated Regions/genetics</k1>
<k1>Basic-Leucine Zipper Transcription Factors/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor/chemistry/virology</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Fanconi Anemia Complementation Group Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 8, Human/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Luciferases/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>MicroRNAs/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<ab>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small noncoding RNAs that posttranscriptionally regulate gene expression by binding to 3&amp;#39;-untranslated regions (3&amp;#39;UTRs) of target mRNAs. Kaposi&amp;#39;s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV), a virus linked to malignancies including primary effusion lymphoma (PEL), encodes 12 miRNA genes, but only a few regulatory targets are known. We found that KSHV-miR-K12-11 shares 100% seed sequence homology with hsa-miR-155, an miRNA frequently found to be up-regulated in lymphomas and critically important for B-cell development. Based on this seed sequence homology, we hypothesized that both miRNAs regulate a common set of target genes and, as a result, could have similar biological activities. Examination of five PEL lines showed that PELs do not express miR-155 but do express high levels of miR-K12-11. Bioinformatic tools predicted the transcriptional repressor BACH-1 to be targeted by both miRNAs, and ectopic expression of either miR-155 or miR-K12-11 inhibited a BACH-1 3&amp;#39;UTR-containing reporter. Furthermore, BACH-1 protein levels are low in cells expressing either miRNA. Gene expression profiling of miRNA-expressing stable cell lines revealed 66 genes that were commonly down-regulated. For select genes, miRNA targeting was confirmed by reporter assays. Thus, based on our in silico predictions, reporter assays, and expression profiling data, miR-K12-11 and miR-155 regulate a common set of cellular targets. Given the role of miR-155 during B-cell maturation, we speculate that miR-K12-11 may contribute to the distinct developmental phenotype of PEL cells, which are blocked in a late stage of B-cell development. Together, these findings indicate that KSHV miR-K12-11 is an ortholog of miR-155. </ab>
<no>id: 7; LR: 20091118; GR: 5T32CA009126-30/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM07250/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (3&amp;#39; Untranslated Regions); 0 (BACH1 protein, human); 0 (Basic-Leucine Zipper Transcription Factors); 0 (Fanconi Anemia Complementation Group Proteins); 0 (MIRN155 microRNA, human); 0 (MicroRNAs); 0 (RNA, Viral); EC 1.13.12.- (Luciferases); OID: NLM: PMC2169101; 2007/09/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5514; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, and Shands Cancer Center, 1376 Mowry Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-3633, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17881434; JVI.01804-07 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.01804-07</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20070919</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17881434</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2169101</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1407</id>
<a1>Stanway,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Gibbs,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Kearsey,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>The yeast co-activator GAL11 positively influences transcription of the phosphoglycerate kinase gene, but only when RAP1 is bound to its upstream activation sequence </t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>243</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>207</sp>
<op>214</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>GTP-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Mediator Complex</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phosphoglycerate Kinase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA/methods</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Zinc Fingers/genetics</k1>
<k1>rap GTP-Binding Proteins</k1>
<ab>Transcription of the yeast phosphoglycerate kinase gene (PGK) is activated by an array of nuclear factors including the multifunctional protein RAP1. We have demonstrated that the transcriptional co-activator GAL11, which was identified as an auxiliary factor to GAL4 and which is believed to interact with the zinc finger of the trans-activator, positively influences the level of PGK transcription on both fermentable and non-fermentable carbon sources. This positive effect is only observed when the RAP1 site in the upstream activation sequence (UAS) is present, implying that GAL11 acts through RAP1. Expression of the RAP1 gene is not reduced in the gal11 background, and in vivo footprinting shows that GAL11 does not influence RAP1 DNA-binding activity. Therefore the effect of GAL11 on PGK transcription must be mediated at the PGK UAS, presumably as part of the activation complex. It has been proposed that RAP1 may act as a facilitator of GCR1 binding at the PGK UAS and therefore it is conceivable that the target for GAL11 may in fact be GCR1. A further implication of this study is that GAL11 can interact with proteins such as RAP1 or GCR1 that are apparently structurally dissimilar from GAL4 and other zinc finger DNA-binding proteins. </ab>
<no>id: 10; LR: 20091119; GR: GM-41330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0125036; 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GAL11 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Mediator Complex); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Transcription Factors); EC 2.7.2.3 (Phosphoglycerate Kinase); EC 3.6.1.- (GTP-Binding Proteins); EC 3.6.5.2 (rap GTP-Binding Proteins); ppublish </no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<ad>Department of Plant Sciences, University of Oxford, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8177217</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8177217</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1379</id>
<a1>Tsujimoto,H.</a1>
<a1>Uchida,T.</a1>
<a1>Efron,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Scumpia,P. O.</a1>
<a1>Verma,A.</a1>
<a1>Matsumoto,T.</a1>
<a1>Tschoeke,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Ungaro,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Ono,S.</a1>
<a1>Seki,S.</a1>
<a1>Clare-Salzler,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Mochizuki,H.</a1>
<a1>Ramphal,R.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Flagellin enhances NK cell proliferation and activation directly and through dendritic cell-NK cell interactions </t1>
<jf>Journal of leukocyte biology</jf>
<jo>J.Leukoc.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>888</sp>
<op>897</op>
<k1>3T3 Cells</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>CD4-Positive T-Lymphocytes/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Communication/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Count</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Dendritic Cells/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Interferon-gamma/biosynthesis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Killer Cells, Natural/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Lymphocyte Activation/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Lymphocyte Subsets/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C3H</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<ab>Flagellin, the principal component of bacterial flagella, is a ligand for Toll-like receptor 5 (TLR5) or TLR11 and contributes to systemic inflammation during sepsis through activation of dendritic cells (DCs) and other cells of the innate immune system. Here, we report that flagellin and the TLR4 ligand, lipopolysaccharide (LPS), induced phenotypic and functional maturation of murine bone marrow-derived DCs and enhanced DC accumulation in the draining popliteal lymph node following their footpad injection. It is interesting that flagellin injection enhanced myeloid (CD8alpha(-1)) and plasmacytoid (plasmacytoid DC antigen(+) B220(+)) DC subsets, whereas LPS only increased myeloid DCs in the draining lymph node. In addition, the footpad injection of flagellin or LPS induced significant CD4(+) T cell activation in the draining popliteal lymph node, as judged by increased CD69 or CD25 expression. We illustrate, for the first time, that flagellin also increases natural killer (NK) cell number and activation status in the draining lymph node after footpad injection. Using coculture with enriched carboxy-fluorescein diacetate succinimidyl ester-labeled NK cells, flagellin-treated DCs induce significant NK cell proliferation and activation. In fact, direct treatment of NK cells with flagellin induces a greater increase in cell proliferation than treatment with LPS. In contrast, flagellin treatment of NK cells was not a strong inducer of interferon-gamma (IFN-gamma) production, indicating that NK cell proliferation and IFN-gamma production may be regulated differentially. These data suggest that flagellin is a capable maturation agent for murine myeloid-derived DCs, and flagellin-activated DCs and flagellin itself are potent inducers of NK cell proliferation. </ab>
<no>id: 2; LR: 20081121; GR: R01 GM-63041/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37 GM-40586/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08721/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8405628; 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); 82115-62-6 (Interferon-gamma); 2005/07/20 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0741-5400; 0741-5400</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0286, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16033815; jlb.0105051 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1189/jlb.0105051</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20050720</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16033815</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1403</id>
<a1>Tumer,N.</a1>
<a1>Scarpace,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Larochelle,J. S.</a1>
<t1>AP-1 transcription factor binding activity in rat adrenal medulla and hypothalamus with age and cold exposure </t1>
<jf>Neuropharmacology</jf>
<jo>Neuropharmacology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1065</sp>
<op>1069</op>
<k1>Adrenal Medulla/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Aging/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cold Temperature</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hypothalamus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred F344</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factor AP-1/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The AP-1 regulatory element has been implicated in the cold-induced expression of tyrosine hydroxylase in the adrenal medulla. Since in this tissue, the cold-induced increase in tyrosine hydroxylase expression is impaired with age and in other tissues, there is some evidence that AP-1 transcription factor binding is diminished with age, we examined the cold-stimulated AP-1 transcription factor binding to an oligonucleotide with the consensus sequence of the AP-1 response element in nuclear extracts from adrenal medulla and hypothalamus of young and senescent rats. AP-1 transcription factor binding activity diminished by 38% with age in unstimulated adrenal medulla. Following cold stimulation, the AP-1 binding activity increased by 21-25% in the adrenal medulla of both young and senescent rats. However, the level of AP-1 binding in cold-stimulated senescent rats was still less than in cold-stimulated younger rats. There were no changes in AP-3 binding activity with either age or cold exposure in the adrenal medulla. Similarly, in the hypothalamus, there was a 25% decrease with age and a 25% increase following cold stimulation in the level of AP-1 binding. There was a 62% age-related increase in AP-3 binding activity but no change with cold exposure. These data indicate that there is reduced AP-1 binding activity in senescent control rats. Moreover, the demonstration that cold stimulus evokes similar increases in AP-1 binding activity in both young and old rats suggests that the stimulation pathway that increases AP-1 transcription factor is maintained in the senescent animal. </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20081121; JID: 0236217; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factor AP-1); ppublish </no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-3908; 0028-3908</sn>
<ad>Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, Department of Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Gainesville, Florida 32608-1197, U.S.A.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9294971; S0028390897000932 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9294971</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1396</id>
<a1>Turkel,S.</a1>
<a1>Turgut,T.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Uemura,H.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>Mutations in GCR1 affect SUC2 gene expression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae </t1>
<jf>Molecular genetics and genomics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Genet.Genomics</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>268</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>825</sp>
<op>831</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Fungal/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Glucose/metabolism/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Glycoside Hydrolases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Lac Operon</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/drug effects/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<k1>beta-Fructofuranosidase</k1>
<ab>Transcription of SUC2, the gene that encodes the cytoplasmic and secreted forms of the enzyme invertase, is controlled by glucose repression and derepression mechanisms in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Several regulatory factors such as the Mig1p-Tup1p-Ssn6p repressor complex and the Snf1p kinase complex have been identified previously as regulators of SUC2 expression. We show that, in addition to these factors, expression of SUC2 is affected by mutations in the gene GCR1 that encodes the glycolysis regulatory protein Gcr1p. Expression of Suc2-LacZ was not repressed by glucose in gcr1 mutant yeast cells exposed to glucose. Furthermore, secreted invertase activity was constitutively expressed under glucose-repressed and derepressed conditions in gcr1 mutants. DNA gel mobility shift assays and in-vitro DNase I protection experiments mapped a DNA binding site for Gcr1p in the transcriptional control region of the SUC2 gene, next to a previously mapped Mig1p binding site. However, the mechanism by which gcr1 mutations relieve glucose repression remains obscure. </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20091119; JID: 101093320; 0 (DNA, Fungal); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); 50-99-7 (Glucose); EC 3.2.1.- (Glycoside Hydrolases); EC 3.2.1.26 (beta-Fructofuranosidase); 2002/10/07 [received]; 2002/12/13 [accepted]; 2003/02/25 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>1617-4615; 1617-4623</sn>
<ad>Department of Biology, Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Uludag University, 16059 Bursa, Turkey.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12655409</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00438-003-0808-4</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20030225</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12655409</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1402</id>
<a1>Uemura,H.</a1>
<a1>Koshio,M.</a1>
<a1>Inoue,Y.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<t1>The role of Gcr1p in the transcriptional activation of glycolytic genes in yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae </t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>147</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>521</sp>
<op>532</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>DNA, Recombinant</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Glycolysis</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation</k1>
<ab>To study the interdependence of Gcr1p and Rap1p, we prepared a series of synthetic regulatory sequences that contained various numbers and combinations of CT-boxes (Gcr1p-binding sites) and RPG-boxes (Rap1p-binding sites). The ability of the synthetic oligonucleotides to function as regulatory sequences was tested using an ENO1-lacZ reporter gene. As observed previously, synthetic oligonucleotides containing both CT- and RPG-boxes conferred strong UAS activity. Likewise, a lone CT-box did not show any UAS activity. By contrast, oligonucleotides containing tandem Ct-boxes but no RPG-box conferred strong promoter activity. This UAS activity was not dependent on position or orientation of the oligonucleotides in the 5&amp;#39; noncoding region. However, it was dependent on both GCR1 and GCR2. These results suggest that the ability of Gcr1p to bind Gcr1p-binding sites in vivo is not absolutely dependent on Rap1p. Eleven independent mutants of GCR1 were isolated that conferred weak UAS activity to a single CT-box. Five mutants has single mutations in Gcr1p&amp;#39;s DNA-binding domain and displayed slightly higher affinity for the CT-box. These results support the hypothesis that Gcr1p and Gcr2p play the central role in glycolytic gene expression and that the function of Rap1p is to facilitate the binding of Gcr1p to its target. </ab>
<no>id: 5; LR: 20091119; JID: 0374636; 0 (DNA, Recombinant); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 0 (GCR1 protein, S cerevisiae); 0 (Saccharomyces cerevisiae Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); OID: NLM: PMC1208175; ppublish </no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0016-6731; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Biology, National Institute of Bioscience and Human-Technology, Tsukuba Research Center, Ibaraki, Japan. uemura@nibh.go.jp</ad>
<an>PMID: 9335590</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9335590</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1208175</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1398</id>
<a1>Varela,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Goldstein,M. H.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Microarray analysis of gene expression patterns during healing of rat corneas after excimer laser photorefractive keratectomy </t1>
<jf>Investigative ophthalmology &amp; visual science</jf>
<jo>Invest.Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1772</sp>
<op>1782</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cornea/metabolism/surgery</k1>
<k1>DNA, Complementary/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Eye Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Lasers, Excimer</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Photorefractive Keratectomy</k1>
<k1>RNA/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Wound Healing/genetics</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To characterize changes over time in the genomic expression profile of rat corneas after excimer laser photorefractive keratectomy (PRK), in an effort to better understand the cellular response to injury and the dynamic changes that occur in gene expression patterns as a wound heals. METHODS: The corneal gene expression profile of 1176 genes at 3 and 7 days after PRK was determined and compared with untreated corneal gene expression patterns by interrogating commercially available cDNA arrays with labeled target cDNA prepared from pooled total RNA harvested from the respective treatment group of adult male rats. The gene expression patterns were inferred based on the hybridization intensities of the probes on the cDNA arrays. The hybridization signals were globally normalized and filtered. The data were analyzed by using hierarchical and k-means clustering algorithms before and after normalization of variances. RESULTS: Of the 1176 cDNA elements on the array, 588 consistently produced similar results in replicate experiments and comprised the data set analyzed in this work. In total, 73 genes were identified, with expression levels that differed by at least threefold at either 3 or 7 days after PRK. At 3 days after PRK, 70 genes were identified with expression levels that differed by more than threefold, compared with the expression level in untreated animals. The expression of 42 genes increased by threefold or more, whereas expression of 28 genes decreased by threefold or more. By day 7 after PRK, the number of genes displaying more than a threefold difference in expression pattern was reduced to 27 genes, 20 of which showed elevated levels, whereas 7 exhibited decreased levels. Hierarchical clustering of the 588 studied genes produced 10 clusters with correlation coefficients of 0.9 or greater. To determine whether any of the clusters were overrepresented by genes with related functions, the cumulative hypergeometric probability was calculated by obtaining the observed number of functionally related genes within each of the 10 clusters. Seven of the clusters were statistically overrepresented by one or more categories of functionally related genes, such as cell cycle regulators, transcription factors, and metabolic pathway genes. Clustering analysis of 56 genes generally considered to influence corneal wound healing produced 10 gene clusters with correlation coefficients of at least 0.9. Expression of 23 of these 56 genes increased at day 3, then decreased at day 7 to levels similar to those on day 0. These included several growth factors (VEGF, FGF, IGF-I), proteases (PAI-1, PAI-2A) and protease inhibitors (TIMP-2 and TIMP-3). Expression of nine genes increased on both days 3 and 7 compared with expression on day 0 (e.g., TGFB1, TGFBIIR, M6P/IGFR-2), and no genes decreased on both days 3 and 7, compared with day 0. CONCLUSIONS: Microarray analysis of 1176 identified 588 genes with reproducible patterns of expression in rat corneas on days 3 and 7 after PRK and 73 genes with a threefold change in expression compared with untreated corneas. Hierarchical clustering of these 588 genes identified 10 clusters of genes with very similar patterns of expression. Clustering of genes with similar patterns of expression implies a common regulatory pathway for the genes within a cluster, and identifies potential new targets for regulating corneal wound healing. </ab>
<no>id: 1; LR: 20081121; GR: EY05587/EY/NEI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703701; 0 (DNA, Complementary); 0 (Eye Proteins); 63231-63-0 (RNA); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0146-0404; 0146-0404</sn>
<ad>Institute for Wound Research and Department of Ophthalmology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0294, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12036978</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12036978</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1389</id>
<a1>Velardo,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Burger,C.</a1>
<a1>Williams,P. R.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Mareci,T. H.</a1>
<a1>White,T. E.</a1>
<a1>Muzyczka,N.</a1>
<a1>Reier,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Patterns of gene expression reveal a temporally orchestrated wound healing response in the injured spinal cord </t1>
<jf>The Journal of neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</jf>
<jo>J.Neurosci.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep 29</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>39</is>
<sp>8562</sp>
<op>8576</op>
<k1>Algorithms</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Hypoxia/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Nude</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Skin/injuries</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord Injuries/immunology/metabolism/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocytes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Wound Healing/genetics/immunology/physiology</k1>
<ab>Spinal cord injury (SCI) induces a progressive pathophysiology affecting cell survival and neurological integrity via complex and evolving molecular cascades whose interrelationships are not fully understood. The present experiments were designed to: (1) determine potential functional interactions within transcriptional expression profiles obtained after a clinically relevant SCI and (2) test the consistency of transcript expression after SCI in two genetically and immunologically diverse rat strains characterized by differences in T cell competence and associated inflammatory responses. By interrogating Affymetrix U34A rat genome GeneChip microarrays, we defined the transcriptional expression patterns in midcervical contusion lesion sites between 1 and 90 d postinjury of athymic nude (AN) and Sprague Dawley (SD) strains. Stringent statistical analyses detected significant changes in 3638 probe sets, with 80 genes differing between the AN and SD groups. Subsequent detailed functional categorization of these transcripts unveiled an overall tissue remodeling response that was common to both strains. The functionally organized gene profiles were temporally distinct and correlated with repair indices observed microscopically and by magnetic resonance microimaging. Our molecular and anatomical observations have identified a novel, longitudinal perspective of the post-SCI response, namely, that of a highly orchestrated tissue repair and remodeling repertoire with a prominent cutaneous wound healing signature that is conserved between two widely differing rat strains. These results have significant bearing on the continuing development of cellular and pharmacological therapeutics directed at tissue rescue and neuronal regeneration in the injured spinal cord. </ab>
<no>id: 2; LR: 20071114; GR: P01-NS36302/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: P41 RR16105/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS42075/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8102140; 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1529-2401; 0270-6474</sn>
<ad>Department of Neuroscience, McKnight Brain Institute of the University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0244, USA. velardo@mbi.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15456830; 24/39/8562 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3316-04.2004</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15456830</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1390</id>
<a1>Virella-Lowell,I.</a1>
<a1>Herlihy,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Liu,B.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,C.</a1>
<a1>Cruz,P.</a1>
<a1>Muller,C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Flotte,T. R.</a1>
<t1>Effects of CFTR, interleukin-10, and Pseudomonas aeruginosa on gene expression profiles in a CF bronchial epithelial cell Line </t1>
<jf>Molecular therapy : the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</jf>
<jo>Mol.Ther.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>562</sp>
<op>573</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bronchi/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cystic Fibrosis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-10/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</k1>
<k1>Respiratory Mucosa/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>Mutations in CFTR lead to a complex phenotype that includes increased susceptibility to Pseudomonas infections, a functional deficiency of IL-10, and an exaggerated proinflammatory cytokine response. We examined the effects of CFTR gene correction on the gene expression profile of a CF bronchial epithelial cell line (IB3-1) and determined which CF-related gene expression changes could be reversed by IL-10 expression. We performed microarray experiments to monitor the gene expression profile of three cell lines over a time course of exposure to Pseudomonas. At baseline, we identified 843 genes with statistically different levels of expression in CFTR-corrected (S9) cells compared to the IB3-1 line or the IL-10-expressing line. K-means clustering and functional group analysis revealed a primary up-regulation of ubiquitination enzymes and TNF pathway components and a primary down-regulation of protease inhibitors and protein glycosylation enzymes in CF. Key gene expression changes were confirmed by real-time RT-PCR. Massive reprogramming of gene expression occurred 3 h after Pseudomonas exposure. Changes specific to CF included exaggerated activation of cytokines, blunted activation of anti-proteases, and repression of protein glycosylation enzymes. In conclusion, the CFTR genotype changes the expression of multiple genes at baseline and in response to bacterial challenge, and only a subset of these changes is secondary to IL-10 deficiency. </ab>
<no>id: 3; LR: 20071114; GR: HL51811/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: HL67260/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100890581; 126880-72-6 (Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator); 130068-27-8 (Interleukin-10); 2003/09/30 [received]; 2004/06/05 [accepted]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-0016; 1525-0016</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston, SC 29401, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15336656; S1525001604005027 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ymthe.2004.06.215</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15336656</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1373</id>
<a1>Wen,Z. T.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Influence of BrpA on critical virulence attributes of Streptococcus mutans </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>188</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>2983</sp>
<op>2992</op>
<k1>Acids/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/analysis/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Durapatite</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Gel, Two-Dimensional</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Confocal</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Oxidative Stress</k1>
<k1>Proteome/analysis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus mutans/drug effects/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>Streptococcus mutans, the primary etiological agent of human dental caries, has developed multiple mechanisms to colonize and form biofilms on the tooth surface. The brpA gene codes for a predicted surface-associated protein with apparent roles in biofilm formation, autolysis, and cell division. In this study, we used two models to further characterize the biofilm-forming characteristics of a BrpA-deficient mutant, strain TW14. Compared to those of the parent strain, UA159, TW14 formed long chains and sparse microcolonies on hydroxylapatite disks but failed to accumulate and form three-dimensional biofilms when grown on glucose as the carbohydrate source. The biofilm formation defect was also readily apparent by confocal laser scanning microscopy when flow cells were used to grow biofilms. When subjected to acid killing at pH 2.8 for 45 min, the survival rate of strain TW14 was more than 1 log lower than that of the wild-type strain. TW14 was at least 3 logs more susceptible to killing by 0.2% hydrogen peroxide than was UA159. The expression of more than 200 genes was found by microarray analysis to be altered in cells lacking BrpA (P </ab>
<no>id: 6; LR: 20091118; GR: R01 DE 13239/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Acids); 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (BrpA protein, Streptococcus mutans); 0 (Proteome); 1306-06-5 (Durapatite); OID: NLM: PMC1447002; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Oral Biology, College of Dentistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16585759; 188/8/2983 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.188.8.2983-2992.2006</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16585759</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1447002</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1354</id>
<a1>Winfield,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Delano,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Dixon,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Schierding,W. S.</a1>
<a1>Cendan,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Lottenberg,L.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Cuschieri,J.</a1>
<t1>Differences in outcome between obese and nonobese patients following severe blunt trauma are not consistent with an early inflammatory genomic response </t1>
<jf>Critical care medicine</jf>
<jo>Crit.Care Med.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>51</sp>
<op>58</op>
<k1>Academic Medical Centers</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Body Mass Index</k1>
<k1>Chi-Square Distribution</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Databases, Factual</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/genetics/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Injury Severity Score</k1>
<k1>Intensive Care/methods</k1>
<k1>Length of Stay</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Obesity/complications/genetics/mortality</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/mortality</k1>
<k1>Probability</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Regression Analysis</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Trauma Centers</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Wounds, Nonpenetrating/genetics/mortality/therapy</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Obesity has been demonstrated to alter a number of acute and chronic medical conditions. The effect of obesity on severely injured patients, however, remains incompletely defined. We sought to unravel potential physiologic and genomic alterations induced by obesity in severely injured blunt trauma patients. DESIGN: A retrospective review of clinical and genomic information contained in the Inflammation and the Host Response to Injury multicenter trauma-related database examining the relationship between body mass index and the early genomic response from peripheral blood leukocytes to patient outcome following severe blunt trauma was performed. SETTING: Multicenter collaboration between university-based academic trauma centers. PATIENTS: Severely injured blunt trauma patients enrolled in the database. INTERVENTIONS: None. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS: Univariate analysis of 455 severely injured trauma patients using the National Institutes of Health/World Health Organization body mass index classification system revealed significant increases in morbidity, including longer intensive care unit stays and a greater number of ventilator days, cardiac arrests, episodes of acute renal failure, and patients developing multiple organ failure. Regression modeling identified body mass index class as being independently associated with adverse outcomes and increased morbidity but an inverse relationship with mortality in patients who suffered severe blunt traumatic injury. Initial leukocyte genomic expression patterns between 163 patients in the four different body mass index groupings did not differ; however, analysis of gene differences between body mass index classes occurring over time demonstrated significant changes in 513 probe sets with significant pathway differences being related to cellular metabolism. CONCLUSIONS: Increasing body mass index is associated with increased morbidity following severe blunt trauma. The initial blood leukocyte inflammatory response to blunt trauma does not appear to differ significantly between patients despite increasing body mass index. Resolution of the inflammatory response may differ between patients on the basis of body mass index; however, additional work is needed to clarify the potential causality of this finding. </ab>
<no>id: 7; GR: T32 CA106493-02/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 GM-08421-11/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: U54 GM062119-7/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0355501; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1530-0293; 0090-3493</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Laboratory of Inflammation Biology and Surgical Science, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19661803</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Multicenter Study; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/CCM.0b013e3181b08089</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19661803</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1385</id>
<a1>Wu,W.</a1>
<a1>Badrane,H.</a1>
<a1>Arora,S.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Jin,S.</a1>
<t1>MucA-mediated coordination of type III secretion and alginate synthesis in Pseudomonas aeruginosa </t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>186</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>7575</sp>
<op>7585</op>
<k1>Alginates/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sigma Factor/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The type III secretion system (T3SS) of Pseudomonas aeruginosa is an important virulence factor. The T3SS of P. aeruginosa can be induced by a low calcium signal or upon direct contact with the host cells. The exact pathway of signal sensing and T3SS activation is not clear. By screening a transposon insertion mutant library of the PAK strain, mutation in the mucA gene was found to cause repression of T3SS expression under both type III-inducing and -noninducing conditions. Mutation in the mucA gene is known to cause alginate overproduction, resulting in a mucoid phenotype. Alginate production responds to various environmental stresses and plays a protective role for P. aeruginosa. Comparison of global gene expression of mucA mutant and wild-type PAK under T3SS-inducing conditions confirmed the down regulation of T3SS genes and up regulation of genes involved in alginate biosynthesis. Further analysis indicated that the repression of T3SS in the mucA mutant was AlgU and AlgR dependent, as double mutants mucA/algU and mucA/algR showed normal type III expression. An algR::Gm mutant showed a higher level of type III expression, while overexpression of the algR gene inhibited type III gene expression; thus, it seems that the AlgR-regulated product inhibits the expression of the T3SS genes. It is likely that P. aeruginosa has evolved tight regulatory networks to turn off the energy-expensive T3SS when striving for survival under environmental stresses. </ab>
<no>id: 8; LR: 20091118; JID: 2985120R; 0 (AlgR protein, Pseudomonas aeruginosa); 0 (AlgU protein, Pseudomonas aeruginosa); 0 (Alginates); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (MucA protein, Pseudomonas); 0 (Sigma Factor); 0 (Trans-Activators); OID: NLM: PMC524895; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15516570; 186/22/7575 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.186.22.7575-7585.2004</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15516570</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC524895</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1351</id>
<a1>Zeier,Z.</a1>
<a1>Aguilar,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Devi-Rao,G. B.</a1>
<a1>Watson,Z. L.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Wagner,E. K.</a1>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<t1>A limited innate immune response is induced by a replication-defective herpes simplex virus vector following delivery to the murine central nervous system </t1>
<jf>Journal of neurovirology</jf>
<jo>J.Neurovirol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>5-6</is>
<sp>411</sp>
<op>424</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, CD11b/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Antigens, CD11c/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Central Nervous System/immunology/virology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Gene Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Genes, Immediate-Early/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 1, Human/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Lac Operon/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Microinjections</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1)-based vectors readily transduce neurons and have a large payload capacity, making them particularly amenable to gene therapy applications within the central nervous system (CNS). Because aspects of the host responses to HSV-1 vectors in the CNS are largely unknown, we compared the host response of a nonreplicating HSV-1 vector to that of a replication-competent HSV-1 virus using microarray analysis. In parallel, HSV-1 gene expression was tracked using HSV-specific oligonucleotide-based arrays in order to correlate viral gene expression with observed changes in host response. Microarray analysis was performed following stereotactic injection into the right hippocampal formation of mice with either a replication-competent HSV-1 or a nonreplicating recombinant of HSV-1, lacking the ICP4 gene (ICP4-). Genes that demonstrated a significant change (P </ab>
<no>id: 4; GR: AI48633/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA11861/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9508123; 0 (Antigens, CD11b); 0 (Antigens, CD11c); ppublish </no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1538-2443; 1355-0284</sn>
<ad>Departments of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20095947</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.3109/13550280903473452</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20095947</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1348</id>
<a1>Zhou,B.</a1>
<a1>Xu,W.</a1>
<a1>Herndon,D.</a1>
<a1>Tompkins,R.</a1>
<a1>Davis,R.</a1>
<a1>Xiao,W.</a1>
<a1>Wong,W. H.</a1>
<a1>Inflammation and Host Response to Injury Program</a1>
<a1>Toner,M.</a1>
<a1>Warren,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Schoenfeld,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Rahme,L.</a1>
<a1>McDonald-Smith,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Hayden,D.</a1>
<a1>Mason,P.</a1>
<a1>Fagan,S.</a1>
<a1>Yu,Y. M.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Remick,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Mannick,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Lederer,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Gamelli,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Silver,G. M.</a1>
<a1>West,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Shapiro,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Smith,R.</a1>
<a1>Camp,D. G.,2nd</a1>
<a1>Qian,W.</a1>
<a1>Storey,J.</a1>
<a1>Mindrinos,M.</a1>
<a1>Tibshirani,R.</a1>
<a1>Lowry,S.</a1>
<a1>Calvano,S.</a1>
<a1>Chaudry,I.</a1>
<a1>West,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Cohen,M.</a1>
<a1>Moore,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,J.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Efron,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Balis,U. G.</a1>
<a1>Billiar,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Ochoa,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Sperry,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Miller-Graziano,C. L.</a1>
<a1>De,A. K.</a1>
<a1>Bankey,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Finnerty,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Jeschke,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Minei,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Arnoldo,B. D.</a1>
<a1>Hunt,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Horton,J.</a1>
<a1>Cobb,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Brownstein,B.</a1>
<a1>Freeman,B.</a1>
<a1>Maier,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Nathens,A. B.</a1>
<a1>Cuschieri,J.</a1>
<a1>Gibran,N.</a1>
<a1>Klein,M.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Keefe,G.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of factorial time-course microarrays with application to a clinical study of burn injury </t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>9923</sp>
<op>9928</op>
<ab>Time-course microarray experiments are capable of capturing dynamic gene expression profiles. It is important to study how these dynamic profiles depend on the multiple factors that characterize the experimental condition under which the time course is observed. Analytic methods are needed to simultaneously handle the time course and factorial structure in the data. We developed a method to evaluate factor effects by pooling information across the time course while accounting for multiple testing and nonnormality of the microarray data. The method effectively extracts gene-specific response features and models their dependency on the experimental factors. Both longitudinal and cross-sectional time-course data can be handled by our approach. The method was used to analyze the impact of age on the temporal gene response to burn injury in a large-scale clinical study. Our analysis reveals that 21% of the genes responsive to burn are age-specific, among which expressions of mitochondria and immunoglobulin genes are differentially perturbed in pediatric and adult patients by burn injury. These new findings in the body&amp;#39;s response to burn injury between children and adults support further investigations of therapeutic options targeting specific age groups. The methodology proposed here has been implemented in R package &amp;quot;TANOVA&amp;quot; and submitted to the Comprehensive R Archive Network at http://www.r-project.org/. It is also available for download at http://gluegrant1.stanford.edu/TANOVA/. </ab>
<no>id: 1; JID: 7505876; 2010/05/17 [aheadofprint]; ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1091-6490; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Massachusetts General Hospital.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20479259; 1002757107 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.1002757107</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<wp>20100517</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20479259</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1376</id>
<a1>Zujovic,V.</a1>
<a1>Luo,D.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Miller,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Streit,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Harrison,J. K.</a1>
<t1>The facial motor nucleus transcriptional program in response to peripheral nerve injury identifies Hn1 as a regeneration-associated gene </t1>
<jf>Journal of neuroscience research</jf>
<jo>J.Neurosci.Res.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec 1</fd>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>581</sp>
<op>591</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Axotomy</k1>
<k1>Facial Nerve/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Facial Nerve Injuries/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Motor Neurons/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nerve Regeneration/genetics</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Sprague-Dawley</k1>
<k1>Rhombencephalon/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcriptional Activation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Up-Regulation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vagus Nerve/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vagus Nerve Diseases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Facial nerve axotomy (FNA) is a well-established experimental model of motoneuron regeneration. After peripheral nerve axotomy, a sequence of events including glial activation and axonal regrowth leads to functional recovery of the afflicted pool of motoneurons. Using microarray analysis we identified an increase in the expression of 60 genes (at a false discovery rate of 0.1, genes were significant P </ab>
<no>id: 9; LR: 20081121; GR: NS34901/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7600111; 0 (Hn1 protein, mouse); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); ppublish </no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0360-4012; 0360-4012</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, University of Florida College of Medicine,Gainesville, Florida 32610-0267, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16267826</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/jnr.20676</do>
<ds>refworks</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16267826</pmid></reference></refworks>
