<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1498</id>
<a1>Alvarado Bremer,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Ely,B.</a1>
<t1>A provisional study of northern bluefin tuna populations</t1>
<jo>International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas Collective Volume of Scientific Papers</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>127</sp>
<op>127-129</op>
<db>Zoological Record (WOK)</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1496</id>
<a1>Alvarado-Bremer,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Ely,B.</a1>
<t1>Orthodox and unorthodox phylogenetic relationships among tunas revealed by the nucleotide sequence analysis of the mitochondrial DNA control region</t1>
<jo>Journal of Fish Biology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>540</sp>
<op>540-554</op>
<db>Web of Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1495</id>
<a1>Berg,E.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Sobol,S. E.</a1>
<t1>The role of airway fluoroscopy in the evaluation of children with stridor</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>134</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>415</sp>
<op>418</op>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Endoscopy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fluoroscopy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Diseases/complications/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Predictive Value of Tests</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Respiratory Sounds/etiology</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tracheal Diseases/complications/diagnosis</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine the sensitivity and specificity of airway fluoroscopy in the diagnosis of pediatric laryngotracheal abnormalities. DESIGN: Retrospective chart review. SETTING: Tertiary care children&amp;#39;s hospital. PATIENTS: Thirty-nine children, with a mean age of 18 months at the time of evaluation, were evaluated for stridor. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Diagnoses made by airway fluoroscopy and endoscopy. The medical records of patients who had undergone both airway fluoroscopy and airway endoscopy for the evaluation of stridor over a 5-year period were reviewed. The sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values of airway fluoroscopy in the diagnosis of laryngomalacia, tracheomalacia, airway stenosis at any level, and airway mass lesions were determined using endoscopic evaluation as the &amp;quot;gold standard.&amp;quot; RESULTS: Twenty-three of 39 patients (59%) received a different diagnosis by airway endoscopy than by airway fluoroscopy. The sensitivity of airway fluoroscopy in the diagnosis of laryngomalacia, tracheomalacia, airway stenosis, and an airway mass was 27%, 20%, 69%, and 43%, respectively. The specificity for the same diagnoses was 100%, 94%, 100%, and 100%, respectively. CONCLUSIONS: Airway fluoroscopy appears to be reliable in the diagnosis of laryngomalacia, tracheomalacia, airway stenosis, and airway masses because of its high specificity. However, its sensitivity in detecting these common causes of stridor is poor. Negative fluoroscopic study results require further diagnostic evaluation if the clinical indication exists; therefore, the value of fluoroscopy as a screening tool remains uncertain.</ab>
<no>JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1538-361X; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Emory University, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18427008; 134/4/415 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archotol.134.4.415</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18427008</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1493</id>
<a1>DelGaudio,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Wise,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Proximal pharyngeal reflux correlates with increasing severity of lingual tonsil hypertrophy</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>138</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>473</sp>
<op>478</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Body Mass Index</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hypertrophy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Palatine Tonsil/pathology</k1>
<k1>Pharyngeal Diseases/pathology</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Tongue</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine if degree of lingual tonsil hypertrophy (LTH) correlates with pharyngeal reflux. DESIGN: Prospective. METHODS: Patients with flexible laryngoscopic evidence of LTH were included. Degree of LTH was graded mild, moderate, or severe by two otolaryngologists blinded to pH study results. Three-sensor pH study results were correlated to LTH grade. RESULTS: Nineteen patients were included (five with mild LTH, eight with moderate LTH, and six with severe LTH). Nasopharyngeal reflux (NPR) events &amp;lt;pH4 were found in four of six severe LTH patients but no mild or moderate LTH patients (P = 0.006). All severe LTH patients had NPR events &amp;lt;pH5, compared with only 4 of 11 mild or moderate LTH patients (P = 0.017). At the UES, 4 of 6 severe LTH patients had pathologic reflux, compared with 4 of 13 mild or moderate (P = 0.025). Interobserver reliability calculated by Cohen&amp;#39;s kappa was excellent (0.92). CONCLUSIONS: Our study shows a continuum of increasing pharyngeal reflux with higher LTH severity. Severe LTH may be a reliable physical sign of pharyngeal reflux, especially NPR.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 8508176; 2007/09/06 [received]; 2007/12/12 [revised]; 2007/12/18 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, School of Medicine, Emory University, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA. jdelgaudio@emroyhealthcare.org</ad>
<an>PMID: 18359357; S0194-5998(07)02039-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2007.12.023</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18359357</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1497</id>
<a1>Ely,B.</a1>
<a1>Stoner,D. S.</a1>
<a1>Alvarado Bremer,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Thelen,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Jones,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Black,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Smith,L.</a1>
<a1>Scott,K.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Quattro,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Genetic analyses of Atlantic northern bluefin tuna populations</t1>
<jo>International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas Collective Volume of Scientific Papers</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>52</vo>
<sp>1145</sp>
<op>1145-1149</op>
<db>Zoological Record (WOK)</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1494</id>
<a1>Ely,B.</a1>
<a1>Stoner,D. S.</a1>
<a1>Bremer,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Dean,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Addis,P.</a1>
<a1>Cau,A.</a1>
<a1>Thelen,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Jones,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Black,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Smith,L.</a1>
<a1>Scott,K.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Quattro,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Analyses of nuclear ldhA gene and mtDNA control region sequences of Atlantic northern bluefin tuna populations</t1>
<jf>Marine biotechnology (New York, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Mar.Biotechnol.(NY)</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>583</sp>
<op>588</op>
<ab>There has been considerable debate about whether the Atlantic northern bluefin tuna exist as a single panmictic unit. We have addressed this issue by examining both mitochondrial DNA control region nucleotide sequences and nuclear gene ldhA allele frequencies in replicate size or year class samples of northern bluefin tuna from the Mediterranean Sea and the northwestern Atlantic Ocean. Pairwise comparisons of multiple year class samples from the 2 regions provided no evidence for population subdivision. Similarly, analyses of molecular variance of both mitochondrial and ldhA data revealed no significant differences among or between samples from the 2 regions. These results demonstrate the importance of analyzing multiple year classes and large sample sizes to obtain accurate estimates when using allele frequencies to characterize a population. It is important to note that the absence of genetic evidence for population substructure does not unilaterally constitute evidence of a single panmictic population, as genetic differentiation can be prevented by large population sizes and by migration.</ab>
<no>JID: 100892712; 2001/08/28 [received]; 2002/02/25 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1436-2228; 1436-2228</sn>
<ad>Department of Biological Sciences, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC 29208, USA. Ely@sc.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 14961233</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<do>10.1007/s10126-002-0040-y</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14961233</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1500</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>DelGaudio,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Predictors of failure of primary surgery</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<sp>19</sp>
<op>19-25</op>
<k1>Electronic books</k1>
<no>50611 Access limited to UF students, faculty, staff, and other registered users.; 52112 Scholarly &amp;amp; Professional Springer</no>
<a2>Kountakis,Stilianos</a2><a2> Jacobs,J.</a2><a2>Gosepath,J.</a2>
<t2>Revision Sinus Surgery [electronic resource]</t2>
<pb>Springer Sept</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<sn>3540789308 (Trade Cloth); 9783540789307</sn>
<lk>Click here for full text options http://UH7QF6FD4H.search.serialssolutions.com/?V=1.0&amp;L=UH7QF6FD4H&amp;S=JCs&amp;C=TC0000237677&amp;T=marc&amp;tab=BOOKS Licensed for access by UF students, faculty, staff, and other registered users.</lk>
<cn>RF350 (ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1492</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Durden,F. L.</a1>
<a1>Sobol,S. E.</a1>
<t1>Pediatric airway consultation survey in a tertiary care children&amp;#39;s hospital: an interobserver analysis</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1266</sp>
<op>1268</op>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Hospitals, Pediatric</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Mass Screening</k1>
<k1>Observer Variation</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Referral and Consultation</k1>
<k1>Respiration</k1>
<k1>Respiration Disorders/diagnosis/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>We conducted a prospective analysis to independently observe the initial opinion of: (1) consulting pediatric residents (postgraduate year 2 [PGY-2]), (2) corresponding consulting attending physicians (general pediatric or pediatric emergency medicine), and (3) consulting otolaryngology PGY-2 residents when assessing patients for &amp;quot;noisy breathing.&amp;quot; Each was asked to define the type of noisy breathing present and to formulate a diagnosis based on a limited set of choices. The final diagnosis was determined by a single attending pediatric otolaryngologist (S.E.S.) at the completion of the diagnostic workup. The accuracy for characterization of breath sounds for the pediatric residents, attending pediatricians, and otolaryngology residents were 26.1%, 23.5%, and 98.6%, respectively. The positive predictive values for the determination of diagnosis were 71.6%, 69.4%, and 76.6%, respectively. These findings indicate that pediatric residents and attending pediatricians may be deficient in their ability to characterize the breath sounds commonly seen in patients with noisy breathing. Further education of pediatricians may lead to a more accurate diagnostic evaluation of a child with noisy breathing.</ab>
<no>JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1942-7522; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20013680</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20013680</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1490</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Jerris,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Sobol,S. E.</a1>
<t1>Nationwide trends in pediatric Staphylococcus aureus head and neck infections</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>135</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>14</sp>
<op>16</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Anti-Infective Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Head</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Methicillin Resistance</k1>
<k1>Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Neck</k1>
<k1>Otorhinolaryngologic Diseases/drug therapy/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Prevalence</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcal Infections/complications/drug therapy/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>United States/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the epidemiologic manifestations of pediatric Staphylococcus aureus head and neck infections nationwide and to identify possible trends in the antibiotic drug susceptibility of S aureus during a 6-year period. DESIGN: Retrospective review of microbiologic data from a peer-reviewed national database. SETTING: More than 300 hospitals nationwide. PATIENTS: All pediatric patients with head and neck infections involving S aureus. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Anatomic sites were divided into oropharynx/neck, sinonasal, and otologic infection categories. Demographic and antimicrobial drug susceptibility patterns were reviewed. RESULTS: A total of 21,009 pediatric head and neck S aureus infections that occurred between January 2001 and December 31, 2006 were gathered from the database. Predominance was observed in the oropharyngeal/neck category (60.3%). For all sites, the mean patient age was 6.7 years (range, 0-18 years), with a 51.7% male predominance. There was a high occurrence in the North East Central region of the United States. Overall, methicillin-resistant S aureus was seen in 21.6% of all patient isolates (n = 4534), with rates of 11.8%, 12.5%, 18.1%, 27.2%, 25.5%, and 28.1% for 2001 through 2006, respectively. This represents a 16.3% increase in methicillin-resistant S aureus during these 6 years for all pediatric head and neck S aureus infections. CONCLUSIONS: There is an alarming nationwide increase in the prevalence of pediatric methicillin-resistant S aureus head and neck infections. Disparities in the treatment of various head and neck infections nationwide may contribute to the regional differences in the prevalence of such infections. Judicious use of antibiotic agents and increased effectiveness in diagnosis and treatment are warranted to reduce further antimicrobial drug resistance in pediatric head and neck infections.</ab>
<no>JID: 8603209; 0 (Anti-Infective Agents); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1538-361X; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19153301; 135/1/14 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archoto.2008.511</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19153301</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1501</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Saini,R.</a1>
<a1>Welsh,C. T.</a1>
<t1>Radiological case of the month... ganglioglioma</t1>
<jf>Applied Radiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Radiol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>03</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>48</sp>
<op>49</op>
<k1>Glioma -- Radiography -- In Infancy and Childhood</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Craniotomy</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Whites</k1>
<sn>0160-9963</sn>
<ad>Resident, Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Emory University, Atlanta, GA; Publisher URL: www.cinahl.com/cgi-bin/refsvc?jid=122&amp;accno=2004184357</ad>
<an>2004184357</an>
<la>English</la>
<lk>http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=cin20&amp;AN=2004184357&amp;site=ehost-live</lk>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1499</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Sobol,S. E.</a1>
<t1>Regional and intracranial complications of acute otitis media</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<is>7</is>
<sp>105</sp>
<op>105-117</op>
<k1>Pediatric otolaryngology</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Neck -- physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Otorhinolaryngologic Diseases</k1>
<ab>Contents: 01 Congenital malformations of the head and neck / Ken Kazahaya, Davinder J. Singh -- Diseases of the external ear / Jeffrey L. Keller -- Pediatric communication disorders / Judith S. Gravel ... [et al.] -- Hearing loss / John A. Germiller -- Otitis media / Lisa M. Elden -- Chronic disorders of the middle ear and mastoid / Eric D. Baum, William P. Potsic -- Regional and intracranial complications of otitis media / Steven E. Sobol -- Acute sinusitis and its complications / Steven E. Sobol -- Diagnosis and management of chronic sinusitis / Lawrence W. C. Tom -- Acute and chronic infection of the oral cavity and pharynx / Udayan K. Shah -- Infections and inflammatory disorders of the upper airway / Steven G. Wolfe, Steven D. Handler -- Foreign bodies of the upper aerodigestive tract / Daniel S. Samadi -- Management of chronic airway obstruction / Karen B. Zur, Ian N. Jacobs -- Sleep-disordered breathing / Ralph F. Wetmore -- Pediatric neck masses / Ralph F. Wetmore -- Pediatric facial trauma / Ken Kazahaya, Davinder J. Singh.</ab>
<no>[edited by] Ralph F. Wetmore. : [edited by] Ralph F. Wetmore.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Wetmore,Ralph F.</a2>
<t2>Pediatric otolaryngology : The requisites in pediatrics</t2>
<ed>1</ed>
<pb>Mosby/Elsevier</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia, PA</pp>
<a3>Bell,Louis M.</a3>
<t3>The Requisites in Pediatrics Series</t3>
<sn>0323048552; 9780323048552</sn>
<lk>Table of contents only http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip073/2006033359.html</lk>
<cn>WV140P37086 2007 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY General Collection); WV140.P37086 2007 (Jacksonville UFHSCL Borland)</cn>
<db>UF Library Catalog</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1491</id>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Wise,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Klein,A. M.</a1>
<t1>A rare cause of dysphonia</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>E09</sp>
<k1>Adrenal Cortex Hormones/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Dysphonia/drug therapy/etiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic/complications/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<ab>Although dysphonia is a common complaint among patients seen in an otolaryngology clinic, an autoimmune cause of the problem is less common. Autoimmune disease can be the source of various laryngologic manifestations, but diagnosis depends on a high index of suspicion, careful patient evaluation and testing, and videolaryngoscopy (videostroboscopy if available) to uncover specific identifying findings. This report describes a patient presenting with upper-range vocal difficulties who was found to have early systemic lupus erythematosus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090520; JID: 7701817; 0 (Adrenal Cortex Hormones); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1942-7522; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18712682</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18712682</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1502</id>
<a1>Rogers,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Naseri,I.</a1>
<a1>Sobol,S. E.</a1>
<t1>Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus Orbital Abscess in a Neonate</t1>
<jf>International journal of pediatric otorhinolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Pediatr.Otorhinolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>06</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>991</sp>
<op>991</op>
<no>TY: ABST; M3: Abstract</no>
<sn>01655876</sn>
<an>24968816</an>
<lk>http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=aph&amp;AN=24968816&amp;site=ehost-live</lk>
<do>10.1016/j.ijporl.2007.02.029</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
