
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3316</id>
<a1>Ellis,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Hayes,G. W.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>The efficacy of small cell foundation as a varroa mite (Varroa destructor) control</t1>
<jf>Experimental and Applied Acarology</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>311</sp>
<op>316</op>
<ab>Due to a continuing shift toward reducing/minimizing the use of chemicals in honey bee colonies, we explored the possibility of using small cell foundation as a varroa control. Based on the number of anecdotal reports supporting small cell as an efficacious varroa control tool, we hypothesized that bee colonies housed on combs constructed on small cell foundation would have lower varroa populations and higher adult bee populations and more cm(2) brood. To summarize our results, we found that the use of small cell foundation did not significantly affect cm(2) total brood, total mites per colony, mites per brood cell, or mites per adult bee, but did affect adult bee population for two sampling months. Varroa levels were similar in all colonies throughout the study. We found no evidence that small cell foundation was beneficial with regard to varroa control under the tested conditions in Florida.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0168-8162</sn>
<an>000263789300006</an>
<do>10.1007/s10493-008-9221-3</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3314</id>
<a1>Ellis,Amanda M.</a1>
<a1>Hayes,Gerry W.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<t1>The efficacy of dusting honey bee colonies with powdered sugar to reduce varroa mite populations</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>72</sp>
<op>76</op>
<ab>Controlling varroa mite (Varroa destructor Anderson and Trueman) populations in honey bee (Apis mellifera L.) colonies with acaricides has been a challenge for beekeepers due to the rapid development of resistant mite populations. For this reason, many beekeepers are adopting Integrated Pest Management strategies as alternatives to chemocentric varroa control schemes. One non-chemical tool that has been used for varroa control is dusting bee colonies with powdered sugar. The objective of our study was to determine the efficacy of powdered sugar as a varroa control by comparing mite populations, adult bee populations, and brood area in untreated colonies with those in colonies dusted every two weeks for 11 months with 120 g powdered sugar per application. We found that dusting colonies with powdered sugar did not significantly affect the adult bee population (treated: 10061.72 +/- 629.42; control: 10691.00 +/- 554.44) or amount of brood (treated: 4521.91 +/- 342.84 cm(2); control: 4472.55 +/- 365.85 cm(2)). We also found no significant differences between the total number of mites per colony (treated: 2112.15 +/- 224.62; control: 2197.80 +/- 207.75), number of mites per adult bee (treated: 0.080 +/- 0.010; control: 0.097 +/- 0.010), or number of mites per capped brood cell (treated: 0.112 +/- 0.013; control: 0.106 +/- 0.018). All data are mean +/- s.e. Within the limits of our study and at the application rates used, we did not find that dusting colonies with powdered sugar afforded significant varroa control.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000264029800014</an>
<do>10.3896/IBRA.1.48.1.14</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3341</id>
<a1>Ellis,J.</a1>
<t1>Life behind bars: Why honey bees feed small hive beetles</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>142</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>267</sp>
<op>269</op>
<ab>Small hive beetles (SHB) continue to be a problem for beekeepers in the Southeast and they are spreading into other areas of the United States. Prior to the arrival of SHB to the U.S., only two papers on the menace existed, one by A.E. Lundie (1940), and another by M.D. Schmolke (1974). Both authors seem to down play the threat of SHB and only hint towards the beetles&amp;#39; potential to inflict severe damage to honey bee colonies.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000174513900012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3325</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Progress towards controlling small beetles with IPM: Integrating current treatments - Part II of two parts</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>145</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>207</sp>
<op>210</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000227290300019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3326</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Progress towards controlling small hive beetles with IPM: Knowing our options - Part I of two parts</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>145</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>119</op>
<ab>Through research, we have taken great strides toward understanding small hive beetle (hereafter referred to as &amp;#39;beetle&amp;#39;) biology and behavior. Despite the advances researchers are making, the beetle remains an applied problem for beekeepers (Figure 1). Indeed, it is for this reason alone that in recent years we have seen a resurgence in beetle research, a large portion of which has been concerned with controlling beetles. In this 2-part series, I will discuss many of the currently available control measures in their appropriate category (chemical, biological, etc.) (Part I) and then attempt to suggest ways that these can be integrated for maximum efficacy (Part II). In the end, I hope that these articles will serve to identify beetle controls that will produce results with the fewest environmental impacts, a novel goal for any pest control scheme.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000226771100011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3324</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Reviewmg the confinement of small hive beetles (Aethina tumida) by western honey bees (Apis mellifera)</t1>
<jf>Bee World</jf>
<jo>Bee World</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>56</sp>
<op>62</op>
<ab>Although only scavengers in honey bee colonies in their native range of subsaharan Africa, small hive beetles can cause considerable damage in colonies of European honey bees in Australia and the south-eastern USA. Early research on the beetle focused mainly on its biology and control although: there has recently been a shift towards studying its intra-colonial behaviour. Researchers have shown that when small hive beetles enter a bee colony, a cohort of guard bees confines them to the nest periphery (a bee response that limits beetle reproduction). Despite a myriad of bee behaviours that culminate in beetle confinement the beetles are able to remain alive by soliciting food from their honey bee guards. Herein, I review confinement dynamics and the associated interactions.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0005-772X</sn>
<an>000232041700003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3345</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>The future of Varroa control: Integrating current treatments with the latest advancements</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>141</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>127</sp>
<op>131</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000166695200016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3346</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>How honey bees ensure our food supply</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>501</sp>
<op>502</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>A1996UV55500012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3344</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<t1>A scientific note on Apis mellifera brood attractiveness to Varroa destructor as affected by the chemotherapeutic history of the brood</t1>
<jf>Apidologie</jf>
<jo>Apidologie</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>SEP-OCT</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>449</sp>
<op>450</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-8435</sn>
<an>000171455500006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3333</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of modified hive entrances and a bottom screen device for controlling aethina tumida (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae) infestations in Apis mellifera (Hymenoptera : Apidae) colonies</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1647</sp>
<op>1652</op>
<ab>This study was designed to test whether hive entrances reduced with polyvinyl chloride pipe reduce the ingress of Aethina tumida Murray into Apis mellifera L. colonies and whether screen-mesh bottom boards alleviate side effects associated with restricted entrances. Forty-eight colonies distributed equally between two locations each received one of six experimental treatments: 1) conventional solid bottom board and open entrance, 2) ventilated bottom board and open entrance, 3) conventional bottom and 1.9-cm-i.d. pipe entrance, 4) conventional bottom and 3.8-cm pipe entrance, 5) screen bottom and 1.9-cm pipe entrance, and 6) screen bottom and 3.8-cm pipe entrance. Results were inconsistent between apiaries. In apiary 1, colonies with 3.8-cm pipe entrances had fewer A. tumida than colonies with open entrances, but this benefit was Dot apparent in apiary 2. Pipe entrances tended to reduce colony and brood production in both apiaries, and these losses were only partly mitigated with the addition of screened bottom boards. Pipe entrances bad no measurable liability concerning colony thermoregulation. There were significantly fewer frames of adult A. mellifera in colonies with 3.8- or 1.9-cm pipe entrances compared with open entrances but more in colonies with screens. There were more frames of pollen in colonies with open or 3.8-cm pipe entrances than 1.9-cm entrances. We conclude that the efficacy of reduced hive entrances in reducing ingress of A. tumida remains uncertain due to observed differences between apiaries. Furthermore, there were side effects associated with restricted entrances that could be only partly mitigated with screened bottom boards.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000188467500004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3340</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Hood,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray) weight, gross biometry, and sex proportion at three locations in the southeastern United States</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>142</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>520</sp>
<op>522</op>
<ab>This study was designed to appraise differences in sex proportion and mean body width, length, and weight between sexes of small hive beetles (SHB) from Clemson, SC; Wadmalaw Island, SC; and Richmond Hills, GA. Adult female beetles were significantly longer than males within each location. Overall means did not differ for width between sexes. Due to small variation in width between sexes, width may be an important factor when designing exclusion or trapping devices for SHB. Overall, female beetles weighed significantly more than males. There tended to be more females than males at each location.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000176375100016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3343</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Hood,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of a bottom screen device, Apistan (TM), and Apilife VAR (TM), in controlling Varroa destructor</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>141</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>813</sp>
<op>816</op>
<ab>This study tested the efficacy of a hive bottom screen device in controlling varroa mites, when used alone or in conjunction with the miticides Apistan (TM) and ApilifeVART (TM). Thirty-six colonies were equalized and each assigned to one of six treatments: (1) no treatment, (2) bottom screen, (3) Apistan, (4) Apistan + screen, (5) Apilife, and (6) Apilife + screen. Adult bee populations were not affected by treatment, but the number of brood cells was significantly reduced in colonies treated exclusively with Apilife compared to that of colonies treated with Apistan or exclusively with a bottom screen. Brood production was numerically highest in colonies treated exclusively with a bottom screen. Varroa populations were significantly reduced in colonies receiving acaricide compared to non-treated colonies. Varroa populations in colonies treated exclusively with a bottom screen were 14.9 % lower than that of non-treated colonies, but this difference was not significant. The bottom screen did not affect the percentage of varroa mite population phoretic on adult bees. Apistan provided 100% mite control in South Carolina, whereas in Georgia it provided 0% control in colonies treated exclusively with Apistan. With the addition of a bottom screen, Apistan-treated colonies in Georgia experienced an average mite control of 44.3%. This suggests that fluvalinate resistance exists in Georgia varroa mites. It also indicates that a bottom screen may help compensate for reduced acaricide efficacy. Average efficacy of Apilife ranged from 65.2 - 97.1%.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000171853100021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3331</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Richards,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Berry,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hygienic behavior of Cape and European Apis mellifera (Hymenoptera : Apidae) toward Aethina tumida (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae) eggs oviposited in sealed bee brood</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>97</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>860</sp>
<op>864</op>
<ab>In this study, we tested for the presence and efficacy of hygienic behavior by Cape honey bees in South Africa and European honey bees, Apis mellifera L. (Hymenoptera: Apidae), of mixed origin in the United States toward Aethina tumida Murray (Coleoptera: Nitidulidae) eggs oviposited in sealed bee brood. We looked for colony differences in removal rates of brood in cells with cappings perforated by A. tumida within each subspecies to identify colonies within location that display superior hygienic behavior. Finally, we determined the oviposition rate (number of A. tumida-perforated cells actually oviposited in by A. tumida/total number of A. timida-perforated cells) in A. tumida-perforated cells and the number of A. tumida eggs oviposited in each cell. There were no colony differences within subspecies for the removal of normal capped brood, artificially perforated brood (capped cells perforated by experimenter with a pin), and A. tumida-perforated brood. For both subspecies, the bees removed significantly more A. tumida-perforated brood than either normal or artificially perforated brood. A. tumida oviposited significantly more eggs per cell in Cape colonies than in European colonies, but the oviposition rate in A. tumida-perforated cells did not differ between Cape and European colonies. Both subspecies removed a proportion of A. tumida-perforated brood statistically indistinguishable from the proportion of A. tumida-perforated brood containing A. tumida eggs. Thus, both C ape and European A. mellifera preferentially remove the contents of A. tumida-perforated cells in which A. tumida have actually oviposited.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>000222642400031</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3322</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,H. R.</a1>
<t1>An ecological digest of the small hive beetle (Aethina tumida), a symbiont in honey bee colonies (Apis mellifera)</t1>
<jf>Insectes Sociaux</jf>
<jo>Insectes Soc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>8</sp>
<op>19</op>
<ab>The small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray) is an endemic scavenger in colonies of western honey bee subspecies (Apis mellifera L.) inhabiting sub-Saharan Africa where it only occasionally damages host colonies. Such damage is usually restricted to weakened/diseased colonies or is associated with after absconding events (all bees, including the queen, leave the hive) due to behavioral resistance mechanisms of its host. In sharp contrast, the beetle has proven deleterious to honey bee colonies in introduced ranges of the United States and Australia. With this review we synthesize the existing data in a manner that allows us to discuss the beetle&amp;#39;s natural history from an ecological perspective. A thorough exploration of beetle ecology allows us to 1) illuminate the unique symbiotic relationship it and its host share and understand how this relationship is fostered, 2) place this relationship in context with those of other arthropods inhabiting social insect colonies, 3) understand its natural reliance on honey bee colonies, 4) predict its spread outside its native range, and 5) predict its effects on non-African honey bees and non-target species. Here we present an amalgamation of information that will contribute to a more thorough and appropriate understanding of not only small hive beetles as symbionts, but of social insect symbionts in general.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0020-1812</sn>
<an>000235635500002</an>
<do>10.1007/s00040-005-0851-8</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3338</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,H. R.</a1>
<t1>A note on mapping propolis deposits in Cape honey bee (Apis mellifera capensis) colonies</t1>
<jf>African Entomology</jf>
<jo>Afr.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>122</sp>
<op>124</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1021-3589</sn>
<an>000183701600014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3334</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,H. R.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Social encapsulation of the small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray) by European honeybees (Apis mellifera L.)</t1>
<jf>Insectes Sociaux</jf>
<jo>Insectes Soc.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>286</sp>
<op>291</op>
<ab>European and African subspecies of honeybees (Apis mellifera L.) utilize social encapsulation to contain the small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray), a honeybee colony scavenger. Using social encapsulation, African honeybees successfully limit beetle reproduction that can devastate host colonies. In sharp contrast, European honeybees often fail to contain beetles, possibly because their social encapsulation skills may be less developed than those of African honeybees. In this study, we quantify beetle and European honeybee behaviours associated with social encapsulation, describe colony and time (morning and evening) differences in these behaviours (to identify possible circadian rhythms), and detail intra-colonial, encapsulated beetle distributions. The data help explain the susceptibility of European honeybees to depredation by small hive beetles. There were significant colony differences in a number of social encapsulation behaviours (the number of beetle prisons and beetles per prison, and the proportion of prison guard bees biting at encapsulated beetles) suggesting that successful encapsulation of beetles by European bees varies between colonies. We also found evidence for the existence of circathan rhythms in small hive beetles, as they were more active in the evening rather than morning. In response to increased beetle activity during the evening, there was an increase in the number of prison guard bees during evening. Additionally, the bees successfully kept most (similar to93%) beetles out of the combs at all times, suggesting that social encapsulation by European honeybees is sufficient to control small populations of beetles (as seen in this study) but may ultimately fail if beetle populations are high.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0020-1812</sn>
<an>000185487800015</an>
<do>10.1007/s00040-003-0671-7</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3336</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>A scientific note on small hive beetle (Aethina tumida) oviposition and behaviour during European (Apis mellifera) honey bee clustering and absconding events</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>47</sp>
<op>48</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000184773500006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3337</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>The effects of adult small hive beetles, Aethina tumida (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae), on nests and flight activity of Cape and European honey bees (Apis mellifera)</t1>
<jf>Apidologie</jf>
<jo>Apidologie</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>JUL-AUG</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>399</sp>
<op>408</op>
<ab>This study identifies differences in the effects of small hive beetles on flight activity and nests of European-derived honey bees (Apis mellifera) in the United States and Cape honey bees (Apis mellifera capensis) in South Africa. Treatments consisted of control colonies (&amp;lt;5 beetles/colony) and experimental colonies receiving beetles (treatment). Absconding day did not differ significantly between treatment or bee race but absconding was greater between the two treatments in European colonies than in Cape ones. Cape bees used significantly more propolis than European bees. Honey stores were significantly greater in Cape honey bee colonies than in European ones. Bee weight did not differ significantly between treatments or bee race. Treatment did not significantly affect bee populations, brood area, or average flight activity in Cape colonies but it did significantly lower all of these in European colonies. The effects of treatment in European colonies are symptomatic of absconding preparation. Treatment significantly lowered the amount of pollen stores in Cape colonies, but this effect was not found in European colonies. The number of beetles in control colonies was significantly higher in European colonies than Cape ones while the percentage of beetles remaining in non-absconding treated colonies was higher in Cape colonies than European ones. These data indicate that adult small hive beetles are sufficient to cause significant harmful effects on colonies of European, but not Cape, honey bees.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-8435</sn>
<an>000184099600009</an>
<do>10.1051/apido:2003038</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3328</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Confinement behavior of Cape honey bees (Apis mellifera capensis Esch.) in relation to population densities of small hive beetles (Aethina tumida Murray)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Insect Behavior</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Behav.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>835</sp>
<op>842</op>
<ab>We quantified the effects of increasing small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray) populations on guarding behavior of Cape honey bees ( Apis mellifera capensis, an African subspecies). We found more confinement sites ( prisons) at the higher ( 50 beetles per colony) rather than lower ( 25 beetles per colony) beetle density. The number of beetles per prison did not change with beetle density. There were more guard bees per beetle during evening than morning. Neither guard bee nor beetle behavior varied with beetle density or over time. Forty-six percent of all beetles were found among the combs at the low beetle density and this increased to 58% at the higher one. In neither instance were beetles causing depredation to host colonies. Within the limits of the experiment, guarding behavior of Cape honey bees is relatively unaffected by increasing beetle density ( even if significant proportions of beetles reach the combs).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0892-7553</sn>
<an>000225299400008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3330</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Confinement of small hive beetles (Aethina tumida) by Cape honeybees (Apis mellifera capensis)</t1>
<jf>Apidologie</jf>
<jo>Apidologie</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUL-AUG</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>389</sp>
<op>396</op>
<ab>In this study we quantify small hive beetle (Aethina tumida. Murray) and Cape honeybee (A.m. capensis Esch., an African subspecies) behaviours that are associated with beetle confinement in an effort to understand why Cape bees can withstand large beetle infestations. Four observation hives were each inoculated with 25 beetles and were observed for 11-17 days. Data collected included guard bee (worker bees who guard beetle confinement sites) and confined beetle behaviour. There was considerable colony variation for many bee and beetle behaviours. Overall, there were more beetle guards during evening, which was likely an effort to keep increasingly active beetles contained. About one-fifth of the beetles were found at the comb periphery although the colonies suffered no ill effects. Although beetles reached the combs, the bees were able to prevent beetle reproduction. Our data suggest that confinement is more likely an initial defence against invading beetles and not the sole reason African subspecies of honeybees are usually immune to beetle infestations while European bees are not.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-8435</sn>
<an>000223717700007</an>
<do>10.1051/apido:2004030</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3329</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Luckman,B.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Effects of soil type, moisture, and density on pupation success of Aethina tumida (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>794</sp>
<op>798</op>
<ab>We tested the effects of different soils (soils A-F) representing four soil types, two moisture extremes (wet and dry), and two soil densities (packed and tilled) on the number of emerging Aethina tumida Murray (Coleoptera: Nitidulidae) adults. We further determined the effect of soil type and A. tumida sex on the time spent in the soil (where the beetle pupates). Three thousand A. tumida larvae were placed in the moist soil treatments (wet/packed and wet/tilled), of which 2,746 emerged from the soil as adults. Additionally, 3,000 larvae were placed in the dry soil treatments (dry/packed and dry/ tilled), of which none emerged as adults. In only one soil were emersion rates different from those in other soils. For every soil, there were significantly more emerging A. tumida in the wet treatments than in the dry ones. Female A. tumida spent less time in the soil than mate A. tumida but only by an average of less than half a day. Soil type did affect the length of time A. tumida spent as pupae, despite which average emersion as adults occurred within a tight range. The data suggest that biological requirements of A. tumida may limit/enhance their reproductive potential in various soil environments (especially in dry climates).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000223650800002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3335</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Holland,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Cape (Apis mellifera capensis) and European (Apis mellifera) honey bee guard age and duration of guarding small hive beetles (Aethina tumida)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>34</op>
<ab>The guard age and duration of European (Apis mellifera) and Cape (A. m. capensis) honey bees guarding small hive beetles (Aethina tumida) were determined using 3-frame observation hives, noting the commencement and termination of beetle guarding by individually labelled honey bees. European honey bees in the USA began guarding small hive beetles significantly earlier (beginning age 18.55 +/- 0.52 days; mean +/- s.e.), guarded beetles significantly longer (duration 2.36 +/- 0.31 days), and stopped guarding beetles significantly sooner (ending age 19.91 +/- 0.57 days) than Cape honey bees in South Africa (beginning age 20.61 +/- 0.38 days; duration 1.43 +/- 0.12 days; and ending age 21.04 +/- 0.37 days). Although the timing of beetle guarding behaviour between the two subspecies is significantly different, it does not explain the differential damage to European and Cape honey bee colonies caused by small hive beetles.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000184773500002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3323</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Munn,P. A.</a1>
<t1>The worldwide health status of honey bees</t1>
<jf>Bee World</jf>
<jo>Bee World</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>88</sp>
<op>101</op>
<ab>In 1988, a comprehensive review of world bee health was published in Bee World. Intended as an accessible and reliable reference to worldwide bee health status, updates have been published at intervals since then, including one devoted to viruses. These reviews have proved a valuable and accurate source of information on worldwide bee health. The last was published 10 years ago and the long-awaited latest in the series is presented here.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0005-772X</sn>
<an>000234660000003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3339</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Longevity and reproductive success of Aethina tumida (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae) fed different natural diets</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>95</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>902</sp>
<op>907</op>
<ab>The longevity and reproductive success of newly emerged, unfed adult Aethina tumida Murray assigned different diets (control = unfed; honey-pollen; honey; pollen; empty brood comb; bee brood; fresh Kei apples; and rotten Kei apples) were determined. Longevity in honey-fed small hive beetle adults (average maximum: 167 d) was significantly higher than on other diets. Small hive beetles fed empty brood comb lived significantly longer (average maximum: 49.8 d) than unfed beetles (average maximum: 9.6 d). Small hive beetle offspring were produced on honey-pollen, pollen, bee brood, fresh Kei apples, and rotten Kei apples but not on honey alone, empty brood comb, or in control treatments. The highest reproductive success occurred in pollen fed adults (1773.8 +/- 294.4 larvae per three mating pairs of adults). The data also show that A. tumida can reproduce on fruits alone, indicating that they are facultative parasites. The pupation success and sex ratio of small hive beetle offspring were also analyzed. Larvae fed pollen, honey-pollen, or brood had significantly higher pupation success rates of 0.64,0.73, and 0.65 respectively than on the other diets. Sex ratios of emerging adults fed diets of pollen or brood as larvae were significantly skewed toward females. Because small hive beetle longevity and overall reproductive success was highest on foodstuffs located in honey bee colonies, A. tumida are efficient at causing large-scale damage to colonies of honey bees resulting in economic injury for the beekeeper. Practical considerations for the control of A. tumida are briefly discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000178550000004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3332</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Rong,I. H.</a1>
<a1>Hill,M. P.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,H. R.</a1>
<a1>Elzen,P. J.</a1>
<t1>The susceptibility of small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray) pupae to fungal pathogens</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>144</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>486</sp>
<op>488</op>
<ab>In this study, otherwise-healthy, small hive beetle larvae (Aethina tumida Murray) were exposed to beetle larvae that had died during pupation and were colonized by fungi. Exposure was induced either via 1) ingestion of honey bee brood inoculated with an emulsion of the dead, colonized larvae or 2) contact with the dead, colonized larvae post-feeding. Larval mortality was determined in a preliminary assessment of the fungal pathogen&amp;#39;s potential as a biological control agent. Similar numbers of beetle larvae eclosed when feeding on either the control or treatment brood. However, the number of eclosing beetles was significantly lower for healthy larvae that had contacted pathogen-killed larvae post-feeding than for those larvae that had not. Two species of Aspergillus were found colonizing the larvae, A. flavus Link:Gray. and A. niger van Tieghem Both are soil fungi known to attack insects, but they have documented side effects. Aspergillus flavus produces carcinogenic compounds and both species cause diseases in honey bees. Three additional fungi, all saprotrophic, were also found on the surface of the cadavers. They include Clonostachys rosea (Link:Fr.) Schoers, Samuels, Seifert &amp;amp; W. Gams, Gliocladium catenulatum Gilm. &amp;amp; Abbott, and Mucor plumbeus Bonard. Further investigations must be conducted to ascertain which pathogen caused increased mortality of beetle larvae.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000221706100021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3313</id>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Spiewok,S.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Buchholz,S.</a1>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Tedders,W. L.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Aethina tumida (Coleoptera: Nitidulidae) Larvae and Pupae to Entomopathogenic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>9</op>
<ab>In this study, we evaluated the potential use of entomopathogenic nematodes as a control for the beetle Aethina tumida Murray (Coleoptera: Nitidulidae). In particular, we conducted 1) four screening bioassays to determine nematode (seven species, 10 total strains tested) and application level effects on A. tumida larvae and pupae, 2) a generational persistence bioassay to determine whether single inoculations with nematodes would control multiple generations of A. tumida larvae in treated soil, and 3) a field bioassay to determine whether the nematodes would remain efficacious in the field. In the screening bioassays, nematode efficacy varied significantly by tested nematode and the infective juvenile (IJ) level at which they were applied. Although nematode virulence was moderate in screening bioassays 1-3 (0 - 68% A. tumida mortality), A. tumida mortality approached higher levels in screening bioassay 4 (nearly 100% after 39 d) that suggest suitable applicability of some of the test nematodes as field controls for A. tumida. In the generational persistence bioassay, Steinernema Hobrave Cabanillas, Poinar &amp;amp; Raulston 7-12 strain and Heterorhabditis indica Poinar, Karunaka &amp;amp; David provided adequate A. tumida control for 19 wk after a single soil inoculation (76-94% mortality in A. tumida pupae). In the field bioassay, the same two nematode species also showed high virulence toward pupating A. tumida (88-100%) mortality. Our data suggest that nematode use may be an integral component of an integrated pest management scheme aimed at reducing A. tumida populations in bee colonies to tolerable levels.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000274261700001</an>
<do>10.1603/EC08384</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3319</id>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,Keith S.</a1>
<t1>Small hive beetle (Aethina tumida) oviposition behaviour in sealed brood cells with notes on the removal of the cell contents by European honey bees (Apis mellifera)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>210</sp>
<op>215</op>
<ab>Small hive beetles (Aethina tumida Murray) can lay eggs cryptically through the cappings of sealed bee brood cells. However, honey bees (Apis mellifera L.) can detect this activity and respond by removing cell cappings and contents (hygienic behaviour). We were interested in identifying conditions that regulate this syndrome of stimulus and response. Beetle oviposition rate (proportion of cells in which beetles perforate the capping and oviposit) into sealed brood cells was shown to be unaffected by a range of beetle densities created experimentally in caged sections of sealed brood. Oviposition rate was, however, increased when beetles had access to a sealed brood cell not only at the capping, but also along at least one side if the cell was next to an empty cell. Beetle oviposition rates into sealed brood cells were unaffected by the presence of Varroa destructor mites in the cell within a range of 1-4 mites per cell. The expression of hygienic behaviour toward beetle-perforated brood cells ranged from 10.6 - 77.2 % across colonies, but was unaffected by the colony strength parameters of bee population and cm(2) brood.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000258938700009</an>
<do>10.3827/IBRA.1.47.3.09</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3320</id>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,Keith S.</a1>
<t1>The effects of three acaricides on the developmental biology of small hive beetles (Aethina tumida)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>256</sp>
<op>259</op>
<ab>Small hive beetles (Aethina tumida, SHB) are an emerging problem for beekeepers internationally. Here we report how SHB development is affected by three acaricides, representing three chemical classes, that are used to control varroa mites (Varroa destructor): pyrethroids (fluvalinate - Apistan (R)), botanical extracts (thymol, camphor, menthol, eucalyptol - Apilife VAR (R)), and organophosphates (coumaphos - Checkmite+(R)). Our data indicate that the three acaricides vary in toxicity to SHB developmental stages. Apistan was toxic to feeding and wandering larvae but innocuous to adults while Apilife VAR only exhibited toxicity to perpetually-wandering larvae. Checkmite+ had the broadest toxicity, killing both larvae and adults. The three acaricides only affected pupal development with regard to d spent pupating. There was no increased mortality in pupae that were exposed to the acaricides as feeding or wandering larvae. Our data are useful for developing chemical controls for various developmental stages of SHB by demonstrating which developmental stages are most vulnerable to three chemical treatments.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000252127300008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3321</id>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,Keith S.</a1>
<t1>The effects of habitat type, ApilifeVar (TM), and screened bottom boards on small hive beetle (Aethina tumida) entry into honey bee (Apis mellifera) colonies</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>146</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>537</sp>
<op>539</op>
<ab>In this study we investigated how habitat type (open field vs. shaded area), Apilife VAR (TM), and screened bottom boards affect small hive beetle (Aethina tumida) entry into honey bee (Apis mellifera) colonies in late summer and fall. Data on ending number of beetles and number of deep frames of bees, pollen, honey and total brood were collected on day 27 for both of two trials. Bottom screens failed to repel beetles, although their use did not lead to greater beetle populations in test colonies. Bottom board type did not affect any of the colony strength parameters except honey in trial 2 (more honey in colonies with conventional wooden bottom boards than screened ones). The use of Apilife VAR did not affect beetle entry or any of the colony strength parameters. Habitat type did not affect any of the measured parameters except honey (more honey in colonies in the open than shaded area). The data suggest that small hive beetles disperse within an apiary, at least initially, without regard to habitat, presence of ApilifeVAR, or screened bottom boards.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000240971500020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3318</id>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<a1>Delaplane,Keith S.</a1>
<a1>Cline,Andrew</a1>
<a1>McHugh,Joseph V.</a1>
<t1>The association of multiple sap beetle species (Coleoptera : Nitidulidae) with western honey bee (Apis mellifera) colonies in North America</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>188</sp>
<op>189</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000258938700004</an>
<do>10.3827/IBRA.1.47.3.04</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3312</id>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<a1>Evans,Jay D.</a1>
<a1>Pettis,Jeff</a1>
<t1>Colony losses, managed colony population decline, and Colony Collapse Disorder in the United States</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>134</sp>
<op>136</op>
<no>PT: J; SI: Sp. Iss. SI</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000276090500030</an>
<do>10.3896/IBRA.1.49.1.30</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3327</id>
<a1>Goulson,D.</a1>
<a1>Darvill,B.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,J.</a1>
<a1>Knight,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Hanley,M. E.</a1>
<t1>Interspecific differences in response to novel landmarks in bumblebees (Bombus sp.)</t1>
<jf>Apidologie</jf>
<jo>Apidologie</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>NOV-DEC</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>619</sp>
<op>622</op>
<ab>We provide evidence for interspecific differences in the behaviour of bumblebees which suggests that there may be important differences in the way that they navigate. Bumblebees commonly investigate the novel landmark presented by a human standing in open countryside. When doing so they perform a characteristic flight similar to that observed when a naive bee first leaves the nest, suggesting that they are memorising the location of an unfamiliar landmark. We compare the frequency with which different bee species perform this behaviour. Striking patterns emerge. Only workers of certain bumblebee species were recorded investigating novel human landmarks, notably Bombus lapidarius and B. soroeensis. Other species such as B. pascuorum, B. hortorum and B. pratorum never performed this behaviour, yet were abundant in the study area. We suggest that this behaviour may be indicative of species with long foraging ranges and therefore greater need to pay attention to landmarks.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0044-8435</sn>
<an>000225889300007</an>
<do>10.1051/apido:2004053</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3315</id>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,J. D.</a1>
<t1>The small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray, Coleoptera: Nitidulidae): distribution, biology and control of an invasive species (vol 47, pg 181, 2008)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>81</sp>
<op>81</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000264029800017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3317</id>
<a1>Neumann,Peter</a1>
<a1>Ellis,James D.</a1>
<t1>The small hive beetle (Aethina tumida Murray, Coleoptera : Nitidulidae): distribution, biology and control of an invasive species</t1>
<jf>Journal of Apicultural Research</jf>
<jo>J.Apic.Res.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>183</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0021-8839</sn>
<an>000258938700001</an>
<do>10.3827/IBRA.1.47.3.01</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3342</id>
<a1>Westervelt,D.</a1>
<a1>Causey,D.</a1>
<a1>Neumann,P.</a1>
<a1>Ellis,J.</a1>
<a1>Hepburn,R.</a1>
<t1>Grease patties worsen small hive beetle infestations</t1>
<jf>American Bee Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Bee J.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>141</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>775</sp>
<op>775</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-7626</sn>
<an>000171853100008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
