
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3832</id>
<a1>Coler,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Boucias,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Frank,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Garciacanedo,A.</a1>
<a1>Pendland,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Characterization and Description of a Virus Causing Salivary-Gland Hyperplasia in the Housefly, Musca-Domestica</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>275</sp>
<op>282</op>
<ab>A double-stranded DNA virus was isolated from hyperplasic salivary glands of male and female houseflies, Musca domestica L. (Diptera: Muscidae), collected from a dairy in Alachua County, Florida, U.S.A. Sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS)-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) of this housefly salivary gland hyperplasia (SGH) virus revealed the presence of two major and eight minor structural polypeptides. Restriction endonuclease analysis indicated that the c. 137 kilobase pair DNA was double-stranded. Weekly sweep-net sampling of the fly population throughout the season (May-October, 1991) showed that 1.5-18.5% of the dissected flies possessed hyperplasic salivary glands. The virus replicated within the nuclei of the salivary gland cells and was transmitted per os to newly-emerged healthy adult flies.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>A1993LM80400012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3830</id>
<a1>De Moraes,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Funderburk,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<t1>Polymerase chain reaction techniques to detect multiple-nucleopolyhedrovirus in Anticarsia gemmatalis (Lepidoptera : Noctuidae) and predator populations in soybean</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>968</sp>
<op>975</op>
<ab>The detection of species and strains of baculoviruses in natural field insect populations facilitates ecological studies, risk assessment evaluation and quality control programs where wild type and/or recombinant baculoviruses are used. The polymerase chain reaction (PCR! was evaluated as a detection tool for determining viral persistence and spread in Anticarsia gemmatalis Hubner and predatory hemipteran populations in fields of soybean, Glycine max (L.) Merril. Tao isolates of the A. gemmatalis nucleopolyhedrovirus (AgMNPV-2D) and AgMNPV-D7) were applied individually and mixed in replicated field plots. The insect populations were sampled II 10, 15, 30, and 45 d after viral application and taken to the laboratory for PCR analysis. PCR analysis targeted the coding region of the viral polyhedrin gene and the highly variable homologous region 4 (hr4 region). The size of the expected products was 575 base pairs (Lp) for the polyhedrin-PCR and 1,726 bp (AgMNPV-2D) and 1,345 bp (AgMNPV-D7) for the hr4 region. The virus was detected in A. gemmatalis larvae and predators collected on all sample dates by PCR amplification of the polyhedrin region. AgMNPV was detected in the host and predator populations 1-45 d after application in the field. Virus movement into the control plots indicated that AgMNPV dispersed at a rate of 2-3 m per day. PCR amplification of the hr4 region was effective in distinguishing between AgMNPV-2D and AgMNPV-D7 isolates. The polymerase chain reaction proved to be a useful tool in ecological studies of this baculovirus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000075789800022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3831</id>
<a1>Demoraes,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Nation,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<t1>Organ-Culture of Salivary-Glands of Male Anastrepha-Suspensa (Diptera, Tephritidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>467</sp>
<op>473</op>
<ab>Salivary glands from male Caribbean fruit flies, Anastrepha suspensa, were isolated individually by dissection and cultured in Schneider&amp;#39;s medium containing 10% Fetal Bovine Serum and antibiotics. A total of 103 salivary glands were successfully cultured. Two different procedures were used to evaluate viability. A trypan blue dye test revealed that no more than 10% of the cultured cells were non-viable, since they acquired blue coloration. In the second set of experiments, acid phosphatase activity of the cultured glands was measured colorimetrically from absorbance at 415 nm of liberated p-nitrophenol. This method indicated that the cultured glands stayed metabolically active, with enzyme activity equal to that of freshly excised glands on the fifth, eighth, and fifteenth days of the experiment. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) showed no visual differences in tissue organization and size of individual cells when freshly excised salivary glands and cultured glands were compared. SEM showed that the cells of cultured glands were neither swollen nor shrunken, and close-up views showed no evidence of cell deterioration or lysing.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1995RX01300008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3825</id>
<a1>Grant,Rebecca J.</a1>
<a1>Kelley,Karen L.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<a1>Garcia-Maruniak,Alejandra</a1>
<a1>Barrett,Tom</a1>
<a1>Manire,Charles A.</a1>
<a1>Romero,Carlos H.</a1>
<t1>Expression from baculovirus and serological reactivity of the nucleocapsid protein of dolphin morbillivirus</t1>
<jf>Veterinary microbiology</jf>
<jo>Vet.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>JUL 14</fd>
<vo>143</vo>
<is>2-4</is>
<sp>384</sp>
<op>388</op>
<ab>The nucleocapsid (N) protein of dolphin morbillivirus (DMV) was expressed from a baculovirus (Autographa californica nuclear polyhedrosis virus) vector and shown by SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis to be about 57 kDa. Transmission electron microscopy revealed fully assembled nucleocapsid-like particles (NLPs) exhibiting the typical helical herringbone morphology. These NLPs were approximately 20-22 nm in diameter and varied in length from 50 to 100 nm. Purified DMV-N protein was used as antigen in an indirect ELISA (iELISA) and shown to react with rabbit and human antisera to measles virus (MV) and dog sera with antibodies to canine distemper virus (CDV). The iELISA was used for the demonstration of morbillivirus antibodies in the serum of cetaceans and manatees, showing potential as a serological tool for the mass screening of morbillivirus antibodies in marine mammals. (C) 2009 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0378-1135</sn>
<an>000279124500037</an>
<do>10.1016/j.vetmic.2009.11.019</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3829</id>
<a1>Levy,H. C.</a1>
<a1>Garcia-Maruniak,A.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<t1>Strain identification of Spodoptera frugiperda (Lepidoptera : Noctuidae) insects and cell line: PCR-RFLP of cytochrome oxidase C subunit I gene</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>186</sp>
<op>190</op>
<ab>A simple method was developed to analyze the two morphologically indistinguishable host-associated strains of the fall armyworm (FAW), Spodoptera frugiperda (J. E. Smith). Total DNA extracted from the FAW corn and rice strains, as well as from the S. frugiperda cell line (SF9) was used to PCR amplify a 569 base pairs region of the mitochondrial gene cytochrome oxidase subunit I (COI). The amplified DNA from the Spodoptera corn strain and the SF9 cell line contained a restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) marker, the MspI recognition site that was not present in the rice strain, This PCR-RFLP method does not require purification of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) or the use of radioactive isotopes, and differs from previous methods in that only a few nanograms of total DNA are needed to yield clear and accurate strain identification of individual insects.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000175200200022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3827</id>
<a1>Rios,L. M. V.</a1>
<a1>Sheu,J. -J</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Seino,K.</a1>
<a1>Zaretsky,H.</a1>
<a1>Long,M. T.</a1>
<t1>Environmental risk factors associated with West Nile virus clinical disease in Florida horses</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>357</sp>
<op>366</op>
<ab>The objective of this study was to examine the extrinsic risk factors of West Nile virus (WNV) clinical disease in Florida horses as established from confirmed and negative horses tested within the state from 2001 to 2003. An Arboviral Case Information Form (ACF) was submitted by a referring veterinarian at the time of testing to the Florida Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services on every horse suspected of a viral encephalitis in Florida. A follow-up survey that focused on arbovirus prevention and farm ecology was created and mailed to the owner of each tested horse. Data from the follow-up survey indicated peak WNV prevalence in the late summer months in Florida. Quarter horses were the most commonly affected breed. The WNV vaccine was highly protective and natural water on the property also had a protective association. Factors that increased the risk of WNV to horses were the use of fans and a stable construction of solid wood or cement. Some risk indicators were dead birds on the property and other ill animals on the property. Data from this retrospective study have helped identify factors associated with WNV transmission in equines in Florida. Horses that have not been vaccinated and show clinical signs of arboviral infection from June to November should be tested for WNV. Horses that have been vaccinated and show clinical signs should be tested when the vaccination was administered within 1 month or greater than 6 months prior to the onset of clinical symptoms associated with WN infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>000271974700007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3828</id>
<a1>Rodrigues,Sandra C. G.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<t1>Blood meal identification from mosquitoes collected at a commercial alligator farm</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>557</sp>
<op>560</op>
<ab>Outbreaks of West Nile virus on a Florida alligator farm prompted an investigation of which species of mosquitoes were feeding on the animals at the farm. Mosquitoes were collected on 4 separate overnight trips in September and October 2003 by using CO2-baited Centers for Disease Control light traps and wooden resting boxes that were placed inside or near the alligator housing pens. Mosquitoes were identified to species, bloodfed individuals were separated, and their abdomens were removed for DNA extraction. The DNA was tested to determine the vertebrate origin of the blood meal by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification by using 4 primer sets specific to crocodilians, alligators, mammals, and birds. PCR products were sequenced to identify hosts. Of the 37 mosquito blood meals tested, 13 blood meals were positively identified to species, and 7 blood meals of those 13 were from Alligator mississippiensis, the American alligator. Alligator blood was found in Culex erraticus, Mansonia dyari, and Ma. titillans, and to our knowledge, this represents the first report of these mosquito species feeding on American alligators.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000241120700034</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3826</id>
<a1>Watts,Stacey L.</a1>
<a1>Fitzpatrick,Daniel M.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,James E.</a1>
<t1>Blood Meal Identification from Florida Mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>619</sp>
<op>622</op>
<ab>Mosquitoes from different species endemic to North Florida were collected over a 12-month period and blood meal analyses were conducted on engorged females to determine the range of vertebrate hosts each species fed on. Thirty-one mosquito blood meals from 6 mosquito species were identified and blood meal hosts identified included horse, cow, armadillo, deer, raccoon rabbit, and owl. Several mosquitoes captured in the study should be considered potential bridge vectors for encephalitis viruses considering their ubiquity, their preference for mammalian blood meals, and their competence as viral vectors.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000273108500014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
