<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>141</id>
<a1>Baluch,J.</a1>
<a1>Sussman,R.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<t1>Induction of prophage lambda without amplification of recA protein</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; general genetics : MGG</jf>
<jo>Mol.Gen.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>178</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>317</sp>
<op>323</op>
<k1>Bacteriophage lambda/genetics/growth &amp; development/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Radiation</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Rifampin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Ultraviolet Rays</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virus Activation/drug effects</k1>
<ab>The requirement for amplified synthesis of recA protein in the UV-promoted induction of coliphage lambda was studied. We confirmed that a low concentration of rifampicin inhibited specifically the increased synthesis of recA protein after an inducing treatment (Satta and Pardee, 1978). Under these conditions, using an optimal dose of UV, E. coli lysogens were induced, producing active phage. The drug delayed the onset of induction and with increasing concentrations affected the yield of phage, but all the cells lysed. The results established that induction can proceed without amplification of recA protein synthesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0125036; 0 (Viral Proteins); 13292-46-1 (Rifampin); ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0026-8925; 0026-8925</sn>
<an>PMID: 6446647</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6446647</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>145</id>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<a1>Bedell,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Eppig,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Handel,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Williams,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Lyman,S. D.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Jenkins,N. A.</a1>
<a1>Copeland,N. G.</a1>
<t1>Developmental abnormalities in Steel17H mice result from a splicing defect in the steel factor cytoplasmic tail</t1>
<jf>Genes &amp; development</jf>
<jo>Genes Dev.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1832</sp>
<op>1842</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm</k1>
<k1>DNA</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development/genetics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Homozygote</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sex Differentiation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Stem Cell Factor</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>The murine dominant White spotting (W) and Steel (Sl) loci encode the c-kit tyrosine kinase receptor and its cognate ligand steel factor (SLF), respectively. Mutations at either locus produce deficiencies in the same three migratory cell populations--those giving rise to pigment cells, germ cells, and blood cells. The identification of the gene products of these two loci combined with the plethora of W and Sl mutations available for molecular analysis offers a unique opportunity to dissect the role of a tyrosine kinase receptor and its cognate ligand during development in a fashion not possible for most other mammalian genes. Among the most interesting Sl mutations available for study are those that induce sterility in only one sex. In studies described here, we show that one of these alleles, Sl17H, which in the homozygous condition induces sterility in males but not females, is the result of a splicing defect in the SLF cytoplasmic tail. We also characterize the nature of the germ cell defects in male and female Sl17H mice and show that both sexes are affected equally during embryonic but not postnatal development. These studies provide new insights into the role of SLF in germ cell development and indicate that the cytoplasmic domain of SLF is important for its normal biological function.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: HD-20575/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: N0I-CO-74101/CO/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8711660; 0 (Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Stem Cell Factor); 9007-49-2 (DNA); EC 2.7.10.1 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0890-9369; 0890-9369</sn>
<ad>Mammalian Genetics Laboratory, National Cancer Institute-Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center, Maryland 21702.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1383087</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1383087</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>146</id>
<a1>Carswell,S.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Alwine,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Construction and characterization of CV-1P cell lines which constitutively express the simian virus 40 agnoprotein: alteration of plaquing phenotype of viral agnogene mutants</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>415</sp>
<op>422</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Simian virus 40/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/analysis/biosynthesis/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Regulatory and Accessory Proteins</k1>
<ab>The simian virus 40 (SV40) agnoprotein is a 61-amino-acid polypeptide encoded in the leader region of some late viral mRNAs. Its function is unclear, although previous investigations suggest that the agnoprotein may function in late transcriptional regulation and virus assembly. To define the specific role(s) of agnoprotein in the SV40 lytic cycle, CV-1P cell lines were constructed in which the agnogene was stably integrated and constitutively expressed under the control of a retroviral long terminal repeat. Two types of cell lines were isolated. One group, typified by the cell line Ag18, produced low levels of agnogene-specific mRNA and agnoprotein. The other type, represented by a single isolate named Ag8, produced high levels of agnogene-specific mRNA and correspondingly high levels of agnoprotein. By indirect immunofluorescence, the agnoprotein was located predominantly in the cytoplasmic and perinuclear region of both cell lines; this is its site of localization in wild-type (WT)-infected CV-1P cells. Viruses that were agnoprotein-minus formed small plaques on normal CV-1P cells, but produced nearly WT-sized plaques on Ag18 cells. Conversely, the plaques formed on Ag8 cells infected with agnoprotein-minus mutants of WT SV40 were markedly smaller than the plaques formed by these viruses when they were grown on control cells. Overall, our results suggest that the agnoprotein is a trans-effector of virus production. The opposite effects on plaquing that were observed with Ag8 and Ag18 cells correlated with the very different levels of agnogene expression in the two cell lines. This suggests that the nature of the effect of the agnoprotein on virus production may vary depending on its intracellular concentration.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: CA-28379/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA-33656/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Regulatory and Accessory Proteins); 0 (agnoprotein, polyomavirus); OID: NLM: PMC288908; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 3021977</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3021977</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC288908</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>137</id>
<a1>Chamberlain,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Johnstone,K. A.</a1>
<a1>DuBose,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Simon,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Bartolomei,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<t1>Evidence for genetic modifiers of postnatal lethality in PWS-IC deletion mice</t1>
<jf>Human molecular genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Mol.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Dec 1</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>2971</sp>
<op>2977</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Genes, Lethal</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred Strains</k1>
<k1>Prader-Willi Syndrome/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<ab>Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS), most notably characterized by infantile hypotonia, short stature and morbid obesity, results from deficiencies in multiple genes that are subject to genomic imprinting. The usefulness of current mouse models of PWS has been limited by postnatal lethality in affected mice. Here, we report the survival of the PWS-imprinting center (IC) deletion mice on a variety of strain backgrounds. Expression analyses of the genes affected in the PWS region suggest that while there is low-level expression from both parental alleles in PWS-IC deletion pups, this expression does not explain their survival on certain strain backgrounds. Rather, the data provide evidence for strain-specific modifier genes that support the survival of PWS-IC deletion mice.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01 HD37872/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9208958; 0 (DNA Primers); 2004/09/30 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0964-6906; 0964-6906</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15459179; ddh314 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/hmg/ddh314</do>
<wp>20040930</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15459179</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>143</id>
<a1>Cohen,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Sussman,R.</a1>
<t1>Interaction of single-strand binding protein and RecA protein at the single-stranded DNA site</t1>
<jf>Journal of Molecular Biology</jf>
<jo>J.Mol.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Jul 15</fd>
<vo>167</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>901</sp>
<op>909</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Repair</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Deoxyadenine Nucleotides/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rec A Recombinases</k1>
<ab>Escherichia coli single-strand binding protein (SSB), which participates in DNA replication, also plays a role in DNA repair and induction of SOS functions. We show that the formation of RecA-dATP-single-stranded DNA complexes is influenced by the presence of SSB. In equilibrium reactions with limiting bacteriophage fd DNA, the mutant SSB113 protein competes more effectively than SSB with RecA protein for sites on the DNA. This result can account for the inability of strain ssb113 to amplify RecA protein synthesis and induce lambda prophage. SSB fails to displace RecA protein completely, even at very high concentrations. Both proteins inhibit the dATPase activity of RecA protein in spite of a large proportion of RecA protein still complexed to single-stranded DNA. Analysis of the multiple RecA protein activities and how they respond to the presence of SSB suggests that they fall into two distinct classes. Those that are enhanced by SSB (proteolysis and strand assimilation) and those inhibited by SSB (NTPase, reannealing of complementary single-stranded DNA). We propose a two-state model of conformational change of RecA protein, affected by the number of available free bases in single-stranded DNA relative to the number of RecA monomers, that would explain the choice of mutually exclusive catalytic activities.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AIGM 13415/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985088R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); 0 (Deoxyadenine Nucleotides); 1927-31-7 (2&amp;#39;-deoxyadenosine triphosphate); EC 2.7.7.- (Rec A Recombinases); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-2836; 0022-2836</sn>
<an>PMID: 6348299</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6348299</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>147</id>
<a1>Dolci,S.</a1>
<a1>Williams,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Ernst,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<a1>Lock,L. F.</a1>
<a1>Lyman,S. D.</a1>
<a1>Boswell,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Requirement for mast cell growth factor for primordial germ cell survival in culture</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Aug 29</fd>
<vo>352</vo>
<is>6338</is>
<sp>809</sp>
<op>811</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Division/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival/physiology</k1>
<k1>Embryo, Mammalian</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/cytology</k1>
<k1>Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors/genetics/pharmacology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Stem Cell Factor</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>Mast-cell growth factor (MGF) is encoded by the murine steel (Sl) locus and is a ligand for the tyrosine kinase receptor protein encoded by the proto-oncogene c-kit at the murine dominant white spotting (W) locus. Mutations at both these loci affect mast cells, primordial germ cells (PGCs), haemopoietic stem cells and melanocytes. In many Sl and W mutants, the rapid proliferation of PGC that normally occurs between day 7 and 13.5 of embryonic development fails to occur. As c-kit is expressed in PGCs while MGF is expressed in the surrounding mesenchyme, MGF might promote the proliferation of PGCs. Here we report that MGF is essential for PGC survival in culture, but does not stimulate PGC proliferation. Moreover, whereas both the transmembrane and soluble proteolytic cleavage forms of MGF stimulate mast-cell proliferation, soluble MGF has a relatively limited ability to support survival of PGCs in culture, thus explaining the sterility in mice carrying the steel-dickie (Sld) mutation, which encodes only a soluble form of MGF, and providing a functional role for a transmembrane growth factor.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 0410462; 0 (Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Stem Cell Factor); EC 2.7.10.1 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Mammalian Genetics Laboratory, NCl-Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center, Maryland 21702-1201.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1715518</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/352809a0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1715518</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>148</id>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<a1>de Miguel,M.</a1>
<a1>Cheng,L.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Primordial germ cells, stem cells and testicular cancer</t1>
<jf>APMIS : Acta Pathologica, Microbiologica, et Immunologica Scandinavica</jf>
<jo>APMIS</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>134</sp>
<op>141</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit/physiology</k1>
<k1>Stem Cells/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Testicular Neoplasms/pathology</k1>
<k1>Testis/embryology/pathology/physiology</k1>
<ab>Primordial Germ Cells (PGCs) arise in the mouse embryo as a small population of cells some way from the gonad anlagen. In order for the embryo to develop into a fully fertile adult animal the PGCs must increase in number and reach the gonad. Mutations causing sterility in the mouse have identified some of the genes involved in regulating PGC development and some of these genes have been molecularly cloned. Similarly, mutations affecting the development and differentiation of PGC-derived tumors (teratomas and teratocarcinomas) have been identified in certain strains of mice and these identify genes involved in the normal growth and differentiation of PGCs. These studies should help to define the role of growth factors in PGC development and in the development of germ-cell-derived tumors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 8803400; EC 2.7.10.1 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-kit); RF: 46; ppublish</no>
<pp>DENMARK</pp>
<sn>0903-4641; 0903-4641</sn>
<ad>Department of Cell Biology and Genetics, University of Alcala de Henares, Madrid, Spain.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9524571</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9524571</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>131</id>
<a1>DuBose,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Johnstone,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Smith,E. Y.</a1>
<a1>Hallett,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Atp10a, a gene adjacent to the PWS/AS gene cluster, is not imprinted in mouse and is insensitive to the PWS-IC</t1>
<jf>Neurogenetics</jf>
<jo>Neurogenetics</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>145</sp>
<op>151</op>
<ab>Mutations affecting a cluster of coordinately regulated imprinted genes located at 15q11-q13 underlie both Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) and Angelman syndrome (AS). Disruption of the predominately maternally expressed UBE3A locus is sufficient to meet diagnostic criteria for AS. However, AS patients with a deletion of the entire PWS/AS locus often have more severe traits than patients with point mutations in UBE3A suggesting that other genes contribute to the syndrome. ATP10A resides 200 kb telomeric to UBE3A and is of uncertain imprinted status. An initial report indicated bialleleic expression of the murine Atp10a in all tissues, but a subsequent report suggests that Atp10a is predominantly maternally expressed in the hippocampus and olfactory bulb. To resolve this discrepancy, we investigated Atp10a allelic expression in the brain, DNA methylation status, and sensitivity to mutations of the PWS imprinting center, an element required for imprinted gene expression in the region. We report that Atp10a is biallelically expressed in both the newborn and adult brain, and Atp10a allelic expression is insensitive to deletion or mutation of the PWS imprinting center. The CpG island associated with Atp10a is hypomethylated, a result consistent with the notion that Atp10a is not an imprinted gene.</ab>
<no>GR: HD037872/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9709714; 2009/08/21 [received]; 2009/10/09 [accepted]; 2009/11/06 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1364-6753; 1364-6745</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19894069</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s10048-009-0226-9</do>
<wp>20091106</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19894069</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>135</id>
<a1>Johnstone,K. A.</a1>
<a1>DuBose,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Futtner,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Elmore,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>A human imprinting centre demonstrates conserved acquisition but diverged maintenance of imprinting in a mouse model for Angelman syndrome imprinting defects</t1>
<jf>Human molecular genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Mol.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb 1</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>393</sp>
<op>404</op>
<k1>Angelman Syndrome/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Autoantigens</k1>
<k1>Conserved Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Genomic Imprinting/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Inheritance Patterns</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Obesity/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Prader-Willi Syndrome/genetics</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases/genetics</k1>
<k1>snRNP Core Proteins</k1>
<ab>Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) and Angelman syndrome (AS) are caused by the loss of imprinted gene expression from chromosome 15q11-q13. Imprinted gene expression in the region is regulated by a bipartite imprinting centre (IC), comprising the PWS-IC and the AS-IC. The PWS-IC is a positive regulatory element required for bidirectional activation of a number of paternally expressed genes. The function of the AS-IC appears to be to suppress PWS-IC function on the maternal chromosome through a methylation imprint acquired during female gametogenesis. Here we have placed the entire mouse locus under the control of a human PWS-IC by targeted replacement of the mouse PWS-IC with the equivalent human region. Paternal inheritance of the human PWS-IC demonstrates for the first time that a positive regulatory element in the PWS-IC has diverged. These mice show postnatal lethality and growth deficiency, phenotypes not previously attributed directly to the affected genes. Following maternal inheritance, the human PWS-IC is able to acquire a methylation imprint in mouse oocytes, suggesting that acquisition of the methylation imprint is conserved. However, the imprint is lost in somatic cells, showing that maintenance has diverged. This maternal imprinting defect results in expression of maternal Ube3a-as and repression of Ube3a in cis, providing evidence that Ube3a is regulated by its antisense and creating the first reported mouse model for AS imprinting defects.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: GM55272/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: HD37872/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9208958; 0 (Autoantigens); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear); 0 (UBE3A protein, human); 0 (snRNP Core Proteins); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases); 2005/12/20 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0964-6906; 0964-6906</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Center for Mammalian Genetics, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Fl 32610-0266, USA. karenj@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16368707; ddi456 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/hmg/ddi456</do>
<wp>20051220</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16368707</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>132</id>
<a1>Leung,K. N.</a1>
<a1>Vallero,R. O.</a1>
<a1>DuBose,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>LaSalle,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Imprinting regulates mammalian snoRNA-encoding chromatin decondensation and neuronal nucleolar size</t1>
<jf>Human molecular genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Mol.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov 15</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>4227</sp>
<op>4238</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleolus/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Chromatin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Chromatin Assembly and Disassembly</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Mammalian/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genomic Imprinting</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neurons/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Prader-Willi Syndrome/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Small Nucleolar/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>snRNP Core Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Imprinting, non-coding RNA and chromatin organization are modes of epigenetic regulation that modulate gene expression and are necessary for mammalian neurodevelopment. The only two known mammalian clusters of genes encoding small nucleolar RNAs (snoRNAs), SNRPN through UBE3A(15q11-q13/7qC) and GTL2(14q32.2/12qF1), are neuronally expressed, localized to imprinted loci and involved in at least five neurodevelopmental disorders. Deficiency of the paternal 15q11-q13 snoRNA HBII-85 locus is necessary to cause the neurodevelopmental disorder Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS). Here we show epigenetically regulated chromatin decondensation at snoRNA clusters in human and mouse brain. An 8-fold allele-specific decondensation of snoRNA chromatin was developmentally regulated specifically in maturing neurons, correlating with HBII-85 nucleolar accumulation and increased nucleolar size. Reciprocal mouse models revealed a genetic and epigenetic requirement of the 35 kb imprinting center (IC) at the Snrpn-Ube3a locus for transcriptionally regulated chromatin decondensation. PWS human brain and IC deletion mouse Purkinje neurons showed significantly decreased nucleolar size, demonstrating the essential role of the 15q11-q13 HBII-85 locus in neuronal nucleolar maturation. These results are relevant to understanding the molecular pathogenesis of multiple human neurodevelopmental disorders, including PWS and some causes of autism.</ab>
<no>GR: 1R01HD048799/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: C06 RR-12088-01/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: HD037872/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD041462-06A2/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD041462-07/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD048799-01A1/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD048799-02/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD048799-03/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD048799-04/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD048799-05/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R24MH068855/MH/NIMH NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9208958; 0 (Chromatin); 0 (RNA, Small Nucleolar); 0 (UBE3A protein, human); 0 (snRNP Core Proteins); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ube3a protein, mouse); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases); OID: NLM: PMC2766290; 2009/08/05 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1460-2083; 0964-6906</sn>
<ad>Microbiology and Immunology and Rowe Program in Human Genetics, UC Davis School of Medicine, Davis, CA 95616, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19656775; ddp373 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/hmg/ddp373</do>
<wp>20090805</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19656775</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2766290</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>134</id>
<a1>Maatouk,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Kellam,L. D.</a1>
<a1>Mann,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lei,H.</a1>
<a1>Li,E.</a1>
<a1>Bartolomei,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>DNA methylation is a primary mechanism for silencing postmigratory primordial germ cell genes in both germ cell and somatic cell lineages</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>133</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>3411</sp>
<op>3418</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Cell Lineage</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA (Cytosine-5-)-Methyltransferase/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Urogenital System/embryology</k1>
<k1>X Chromosome</k1>
<ab>DNA methylation is necessary for the silencing of endogenous retrotransposons and the maintenance of monoallelic gene expression at imprinted loci and on the X chromosome. Dynamic changes in DNA methylation occur during the initial stages of primordial germ cell development; however, all consequences of this epigenetic reprogramming are not understood. DNA demethylation in postmigratory primordial germ cells coincides with erasure of genomic imprints and reactivation of the inactive X chromosome, as well as ongoing germ cell differentiation events. To investigate a possible role for DNA methylation changes in germ cell differentiation, we have studied several marker genes that initiate expression at this time. Here, we show that the postmigratory germ cell-specific genes Mvh, Dazl and Scp3 are demethylated in germ cells, but not in somatic cells. Premature loss of genomic methylation in Dnmt1 mutant embryos leads to early expression of these genes as well as GCNA1, a widely used germ cell marker. In addition, GCNA1 is ectopically expressed by somatic cells in Dnmt1 mutants. These results provide in vivo evidence that postmigratory germ cell-specific genes are silenced by DNA methylation in both premigratory germ cells and somatic cells. This is the first example of ectopic gene activation in Dnmt1 mutant mice and suggests that dynamic changes in DNA methylation regulate tissue-specific gene expression of a set of primordial germ cell-specific genes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: HD38429/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 CA09126/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8701744; 0 (DNA Primers); EC 2.1.1.37 (DNA (Cytosine-5-)-Methyltransferase); EC 2.1.1.37 (DNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase 1); 2006/08/03 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-1991; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, PO Box 100266, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16887828; dev.02500 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1242/dev.02500</do>
<wp>20060803</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16887828</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>138</id>
<a1>Maatouk,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Continuing primordial germ cell differentiation in the mouse embryo is a cell-intrinsic program sensitive to DNA methylation</t1>
<jf>Developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>258</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>208</op>
<k1>Alkaline Phosphatase/analysis</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Nuclear/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Azacitidine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Biological Markers</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cell Division</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/drug effects/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Hydroxamic Acids/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Meiosis</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred Strains</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Oogonia/cytology/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sex Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Spermatogonia/cytology/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tetradecanoylphorbol Acetate/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Tretinoin/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>The initial cohort of mammalian gametes is established by the proliferation of primordial germ cells in the early embryo. Primordial germ cells first appear in extraembyronic tissues and subsequently migrate to the developing gonad. Soon after they arrive in the gonad, the germ cells cease dividing and undertake sexually dimorphic patterns of development. Male germ cells arrest mitotically, while female germ cells directly enter meiotic prophase I. These sex-specific differentiation events are imposed upon a group of sex-common differentiation events that are shared by XX and XY germ cells. We have studied the appearance of GCNA1, a postmigratory sex-common germ cell marker, in cultures of premigratory germ cells to investigate how this differentiation program is regulated. Cultures in which proliferation was either inhibited or stimulated displayed a similar extent of differentiation as controls, suggesting that some differentiation events are the result of a cell-intrinsic program and are independent of cell proliferation. We also found that GCNA1 expression was accelerated by agents which promote DNA demethylation or histone acetylation. These results suggest that genomic demethylation of proliferative phase primordial germ cells is a mechanism by which germ cell maturation is coordinated.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: HD38429/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 CA09126/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372762; 0 (Antigens, Nuclear); 0 (Biological Markers); 0 (Hydroxamic Acids); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 16561-29-8 (Tetradecanoylphorbol Acetate); 302-79-4 (Tretinoin); 320-67-2 (Azacitidine); 58880-19-6 (trichostatin A); EC 3.1.3.1 (Alkaline Phosphatase); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0012-1606; 0012-1606</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, P.O. Box 10266, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12781693; S0012160603001106 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12781693</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>149</id>
<a1>Paules,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Kasenally,A. B.</a1>
<a1>Ernst,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P.</a1>
<a1>Vande Woude,G. F.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of activated and normal mouse Mos gene in murine 3T3 cells</t1>
<jf>Oncogene</jf>
<jo>Oncogene</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2489</sp>
<op>2498</op>
<k1>3T3 Cells</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Cycle/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Codon</k1>
<k1>Cysteine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, mos</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyurea/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Methionine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Moloney murine sarcoma virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphoproteins/analysis/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphorylation</k1>
<k1>Protein-Tyrosine Kinases/analysis/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-mos/analysis/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Regulatory Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<ab>We have characterized the mouse Mos proto-oncogene product, pp39Mos, in murine fibroblasts. When expressed in NIH3T3 cells under the influence of the long terminal repeat regulatory element from Moloney murine sarcoma virus [NIH(pTS-1) cells], the Mos protein was present in low levels and had a half-life of about 30 min. In extracts from NIH(pTS-1) cells, we detected additional forms of Mos protein that apparently arose from internal initiation codons (p24Mos and p29Mos) or from upstream non-AUG initiation codons (p42Mos and p44Mos). The Mos protein was found to exist in these cells as a phosphoprotein, pp39Mos, and, when immunoprecipitated with an antiserum specific for the Mos N-terminus [anti-Mos(6-24)], had autophosphorylating kinase activity. We found that anti-Mos(6-24) also detected non-Mos protein kinase activity and non-Mos phosphoproteins in addition to p39Mos. We present evidence, on both the RNA and protein levels, that non-transformed mouse 3T3 cells do not express endogenous Mos.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: N01-CO-74101/CO/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8711562; 0 (Codon); 0 (Phosphoproteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 127-07-1 (Hydroxyurea); 52-90-4 (Cysteine); 63-68-3 (Methionine); EC 2.7.10.1 (Protein-Tyrosine Kinases); EC 2.7.11.1 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-mos); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-9232; 0950-9232</sn>
<ad>Mammalian Molecular Genetics Group, National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina 27709.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1461652</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1461652</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>133</id>
<a1>Peery,E. G.</a1>
<a1>Elmore,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<a1>Johnstone,K. A.</a1>
<t1>A targeted deletion upstream of Snrpn does not result in an imprinting defect</t1>
<jf>Mammalian genome : official journal of the International Mammalian Genome Society</jf>
<jo>Mamm.Genome</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>255</sp>
<op>262</op>
<k1>Angelman Syndrome/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Autoantigens/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>Genomic Imprinting/genetics</k1>
<k1>Inheritance Patterns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases/genetics</k1>
<k1>snRNP Core Proteins</k1>
<ab>Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) and Angelman syndrome (AS) result from the disturbance of imprinted gene expression within human chromosome 15q11-q13. Some cases of PWS and AS are caused by microdeletions near the SNRPN gene that disrupt a regulatory element termed the imprinting center (IC). The IC has two functional components; an element at the promoter of SNRPN involved in PWS (PWS-IC) and an element 35 kilobases (kb) upstream of SNRPN involved in AS (AS-IC). To further understand the function of the IC, we sought to create a mouse model for AS-IC mutations. We have generated two deletions at a location analogous to that of the human AS-IC. Neither deletion produced an imprinting defect as indicated by DNA methylation and gene expression analyses. These results indicate that no elements critical for AS-IC function in mouse reside within the 12.8-kb deleted region and suggest that the specific location of the AS-IC is not conserved between human and mouse.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: GM55272/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9100916; 0 (Autoantigens); 0 (Mkrn3 protein, mouse); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear); 0 (SNRPN protein, human); 0 (snRNP Core Proteins); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ube3a protein, mouse); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases); 2007/01/24 [received]; 2007/03/01 [accepted]; 2007/05/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0938-8990; 0938-8990</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17514346</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00335-007-9019-3</do>
<wp>20070519</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17514346</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>130</id>
<a1>Relkovic,D.</a1>
<a1>Doe,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Humby,T.</a1>
<a1>Johnstone,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Holland,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Hagan,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Wilkinson,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Isles,A. R.</a1>
<t1>Behavioural and cognitive abnormalities in an imprinting centre deletion mouse model for Prader-Willi syndrome</t1>
<jf>The European journal of neuroscience</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Neurosci.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>156</sp>
<op>164</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Attention</k1>
<k1>Body Weight</k1>
<k1>Brain/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Cognition Disorders/genetics/metabolism/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Discrimination (Psychology)</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Exploratory Behavior/physiology</k1>
<k1>Failure to Thrive/genetics/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genomic Imprinting</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Motor Activity/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Neuropsychological Tests</k1>
<k1>Prader-Willi Syndrome/genetics/physiopathology/psychology</k1>
<k1>Reaction Time</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Startle Reaction/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>The genes in the imprinted cluster on human chromosome 15q11-q13 are known to contribute to psychiatric conditions such as schizophrenia and autism. Major disruptions of this interval leading to a lack of paternal allele expression give rise to Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS), a neurodevelopmental disorder with core symptoms of a failure to thrive in infancy and, on emergence from infancy, learning disabilities and over-eating. Individuals with PWS also display a number of behavioural problems and an increased incidence of neuropsychiatric abnormalities, which recent work indicates involve aspects of frontal dysfunction. To begin to examine the contribution of genes in this interval to relevant psychological and behavioural phenotypes, we exploited the imprinting centre (IC) deletion mouse model for PWS (PWS-IC(+/-)) and the five-choice serial reaction time task (5-CSRTT), which is primarily an assay of visuospatial attention and response control that is highly sensitive to frontal manipulations. Locomotor activity, open-field behaviour and sensorimotor gating were also assessed. PWS-IC(+/-) mice displayed reduced locomotor activity, increased acoustic startle responses and decreased prepulse inhibition of startle responses. In the 5-CSRTT, the PWS-IC(+/-) mice showed deficits in discriminative response accuracy, increased correct reaction times and increased omissions. Task manipulations confirmed that these differences were likely to be due to impaired attention. Our data recapitulate several aspects of the PWS clinical condition, including findings consistent with frontal abnormalities, and may indicate novel contributions of the imprinted genes found in 15q11-q13 to behavioural and cognitive function generally.</ab>
<no>JID: 8918110; 2009/12/23 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>France</pp>
<sn>1460-9568; 0953-816X</sn>
<ad>Laboratory of Cognitive and Behavioural Neuroscience, The Babraham Institute, Babraham Research Campus, Cambridge, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20092561; EJN7048 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1460-9568.2009.07048.x</do>
<wp>20091223</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20092561</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>150</id>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Boyd,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Haffey,M. L.</a1>
<t1>DNA binding by the herpes simplex virus type 1 ICP4 protein is necessary for efficient down regulation of the ICP0 promoter</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2497</sp>
<op>2503</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Immediate-Early Proteins</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Simplexvirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The herpes simplex virus type 1 ICP4 and ICP0 polypeptides are immediate-early proteins that positively and negatively regulate expression of other viral genes in trans. ICP4 has recently been shown to bind DNA bearing the consensus sequence 5&amp;#39;-ATCGTCNNNN(T/C)CG(A/G)C-3&amp;#39;, present upstream of a number of viral genes. To test the hypothesis that this DNA-binding activity is involved in ICP4-mediated gene regulation, site-specific mutagenesis was employed to mutate the version of this sequence in the promoter of the ICP0 gene. The mutation eliminated detectable binding of ICP4 to the promoter as measured in vitro by a gel electrophoresis band shift assay. The ability of the mutated ICP0 promoter to direct synthesis of a reporter gene was also investigated in a transient transfection assay. Whereas ICP4 was found to transactivate the wild-type ICP0 promoter two- to threefold, the mutated promoter was transactivated seven- to ninefold. In assays containing the ICP0 transactivator gene, ICP4 down regulated the wild-type promoter far more efficiently than the mutated promoter. Finally, both the wild-type and mutated ICP0 promoters exhibited a similar response to ICP4 in transfections that included a vector expressing the viral transactivator protein VP16. These experiments suggest that the sequence-specific DNA-binding activity of ICP4 is an essential element of its role as a negative regulator of gene expression.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Immediate-Early Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (herpes simplex virus, type 1 protein ICP4); EC 6.3.2.19 (Ubiquitin-Protein Ligases); EC 6.3.2.19 (Vmw110 protein, Human herpesvirus 1); OID: NLM: PMC250711; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Virology, Squibb Institute for Medical Research, Princeton, New Jersey 08540.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2542567</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2542567</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC250711</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>151</id>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Shenk,T.</a1>
<t1>Simian virus 40 agnoprotein facilitates normal nuclear location of the major capsid polypeptide and cell-to-cell spread of virus</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1098</sp>
<op>1106</op>
<k1>Capsid/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Compartmentation</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>Simian virus 40/physiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Regulatory and Accessory Proteins</k1>
<k1>Virion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>The simian virus 40 agnoprotein is a 61-amino-acid, highly basic polypeptide that is coded within the 5&amp;#39; leader of late 16S mRNAs. To better understand agnoprotein function and to more effectively differentiate cis-from trans-acting effects of an agnogene mutation, we constructed a mutant virus that carries a single-base-pair substitution and fails to produce agnoprotein. pm 1493 contains a T/A to A/T transversion at sequence position 335. This mutation converts the agnoprotein initiation codon from ATG to TTG, preventing synthesis of the protein. The mutant displays only a modest growth defect in CV-1P and AGMK cells and no defect in BSC-1 cells. Early-gene expression, DNA replication, synthesis of late viral products, and the kinetics of virion assembly all appear normal in pm 1493-infected CV-1P cells. Immunofluorescent studies, however, indicate that localization of the major capsid polypeptide VP1 is different in mutant- than wild-type virus-infected cells. Furthermore, the lack of agnoprotein led to inefficient release of mature virus from the infected cell. Agnogene mutants could be severely compromised in their ability to propagate in monkeys given their reduced capacity for cell-to-cell spread.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: CA38965/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Regulatory and Accessory Proteins); 0 (agnoprotein, polyomavirus); OID: NLM: PMC253355; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 3023661</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3023661</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC253355</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>142</id>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Sussman,R.</a1>
<t1>Cobalt: an effector of E. coli recA protein activity</t1>
<jf>Nucleic acids research</jf>
<jo>Nucleic Acids Res.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Sep 11</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>5239</sp>
<op>5253</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphatases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cations, Divalent</k1>
<k1>Cobalt/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/drug effects/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Rec A Recombinases</k1>
<ab>Studies of cation requirements in the recA-catalyzed proteolysis of lambda repressor and strand assimilation reactions have demonstrated that Co2+ significantly enhances both activities. In the presence of 4mM MgCl2, the optimal concentration of CoCl2 for proteolysis was 1mM. 2mM Co2+ increased the rate and extent of D-loop formation as measured by membrane filtration. Cobalt did not replace Mg2+ for the ssDNA-dependent ATPase activity of recA, and did not affect the rate of hydrolysis of ATP, measured over a wide range of DNA concentrations. Cobalt did prevent the Mg-dependent ssDNA renaturation catalyzed by recA protein. Membrane filter binding assays established that Co2+ increases the affinity of recA protein for ssDNA with ATP, dATP, or ATP gamma S as cofactors. The dissociation of recA protein from ssDNA-nucleoside triphosphate complex was much slower with CoCl2. This metal provides an excellent tool for dissecting the various activities inherent in recA protein.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 13415/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0411011; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Cations, Divalent); 7440-48-4 (Cobalt); EC 2.7.7.- (Rec A Recombinases); EC 3.6.1.- (Adenosine Triphosphatases); OID: NLM: PMC320868; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0305-1048; 0305-1048</sn>
<an>PMID: 6216455</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6216455</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC320868</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>144</id>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Sussman,R.</a1>
<t1>Escherichia coli single-strand DNA binding protein from wild type and lexC113 mutant affects in vitro proteolytic cleavage of phage lambda repressor</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>2832</sp>
<op>2835</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacteriophage lambda/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Repair</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli</k1>
<k1>Lysogeny</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>In Escherichia coli, the single-strand DNA-binding protein (SSB) is required for DNA replication. A mutation of the ssb gene, lexC113, imparts to the cells UV sensitivity and inability to induce lambda prophage and to amplify recA protein, indicating participation of SSB in DNA repair and viral induction processes. We report the effect of purified SSB, isolated from wild-type and lexC113 strains, on the recA-mediated proteolysis of lambda repressor in vitro. (i) These proteins abolished the inhibition produced by excess single-strand DNA and (ii) in the presence of the binding proteins, the apparent stoichiometry--1 monomer of recA to 6 nucleotides of single-strand DNA [Craig, N. L. &amp;amp; Roberts, J. W. (1980) Nature (London) 283, 26-30] was no longer observed. (iii) At the optimal concentration--1 protein monomer to 8 nucleotides--they increased the rate and extent of repressor cleavage at all single-strand DNA concentrations, including that observed at the apparent optimal DNA concentration. (iv) At binding protein/nucleotide ratios greater than or equal to 1:3, SSB from lexC113 inhibited repressor cleavage while that from wild type did not. (v) These results are consistent with the notion that SSB is probably involved in the induction of prophages in vivo.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 13415/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); OID: NLM: PMC346300; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 6211675</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6211675</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC346300</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>153</id>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Bixler,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Cheng,L.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Long-term proliferation of mouse primordial germ cells in culture</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Oct 8</fd>
<vo>359</vo>
<is>6395</is>
<sp>550</sp>
<op>551</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Division</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 2/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/cytology</k1>
<k1>Growth Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Immunoenzyme Techniques</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-6</k1>
<k1>Leukemia Inhibitory Factor</k1>
<k1>Lymphokines/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Stem Cell Factor</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Primordial germ cells (PGCs) are first identifiable as a population of about eight alkaline phosphatase-positive cells in the 7.0 days postcoitum mouse embryo. During the next 6 days of development they proliferate to give rise to the 25,000 cells that will establish the meiotic population. Steel factor is required for PGC survival both in vivo and in vitro and together with leukaemia inhibitory factor stimulates PGC proliferation in vitro. In feeder-dependent culture, PGCs will proliferate for up to 7 days, but their numbers eventually decline and their proliferative capacity is only a fraction of that seen in vivo. Here we report a further factor that stimulates PGC proliferation in vitro, basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF). Furthermore, bFGF, in the presence of steel factor and leukaemia inhibitory factor, stimulates long-term proliferation of PGCs, leading to the derivation of large colonies of cells. These embryonic germ cells resemble embryonic stem cells, pluripotent cells derived from preimplantation embryos, or feeder-dependent embryonal carcinoma cells, pluripotent stem cells of PGC-derived tumours (teratomas and teratocarcinomas). To our knowledge, these results provide the first system for long-term culture of PGCs.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0410462; 0 (Growth Inhibitors); 0 (Hematopoietic Cell Growth Factors); 0 (Interleukin-6); 0 (Leukemia Inhibitory Factor); 0 (Lif protein, mouse); 0 (Lymphokines); 0 (Stem Cell Factor); 103107-01-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 2); CIN: Nature. 1992 Oct 8;359(6395):482-3. PMID: 1406966; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Mammalian Genetics Laboratory, ABL-Basic Research Program, NCI-FCRDC, Frederick, Maryland 21702-1201.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1383830</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/359550a0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1383830</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>152</id>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Ortiz,M.</a1>
<a1>Keller,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Role of fibroblast growth factors and their receptors in mouse primordial germ cell growth</t1>
<jf>Biology of reproduction</jf>
<jo>Biol.Reprod.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>59</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1224</sp>
<op>1229</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Division</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 2/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Iodine Radioisotopes</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Meiosis</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C3H</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mitosis</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Fibroblast Growth Factor/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Stem Cells/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Primordial germ cells (PGCs) are the embryonic progenitors of mature germ cells. During their proliferative stage, murine PGCs may be transiently cultured on mitotically inactive feeder layers. This culture system has permitted identification of several growth factors active toward PGCs. We and others have previously identified basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) as a powerful mitogen in this system. Here we characterize some of the functions of bFGF in PGC culture. Our data demonstrate that fibroblast growth factor (FGF) receptors I and II are present in the developing gonad and are consistent with expression of these receptors by PGCs. Moreover, PGCs can bind radiolabeled bFGF in vitro, demonstrating that the factor can act directly on these cells. While mitotic PGCs of either sex are shown to bind radiolabeled bFGF, oogonia that are undergoing meiotic arrest exhibit reduced bFGF binding, indicating potential developmental regulation of an FGF receptor.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0207224; 0 (Iodine Radioisotopes); 0 (Receptors, Fibroblast Growth Factor); 103107-01-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0006-3363; 0006-3363</sn>
<ad>Cell Biology of Development and Differentiation Group, ABL-Basic Research Program, SAIC-Frederick, National Cancer Institute-Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center, Frederick, Maryland 21702-1201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9780331</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9780331</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>155</id>
<a1>Richards,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Enders,G. C.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Activin and TGFbeta limit murine primordial germ cell proliferation</t1>
<jf>Developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar 15</fd>
<vo>207</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>470</sp>
<op>475</op>
<k1>Activin Receptors</k1>
<k1>Activins</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Cell Division/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Histocytochemistry</k1>
<k1>Inhibins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred Strains</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Growth Factor/genetics</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Transforming Growth Factor beta/genetics</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transforming Growth Factor beta/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>Mammalian primordial germ cells (PGCs) proliferate as they migrate from their initial location in the extraembryonic mesoderm to the genital ridge, the gonadal anlage. Once in the genital ridge, PGCs cease dividing and differentiate according to their gender. To identify ligands that might limit PGC proliferation, we analyzed growth factor receptors encoded in RNA obtained from purified germ cells shortly after their arrival in the genital ridge. Receptors for two members of the TGFbeta superfamily were found, TGFbeta1 and activin. As the signal-transducing domains of both receptor systems are highly conserved, the effects of both TGFbeta1 and activin on PGCs would be expected to be similar. We found that both ligands limited the accumulation of germ cells in primary PGC cultures. BrdU incorporation assays demonstrated that either ligand inhibits PGC proliferation. These results suggest that these signal transduction pathways are important elements of the mechanism that determines germ cell endowment.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; CI: Copyright 1999; JID: 0372762; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Receptors, Growth Factor); 0 (Receptors, Transforming Growth Factor beta); 0 (Transforming Growth Factor beta); 104625-48-1 (Activins); 57285-09-3 (Inhibins); EC 2.7.11.30 (Activin Receptors); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0012-1606; 0012-1606</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10068477; S0012-1606(98)99174-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/dbio.1998.9174</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10068477</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>154</id>
<a1>Richards,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Enders,G. C.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Differentiation of murine premigratory primordial germ cells in culture</t1>
<jf>Biology of reproduction</jf>
<jo>Biol.Reprod.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1146</sp>
<op>1151</op>
<k1>Alkaline Phosphatase/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Germ Cells/cytology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Receptor Subfamily 6, Group A, Member 1</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Cytoplasmic and Nuclear/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>In the mouse embryo, primordial germ cells first appear in the extraembryonic mesoderm and divide rapidly while migrating to the fetal gonad. Shortly after their arrival in the gonad, germ cells sexually differentiate as proliferation ceases. Previous studies have established that primordial germ cells proliferate and migrate in feeder layer culture. To explore cellular regulation of fetal germ cell development, we have used germ cell nuclear antigen 1 (GCNA1), a marker normally expressed only in postmigratory germ cells, to investigate the developmental potency of both pre- and postmigratory cells in this culture system. We found that explanted premigratory germ cells will initiate expression of this marker and are, therefore, capable of undertaking some aspects of gonocyte differentiation without intimate exposure to the fetal gonad. We have also tested whether postmigratory gonocytes are stable in culture. As detected by either alkaline phosphatase or GCNA1, we did not detect long-term survival of either prospermatogonia or oogonia under conditions that support the survival, proliferation, and differentiation of earlier premigratory cells. These observations are consistent with an autonomous cellular mechanism governing the initial stages of gonocyte differentiation, and suggest that differentiation towards gonocytes is accompanied by a change in requirements for cell survival.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 0207224; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Nr6a1 protein, mouse); 0 (Nuclear Receptor Subfamily 6, Group A, Member 1); 0 (Receptors, Cytoplasmic and Nuclear); EC 3.1.3.1 (Alkaline Phosphatase); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0006-3363; 0006-3363</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10491656</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10491656</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>136</id>
<a1>Rodic,N.</a1>
<a1>Oka,M.</a1>
<a1>Hamazaki,T.</a1>
<a1>Murawski,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Jorgensen,M.</a1>
<a1>Maatouk,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Li,E.</a1>
<a1>Terada,N.</a1>
<t1>DNA methylation is required for silencing of ant4, an adenine nucleotide translocase selectively expressed in mouse embryonic stem cells and germ cells</t1>
<jf>Stem cells (Dayton, Ohio)</jf>
<jo>Stem Cells</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1314</sp>
<op>1323</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA (Cytosine-5-)-Methyltransferase/deficiency/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>Embryo, Mammalian/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mitochondrial ADP, ATP Translocases/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Spermatozoa/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Stem Cells/cytology/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Testis/cytology</k1>
<ab>The capacity for cellular differentiation is governed not only by the repertoire of available transcription factors but by the accessibility of cis-regulatory elements. Studying changes in epigenetic modifications during stem cell differentiation will help us understand how cells maintain or lose differentiation potential. We investigated changes in DNA methylation during the transition of pluripotent embryonic stem cells (ESCs) into differentiated cell types. Using a methylation-sensitive restriction fingerprinting method, we identified a novel adenine nucleotide (ADP/ATP) translocase gene, Ant4, that was selectively hypomethylated and expressed in undifferentiated mouse ESCs. In contrast to other pluripotent stem cell-specific genes such as Oct-4 and Nanog, the Ant4 gene was readily derepressed in differentiated cells after 5-aza-2&amp;#39;-deoxycytidine treatment. Moreover, expression of de novo DNA methyltransferases Dnmt3a and Dnmt3b was essential for repression and DNA methylation of the Ant4 gene during ESC differentiation. Although the deduced amino acid sequence of Ant4 is highly homologous to the previously identified Ant isoforms, the expression of Ant4 was uniquely restricted to developing gametes in adult mice, and its promoter hypomethylation was observed only in testis. Additionally, Ant4 was expressed in primordial germ cells. These data indicate that Ant4 is a pluripotent stem cell- and germ cell-specific isoform of adenine nucleotide translocase in mouse and that DNA methylation plays a primary role in its transcriptional silencing in somatic cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: DK59699/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: RR17001/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9304532; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 9068-80-8 (Mitochondrial ADP, ATP Translocases); EC 2.1.1.- (DNA methyltransferase 3B); EC 2.1.1.37 (DNA (Cytosine-5-)-Methyltransferase); EC 2.1.1.37 (DNA methyltransferase 3A); 2005/07/28 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1066-5099; 1066-5099</sn>
<ad>Department of Pathology, University of Florida College of Medicine, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16051982; 2005-0119 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1634/stemcells.2005-0119</do>
<wp>20050728</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16051982</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>140</id>
<a1>Sussman,R.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J.</a1>
<a1>Calame,K.</a1>
<a1>Baluch,J.</a1>
<t1>Interaction of bacteriophage lambda repressor with nonoperator DNA containing single-strand gaps</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5817</sp>
<op>5821</op>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Binding, Competitive</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Lysogeny</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Structure-Activity Relationship</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>In direct binding assays, purified lambdaind+ repressor displayed high affinity for nonoperator DNA containing single-strand gaps. Its affinity for this same DNA but completely double-stranded, nicked, or denatured was considerably lower. In contrast, purified lambdaind- repressor had 1/10th the affinity for the gapped DNA, a level comparable to that of purified lac repressor. In the presence of limiting amounts of ind+ repressor, nonoperator DNA containing gaps could be shown to compete effectively with lambda DNA for binding of repressor. A previous model of lambda induction [Sussman, R. &amp;amp; Ben-Zeev, H. (1975) Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 72, 1973--1976], based on the assumption that this phenomenon involves the binding of repressor to lesions in the host DNA, is reevaluated in the light of the data reported here.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); OID: NLM: PMC393066; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 282604</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>282604</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC393066</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>156</id>
<a1>Weinheimer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Boyd,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Durham,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Boyle,D. R.,2nd</a1>
<t1>Deletion of the VP16 open reading frame of herpes simplex virus type 1</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>258</sp>
<op>269</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Transformed</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Simplexvirus/genetics/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/genetics</k1>
<ab>VP16 (also called Vmw65 and alpha TIF) is a structural protein of herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) that trans-induces HSV-1 immediate-early gene transcription. This report describes an HSV-1 VP16 deletion mutant that was constructed and propagated in a cell line transformed with a VP16 expression vector. The VP16 deletion mutant replicated like wild-type HSV-1 during infection of the VP16-expressing cell line. Deletion mutant virions propagated in this cell line contained wild-type, cell-derived VP16 protein that was recruited during virion assembly and was functional for immediate-early gene trans-induction. The mutant failed to replicate during subsequent infection of cells that do not express VP16, as determined in plaque assays and single-step replication assays. The deletion mutant induced nearly normal levels of viral DNA synthesis and capsid production during these infections, but it induced slightly lower levels of viral DNA encapsidation and appeared by transmission electron microscopy to be defective in further steps of virion maturation. A genetic revertant of the deletion mutant that was restored for VP16-coding sequences exhibited fully wild-type replication properties in both VP16-expressing and nonexpressing cells. The absence of VP16 protein synthesis at late times of HSV-1 infection prevents the production of infectious progeny virus and correlates with a profound defect in HSV-1 particle assembly.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081120; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Viral Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC238283; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Virology, Bristol-Myers Squibb Pharmaceutical Research Institute, Princeton, New Jersey 08543-4000.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1309245</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1309245</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC238283</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>157</id>
<a1>Wickramasinghe,D.</a1>
<a1>Becker,S.</a1>
<a1>Ernst,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Centanni,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Tessarollo,L.</a1>
<a1>Grabel,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Donovan,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Two CDC25 homologues are differentially expressed during mouse development</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>2047</sp>
<op>2056</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blastocyst/physiology</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Cell Cycle Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphoprotein Phosphatases/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Protein Tyrosine Phosphatases/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>cdc25 Phosphatases</k1>
<ab>The cdc25 gene product is a tyrosine phosphatase that acts as an initiator of M-phase in eukaryotic cell cycles by activating p34cdc2. Here we describe the cloning and characterization of the developmental expression pattern of two mouse cdc25 homologs. Sequence comparison of the mouse genes with human CDC25 genes reveal that they are most likely the mouse homologs of human CDC25A and CDC25B respectively. Mouse cdc25a, which has not been described previously, shares 84% sequence identity with human CDC25A and has a highly conserved phosphatase domain characteristic of all cdc25 genes. A glutathione-S-transferase-cdc25a fusion protein can hydrolyze para-nitro-phenylphosphate confirming that cdc25a is a phosphatase. In adult mice, cdc25a transcripts are expressed at high levels in the testis and at lower levels in the ovary, particularly in germ cells; a pattern similar to that of twn, a Drosophila homolog of cdc25. Lower levels of transcript are also observed in kidney, liver, heart and muscle, a transcription pattern that partially overlaps, but is distinct from that of cdc25b. Similarly, in the postimplantation embryo cdc25a transcripts are expressed in a pattern that differs from that of cdc25b. cdc25a expression is observed in most developing embryonic organs while cdc25b expression is more restricted. An extended analysis of cdc25a and cdc25b expression in preimplantation embryos has also been carried out. These studies reveal that cdc25b transcripts are expressed in the one-cell embryo, decline at the two-cell stage and are re-expressed at the four-cell stage, following the switch from maternal to zygotic transcription which mirrors the expression of string, another Drosophila homolog of cdc25. In comparison, cdc25a is not expressed in the preimplantation embryo until the late blastocyst stage of development, correlating with the establishment of a more typical G1 phase in the embryonic cell cycles. Both cdc25a and cdc25b transcripts are expressed at high levels in the inner cell mass and the trophectoderm, which proliferate rapidly prior to implantation. These data suggest the cdc25 genes may have distinct roles in regulating the pattern of cell division during mouse embryogensis and gametogenesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; GENBANK/U27323; GR: N01-CO-74101/CO/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8701744; 0 (Cell Cycle Proteins); 0 (DNA Primers); EC 3.1.3.16 (Phosphoprotein Phosphatases); EC 3.1.3.48 (Protein Tyrosine Phosphatases); EC 3.1.3.48 (cdc25 Phosphatases); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-1991; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>ABL-Basic Research Program, NCI-Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center, Fort Detrick, MD 21702, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7635051</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7635051</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>158</id>
<a1>Yang,T.</a1>
<a1>Adamson,T. E.</a1>
<a1>Resnick,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Leff,S.</a1>
<a1>Wevrick,R.</a1>
<a1>Francke,U.</a1>
<a1>Jenkins,N. A.</a1>
<a1>Copeland,N. G.</a1>
<a1>Brannan,C. I.</a1>
<t1>A mouse model for Prader-Willi syndrome imprinting-centre mutations</t1>
<jf>Nature genetics</jf>
<jo>Nat.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>25</sp>
<op>31</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Autoantigens/genetics</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genomic Imprinting</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Prader-Willi Syndrome/genetics</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>snRNP Core Proteins</k1>
<ab>Imprinting in the 15q11-q13 region involves an &amp;#39;imprinting centre&amp;#39; (IC), mapping in part to the promoter and first exon of SNRPN. Deletion of this IC abolishes local paternally derived gene expression and results in Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS). We have created two deletion mutations in mice to understand PWS and the mechanism of this IC. Mice harbouring an intragenic deletion in Snrpn are phenotypically normal, suggesting that mutations of SNRPN are not sufficient to induce PWS. Mice with a larger deletion involving both Snrpn and the putative PWS-IC lack expression of the imprinted genes Zfp127 (mouse homologue of ZNF127), Ndn and Ipw, and manifest several phenotypes common to PWS infants. These data demonstrate that both the position of the IC and its role in the coordinate expression of genes is conserved between mouse and human, and indicate that the mouse is a suitable model system in which to investigate the molecular mechanisms of imprinting in this region of the genome.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: GM55272/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9216904; 0 (Autoantigens); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins, Small Nuclear); 0 (SNRPN protein, human); 0 (snRNP Core Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1061-4036; 1061-4036</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida Brain Institute, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9590284</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/ng0598-25</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9590284</pmid></reference></refworks>
