<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3792</id>
<t1>Encyclopedia of entomology. Second edition.</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<sp>4346</sp>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera,John L.</a2>
<sn>978-1-4020-6242-1</sn>
<an>ZOOREC:ZOOR14601005681 ER</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3746</id>
<a1>Alzubaidi,F. S.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Utilization of Food and Nitrogen by the Beet Armyworm, Spodoptera-Exigua (Hubner) (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae), in Relation to Food Type and Dietary Nitrogen Levels</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1604</sp>
<op>1608</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 13</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1984AAM3000031</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3749</id>
<a1>Alzubaidi,F. S.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Application of Different Nitrogen Levels to the Host Plant and Cannibalistic Behavior of Beet Armyworm, Spodoptera-Exigua (Hubner) (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1687</sp>
<op>1689</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1983RW92000014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3703</id>
<a1>Baker,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematodes and nematomorphs as control agents of grasshoppers and locusts</t1>
<jf>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada</jf>
<jo>Mem.Entomol.Soc.Can.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<is>171</is>
<sp>157</sp>
<op>211</op>
<ab>The relationship of nematodes and nematomorphs with grasshoppers and locusts is reviewed, emphasizing the actual or potential role of these parasitoids in microbial management. There are records of mermithids parasitizing grasshoppers worldwide, and they are considered important biological control agents in some grassland ecosystems of Europe, North and South America, Papua New Guinea, New Zealand, and Australia. Nematomorphs, although widely distributed, are uncommon parasitoids of grasshoppers, and their dependence on free-standing water for host infection and apparent host specificity are considered drawbacks to their use in biological control programmes. The ascaridids, spirurids, and acanthocephalans are parasites of birds and mammals, and may use grasshoppers as intermediate hosts. They have been shown to debilitate grasshopper hosts in laboratory studies, but their primary role as parasites of vertebrates precludes any consideration as biological control agents. Rhabditids do not naturally parasitize grasshoppers, but recent advances in mass-culturing techniques have given them a potential role as bioinsecticides for the control of grasshoppers. Quantitative data on the effects of nematodes and nematomorphs on agricultural pests, including grasshoppers and locusts, are generally lacking. However, there is evidence that some, particularly mermithids, are important in the population dynamics of grasshoppers and locusts. Keys to the identification of the Various &amp;#39;worms&amp;#39; found in grasshoppers and locusts are provided, including keys to the species of mermithids.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0071-075X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000071215300012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3693</id>
<a1>Barbara,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Development of a toxic bait for control of eastern lubber grasshopper (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>584</sp>
<op>591</op>
<ab>This study assessed baits for eastern lubber grasshopper, Romalea guttata (Houttuyn). When offered a choice among several grain-based baits (rolled oats, wheat bran, oat bran, yeast, corn meal, cornflakes) and vegetable oils (canola, corn, peanut, soybean), eastern lubber grasshopper adults preferred bait consisting of wheat bran carrier with corn oil as an added phagostimulant. Other carriers were accepted but consumed less frequently. Discrimination by eastern lubber grasshoppers among oils was poor. Similarly, addition of flavorings (peppermint, anise, lemon, banana) resulted in few significant effects. The carbaryl, wheat bran, and oil bait developed in this study was effective at causing eastern lubber grasshopper mortality in field-cage studies. Significant mortality occurred even though grasshoppers had to locate dishes of bait in a large cage, and could feed on daylilies, or grass growing through the bottom of the cage, rather than on the bran flakes. Consumption of as little as a single carbaryl-treated bran flake could induce mortality, although individuals varied greatly in their susceptibility. The bait matrix developed in this study was readily consumed when in the presence of some plant species. We expect that wheat bran and corn oil bait would be most effective as protection for less preferred plants (tomato, pepper, eggplant, leek, parsley, fennel, daylily, lily of the Nile, and canna lily) because baits were readily consumed in the presence of these plants. Plants that are readily consumed in the presence of bait (preferred plants) included butter crunch lettuce, carrot, yellow squash, cauliflower, collards, green onion, chive, cucumber, cabbage, cantalope, endive, red leaf lettuce, society garlic, caladium, and amaryllis. Baits are likely to be less effective in the presence of such plants. On average, vegetables in Solanaceae (i.e., tomato, pepper, and eggplant) and Apiaceae (i.e., fennel and parsley) elicited high levels of bait-feeding activity, indicating that these vegetables were not highly preferred. The plants tested from Liliaceae, Cucurbitaceae, Asteraceae, and Brassicaceae elicited an intermediate-to-low level of bait feeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000183648000013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3771</id>
<a1>Barbosa,P.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Harrington,E. A.</a1>
<t1>Gypsy Moth Parasitoid Complex in Western Massachusetts - Study of Parasitoids in Area of High and Low Host Density</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>842</sp>
<op>846</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 26</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1975AT38100042</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3742</id>
<a1>Brewer,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Deshon,R. E.</a1>
<a1>Walmsley,M. L.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Foliar Nitrogen Levels on Survival, Development, and Reproduction of Western Spruce Budworm, Choristoneura-Occidentalis (Lepidoptera, Tortricidae)</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>117</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>23</sp>
<op>32</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 33</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1985AAX8200004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3786</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Encyclopedia of entomology. Volume 1, A-C.</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>Ed. 2</is>
<sp>lxiv + 1144</sp>
<ab>Volume 1 of this second edition of the Encyclopedia of Entomology covers the letters A-C and is the first of four volumes providing a broad overview of insects and their close relatives, focussing on major taxa of insects, their near relatives and other insect groups; morphology and anatomy; physiology; genetics; behaviour; ecology and evolution; microbiology and pathology; humans and insects; notable and pioneering entomologists; pest management; pesticides and pesticide application; pest groups and their management; medical and veterinary entomology; and arthropods of economic importance. Explanations of some common terms and detailed descriptions of insects and subjects have been provided by distinguished entomologists from around the world. Material has been referenced providing a link to entomological literature.</ab>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2>
<sn>978-1-4020-6242-1</sn>
<an>CABI:20083298251</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3787</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Encyclopedia of entomology. Volume 2, D-K.</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>Ed. 2</is>
<sp>2096</sp>
<ab>Volume 2 of this second edition of the Encyclopedia of Entomology covers the letters D-K and is the second of four volumes providing a broad overview of insects and their close relatives, focussing on major taxa of insects, their near relatives and other insect groups; morphology and anatomy; physiology; genetics; behaviour; ecology and evolution; microbiology and pathology; humans and insects; notable and pioneering entomologists; pest management; pesticides and pesticide application; pest groups and their management; medical and veterinary entomology; and arthropods of economic importance. Explanations of some common terms and detailed descriptions of insects and subjects have been provided by distinguished entomologists from around the world. Material has been referenced providing a link to entomological literature.</ab>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2>
<sn>978-1-4020-6242-1</sn>
<an>CABI:20083298252</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3788</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Encyclopedia of entomology. Volume 3, L-R.</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>Ed. 2</is>
<sp>3224</sp>
<ab>Volume 3 of this second edition of the Encyclopedia of Entomology covers the letters L-R and is the third of four volumes providing a broad overview of insects and their close relatives, focussing on major taxa of insects, their near relatives and other insect groups; morphology and anatomy; physiology; genetics; behaviour; ecology and evolution; microbiology and pathology; humans and insects; notable and pioneering entomologists; pest management; pesticides and pesticide application; pest groups and their management; medical and veterinary entomology; and arthropods of economic importance. Explanations of some common terms and detailed descriptions of insects and subjects have been provided by distinguished entomologists from around the world. Material has been referenced providing a link to entomological literature.</ab>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2>
<sn>978-1-4020-6242-1</sn>
<an>CABI:20083298253</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3785</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Encyclopedia of entomology. Volume 4, S-Z.</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>Ed. 2</is>
<sp>4346</sp>
<ab>Volume 4 of this second edition of the Encyclopedia of Entomology covers the letters S-Z and is the fourth of four volumes providing a broad overview of insects and their close relatives, focussing on major taxa of insects, their near relatives and other insect groups; morphology and anatomy; physiology; genetics; behaviour; ecology and evolution; microbiology and pathology; humans and insects; notable and pioneering entomologists; pest management; pesticides and pesticide application; pest groups and their management; medical and veterinary entomology; and arthropods of economic importance. Explanations of some common terms and detailed descriptions of insects and subjects have been provided by distinguished entomologists from around the world. Material has been referenced providing a link to entomological literature.</ab>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2>
<sn>978-1-4020-6242-1</sn>
<an>CABI:20083298254</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3688</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Relationships between insect pests and weeds: an evolutionary perspective</t1>
<jf>Weed Science</jf>
<jo>Weed Sci.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>892</sp>
<op>901</op>
<ab>Weeds are an important plant resource for insects, although feeding by insects on weeds can have both positive and negative effects on crop productivity. Weeds also indirectly affect crops via their influence on beneficial insects, and by harboring plant and insect diseases. Weeds may affect the ability of dispersing insects to locate crop plants. The host relationship between insects and plants is highly variable, ranging from very specialized to generalized feeding behaviors. Despite the myriad interactions of weeds and insects, many aspects of the relationship are predictable. Most insects, including crop pests, are specialists, and preadapted to feed only on some plants, often within a single plant family. Even polyphagous insects often have a distinct preference hierarchy, feeding more widely only when preferred hosts are unavailable. Use of plants by insects is a dynamic interaction, with characteristics of the insect (e.g., mandible structure) and the plant (e.g., allelochemicals) affecting feeding behavior. Thus, weeds that are closely related to crops are particularly important in harboring insects that attack those crops. Crop production practices should seek to sever the taxonomic association between the crop and the weeds found within the crop, and nearby, by eliminating weeds related to the crop. This will make it less likely that insects will move easily from weed to crop plants, that damaging population densities of insects will develop in the field, and that insect vectors that harbor plant diseases will be harbored in the field. Particularly important integrated pest management practices include crop rotation, reduced use of chemical herbicides, and management of weeds in noncultivated areas.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: Symposium on the Interactions Between Weeds and Other Pests in Agricultural Ecosystems; CY: 2003; CL: Orlando, FL; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0043-1745 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000233835300020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3780</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Relationships between insect pests and weeds: an evolutionary perspective</t1>
<jf>Weed Science</jf>
<jo>Weed Sci.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>NOV-DEC</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>892</sp>
<op>901</op>
<ab>Weeds are an important plant resource for insects, although feeding by insects on weeds can have both positive and negative effects on crop productivity. Weeds also indirectly affect crops via their influence on beneficial insects, and by harboring plant and insect diseases. Weeds may affect the ability of dispersing insects to locate crop plants. The host relationship between insects and plants is highly variable, ranging from very specialized to generalized feeding behaviors. Despite the myriad interactions of weeds and insects, many aspects of the relationship are predictable. Most insects, including crop pests, are specialists, and preadapted to feed only on some plants, often within a single plant family. Even polyphagous insects often have a distinct preference hierarchy, feeding more widely only when preferred hosts are unavailable. Use of plants by insects is a dynamic interaction, with characteristics of the insect (e.g., mandible structure) and the plant (e.g., allelochemicals) affecting feeding behavior. Thus, weeds that are closely related to crops are particularly important in harboring insects that attack those crops. Crop production practices should seek to sever the taxonomic association between the crop and the weeds found within the crop, and nearby, by eliminating weeds related to the crop. This will make it less likely that insects will move easily from weed to crop plants, that damaging population densities of insects will develop in the field, and that insect vectors that harbor plant diseases will be harbored in the field. Particularly important integrated pest management practices include crop rotation, reduced use of chemical herbicides, and management of weeds in noncultivated areas.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0043-1745</sn>
<an>000233835300020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3698</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Handbook of vegetable pests.</t1>
<jf>Handbook of vegetable pests</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<sp>xiv + 729 pp.</sp>
<ab>Primarily intended for horticulturists, cooperative extension service personnel, crop consultants and members of the agrochemical industry, this handbook provides an overview of vegetable crops grown in North America and the major groups of pests that attack them. The appearance, life history and pest management strategies are described. Major and minor pests known to attack each crop and the distinguishing characteristics of the pests are listed. Keys to important groups of pests are appended.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2>
<an>CABI:20013091433</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3714</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Differentiation of Nymphal Instars in Schistocerca-Americana (Orthoptera, Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>175</sp>
<op>179</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1993KV45300015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3713</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Host-Plant Selection by Schistocerca-Americana (Orthoptera, Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>127</sp>
<op>133</op>
<ab>The preference of Schistocerca americana (Drury) for 40 potential host plants relative to bahiagrass, Paspalum notatum, was determined in two-choice and four-choice tests. Although highly polyphagous, S. americana demonstrated clear preference and nonpreference for certain species. Host selection by small nymphs (instars 3 and 4), large nymphs (instars 5 and 6), and adults was highly correlated. Host selection by spring-generation grasshoppers was highly correlated with summer-generation host preference. The presence of alternate hosts, especially nonpreferred species, resulted in modified host-selection behavior wherein grasshoppers were more discriminating in four-choice tests than two-choice tests.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 15</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1993KM00800018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3733</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Observations on Natural and Experimental Parasitism of Insects by Mermis-Nigrescens Dujardin (Nematoda, Mermithidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>159</sp>
<op>162</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987G751600026</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3744</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Determination of Host Plant Preferences of Hemileuca-Oliviae (Lepidoptera, Saturniidae), Paropomala-Wyomingensis (Orthoptera, Acrididae), and Diapheromera-Veli (Orthoptera, Phasmatidae) by Choice Test and Crop Analysis</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>58</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>465</sp>
<op>471</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1985ANT0600012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3748</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Instar Number in Range Caterpillar, Hemileuca-Oliviae Cockerell (Lepidoptera, Saturniidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>344</sp>
<op>347</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1984SS67900020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3757</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Some Effects of Infestation by Bean Aphid, Aphis-Fabae Scopoli, on Carbohydrate and Protein-Levels in Sugarbeet Plants, and Procedures for Estimating Economic Injury Levels</t1>
<jf>Zeitschrift Fur Angewandte Entomologie-Journal of Applied Entomology</jf>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>374</sp>
<op>384</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0044-2240 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1981ML60800007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3760</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Parasitism of the Palestriped Flea Beetle (Chrysomelidae) by an Allantonematid Nematode Howardula Sp - Effect of Parasitism on Adult Longevity and Sugarbeet Foliage Consumption</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>348</sp>
<op>349</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979GV90200006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3762</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Zebra Caterpillar (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) - Foliage Consumption and Development of Larvae on Sugarbeet</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>111</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>905</sp>
<op>909</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979HK19000006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3764</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Consumption of Sugarbeet Foliage by Palestriped Flea Beetle (Coleoptera Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>301</sp>
<op>303</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1978EW26600039</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3765</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Consumption of Sugarbeet Foliage by Saltmarsh Caterpillar Lepidoptera-Arctiidae</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>661</sp>
<op>663</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1978FR91500030</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3766</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Studies of Host Plant Preference and Suitability Exhibited by Early-Instar Range Caterpillar Larvae</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>738</sp>
<op>740</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 20</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1978FV25300029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3768</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Variegated Cutworm - Consumption of Sugarbeet Foliage and Development on Sugarbeet (Lepidoptera-Noctuidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>978</sp>
<op>980</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1978GF10100037</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3775</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Damage to Asparagus Seedlings by Brachycolus-Asparagi</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1974</yr>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>447</sp>
<op>448</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 11</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1974T420300040</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3770</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Barbosa,P.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Natural Diets and Larval Density on Gypsy Moth, Lymantria-Dispar (Lepidoptera-Orgyiidae), Egg Mass Characteristics</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<vo>109</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1313</sp>
<op>1318</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 37</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1977EB41000003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3773</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Barbosa,P.</a1>
<t1>Transmission of Nuclear-Polyhedrosis Virus to Gypsy Moth(lepidoptera-Lymantriidae) Larvae by Calosoma-Sycophanta(coleoptera-Carabidae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>593</sp>
<op>594</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 23</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1975AM05000042</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3769</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Barbosa,P.</a1>
<a1>Hagedorn,H. H.</a1>
<t1>Yolk and Yolk Depletion of Gypsy Moth Eggs - Implications for Population Quality - Lepidoptera-Lymantriidae</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<vo>70</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>40</sp>
<op>42</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 40</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1977CS79900009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3750</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Detling,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Parton,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Assessment of Range Caterpillar (Lepidoptera, Saturniidae) Effects with a Grassland Simulation-Model</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1088</sp>
<op>1094</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 7</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1983RV56700027</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3716</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<t1>Potential for Biological-Control of Soil Insects in the Caribbean Basin using Entomopathogenic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>525</sp>
<op>532</op>
<ab>The numerous species and geographic isolates of entomopathogenic nematodes have a diversity of biological attributes which make them adaptable to many uses, especially management of soil pests. Entomopathogenic nematodes are viable substitutes for soil insecticides due to wide host range, persistence, mobility, safety, ease of application, and absence of registration restrictions. Efficacy is often comparable to chemical insecticides, which tend not to perform well in soil. Although soil is generally a very suitable habitat for nematodes, abiotic and biotic constraints are serious impediments in some locales. Surveys should be conducted in Caribbean countries to identify pre-adapted strains. Recent advances have made nematodes more economic to produce, and storage life has been extended. Entomopathogenic nematodes are appropriate for the Caribbean Basin environment due to favorable soil, humidity and temperatures, occurrence of hosts throughout most of the year, and a high incidence of damage caused by coleopterans and lepidopterans-pests which are usually quite susceptible to infection. In vitro production methods, which require medium-level technology and low cost labor, may be particularly suitable for the Caribbean.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: WORKSHOP ON IMPORTANT ARTHROPOD PESTS OF THE CARIBBEAN BASIN AMENABLE TO BIOLOGICAL CONTROL : HOMOPTERA, COLEOPTERA, LEPIDOPTERA; CY: APR 08-10, 1991; CL: ORLANDO, FL; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992KH68100016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3741</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,D. C.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Adult Western Corn-Rootworm (Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae) Ear Feeding on Irrigated Field Corn in Colorado</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1609</sp>
<op>1612</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1986F375200038</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3722</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Turick,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Responses of Melanoplus-Sanguinipes and M-Differentialis (Orthoptera, Acrididae) to Fenoxycarb</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1163</sp>
<op>1168</op>
<ab>Nymphs and adults of the grasshopper Melanoplus sanguinipes (F.) and nymphs of M. differentialis (Thomas) were treated with the juvenile hormone analog fenoxycarb by topical application or by ingestion of bait. Nymphal mortality was variable, but both species were significantly affected by topical treatment. Neither species succumbed to bait treatment. Both methods of application produced significant effects on nymphal development time, but the nature of the response varied with time of application, and the degree of the response (&amp;lt; 20%) was of questionable biological importance. Fenoxycarb induced morphological deformities, principally wing twisting. Temporary induction of green coloration was also noted, especially in M. differentialis. The most important effect of fenoxycarb application was disruption of reproduction; topical application of M. sanguinipes nymphs at 100-mu-g/insect resulted in complete elimination of egg pod production, and ingestion of 1 and 5% fenoxycarb on bran bait reduced oviposition. M. sanguinipes treated as adults were unaffected by fenoxycarb administered by topical application of up to 100-mu-g/insect or ingestion of 10% bran bait.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 7</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1991GA81600008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3684</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,J. G.</a1>
<t1>Behavioral responses of Schistocerca americana (Orthoptera : Acrididae) to azadirex (Neem)-treated host plants</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>117</sp>
<op>122</op>
<ab>Azadirex (azadirachtin and other biologically active extracts from neem trees) has been shown to have considerable potential to be used in integrated pest management systems based on its growth regulator/ insecticide properties. Less well known are the antifeedant properties. The feeding-deterrent properties of a commercial azadirex formulation (Azatrol EC) were evaluated using both no-choice and choice tests, the American grasshopper, Schistocerca americana (Drury), and four host plants [savoy cabbage, Brassica oleracea variety capitata L.; cos (romaine) lettuce, Lactuca sativa variety longifolia Lam.; sweet orange, Citrus sinensis variety Hamlin L.; and peregrina, Jatropha integerrima Jacq.]. These studies demonstrated that azadirex application can significantly affect the feeding behavior of grasshoppers. Some degree of protection can be afforded to plants that differ markedly in their innate attractiveness to the insect, although the level of protection varies among hosts. The tendency of grasshoppers to sometimes feed on azadirex-treated foliage suggests that it will be difficult to prevent damage from occurring at all times, on all hosts. No evidence of rapid habituation to azadirex was detected. Rapid loss of efficacy was observed under field conditions, suggesting that daily retreatment might be necessary to maintain protection of plants from feeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000243917200017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3790</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,J. G.</a1>
<t1>Behavioral responses of Schistocerca americana (Orthoptera: Acrididae) to azadirex (neem)-treated host plants.</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>117</sp>
<op>122</op>
<ab>Azadirex (azadirachtin and other biologically active extracts from neem trees) has been shown to have considerable potential to be used in integrated pest management systems based on its growth regulator/insecticide properties. Less well known are the antifeedant properties. The feeding-deterrent properties of a commercial azadirex formulation (Azatrol EC) were evaluated using both no-choice and choice tests, the American grasshopper, Schistocerca americana (Drury), and four host plants [savoy cabbage, Brassica oleracea variety capitata L.; cos (romaine) lettuce, Lactuca sativa variety longifolia Lam.; sweet orange, Citrus sinensis variety Hamlin L.; and peregrina, Jatropha integerrima Jacq.]. These studies demonstrated that azadirex application can significantly affect the feeding behavior of grasshoppers. Some degree of protection can be afforded to plants that differ markedly in their innate attractiveness to the insect, although the level of protection varies among hosts. The tendency of grasshoppers to sometimes feed on azadirex-treated foliage suggests that it will be difficult to prevent damage from occurring at all times, on all hosts. No evidence of rapid habituation to azadirex was detected. Rapid loss of efficacy was observed under field conditions, suggesting that daily retreatment might be necessary to maintain protection of plants from feeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>CABI:20093307470</an>
<do>10.1603/0022-0493(2007)100[117:BROSAO]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3745</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Gardner,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Stermitz,F. R.</a1>
<t1>Cantharidin Levels in Blister Beetles (Coleoptera, Meloidae) Associated with Alfalfa in Colorado</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1052</sp>
<op>1055</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 25</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1985ASP8200011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3729</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<t1>Geographic-Variation in Effects of Weather on Grasshopper Infestation</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>8</sp>
<op>14</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 30</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1989T327800002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3734</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Chapman,P. L.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Plant-Density and Late-Season Defoliation on Yield of Field Beans</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>274</sp>
<op>280</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987G892600048</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3761</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Kanost,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of the Zebra Caterpillar (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) to Autographa-Californica Nuclear Polyhedrosis-Virus</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>570</sp>
<op>572</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 8</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979HJ96400030</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3772</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Lilly,J. H.</a1>
<t1>Bionomics and Biotic Control of Asparagus Beetle, Crioceris-Asparagi, in Western Massachusetts</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>93</sp>
<op>96</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1975V655400019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3774</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Lilly,J. H.</a1>
<t1>Tetrastichus-Asparagi, (Hymenoptera-Eulophidae) Parasitoid of Asparagus Beetle(coleoptera-Chrysomelidae) - some Aspects of Host-Parasitoid Interaction</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>595</sp>
<op>596</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1975AM05000043</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3756</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Naranjo,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Packard,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Vapor Density and Water-Loss from Eggs of the Range Caterpillar, Hemileuca-Oliviae (Lepidoptera, Saturniidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>104</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1981LN96300020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3758</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Roltsch,W. J.</a1>
<t1>The Predatory Ant Formica-Neoclara - Effect on Within-Field Bean Aphid Distribution, and Activity in Relation to Thermal Conditions</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>578</sp>
<op>586</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1981LZ69100020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3759</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Roltsch,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Response of Wheat Seedlings to Actual and Simulated Migratory Grasshopper (Orthoptera, Acrididae) Defoliation</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>258</sp>
<op>261</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 45</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1980JP46700022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3704</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Scherer,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Simkins,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Habitat associations of grasshoppers at the MacArthur Agro-Ecology Research Center, Lake Placid, Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>80</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>261</op>
<ab>Grasshopper populations of the MacArthur Agro-Ecology Research Center at Lake Placid, in south-central Florida were monitored during the period 1993-1995. Samples were taken monthly during the spring, summer, and autumn months from 3 discrete habitats: citrus groves, improved pastures, and weedy margins of irrigation ditches. The grasshopper species assemblage at the Research Center consisted of 16 species in the family Acrididae, 7 species in the family Tettigoniidae, and 3 species in the family Tetrigidae. Family and species dominance varied among habitats. Grasshopper abundance was highest in citrus groves and ditch margins, and these habitats had proportionally more acridids. Pastures were inhabited by fewer grasshoppers, and were dominated by tettigoniids. The nymphal tettigoniid population was relatively high, and adult population relatively low in pastures. Tetrigids were infrequent in all habitats. The most abundant grasshoppers were Dichromorpha viridis (Scudder) and Conocephalus fasciatus (DeGeer), grass-feeding species that were abundant in all habitats sampled. Collection of Melanoplus bispinosus Scudder is a new state record. Potential effects of grasshoppers and land management on avifauna are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 2</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1997XE18000011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3691</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Scott,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Walker,T. J.</a1>
<t1>Field guide to grasshoppers, katydids and crickets of the United States.</t1>
<jf>Field guide to grasshoppers, katydids and crickets of the United States</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<sp>vii + 249 pp.</sp>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<a2>Capinera,J. L.</a2><a2> Scott,R. D.</a2><a2>Walker,T. J.</a2>
<an>CABI:20053070522</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3791</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Scott,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Walker,T. J.</a1>
<t1>Field guide to grasshoppers, katydids and crickets of the United States.</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<sp>vii + 249</sp>
<no>PT: B</no>
<a2>Capinera, J. L. Scott, R. D. Walker,T.J.</a2>
<sn>0-8014-8948-2</sn>
<an>CABI:20053070522</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3754</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Sechrist,T. S.</a1>
<t1>Grasshopper (Acrididae) - Host Plant Associations - Response of Grasshopper Populations to Cattle Grazing Intensity</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>114</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1055</sp>
<op>1062</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 43</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1982PR56300007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3699</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Squitier,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal activity of photoactive dyes to American and migratory grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>662</sp>
<op>666</op>
<ab>Many photoactive dyes are relatively nontoxic to vertebrates despite their insecticidal properties. Several photoactive dyes known to be toric to some groups of insects were evaluated at various concentrations for toxicity to American and migratory grasshoppers in laboratory and field studies. Rose bengal and phloxine B were effective at inducing mortality of grasshoppers when applied at 2 and 5% to bran bait, though erythrosin B and uranine were ineffective. Partial replacement of phloxine with uranine in dye mixtures resulted in no significant loss of efficacy. Some indication of feeding inhibition was observed at high dye concentrations, so minimum effective dosages, probably 2%, are optimal. Phloxine B and rose bengal appeared to be stable upon exposure to sunlight, and able to withstand at least 24 h of sunlight without significant degradation. Dyes such as phloxine B could be a viable grasshopper control agent for small or medium-sized grasshopper species because mortality can be induced by consumption of a single flake dusted with 5% dye, and yet pose little hazard to vertebrates. Large species such as American grasshopper must consume several flakes before mortality is induced.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000088599000017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3735</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,D. C.</a1>
<t1>Dynamics and Structure of Grasshopper Assemblages in Shortgrass Prairie</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>567</sp>
<op>575</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 13</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987J510900005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3747</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Hollingsworth,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Taxonomic and Ecological Characteristics of Crop Pests in Colorado</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>202</sp>
<op>206</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1984SN55000041</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3767</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Walmsley,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Visual Responses of some Sugarbeet Insects to Sticky Traps and Water Pan Traps of various Colors</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>926</sp>
<op>927</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 10</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1978GF10100025</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3743</id>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Weissling,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Schweizer,E. E.</a1>
<t1>Compatibility of Intercropping with Mechanized Agriculture - Effects of Strip Intercropping of Pinto Beans and Sweet Corn on Insect Abundance in Colorado</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>354</sp>
<op>357</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 16</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1985AFT0300014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3694</id>
<a1>Capinera,John L.</a1>
<t1>North American vegetable pests: The pattern of invasion.</t1>
<jf>American Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Am.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>20</sp>
<op>39</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>1046-2821 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<an>BIOSIS:PREV200300035737</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3779</id>
<a1>Capinera,John L.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,Jason G.</a1>
<t1>Behavioral responses of Schistocerca americana (Orthoptera : Acrididae) to azadirex (Neem)-treated host plants</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>117</sp>
<op>122</op>
<ab>Azadirex (azadirachtin and other biologically active extracts from neem trees) has been shown to have considerable potential to be used in integrated pest management systems based on its growth regulator/ insecticide properties. Less well known are the antifeedant properties. The feeding-deterrent properties of a commercial azadirex formulation (Azatrol EC) were evaluated using both no-choice and choice tests, the American grasshopper, Schistocerca americana (Drury), and four host plants [savoy cabbage, Brassica oleracea variety capitata L.; cos (romaine) lettuce, Lactuca sativa variety longifolia Lam.; sweet orange, Citrus sinensis variety Hamlin L.; and peregrina, Jatropha integerrima Jacq.]. These studies demonstrated that azadirex application can significantly affect the feeding behavior of grasshoppers. Some degree of protection can be afforded to plants that differ markedly in their innate attractiveness to the insect, although the level of protection varies among hosts. The tendency of grasshoppers to sometimes feed on azadirex-treated foliage suggests that it will be difficult to prevent damage from occurring at all times, on all hosts. No evidence of rapid habituation to azadirex was detected. Rapid loss of efficacy was observed under field conditions, suggesting that daily retreatment might be necessary to maintain protection of plants from feeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000243917200017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3683</id>
<a1>Carrillo,D.</a1>
<a1>Pena,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Host Plants on Successful Parasitism by Haeckeliania sperata (Hymenoptera: Trichogrammatidae) on Diaprepes abbreviatus (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Eggs</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1565</sp>
<op>1572</op>
<ab>Diaprepes abbreviates L. is a highly polyphagous root weevil that causes damage to several fruit crops, ornamental plants, and other naturally occurring plants in Florida. Haeckeliania sperata Pinto is a gregarious endoparasitoid that attacks D. abbreviates eggs. We hypothesized that the reproductive success of H. sperata is affected by the host plant of D. abbreviates. Six host plants with varying degrees of pubescence were used to determine the effect of leaf trichomes on the searching behavior and success of parasitism by H. sperata. No-choice tests showed that H. sperata was able to parasitize Diaprepes eggs laid on the six host plants. However, the plants with a high trichome density on their leaves had a lower percent of parasitism than the plants with smoother leaves. Removing trichomes from a host plant showed that the presence of some leaf trichomes had a negative effect on the overall searching efficiency of H. sperata. The presence of trichomes decreased the total distance traveled and increased the total search time of IT sperata females, resulting in a lower searching speed. Multiple regression analysis was used to establish the relationship between percent parasitism and leaf trichome density, leaf thickness, and the searching speed of H. sperata. Searching speed was the best predictor of percent parasitism; this parameter could be used to predict the suitability of host plants for the establishment of H. sperata. Our findings suggest that the reproductive success of H. sperata is affected by the host plant of D. abbreviatus.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000261633200024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3776</id>
<a1>Carrillo,Daniel</a1>
<a1>Pena,Jorge E.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,John L.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Host Plants on Successful Parasitism by Haeckeliania sperata (Hymenoptera: Trichogrammatidae) on Diaprepes abbreviatus (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Eggs</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1565</sp>
<op>1572</op>
<ab>Diaprepes abbreviates L. is a highly polyphagous root weevil that causes damage to several fruit crops, ornamental plants, and other naturally occurring plants in Florida. Haeckeliania sperata Pinto is a gregarious endoparasitoid that attacks D. abbreviates eggs. We hypothesized that the reproductive success of H. sperata is affected by the host plant of D. abbreviates. Six host plants with varying degrees of pubescence were used to determine the effect of leaf trichomes on the searching behavior and success of parasitism by H. sperata. No-choice tests showed that H. sperata was able to parasitize Diaprepes eggs laid on the six host plants. However, the plants with a high trichome density on their leaves had a lower percent of parasitism than the plants with smoother leaves. Removing trichomes from a host plant showed that the presence of some leaf trichomes had a negative effect on the overall searching efficiency of H. sperata. The presence of trichomes decreased the total distance traveled and increased the total search time of IT sperata females, resulting in a lower searching speed. Multiple regression analysis was used to establish the relationship between percent parasitism and leaf trichome density, leaf thickness, and the searching speed of H. sperata. Searching speed was the best predictor of percent parasitism; this parameter could be used to predict the suitability of host plants for the establishment of H. sperata. Our findings suggest that the reproductive success of H. sperata is affected by the host plant of D. abbreviatus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000261633200024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3710</id>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Herbivore Diet on the Pathogenesis of Steinernema-Carpocapsae (Nematoda, Steinernematidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>487</sp>
<op>491</op>
<ab>The relationship of insect diet to pathogenicity and reproduction of an entomogenous nematode, Steinernema carpocapsae All strain (Nematode: Steinernematidae) was investigated in the black cutworm, Agrotis ipsilon (Hufnagel). Cutworms fed on collard foliage or on artificial diet were equally infected by and killed by S. carpocapsae. However, nematode progeny production was lower in collard-fed cutworm larvae. The difference in progeny production corresponded to difference in lipid content of cutworms; 210 nematodes per mg were produced from collard-fed larvae, which contained 8% lipids, while 390 nematodes per mg were produced from artificial diet-fed larvae, which contained 16% lipids. Addition of commercially obtained sinigrin, a glucosinolate allelochemical found in collards, to artificial diet at biologically relevant levels also demonstrated suppression of nematode progeny production. It appears that host diet is a salient characteristic in progeny production of entomogenous nematodes.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 15</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1994NM71200039</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3709</id>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Invasion Efficiency as a Measure of Efficacy of the Entomogenous Nematode Steinernema-Carpocapsae (Rhabditida, Steinernematidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>366</sp>
<op>370</op>
<ab>Potential of entoniogenous nematodes for biological control generally is assessed by host mortality; nematode efficacy often is estimated by LC50. Nematode invasion efficiency (i.e., the percentage of the&amp;#39; infective-stage juveniles that invade and establish in the host) has been proposed as an alternative to LC50, as a measure of nematode efficacy. The relationship between these two measurements of nematode efficacy was explored in studies with Mexican and All strains of Steinernema carpocapsae (Weiser) tested against last instars of three lepidopteran species: Agrotis ipsilon (Hufnagel), Spodopterafrugiperda (J.E. Smith), and Galleria mellonella (L.). Estimates of LC50 ranged from 4 to 91 infective-stage juveniles (infectives) per host. Invasion efficiency (percentage invading) ranged from 11 to 31% among the six host-nematode combinations when concentrations of 10 to 100 infectives per host larva were tested and ranged from 1 to 28% when single infectives were tested against individual larvae in one-on-one bioassays. We observed no obvious host- or nematode strain-related patterns in invasion efficiency and no correlation between LC50 estimate and invasion efficiency. We recommend that determinations of percentage host mortality and nematode invasion efficiency be done simultaneously for assessments of nematode efficacy.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 11</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1994NR61400017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3731</id>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of the Entomogenous Nematode Steinernema-Feltiae Against a Subterranean Termite, Reticulitermes Tibialis (Isoptera, Rhinotermitidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1313</sp>
<op>1317</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 17</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1988Q418500011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3730</id>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Walter,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Potential Role of Nematophagous Microarthropods as Biotic Mortality Factors of Entomogenous Nematodes (Rhabditida, Steinernematidae, Heterorhabditidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>821</sp>
<op>825</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 61</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1988N664300015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3685</id>
<a1>Gruner,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Slone,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Forensically important Calliphoridae (Diptera) associated with pig carrion in rural north-central Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>515</op>
<ab>A study to determine the relative abundance and seasonality of forensically important blow flies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) in rural north-central Florida was conducted using pig carcasses (Sus scrofa L.) as models for human bodies. Seven species of Calliphoridae were collected: Lucilia coeruleiviridis (=Phaenicia) (Macquart), Cochliomyia macellaria (F.), Chrysomya rufifaces (Maequart), Phormia regina (Meigen), Chrysomya megacephala (F.), and a few specimens of Calliphora livida Hall, and Calliphora vicina Robineau-Desvoidy. Species composition in aerial collections of adult flies, preserved larval collections, and samples of larvae reared to the adult stage were all highly correlated. Relative abundance of the species found was significantly different, with L. coeruleiviridis the most abundant species year-round. The relative abundance of the collected species varied significantly by day of decomposition and by season, with significant interactions between season and day, season and species, and day and species. L. coeruleiviridis, C. macellaria, C. rufifaces, and P. regina were found during the entire year, two C. vicina specimens and 11 C. livida specimens were collected from December to March, whereas C. megacephala was collected only from June through September.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0022-2585 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000246328500017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3687</id>
<a1>Gruner,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Slone,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Forensically important Calliphoridae (Diptera) associated with pig carrion in rural north-central Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>515</op>
<ab>A study to determine the relative abundance and seasonality of forensically important blow flies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) in rural north-central Florida was conducted using pig carcasses (Sus scrofa L.) as models for human bodies. Seven species of Calliphoridae were collected: Lucilia coeruleiviridis (=Phaenicia) (Macquart), Cochliomyia macellaria (F.), Chrysomya rufifaces (Macquart), Phormia regina (Meigen), Chrysomya megacephala (F.), and a few specimens of Calliphora livida Hall, and Calliphora vicina Robineau-Desvoidy. Species composition in aerial collections of adult flies, preserved larval collections, and samples of larvae reared to the adult stage were all highly correlated. Relative abundance of the species found was significantly different, with L. coeruleiviridis the most abundant species year-round. The relative abundance of the collected species varied significantly by day of decomposition and by season, with significant interactions between season and day, season and species, and day and species. L. coeruleiviridis, C. macellaria, C. rufifaces, and P. regina were found during the entire year, two C.vicina specimens and 11 C. livida specimens were collected from December to March, whereas C. megacephala was collected only from June through September.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>CABI:20093326805</an>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2007)44[509:FICDAW]2.0.CO;2 ER</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3789</id>
<a1>Gruner,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Slone,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Forensically important Calliphoridae (Diptera) associated with pig carrion in rural north-central Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>515</op>
<ab>A study to determine the relative abundance and seasonality of forensically important blow flies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) in rural north-central Florida was conducted using pig carcasses (Sus scrofa L.) as models for human bodies. Seven species of Calliphoridae were collected: Lucilia coeruleiviridis (=Phaenicia) (Macquart), Cochliomyia macellaria (F.), Chrysomya rufifaces (Macquart), Phormia regina (Meigen), Chrysomya megacephala (F.), and a few specimens of Calliphora livida Hall, and Calliphora vicina Robineau-Desvoidy. Species composition in aerial collections of adult flies, preserved larval collections, and samples of larvae reared to the adult stage were all highly correlated. Relative abundance of the species found was significantly different, with L. coeruleiviridis the most abundant species year-round. The relative abundance of the collected species varied significantly by day of decomposition and by season, with significant interactions between season and day, season and species, and day and species. L. coeruleiviridis, C. macellaria, C. rufifaces, and P. regina were found during the entire year, two C.vicina specimens and 11 C. livida specimens were collected from December to March, whereas C. megacephala was collected only from June through September.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>CABI:20093326805</an>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2007)44[509:FICDAW]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3778</id>
<a1>Gruner,Susan V.</a1>
<a1>Slone,Daniel H.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,John L.</a1>
<t1>Forensically important Calliphoridae (Diptera) associated with pig carrion in rural north-central Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>515</op>
<ab>A study to determine the relative abundance and seasonality of forensically important blow flies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) in rural north-central Florida was conducted using pig carcasses (Sus scrofa L.) as models for human bodies. Seven species of Calliphoridae were collected: Lucilia coeruleiviridis (=Phaenicia) (Macquart), Cochliomyia macellaria (F.), Chrysomya rufifaces (Maequart), Phormia regina (Meigen), Chrysomya megacephala (F.), and a few specimens of Calliphora livida Hall, and Calliphora vicina Robineau-Desvoidy. Species composition in aerial collections of adult flies, preserved larval collections, and samples of larvae reared to the adult stage were all highly correlated. Relative abundance of the species found was significantly different, with L. coeruleiviridis the most abundant species year-round. The relative abundance of the collected species varied significantly by day of decomposition and by season, with significant interactions between season and day, season and species, and day and species. L. coeruleiviridis, C. macellaria, C. rufifaces, and P. regina were found during the entire year, two C. vicina specimens and 11 C. livida specimens were collected from December to March, whereas C. megacephala was collected only from June through September.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000246328500017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3751</id>
<a1>Hollingsworth,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of Nymphal Development Times in Diapausing and Nondiapausing Strains of Melanoplus-Sanguinipes (F) (Orthoptera, Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>612</sp>
<op>616</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 2</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1983RT87400022</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3726</id>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Host Utilization by Colorado Potato Beetle (Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae) in a Potato Weed (Solanum-Sarrachoides Sendt) System</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>122</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>113</sp>
<op>121</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 17</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1990CU25700013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3732</id>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Host Availability on Diapause and Voltinism in a Non-Agricultural Population of Colorado Potato Beetle (Coleoptera - Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>62</sp>
<op>67</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1988M447100007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3737</id>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Plant Diversity, Host Density, and Host Size on Population Ecology of the Colorado Potato Beetle (Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1019</sp>
<op>1026</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 18</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987L221000035</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3736</id>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal and Host Plant Effects on Parasitism of Colorado Potato Beetle by Myiopharus-Doryphorae (Riley) (Diptera, Tachinidae)</t1>
<jf>Canadian Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Can.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>7-8</is>
<sp>729</sp>
<op>734</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0008-347X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987K067400010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3723</id>
<a1>Horton,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Chapman,P. L.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Detecting Local Adaptation in Phytophagous Insects using Repeated Measures Designs</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>410</sp>
<op>418</op>
<ab>Substantial variation among experimental units may occur in studies that address effects of the host plant on insect performance or preference. Efficiency in demonstrating host effects can be enhanced by recognizing that variation among insects is often important and, more particularly, by using an experimental design appropriate for these conditions. Performance data from studies that address local adaptation in phytophagous insects are often analyzed with a two factor ANOVA, testing for host species, population, and host species x population effects. Local adaptation to different hosts would be indicated by a significant interaction term. Commonly, a completely randomized design is employed. A repeated measures design involving an allocation of siblings across host species can provide considerably more powerful tests on the host x population interaction than a completely randomized design. Allocation of relatives across host species can induce positive correlations among hosts and, depending upon magnitude of correlations, provide conditions suitable for powerful tests of the interaction term. We develop power curves for several patterns of correlation to describe the amount by which the repeated measures design will be more powerful than the completely randomized design. A literature review indicates that conditions appropriate for repeated measures analysis are very common. Finally, we provide an example using two populations of a phytophagous beetle feeding on three plant species, and show that the repeated measures design demonstrates host x population effects missed by the more traditional design.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 11</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1991FH31500004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3705</id>
<a1>Hoy,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Gaskalla,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Keierleber,C. N.</a1>
<t1>Laboratory containment of transgenic arthropods.</t1>
<jf>American Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Am.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>206</sp>
<op>209, 255-256</op>
<ab>Some of the problems and issues that have emerged during the past few years regarding releases of either transgenic or exotic organisms into the environment are discussed with particular reference to transgenic plants, microorganisms and arthropods. It is concluded that the most successful biotechnology projects involving transgenics are those in which public information efforts are implemented the earliest, and effective containment procedures are being seen to be used.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 0</no>
<sn>1046-2821 ER</sn>
<an>CABI:19981104195</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3727</id>
<a1>Kendall,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Geographic and Temporal Variation in the Sex-Ratio of Onion Thrips (Thysanoptera, Thripidae)</t1>
<jf>Southwestern Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Southwest.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>80</sp>
<op>88</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0147-1724 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1990CX70800012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3738</id>
<a1>Kendall,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Onion Growth-Stages to Onion Thrips (Thysanoptera, Thripidae) Damage and Mechanical Defoliation</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>859</sp>
<op>863</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 15</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987L221000004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3755</id>
<a1>Macvean,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Brewer,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Field-Tests of Anti-Desiccants to Extend the Infection Period of an Entomogenous Nematode, Neoaplectana-Carpocapsae, (Rhabditida, Steinernematidae) Against the Colorado Potato Beetle (Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>101</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 27</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1982NF08900025</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3717</id>
<a1>MacVean,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Field Evaluation of Two Microsporidian Pathogens, an Entomopathogenic Nematode, and Carbaryl for Suppression of the Mormon Cricket, Anabrus simplex Hald. (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae)</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>59</sp>
<op>65</op>
<ab>In field enclosures, the microsporidium, Vairimorpha sp., produced significant reductions in survival (&amp;gt;60%) of Mormon crickets treated as first to third instars with bran bait (10(12) spores/kg). This pathogen offers promise as a biological control agent for Mormon crickets. Reductions in survival attributable to Vairimorpha became statistically significant only after accounting for differential predation among treatment groups by the ant Formica criniventris Wheeler and Vesper sparrows. Nosema locustae Canning did not infect Mormon crickets or significantly reduce survival, despite high spore concentrations (10(12) spores/kg) in the bran bait and cannot contribute to Mormon cricket management. The nematode Steinernema carpocapsae (Weiser) failed to infect or to reduce survival of Mormon crickets. Low palatability of nematode bait capsules contributed to the lack of pathogenic effects. Carbaryl bait, highly effective in reducing cricket density, can be applied at low rates of active ingredient per area for cricket suppression on rangeland or for immediate protection of crop fields. (C) 1992 Academic Press, Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>1049-9644 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000207173300009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3707</id>
<a1>Nicolas,B.</a1>
<a1>Epsky,N. D.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Melanoplus-Sanguinipes (Orthoptera, Acrididae) Nymphs to Steinernema-Carpocapsae and S-Scapterisci (Nematoda, Steinernematidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>762</sp>
<op>769</op>
<ab>Infective juveniles of Steinernema carpocapsae Weiser and Steinernema scapterisci Nguyen and Smart infected nymphal grasshoppers under petri dish and simulated field conditions. S. carpocapsae caused higher mortality and was more infective (number of nematodes gaining entry to host) than S. scapterisci. Rate of mortality did not vary significantly among the nymphal instars, but nematodes were more infective in larger nymphs. For hatching grasshoppers digging to the soil surface, mortality and infectivity were positively correlated with soil moisture levels. Pathogenicity was especially enhanced by high humidity at the soil surface. Three sandy soils were also evaluated for effect on mortality and infectivity, but the influence of soil type, while significant, was small relative to soil moisture.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1995RE60500037</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3718</id>
<a1>Peck,S. B.</a1>
<a1>Walker,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Distributional Review of the Orthoptera of Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>329</sp>
<op>342</op>
<ab>Two hundred forty-one species of Orthoptera are now known to occur in Florida. The affinities of most of the species are with the southeastern United States. Forty-one species are restricted to Florida. The south Florida (tropical) fauna contains 129 species. Nine species are introduced. Nine species are naturally and exclusively shared between Florida and the West Indies or mainland Neotropics. The distribution by families is: Tetrigidae, 13 species; Acrididae, 72 species; Tridactylidae, 2 species; Tettigoniidae, 64 species; Gryllacrididae, 12 species; Gryllidae, 74 species; and Gryllotalpidae, 4 species.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992JR36400002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3724</id>
<a1>Przybyszewski,J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Patterns of Parasitism among Shortgrass Prairie Grasshopper (Orthoptera, Acrididae) Populations</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>5</sp>
<op>17</op>
<ab>Parasitism among shortgrass prairie grasshopper populations in northeast Colorado was assessed from 1984 to 1986, during a general decline in grasshopper abundance. Parasitism rates varied widely among species, pastures and years, but overall parasitism was only 2 percent in 1986. The tachinid Acemyia tibialis was prevalent early in the season, with the sarcophagids Blaesoxipha opifera, B. reversa, and B. hunteri more prevalent late in the summer. Parasites frequently were melanized; 24 percent of the grasshoppers containing maggots contained melanized individuals, and 64 percent were melanized in Phlibostroma quadrimaculatum. Parasites were recovered principally from adult grasshoppers, and 61 percent of the parasitized individuals were female. Several new host-parasite relationships were established. Seventy-one percent of the parasites were recovered from only four species of grasshoppers. Mean number of parasites per parasitized host was 3.07; the median number of parasites was 1. There generally was not a significant relationship between grasshopper density and parasitism rates.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1991FV02400002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3728</id>
<a1>Przybyszewski,J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Spatial and Temporal Patterns of Grasshopper (Orthoptera, Acrididae) Phenology and Abundance on a Shortgrass Prairie</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>405</sp>
<op>413</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1990EB94700008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3686</id>
<a1>Rathinasabapathi,B.</a1>
<a1>Rangasamy,M.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,J.</a1>
<a1>Cherry,R. H.</a1>
<a1>McAuslane,H. J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Srivastava,M.</a1>
<a1>Ma,L. Q.</a1>
<t1>Arsenic hyperaccumulation in the Chinese brake fern (Pteris vittata) deters grasshopper (Schistocerca americana) herbivory</t1>
<jf>New Phytologist</jf>
<jo>New Phytol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>175</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>363</sp>
<op>369</op>
<ab>Brake fern, Pteris vittata, not only tolerates arsenic but also hyperaccumulates it in the frond. The hypothesis that arsenic hyperaccumulation in this fern could function as a defense against insect herbivory was tested. Fronds from control and arsenic-treated ferns were presented to nymphs of the grasshopper Schistocerca americana. Feeding damage was recorded by visual observation and quantification of the fresh weight of frond left uneaten and number of fecal pellets produced over a 2-d period. Grasshopper weight was determined before and after 5 d of feeding. Grasshoppers consumed significantly greater amounts of the frond tissue, produced more fecal pellets and had increased body weight on control plants compared with grasshoppers fed arsenic-treated ferns. Very little or none of the arsenic-treated ferns were consumed indicating feeding deterrence. In a feeding deterrent experiment with lettuce, sodium arsenite at 1.0 mM deterred grasshoppers from feeding whereas 0.1 mM did not. In a choice experiment, grasshoppers preferred to feed on lettuce dipped in water compared with lettuce dipped in 1.0 mM sodium arsenite. Our results show that arsenic hyperaccumulation in brake fern is an elemental defense against grasshopper herbivory.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0028-646X</sn>
<an>WOS:000247477700017</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02099.x ER</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3777</id>
<a1>Rathinasabapathi,Bala</a1>
<a1>Rangasamy,Murugesan</a1>
<a1>Froeba,Jason</a1>
<a1>Cherry,Ronald H.</a1>
<a1>McAuslane,Heather J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,John L.</a1>
<a1>Srivastava,Mrittunjai</a1>
<a1>Ma,Lena Q.</a1>
<t1>Arsenic hyperaccumulation in the Chinese brake fern (Pteris vittata) deters grasshopper (Schistocerca americana) herbivory</t1>
<jf>New Phytologist</jf>
<jo>New Phytol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>175</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>363</sp>
<op>369</op>
<ab>Brake fern, Pteris vittata, not only tolerates arsenic but also hyperaccumulates it in the frond. The hypothesis that arsenic hyperaccumulation in this fern could function as a defense against insect herbivory was tested. Fronds from control and arsenic-treated ferns were presented to nymphs of the grasshopper Schistocerca americana. Feeding damage was recorded by visual observation and quantification of the fresh weight of frond left uneaten and number of fecal pellets produced over a 2-d period. Grasshopper weight was determined before and after 5 d of feeding. Grasshoppers consumed significantly greater amounts of the frond tissue, produced more fecal pellets and had increased body weight on control plants compared with grasshoppers fed arsenic-treated ferns. Very little or none of the arsenic-treated ferns were consumed indicating feeding deterrence. In a feeding deterrent experiment with lettuce, sodium arsenite at 1.0 mM deterred grasshoppers from feeding whereas 0.1 mM did not. In a choice experiment, grasshoppers preferred to feed on lettuce dipped in water compared with lettuce dipped in 1.0 mM sodium arsenite. Our results show that arsenic hyperaccumulation in brake fern is an elemental defense against grasshopper herbivory.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0028-646X</sn>
<an>000247477700017</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02099.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3719</id>
<a1>Redak,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Bonham,C. D.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Sagebrush Removal and Herbivory by Mormon Crickets (Orthoptera, Tettigoniidae) on Understory Plant Biomass and Cover</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>94</sp>
<op>102</op>
<ab>The effects of herbivory by the Mormon cricket, Anabrus simplex Haldeman (Orthoptera:Tettigoniidae), and removal of sagebrush (Artemisia tridentata Nutt.) on understory plant biomass production and cover were determined. Averaged over a 3-yr period, 50-75% removal of sagebrush resulted in an almost-equal-to 20% increase in summer understory biomass production; understory plant cover was not affected by sagebrush removal. Mormon crickets, at densities of four and eight crickets per square meter during a 5-wk period, did not significantly affect understory plant biomass production but did reduce forb and total vegetative cover. Mormon cricket herbivory and sagebrush removal were independent with respect to their effects on understory vegetation. Furthermore, the incomplete removal of sagebrush did not affect the feeding ecology of Mormon crickets. Analysis of cricket crop contents suggested that sagebrush was fed upon predominantly; there was little dietary overlap between crickets and cattle. As long as some sagebrush is left intact (e.g., 25%), sagebrush control programs are unlikely to influence Mormon cricket diet selection or damage potential. Cover estimates, which are commonly used by ranchers and rangeland managers to estimate forage availability, provide deceptive assessments of cricket effects, ultimately perhaps leading to an undeserved reputation as a rangeland pest.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992HD78000013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3752</id>
<a1>Roehrig,N. E.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Behavioral and Developmental Responses of Range Caterpillar Larvae, Hemileuca-Oliviae, to Condensed Tannin</t1>
<jf>Journal of insect physiology</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>901</sp>
<op>906</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 10</no>
<sn>0022-1910 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1983RZ36900005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3753</id>
<a1>Rottman,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Insect and Cattle-Induced Perturbations on a Shortgrass Prairie Arthropod Community</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>241</sp>
<op>252</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 8</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1983QP22500019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3700</id>
<a1>Shannag,H. K.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Interference of Steinernema carpocapsae (Nematoda : Steinernematidae) with Cardiochiles diaphaniae (Hymenoptera : Braconidae), a parasitoid of melonworm and picklewormm (Lepidoptera : Pyralidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>612</sp>
<op>617</op>
<ab>Entomopathogenic nematodes are generally considered beneficial organisms. However, they can affect beneficial insects such as parasitoids. The infectivity of Steinernema carpocapsae (Mexican strain) to Cardiochiles diaphaniae Marsh, a solitary internal wasp parasitoid of melonworm, Diaphania hyalinata (L.). and pickleworm, D. nitidalis (Stoll), was determined under laboratory conditions. S. carpocapsae induced 100% infection in melonworm hosts during exposure periods of 6, 24, 36, and 48 h. The number of nematodes penetrating the host was proportional to the length of exposure period, and the emergence rate of wasp parasitoids was inversely proportional to exposure time. Though only 0-10% of immature C. diaphaniae were parasitized by nematodes within hosts, newly emerged and, to a lesser degree, cocoon-spinning wasp larvae were readily infected by nematodes. In contrast, pupae of C. diapahaniae in completely formed cocoons were resistant to infection, S. carpocapsae adversely affected C. diaphaniae developing in melonworm principally by causing the premature death of the host before the wasp could complete its development. If the wasp larvae were 6 or 7 d old when the melonworm host was parasitized by nematodes, then all the wasp larvae died. However, if the wasp larvae were 8 d old when nematodes parasitized the melonworm, then 39-92% of the melonworms successfully produced wasp parasitoids. Many wasp larvae that emerged from nematode-parasitized melonworms did not form cocoons, and died within 24 h of emergence. However, only a small proportion of the larvae contained nematodes as determined by dissection. The percentage of infected parasitoids and the proportion of emerged parasitoid larvae dying increased as the exposure time to nematodes increased. Overall, S. carpocapsae nematodes are somewhat compatible with parasitoids because they do not kill all parasitoids, and the pupal stage is resistant to infection. However, the direct and indirect mortality of wasps caused by nematodes could result in some interference with biological suppression.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 9</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000089623400026</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3708</id>
<a1>Shannag,H. K.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Entomopathogenic Nematode Species for the Control of Melonworm (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>143</sp>
<op>148</op>
<ab>Laboratory bioassays were conducted to determine pathogenicity of five entomopathogenic nematodes from the genera Steinernema and Heterorhabditis against melon-worm, Diaphania hyalinata (L.). S. carpocapsae (Weiser) (Mexican strain) was the most pathogenic nematode species, followed by H. bacteriophora (Poinar), S. feltiae (Filipjev), S. anomali (Kozodoi), and S. glaseri (Steiner), respectively. The LC50 for S. carpocapsae (Mexican) was 39.9 infective juveniles per milliter. The rate of nematode invasion into insects was proportional to the overall pathogenic effect of the various nematodes. The level of insect mortality and infectivity (the number of nematodes invading the insect) were directly related to exposure time. First instars and pupae were significantly less susceptible to S. carpocapsae infection than older larvae and prepupae. The number of nematodes found in the hemocoel increased with larval age. Mortality and infectivity were inversely related to nematode size. In field trials, survival of S. carpocapsae (All strain) on squash plant foliage was reduced to 0.77% within 40 h in a trial under high humidity conditions and to 0.25% after 18 h in a trial under moderate humidity conditions. Field applications of 5 billion nematodes per hectare produced infection rates of 52-55%.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 6</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1995QG51600021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3784</id>
<a1>Shannag,H. K.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Entomopathogenic Nematode Species for the Control of Melonworm (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>143</sp>
<op>148</op>
<ab>Laboratory bioassays were conducted to determine pathogenicity of five entomopathogenic nematodes from the genera Steinernema and Heterorhabditis against melon-worm, Diaphania hyalinata (L.). S. carpocapsae (Weiser) (Mexican strain) was the most pathogenic nematode species, followed by H. bacteriophora (Poinar), S. feltiae (Filipjev), S. anomali (Kozodoi), and S. glaseri (Steiner), respectively. The LC50 for S. carpocapsae (Mexican) was 39.9 infective juveniles per milliter. The rate of nematode invasion into insects was proportional to the overall pathogenic effect of the various nematodes. The level of insect mortality and infectivity (the number of nematodes invading the insect) were directly related to exposure time. First instars and pupae were significantly less susceptible to S. carpocapsae infection than older larvae and prepupae. The number of nematodes found in the hemocoel increased with larval age. Mortality and infectivity were inversely related to nematode size. In field trials, survival of S. carpocapsae (All strain) on squash plant foliage was reduced to 0.77% within 40 h in a trial under high humidity conditions and to 0.25% after 18 h in a trial under moderate humidity conditions. Field applications of 5 billion nematodes per hectare produced infection rates of 52-55%.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1995QG51600021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3711</id>
<a1>Shannag,H. K.</a1>
<a1>Webb,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Entomopathogenic Nematode Effect on Pickleworm (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) Under Laboratory and Field Conditions</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1205</sp>
<op>1212</op>
<ab>Laboratory and field tests were performed to assess the potential of entomopathogenic nematodes from the genera Steinernema and Heterorhabditis as biological control agents for the pickleworm, Diaphania nitidalis (Stoll). In the laboratory, there were significant differences in virulence among five nematode species, based on the lack of overlap of 95% FL of LC(50). S. carpocapsae (Weiser) (Mexican strain) had the lowest LC(50) and was approximate to 2, 4, 30, and 38 times more pathogenic than H. bacteriophora Poinar (HP88 strain), S. feltiae (Filipjev), S. glaseri (Steiner), and S. anomali (Kozodoi), respectively. Nematode infectivity (number of nematodes in the host) was positively correlated with mortality. Larval mortality and penetration rate of infective juveniles into the host were positively correlated to host exposure time for S. carpocapsae (Mexican strain), S. feltiae, and H. bacteriophora. Nematode species that were smaller were more infective and induced mortality more quickly. Nematodes did not affect first instars and pupae to the same extent as older larvae and prepupae; pupae were particularly refractory. S. carpocapsae (All strain) applied to squash plants were able to enter blossoms, where they persisted and infected pickleworms. Nematode applications reduced damage to blossoms and fruit and, when applied weekly at 2.5 billion/ha, protected squash fruit at a level equivalent to the insecticide permethrin.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 12</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1994PK98200013</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3701</id>
<a1>Sieglaff,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Pereira,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Microbial control of Schistocerca americana (Orthoptera : Acrididae) by Metarhizium flavoviride (Deuteromycotina): Instar dependent mortality and efficacy of ultra low volume application under greenhouse conditions</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>76</sp>
<op>85</op>
<ab>The entomopathogenic fungus Metarhizium flavoviride Gams &amp;amp; Rozsypal has been widely tested for the suppression of African grasshoppers, but there has been no research on Nearctic species. We examined the potential of M. flavoviride for the control of the American grasshopper, Schistocerca americana (Drury). When tested under conidial dosages of 1.2 x 10(3), 1.2 x 10(4), and 1.2 x 10(5), 4th-instar S. americana were significantly more susceptible to M. flavoviride than 6th-instar and adult S. americana. At the conidial dosage of 1.2 x 10(5), M. flavoviride produced 89.7, 12.8, and 17.6% mean mortality 7 d after treatment in 4th-instar, 6th-instar, and adult S. americana, respectively. By the 14th d after treatment, the M. flavoviride conidial dosage of 1.2 x 10(5) produced 99.4, 86.1, and 80.8% mean mortality in 4th-instar, 6th-instar, and adult S. americana, respectively. The LD50 estimates for M. flavoviride of 1.7 x 10(4) conidia for the 4th-instar, 1.3 x 10(4) conidia for the 6th-instar, and 3.1 x 10(4) conidia for the adult S. americana are generally greater than those used for other acridids. Furthermore, mortality in M. flavoviride-treated S. americana was positively dosage dependent, as described by mean percentage of cumulative mortality and LT50 estimates. Greenhouse trials evaluating ultra low volume application to grasshoppers, foliage, or grasshoppers and foliage produced from 78.1 to 92.0% mean mortality 14 d after treatment. In this simulated field trial, grasshoppers and M. flavoviride were exposed to temperatures ranging from 10 to 40 degrees C, which demonstrated the potential of M. flavoviride to be effective under large temperature fluctuations, as may occur in the held.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 2</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000073139800011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3706</id>
<a1>Sieglaff,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Pereira,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Pathogenicity of Beauveria bassiana and Metarhizium flavoviride (Deuteromycotina) to Schistocerca americana (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1539</sp>
<op>1545</op>
<ab>The entomopathogenic fungi Beauveria bassiana (Balsamo) Vuillemin and Metarhizium flavoviride Gams and Rozspal have been widely tested for the suppression of grasshoppers. However, with the exception of Melanoplus sanguinipes (F.), there has been little research on Nearctic species. We examined the potential of these 2 microbial agents for control of the American grasshopper, Schistocerca americana (Drury), and the migratory grasshopper, M. sanguinipes. M. flavoviride was much more virulent than B. bassiana to both grasshopper species. At the conidial dosage of 1.2 x 10(5), M, flavoviride produced 69.2 and 74.2% mean mortality 7 d after treatment in S. americana and il. sanguinipes, respectively. In contrast, B, bassiana produced 1.7 and 11.7% mean mortality 7 d after treatment in S. americana and M. sanguinipes, respectively. Treatment with M. flavoviride also caused a significant reduction in feeding beginning 48 h after treatment of Gth-instar S. americana. Furthermore, M, flavoviride-treated S. americana showed an average reduction of 36.6% mean cumulative consumption, 5-8 d after treatment, when compared with untreated grasshoppers.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0022-0493 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000071728600018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3712</id>
<a1>Smith,H. A.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Pena,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Linboterhaar,B.</a1>
<t1>Parasitism of Pickleworm and Melonworm (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) by Cardiochiles-Diaphaniae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1283</sp>
<op>1293</op>
<ab>Pickelworm, Diaphania nitidalis (Stoll), and melonworm, Diaphania hyalinata (L.), larvae were susceptible to parasitism by Cardiochiles diaphaniae Marsh. Melonworm larvae were more susceptible to parasitism than pickleworm, but both exhibited reduced weight gain and head capsule growth in later stadia compared with nonparasitized conspecifics and then perished following initiation of wandering before pupal molt. Melonworm larvae parasitized when in advanced stadia achieved a greater final weight than larvae parasitized when young. Parasitoid larval development time was longest following parasitization of young melonworm, but not significantly different in melonworm larvae parasitized in middle or later instars. Compared with nonparasitized melonworm larvae, the prepupal wandering stage was abbreviated in melonworm larvae parasitized when young, and extended in melonworm larvae parasitized in later instars. Overall, parasitoid development time was significantly longer in pickleworm hosts than melonworm. Adult parasitoid weight increased with host age at the time of parasitization when melonworm served as host and was highest in middle-instar larvae when pickle-worm served as host. C. diaphaniae developing in pickleworm larvae weighed significantly more than those developing in melonworm larvae.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 8</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1994PN32200031</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3690</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Host preferences and habitat associations of some Florida grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>210</sp>
<op>224</op>
<ab>Host-plant preferences were assessed by field measurement of grasshopper abundance in relation to measurements of floral community and by laboratory host-plant preferences. Correlations between grasshoppers and plants (biomass and percentage cover) were based on data gathered at 29 study sites in five distinct Florida habitats (including disturbed, freshwater marsh, high pine, oak hammock, and swamp). Relationships among plants in these habitats and 10 abundant grasshopper species were examined to clarify differences in grasshopper assemblages among habitats. The grasshoppers studied were Aptenopedes sphenarioides Scudder, Chortophaga australior (Rehn and Hebard), Eritettix obscurus (Scudder), Melanoplus bispinosus Scudder, Melanoplus querneus Rehn and Hebard, Paroxya clavuliger (Serville), Schistocerca americana (Drury), Schistocerca ceratiola Hubbell and Walker, and Spharagemon crepitans (Saussure). In addition to correlations among individual plants and the abundance of grasshoppers, multiple regression analysis was used to assess how groups of plants were related to grasshopper abundance. These analyses identified grasshopper-plant associations, but some plants were found to be host plants, whereas others were indicators of preferred habitats (indicator plants). Host-plant preferences were determined in the laboratory using five plant-choice tests to help distinguish between host and indicator plants. The 10 grasshopper species examined for laboratory host-plant preferences were the same species scrutinized in the field study. In almost every case, grasshoppers showed specific plant preferences, and the preference studies successfully distinguished between host plants and indicator species. Similar results were obtained whether biomass or percent cover measurements were used to assess the floral community, although percent cover is much easier and faster to determine.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000226895100028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3782</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Host preferences and habitat associations of some Florida grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>210</sp>
<op>224</op>
<ab>Host-plant preferences were assessed by field measurement of grasshopper abundance in relation to measurements of floral community and by laboratory host-plant preferences. Correlations between grasshoppers and plants (biomass and percentage cover) were based on data gathered at 29 study sites in five distinct Florida habitats (including disturbed, freshwater marsh, high pine, oak hammock, and swamp). Relationships among plants in these habitats and 10 abundant grasshopper species were examined to clarify differences in grasshopper assemblages among habitats. The grasshoppers studied were Aptenopedes sphenarioides Scudder, Chortophaga australior (Rehn and Hebard), Eritettix obscurus (Scudder), Melanoplus bispinosus Scudder, Melanoplus querneus Rehn and Hebard, Paroxya clavuliger (Serville), Schistocerca americana (Drury), Schistocerca ceratiola Hubbell and Walker, and Spharagemon crepitans (Saussure). In addition to correlations among individual plants and the abundance of grasshoppers, multiple regression analysis was used to assess how groups of plants were related to grasshopper abundance. These analyses identified grasshopper-plant associations, but some plants were found to be host plants, whereas others were indicators of preferred habitats (indicator plants). Host-plant preferences were determined in the laboratory using five plant-choice tests to help distinguish between host and indicator plants. The 10 grasshopper species examined for laboratory host-plant preferences were the same species scrutinized in the field study. In almost every case, grasshoppers showed specific plant preferences, and the preference studies successfully distinguished between host plants and indicator species. Similar results were obtained whether biomass or percent cover measurements were used to assess the floral community, although percent cover is much easier and faster to determine.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000226895100028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3689</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Mandibular morphology of some Floridian grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>204</sp>
<op>207</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000230583300016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3781</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Mandibular morphology of some Floridian grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>204</sp>
<op>207</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000230583300016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3692</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Key to the grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae) of Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>537</sp>
<op>550</op>
<ab>A dichotomous key is presented to aid in the identification of the adult stage of the 71 grasshopper species known to occur in Florida. Reflecting recent research one subspecies, Schistocerca alutacea rubiginosa (Scudder), has been elevated to species status Schistocerca rubiginosa (Harris) in this key.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000226262600018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3783</id>
<a1>Smith,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Froeba,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Key to the grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae) of Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>537</sp>
<op>550</op>
<ab>A dichotomous key is presented to aid in the identification of the adult stage of the 71 grasshopper species known to occur in Florida. Reflecting recent research one subspecies, Schistocerca alutacea rubiginosa (Scudder), has been elevated to species status Schistocerca rubiginosa (Harris) in this key.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000226262600018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3696</id>
<a1>Squitier,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Habitat associations of Florida grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>235</sp>
<op>244</op>
<ab>A year-long survey was conducted to assess the grasshopper species assemblage in various natural and anthropogenic habitats in Florida. Distribution, density, and relative abundance data were collected, providing insight into habitat preference and resource utilization. Of the 70 species known to occur in Florida, 52 species were collected in one or more habitats. The number of different species found in each habitat, in descending order of species richness, were: sandhill, 34; freshwater marsh, 27; scrub, 26; roadside, 26; lakeside, 22; disturbed areas, 22; pasture, 19; pine plantation, 19; old fields, 18; flatwoods, 13; salt marshes, 11; oak hammock, 9; crops, 8; coastal scrub, 6; cutthroat seep; 5; and coastal strand, 5. Common species, and the number of habitats they were found to occupy, include Schistocerca americana, 12;Aptenopedes sphenarioides, 10; Dichromorpha viridis, 8; Melanoplus propinquus, 8; Paroxya atlantica, 8; Achurum carinatum, 7; Amblytropidia mysteca, 7; Chortophaga australior, 7;Aptenopedes aptera 6; Melanoplus keeleri, 5; Melanoplus rotundipennis, 5; Orphulella pelidna, 5; and Spharagemon cristatum, 5. Variation in habitat use within selected habitat types was demonstrated by (1) comparison of species richness and abundance on roadsides with grassy or weedy vegetation; weedy vegetation was inhabited by significantly more grasshoppers, and (2) comparison of species richness and abundance in pine plantations with pine trees of different ages; plantations with young trees had significantly more grasshoppers. In contrast, species richness was unaffected within these roadside and pine plantation sites.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000175200200029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3697</id>
<a1>Squitier,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Host selection by grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae) inhabiting semi-aquatic environments</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>336</sp>
<op>340</op>
<ab>Through laboratory choice tests involving 19 plant species, we assessed the host selection behavior of six grasshopper species: Stenacris vitreipennis (Marschall) (glassywinged toothpick grasshopper,), Leptysma marginicollis (Serville) (cattail toothpick grasshopper), Gymnoscirtetes pusillus Scudder (little wingless grasshopper), Pdroxya clavuliger (Senille) (olivegreen swamp grasshopper), Paroxya atlantica Scudder (Atlantic grasshopper), and Romalca microptera (Beauvois) (eastern lubber grasshoppor). This grasshopper assemblage is commonly associated with semi-aquatic habitats in the southeastern United States. These poorly studied species display both graminivorous (S. vetreipennis and L. marginicollis) and mixed graminivorous-forbivorous feeding habits (the remaining species), the nature of which are fairly predictable based on examination of mouthpart morphology, but not entirely consistent with the tendency of cyrtacanthacridine species to food on forbs.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000176498700006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3695</id>
<a1>Squitier,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Observations on the phenology of common Florida grasshoppers (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>227</sp>
<op>234</op>
<ab>Grasshopper occurrence and abundance in several natural and anthropogenic habitats found in north Florida were surveyed for a one-year period to determine periodicity of adult and nymphal stages. Thirty species were sufficiently abundant to assess at least some elements of their phenology. A high proportion (36%) of the species overwintered as adults, and 27% of the species overwintered as nymphs. Three species were found to overwinter in both the adult and nymphal stages. The period of peak nymphal abundance varied among species and was found to include spring, summer, autumn, and winter. The method of data collection used in this study was inadequate to ascertain definitively the number of generations, but six species are suspected of being multivoltine in Florida.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 2</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000175200200028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3702</id>
<a1>Squitier,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Deyrup,M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>A new species of Melanoplus (Orthoptera : Acrididae) from an isolated upland in peninsular Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>451</sp>
<op>460</op>
<ab>A new species of flightless acridid grasshopper, Melanoplus with lacoocheensis n. sp., is described from an isolated upland, the Southern Brooksville Ridge, in west central peninsular Florida. It occurs in open sandhill habitat. It appears to be closely related to Melanoplus rotundipennis Scudder, which is widespread in sandhill and Florida scrub habitats in central and northern peninsular Florida; the species are distinguished by details of the male cerci and genitalia. The new species is one of several species of flightless Melanoplus in Florida whose geographic ranges are small and biogeographically revealing. The new species is the first clear biological indicator of the long-term isolation of the Southern Brooksville Ridge from other uplands, including the Northern Brooksville Ridge.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 3</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:000076426200020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3739</id>
<a1>Thompson,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Pilcher,S. D.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of an Aerial Water-Pan Pheromone Trap with Traditional Trapping Techniques for the European Corn-Borer (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>154</sp>
<op>158</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 11</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987G892600027</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3715</id>
<a1>Valles,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Response of Larvae of the Southern Armyworm, Spodoptera-Eridania (Cramer) (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae), to Selected Botanical Insecticides and Soap</t1>
<jf>Journal of Agricultural Entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Agric.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>145</sp>
<op>153</op>
<ab>Responses of early- and late-instar larvae of the southern armyworm, Spodoptera eridania (Cramer) to four botanical insecticides and one insecticidal soap were evaluated in laboratory and field tests. Laboratory tests consisted of incorporation of insecticidal products at various concentrations into artificial diet; survival and development rate were observed. Field tests consisted of a single maximum recommended dosage (foliar application) of each product; survival and foliage consumption by early instars were evaluated 1, 4, 10, and 24 h after treatment. A synergized pyrethrin product, Pyrenone(R), was most efficacious, and induced rapid mortality and foliage protection. Ryania and sabadilla were effective in laboratory tests, but failed to induce mortality in the field. Both products inhibited larval development and caused some reduction in foliage consumption. Rotenone and the insecticidal soap bad few effects on southern armyworm larvae.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 2</no>
<sn>0735-939X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1993LQ74200001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3720</id>
<a1>Valles,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Periodicity of Attraction of Adult Melonworm, Diaphania-Hyalinata</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>390</sp>
<op>392</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 1</no>
<sn>0015-4040 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992JR36400011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3725</id>
<a1>Valles,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Teal,P. E. A.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Pheromone Trap Design, Height, and Efficiency for Capture of Male Diaphania-Nitidalis (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) in a Field Cage</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1274</sp>
<op>1278</op>
<ab>A field cage was used to study sex pheromone mediated behavior and evaluate female-baited pheromone traps for capture of males of the pickleworm, Diaphania nitidalis (Stoll). Males were attracted to females throughout scotophase with peak attraction occurring during the third (2200-2259 hours), fourth (2300-2359 hours), and fifth (0000-0059 hours) hours. Four traps were evaluated: (1) the box, currently used for monitoring pickleworm moth populations; (2) the Heliothis; (3) the Pherocon 1C (sticky); and (4) the unitrap (bucket). The bucket trap consistently captured and retained more male pickleworm moths than the other traps tested. The bucket trap was evaluated at 30, 80, 150, and 180 cm above ground level. Significantly more males were caught at 80 and 150 cm than at either extreme. Trap efficiency was determined for the bucket trap and a modified (Fluon-coated outer cone) bucket trap. Efficiencies for the bucket and modified bucket traps were not significantly different. The bucket trap caught 20.3 +/- 1.2% (xBAR +/- SEM) of males orienting toward the trap, 29.3 +/- 1.7% of males touching the trap, and 41.0 +/- 3.3% of males landing on the caged females used as the pheromone source.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 16</no>
<sn>0046-225X ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1991GL82700009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3721</id>
<a1>Valles,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Heath,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Production and Release of Sex-Pheromone by Diaphania-Nitidalis (Lepidoptera, Pyralidae) - Periodicity, Age, and Density Effects</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>731</sp>
<op>735</op>
<ab>The periodicity and effect of age of female Diaphania nitidalis (Stoll) on sex pheromone production and emission were determined by measuring the major pheromonal component, (E)-11-hexadecenal, using gas chromatography. Volatile collections revealed that female D. nitidalis emitted at least 9.20 ng/h (E)-11-hexadecenal during scotophase. Pheromone release typically increased sharply during the early hours of scotophase (1-5), peaked during the 5-7 h period, and decreased toward the onset of photophase. Similarly, the amount of pheromone present in extracts of pheromone glands increased at the onset and decreased toward the end of scotophase. However, the pheromone titer remained fairly constant from the third to ninth hours of scotophase. Female density within volatile collection chambers bad a pronounced impact on the amount of pheromone emitted. As female density increased, pheromone emission decreased. Pheromone production was stable for 1- to 5-d-old females, but dropped sharply in 7-d-old females. In addition, the 7-d-old females began to oviposit unfertilized eggs within the collection chambers.</ab>
<no>PT: J; TC: 4</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1992JZ26600009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3740</id>
<a1>Walmsley,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Detling,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Dyer,M. I.</a1>
<t1>Growth of Blue Grama and Western Wheatgrass Following Grasshopper Defoliation and Mechanical Clipping</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</jf>
<jo>J.Kans.Entomol.Soc.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>51</sp>
<op>57</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 5</no>
<sn>0022-8567 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1987G751600007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3763</id>
<a1>Wiener,L. F.</a1>
<a1>Capinera,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Greenbug Response to an Alarm Pheromone Analog - Temperature and Humidity Effects, Disruptive Potential, and Analog Releaser Efficacy (Homoptera, Aphididae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>369</sp>
<op>371</op>
<no>PT: J; TC: 7</no>
<sn>0013-8746 ER</sn>
<an>WOS:A1979GV90200011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
