<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1641</id>
<a1>Chen,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Adult head and neck soft tissue sarcomas</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>259</sp>
<op>263</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Clinical Protocols</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Facial Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Sarcoma/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To analyze the outcomes of adult patients with head and neck soft tissue sarcomas. METHODS: Review of 39 patients treated with radiotherapy (RT) alone (6 patients) or combined with surgery (33 patients) with curative intent between December 1966 and February 2003. Follow-up for living patients ranged from 1 to 21 years (median, 8.7 years). RESULTS: Five-year outcomes were as follows: local control, 78%; distant metastasis-free survival, 85%; cause-specific survival, 69%, and overall survival, 63%. Three of 6 patients (50%) treated with definitive RT were locally controlled compared with 27 of 33 patients (82%) treated with surgery and RT. CONCLUSIONS: Approximately two thirds of patients with head and neck soft tissue sarcomas are cured with RT alone or combined with surgery. Local recurrence is a significant mode of treatment failure. Outcome is influenced by tumor extent, histologic grade, and resectability.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 24; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>University of Miami School of Medicine, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15923798; 00000421-200506000-00008 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15923798</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1665</id>
<a1>Chera,B. S.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiation therapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the soft palate</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1114</sp>
<op>1119</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/pathology</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Multivariate Analysis</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm, Residual/surgery</k1>
<k1>Palate, Soft/pathology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: We report the University of Florida experience with soft-palate carcinoma treated with radiotherapy alone or combined with adjuvant chemotherapy and/or neck dissection for residual disease in the neck. METHODS: A total of 145 patients treated with curative intent from 1963 to 2004 were included. Potential follow-up was &amp;gt; or =2 years. RESULTS: Local control rates at 5 years were: T1, 90%; T2, 91%; T3, 67%; T4, 57%. Nodal control rates at 5 years were: N0, 90%; N1, 82%; N2, 68%; N3, 71%. Ultimate local-regional control rates at 5 years were: stage I, 89%; stage II, 88%; stage III, 96%; stage IVA, 63%; stage IVB, 43%. In multivariate analysis, overall treatment time significantly affected local and ultimate local-regional control, and nodal stage significantly affected overall survival. Overall survival rate at 5 years was 44%. Cause-specific survival rate at 5 years was 73%. CONCLUSIONS: The likelihood of cure after definitive radiotherapy is relatively high and is impacted by disease extent and overall treatment time.</ab>
<no>JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1097-0347; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18615732</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20848</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18615732</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1673</id>
<a1>Cianchetti,M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Diagnostic evaluation of squamous cell carcinoma metastatic to cervical lymph nodes from an unknown head and neck primary site</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2348</sp>
<op>2354</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Biopsy</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/diagnosis/secondary</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Endoscopy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/diagnosis/secondary</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/pathology</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neck</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Positron-Emission Tomography</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<k1>Tonsillectomy</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: To discuss our experience with the diagnostic evaluation in patients with squamous cell carcinomas (SCCAs) of the head and neck metastatic to the cervical lymph nodes from an unknown primary site. METHODS: Between June 1983 and December 2008, 236 patients were evaluated with lymph node biopsy, computed tomography (CT), and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the head and neck, and panendoscopy with directed biopsies. Additional studies included fluorodeoxyglucose-single photon emission computed tomography (FDG-SPECT) in 26 patients and FDG-positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) or FDG-PET/CT in 21 patients. Seventy-nine patients underwent an ipsilateral (72) or bilateral (seven) tonsillectomy. RESULTS: An occult primary site was detected in 126 patients (53.4%); six patients had two synchronous primary cancers. The most common primary sites were in the tonsillar fossa (59 patients; 44.7%) and the base of tongue (58 patients; 43.9%). The primary site was found in 21 (29.2%) of the 72 patients with no suspicious findings on physical exam and/or radiographic evaluation compared with 105 (64.0%) of 164 remaining patients. Tonsillectomy revealed the primary cancer in 35 (44.3%) of 79 patients. FDG-SPECT and FDG-PET or FDG-PET/CT was the sole method of primary site detection in only one patient (2.1%) of 47 patients. CONCLUSIONS: Diagnostic evaluation should include a thorough physical examination, CT and/or MRI of the head and neck, and panendoscopy with directed biopsies. Unilateral or bilateral tonsillectomy should be performed on patients with adequate lymphoid tonsillar tissue. FDG-PET or FDG-PET/CT should be considered for those with indeterminate findings on physical examination and/or head and neck CT and/or MRI if those sites are located outside of the oropharynx.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19718744</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/lary.20638</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19718744</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1675</id>
<a1>Harrison,Louis B.</a1>
<a1>Sessions,Roy B.</a1>
<a1>Hong,Waun Ki</a1>
<t1>Early-stage cancer of the larynx</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<sp>339</sp>
<op>339-353</op>
<no>ID: 457247223</no>
<a2>Harrison,Louis B.</a2><a2> Sessions,Roy B.</a2><a2>Hong,Waun Ki</a2>
<t2>Head and neck cancer a multidisciplinary approach</t2>
<pb>Lipppincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia</pp>
<sn>9780781771368 0781771366</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ul>http://ezproxy.usherbrooke.ca/login?url=http://ovidsp.ovid.com/ovidweb.cgi?T=JS&amp;NEWS=N&amp;PAGE=booktext&amp;D=books&amp;AN=01337298/3rd_Edition/5&amp;XPATH</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1671</id>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Indelicato,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma metastatic to parotid-area lymph nodes</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1989</sp>
<op>1996</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/secondary/therapy</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/pathology</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Parotid Gland</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Skin Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<ab>INTRODUCTION: Metastatic spread to parotid-area lymph nodes (PALN) occurs in 1% to 3% of patients with cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Presented herein is the University of Florida experience using radiation therapy (RT) to treat patients with PALN metastases from a skin primary. METHODS AND MATERIALS: From November 1969 to February 2005, 121 parotids in 117 patients received irradiation for nonmelanotic skin carcinoma metastatic to PALN. Patients were staged by the O&amp;#39;Brien staging system. Of the 121 parotids receiving RT, 17 (14%) were treated preoperatively, 87 (72%) postoperatively, and 17 with RT alone. RESULTS: Five-year actuarial probabilities of local (parotid) control, local-regional control, disease-free survival and overall survival were 78%, 74%, 70%, and 54%, respectively. When patients were separated by O&amp;#39;Brien P-stage, statistically significant differences were seen among the groups for local (parotid) control, local-regional control, and disease-free survival. A statistically significant decrease in local control was seen in patients treated with positive surgical margins (92% vs. 76%) and in local-regional control for patients treated with preoperative RT or RT alone when compared with postoperative RT (59% and 47% vs. 83%, respectively). The 5-year actuarial probability of freedom from distant metastases was 92%. Three (2.6%) patients suffered severe complications. CONCLUSIONS: PALN metastases from a cutaneous head and neck primary site are best treated with surgery and postoperative RT. Our data support the hypothesis that the O&amp;#39;Brien staging system is superior to the American Joint Committee on Cancer system for the staging of cutaneous metastases to PALN. Positive surgical margins confer a worse prognosis in terms of local-regional control and disease-free survival. Patients treated with preoperative RT seem to have a worse prognosis than those treated postoperatively, likely a result of patient selection and the surgeon&amp;#39;s inability to accurately assess viable tumor extent after preoperative RT. Severe complications are uncommon after surgery and RT for PALN metastases.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA. hinerw@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18849863</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/MLG.0b013e318180642b</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18849863</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1649</id>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>T3 and T4 true vocal cord squamous carcinomas treated with external beam irradiation: a single institution&amp;#39;s 35-year experience</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>185</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Vocal Cords</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: The purpose of this study was to report the outcomes after external-beam radiotherapy (RT) for selected T3 and T4 vocal cord squamous cell carcinomas. METHODS AND MATERIALS: One hundred nine patients with previously untreated T3 and T4 squamous cell carcinomas of the glottic larynx were treated with curative intent in this Institutional Review Board-approved outcome study using continuous-course RT alone (106 patients) or followed by a planned neck dissection (3 patients) between September 1966 and June 2002. Patients selected for such treatment had relatively low-volume, unilateral disease. Patients were staged according to the recommendations of the American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) as follows: T3N0, 68 patients (62%); T3N1, 14 patients (13%); T3N2B, 5 patients (5%); T4N0, 17 patients (16%); T4N1, 4 patients (4%); and T4N2B, 1 patient. RESULTS: The 5-year outcomes after treatment were: local control for stage T3 and T4, 78% and 81%; locoregional control for AJCC stage III and IVa, 62% and 78%; distant metastasis-free survival for AJCC stage III and IVa, 97% and 100%; cause-specific survival for AJCC stage III and IVa, 84% and 87%; and overall survival for AJCC stage III and IVa, 52% and 67%, respectively. Severe complications occurred in 13 patients (12%). CONCLUSIONS: The results of this retrospective study compare favorably with those published elsewhere in the literature for T3 and T4 vocal cord carcinomas. Local control and ultimate cure probabilities will hopefully improve further with the addition of concomitant chemotherapy to RT for larger tumors.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology at the University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA. hinerrw@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17414468; 00000421-200704000-00012 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000251368.57302.cc</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17414468</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1660</id>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Postoperative irradiation for squamous cell carcinoma of the oral cavity: 35-year experience</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>984</sp>
<op>994</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Multivariate Analysis</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Invasiveness</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Care</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The purpose of this study was to analyze factors influencing outcome in patients who received postoperative irradiation for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the oral cavity. METHODS: Between October 1964 and November 2000, 226 patients with 230 previously untreated primary invasive squamous cell carcinomas of the oral cavity were treated postoperatively with continuous-course external beam irradiation. All patients had a minimum follow-up of 2 years (analysis, November 2002). No patient was lost to follow-up. RESULTS: The 5-year actuarial rates of locoregional control by pathologic American Joint Committee on Cancer stage were: stage I, 100%; stage II, 84%; stage III, 78%; and stage IV, 66%. Recurrence of cancer above the clavicles developed in 55 patients (24%). In multivariate analysis of locoregional control, positive margins, vascular invasion, perineural invasion, extracapsular extension, and T classification remained significant. CONCLUSIONS: This article provides additional data defining relatively favorable and unfavorable groups of patients in the postoperative setting. Dose recommendations are re-examined and selectively increased for high-risk patients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida Shands Cancer Center, PO Box 100385, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA. hinerrw@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15459927</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20091</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15459927</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1647</id>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Lansford,C. D.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Surgery and postoperative radiotherapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx and pharynx</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>613</sp>
<op>621</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Pharyngeal Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine the rates of local-regional control, survival, and complications for patients treated with postoperative radiation for squamous carcinomas of the larynx, hypopharynx, and oropharynx. METHODS: There were 295 patients with previously untreated squamous cell carcinomas of the larynx (n = 199), hypopharynx (n = 80), and oropharynx (n = 16) treated postoperatively with radiotherapy (RT). RESULTS: Five-year local-regional control rates according to site and pathologic American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) stage were: stage III larynx, 89% versus stage IVA larynx, 85% (P = 0.33); stage III oropharynx/hypopharynx, 76% versus stage IVA oropharynx/hypopharynx, 79% (P = 0.72). Local-regional control rates steadily declined as the number of indications for administering postoperative RT increased. Five-year absolute survival rates versus pathologic AJCC stage for the entire group were: stage III 59% and stage IVA 40% (P = 0.40). CONCLUSION: Rates of local-regional control, survival, and complications support the use of postoperative radiation in selected patients. Tumor control and survival will hopefully improve further with the addition of chemotherapy to postoperative radiation.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32510-0385, USA. hinerrw@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17149000; 00000421-200612000-00016 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000242319.09994.78</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17149000</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1640</id>
<a1>Hodge,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Role of radiotherapy for pleomorphic adenoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>148</sp>
<op>151</op>
<k1>Adenoma, Pleomorphic/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Salivary Gland Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>The purpose of this article was to evaluate the role of radiotherapy (RT) in the treatment of pleomorphic adenoma. This is a retrospective analysis of 17 patients treated with RT alone (2 patients) or combined with surgery (15 patients). Follow up ranged from 1.8 to 27.1 years (median, 9.6 years). Local control was obtained in 8 of 10 patients (80%) with subclinical disease and 3 of 7 patients (43%) with gross disease. Overall local control was obtained in 11 of 17 patients (65%). The 5- and 10-year overall local control rates were 69% and 61%, respectively. One patient died secondary to tumor extension into the central nervous system, 1 patient had recurrence of carcinoma ex-pleomorphic adenoma and died of cancer at the primary site, 5 patients died free of disease, and 10 patients were alive at last follow up. RT is relatively effective at controlling subclinical disease in patients at high risk for developing recurrence after surgery for pleomorphic adenoma. Limited data suggest that RT may also occasionally control gross disease.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15803008; 00000421-200504000-00008 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15803008</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1633</id>
<a1>Hull,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Tannehill,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy alone or combined with a planned neck dissection for squamous cell carcinoma of the pharyngeal wall</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Nov 15</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>2224</sp>
<op>2231</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Dose Fractionation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Pharyngeal Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: In the current study,the authors analyzed the results of definitive radiotherapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the pharyngeal wall. METHODS: Between 1964 and 2000, 148 patients were treated with definitive radiotherapy. All patients had a 2-year minimum follow-up. RESULTS: The following 5-year rates of local and ultimate local control were obtained: T1 disease, 93% and 93%; T2 disease, 82% and 87%; T3 disease, 59% and 61%; and T4 disease, 50% and 50%, respectively. Multivariate analysis revealed that twice-daily fractionation (P = 0.0009), American Joint Committee on Cancer Stage I-II disease (P = 0.0051), and oropharyngeal primary site (P = 0.0193) were associated with improved locoregional control. The following 5-year absolute and cause-specific survival rates were obtained: Stage I, 56% and 89%; Stage II, 52% and 88%; Stage III, 24% and 44%; Stage IV, 22% and 34%; and overall, 30% and 49%, respectively. Eight patients (5%) died of complications. CONCLUSIONS: Locoregional control and survival were found to be related to site, extent of disease, and fractionation schedule. Although outcomes have improved in recent years, the morbidity of treatment was significant in the current study and a substantial proportion of patients died secondary to the malignancy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; CI: Copyright 2003; JID: 0374236; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14601093</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.11772</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14601093</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1631</id>
<a1>Hunyadi,S.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Lewin,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of magnetic resonance imaging on a new electromagnetic implantable middle ear hearing device</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>328</sp>
<op>331</op>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging/adverse effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: A 1.5-T magnetic resonance imager has been shown to be contraindicated for use in patients with pacemakers, cochlear implants, and neurostimulators. Our semi-implantable middle ear device uses a new adhesive bone cement. 4-META/MMA-TBB, for cementation of a 29-mg titanium-encased neodymium-iron-boron (NdFeB) magnet to the incus. METHODS: Five NdFeB magnets and four solid titanium cylinders were cemented onto the incus of five preserved human temporal bones and two cadaver heads. They were all inserted into a magnetic resonance imager and evaluated for possible disruption. RESULTS: Owing to the magnetic torque, the three magnets on the temporal bone were disrupted from the incus. The two cylinders on the temporal bones and the two cylinders and two magnets on the whole heads were not affected. The magnetic resonance imaging field did not affect the coercive force of the NdFeB magnets. CONCLUSION: The large torque produced by a magnetic resonance imager may disrupt the magnet-cement and cement-incus interfaces, causing dislodgement. We postulate that patients with implantable magnets on the incus should not undergo magnetic resonance imaging testing.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7909513; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University, University Hospitals of Cleveland, OH 44106-5045, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9149826</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9149826</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1628</id>
<a1>Leon,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Catalanotto,F. A.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Retronasal and orthonasal olfactory ability after laryngectomy</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>133</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>36</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngectomy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nose</k1>
<k1>Olfaction Disorders/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Self Assessment (Psychology)</k1>
<k1>Smell/physiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To characterize orthonasal and retronasal olfactory ability in patients who have had a total laryngectomy (TL). DESIGN: Prospective psychophysical evaluation of orthonasal and retronasal olfactory function. SETTING: Academic center outpatient clinic. PATIENTS: Volunteer sample of 36 subjects who underwent laryngectomy 0.5 to 25.0 years after TL (median, 3.5 years) and 36 age-, sex-, and smoking history-matched controls. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Scores on established psychophysical tests of orthonasal and retronasal olfaction and self-rating scores of smell assessed with a visual analog scale. RESULTS: Assessment of orthonasal olfactory ability yielded a mean composite score of 4.3 (maximum score, 7) for the TL group and 5.3 for the control group (P = .002). Evaluation of retronasal olfactory ability resulted in a mean score of 11.0 (maximum score, 20) for the TL group vs 14.3 for the control group (P&amp;lt;.001). The mean self-rating scores of smell were 2.9 and 6.6 (maximum score, 10) for the TL and control groups, respectively (P&amp;lt;.001). Self-ratings of smell positively correlated with orthonasal (r(S) = 0.42; P&amp;lt;.001) and retronasal (r(S) = 0.50; P&amp;lt;.001) olfactory ability. CONCLUSIONS: Laryngectomy is associated with measurable decreases in olfactory function that are also subjectively perceived. Quantification of decrements in orthonasal and retronasal olfactory function can be used to characterize the severity of hyposmia and to assess the potential for, and efficacy of, olfactory rehabilitation. Although self-assessment with a simple visual analog scale successfully identifies many laryngectomy patients who have objective evidence of olfactory dysfunction, further investigation is necessary to evaluate and compare its validity and reliability with other available survey instruments that purport to measure olfaction.</ab>
<no>JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology and Community Dentistry and Behavioral Science, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17224519; 133/1/32 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archotol.133.1.32</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17224519</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1663</id>
<a1>Liauw,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Isolated neck recurrence after definitive radiotherapy for node-positive head and neck cancer: salvage in the dissected or undissected neck</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>715</sp>
<op>719</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/drug therapy/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/drug therapy/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Node Excision</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection/methods</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The role of salvage neck dissection for isolated regional recurrences after definitive radiotherapy (RT) is ill-defined. METHODS: Five-hundred fifty patients were treated with RT for lymph node-positive head and neck cancer. RT consisted of a median dose of 74.4 Gy. Chemotherapy was administered in 133 patients (24%). Patients were followed for neck failure after planned neck dissection (n = 341) or observation (n = 209). Salvage therapy was offered to those with isolated neck recurrences. RESULTS: There were 54 (10%) failures in the neck at a median 3.7 months after RT (range, 0 to 17 months). Thirteen patients had isolated recurrences after receiving definitive RT with (n = 11) or without (n = 2) neck dissection. Nine patients underwent attempted surgical salvage with or without re-irradiation and 4 were successfully salvaged without major complications. CONCLUSIONS: Patients with neck failure after definitive therapy usually have poor outcomes, but salvage attempts may be successful in selected patients with an isolated neck recurrence.</ab>
<no>JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17274056</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20580</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17274056</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1667</id>
<a1>Liauw,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Postradiotherapy neck dissection for lymph node-positive head and neck cancer: the use of computed tomography to manage the neck</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Mar 20</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1421</sp>
<op>1427</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiography/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Node Excision</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis/radiography</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm, Residual</k1>
<k1>Predictive Value of Tests</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To determine how to use node response on computed tomography (CT) to indicate the need for neck dissection. PATIENTS AND METHODS: Five hundred fifty patients with lymph node-positive head and neck cancer were treated between 1990 and 2002 with radiotherapy (RT) at a median dose of 74.4 Gy; 24% of these patients (n = 133) were treated with chemotherapy. Three hundred forty-one patients (62%) underwent planned post-RT neck dissection. Physical examination and contrast-enhanced CT were performed 30 days after completion of RT. CT images were reviewed in 211 patients for lymph node size (largest axial dimension) and presence of a focal abnormality (lucency, enhancement, or calcification). By correlating post-RT CT to neck dissection pathology, criteria associated with a low likelihood of residual disease were identified. A subset of patients who fit these criteria of radiographic response who did not undergo post-RT neck dissection was observed for recurrence. RESULTS: Radiographic complete response (rCR) was defined as the absence of any large (&amp;gt; 1.5 cm) or focally abnormal lymph node. Correlation of response with neck dissection pathology indicated a negative predictive value of 77% for complete clinical response and 94% for rCR. In 32 patients (median follow-up time, 3.2 years) with rCR who did not undergo post-RT neck dissection, the 5-year ultimate neck control rate (100%) and cause-specific survival rate (72%) were not significantly different from the rates of patients with a negative post-RT neck dissection. CONCLUSION: Patients with rCR 4 weeks after RT can be spared from a post-RT neck dissection regardless of initial node stage.</ab>
<no>JID: 8309333; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1527-7755; 0732-183X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16549836; 24/9/1421 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1200/JCO.2005.04.6052</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16549836</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1656</id>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Ko,W. H.</a1>
<a1>Rosenbaum,M.</a1>
<a1>Falk,T.</a1>
<a1>Zhu,W. L.</a1>
<a1>Frenz,N. W.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J.</a1>
<a1>Masin,J.</a1>
<a1>Stein,A.</a1>
<a1>Sabri,A.</a1>
<t1>Contactless semi-implantable electromagnetic middle ear device for the treatment of sensorineural hearing loss. Short-term and long-term animal experiments</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>121</sp>
<op>140</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Hearing Aids</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/physiopathology/rehabilitation/surgery</k1>
<k1>Magnetics</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants</k1>
<ab>A contactless electromagnetic hearing device has been designed following basic science experiments, improvement of electronics, and precision micromechanics. Different prototypes have been developed and tested in the laboratory, fresh human temporal bones, and acute and chronic animal experimentation. A conductive hearing loss model was first developed in the cat using samarium cobalt as the target magnet. Later, a highly efficient electromagnetic air-core coil was selected to vibrate a neodymium iron boron magnet cemented to the body of the incus and tested in acute and chronic experiments using the cat as the model. In this group of animals, the ossicular chain was left intact. There was no failure of the target magnet, driving coil, or implanted electronics. The only problem encountered in this evaluation was a malfunction of the receiving antenna that had to be redesigned and retrofitted into the implanted units. This system would be suitable for the treatment of moderate to severe sensorineural hearing loss. Planning to begin human clinical trials is ongoing.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01 DC-0153-01/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0144042; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, University Hospital of Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7739859</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7739859</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1657</id>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Ko,W. H.</a1>
<a1>Rosenbaum,M.</a1>
<a1>Zhu,W. L.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J.</a1>
<a1>Belser,R.</a1>
<a1>Drago,P.</a1>
<a1>Falk,T.</a1>
<a1>Frenz,W.</a1>
<t1>A contactless electromagnetic implantable middle ear device for sensorineural hearing loss</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>78</sp>
<op>82, 84-8, 90</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Cements</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle</k1>
<k1>Electromagnetic Phenomena</k1>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Hearing Aids</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/classification/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Materials Testing</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<ab>Following basic science experiments, improvement of precision micromechanics and electronics design, and development of different prototypes, a contactless electromagnetic hearing device has been successfully implanted in cats (acute experiments). Chronic animal experiments using the cat as well as the rabbit are ongoing to test the components of the device. A highly efficient air core coil is used to vibrate a neodymium-iron-boron magnet cemented to the body of the incus. The parts of the system, including implanted electronics (hybrid circuit, solid state), are laser welded and hermetically sealed. The system allows for the generation of enough force which vibrates the magnet implanted on the incus. It would be suitable for the treatment of moderate to severe sensorineural hearing loss.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: R01 DC-0153-02/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7701817; 0 (Bone Cements); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, University Hospitals of Cleveland, OH 44106.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8168450</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8168450</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1632</id>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Nakabayashi,N.</a1>
<a1>Paparella,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>A new adhesive bonding material for the cementation of implantable devices in otologic surgery</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>327</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Cementation</k1>
<k1>Ear/surgery</k1>
<k1>Ear Ossicles/surgery</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Tissue Adhesives</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Presently, there are no U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved adhesive bone cements for the surgical fixation of prosthetic materials in the middle ear. A promising new cement, 4-META/MMA-TBB opaque resin, has shown remarkable adhesive properties as a bone cement in vivo. The cement is composed of 4-methacryloyloxyethyl trimellitate anhydride (4-META) and methyl methacrylate (MMA) as monomers and tri-n-butyl borane (TBB) as an initiator. METHODS: An electromagnetic semiimplantable hearing device presently under development was implanted into the middle ear of six cats using 4-META/MMA-TBB resin to cement a titanium-encased magnet to the incus. The animals were subsequently killed (at a mean of 9.6 months) to assess the (temporal bones and specifically the magnet-incus complex in each animal. RESULTS: The titanium-encapsulated magnet was firmly adherent to all incuses without any failure of the cement-bone interface. Histopathologic examination of the implanted temporal bones demonstrated lack of middle ear inflammation. Transmission electron microscopy of the incuses demonstrated a unique &amp;quot;hybrid layer&amp;quot; in the bone-side subsurface of the bone-cement interface that elucidates the mechanism of interfacial adhesion. CONCLUSIONS: Our investigation highlights the special biomechanical properties as well as the biocompatibility of 4-META/ MMA-TBB resin that make it an attractive bone-bonding agent for use in otologic surgery, including its potential usefulness during ossicular reconstruction.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01-DC01953-03/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7909513; 0 (Tissue Adhesives); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University, University Hospitals of Cleveland, Ohio 44106-5045, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9149825</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9149825</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1644</id>
<a1>McAfee,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy for juvenile nasopharyngeal angiofibroma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>168</sp>
<op>170</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Angiofibroma/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nasopharyngeal Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To update our experience with definitive radiotherapy (RT) for juvenile nasopharyngeal angiofibroma (JNA). METHODS: Twenty-two patients received definitive RT for advanced JNA between June 1975 and March 2003 and were followed from 2.0 to 30.2 years (median, 12.7 years). Total dose ranged from 30 to 36 Gy. RESULTS: Twenty of 22 patients (91%) remained locally controlled after RT; both patients who developed a local recurrence were salvaged so that the ultimate local control rate was 100%. No patient experienced a severe complication. CONCLUSION: Patients with advanced and/or recurrent JNA thought not to be amenable to complete resection with acceptable morbidity have a high likelihood of cure after RT with a low risk of complications.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16601437; 00000421-200604000-00013 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000203759.94019.76</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16601437</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1636</id>
<a1>McAfee,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Merkel cell carcinoma: treatment and outcomes</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct 15</fd>
<vo>104</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1761</sp>
<op>1764</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Antineoplastic Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Merkel Cell/drug therapy/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Skin Neoplasms/drug therapy/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The purpose of the current study was to determine the outcomes of patients with previously untreated Merkel cell carcinoma of the skin who were treated with curative intent. METHODS: Between October 1984 and January 2002, 34 patients were treated with radiotherapy alone (2 patients) or combined with surgery (32 patients). Nine patients received adjuvant chemotherapy. Patients had follow-up for a median of 3.0 years (range, 0.3 to 18.5 yrs). Follow-up on living patients ranged from 2.2 to 18.5 years (median, 7.1 yrs). RESULTS: The 5-year outcomes were as follows: local control, 94%, locoregional control, 80%; freedom from distant metastases, 60%; cause-specific survival, 52%; and survival, 37%. No patient experienced a severe complication. CONCLUSIONS: Patients treated aggressively with surgery and locoregional radiotherapy have about a 50% chance of cure. Limited data suggest that definitive radiotherapy alone or after incomplete macroscopic resection may control locoregional disease in a significant subset of patients. The dominant site of failure was distant.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright 2005; JID: 0374236; 0 (Antineoplastic Agents); ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16136596</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Multicenter Study; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.21355</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16136596</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1676</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Yeung,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Radiotherapeutic management of the neck</t1>
<yr>2010</yr>
<no>ID: 540411399</no>
<pa>CD ROM given on CV. WorldCat gives print edition pub dates of 2008 and 2010; CV says 2009 for CD-ROM.</pa>
<a2>Ferlito,Alfio</a2><a2> Robbins,K. Thomas</a2><a2>Silver,Carl E.</a2>
<t2>Neck dissection management of regional disease in head and neck cancer</t2>
<pb>Plural</pb>
<pp>San Diego; Oxford</pp>
<sn>9781597563130 1597563137</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1681</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Laryngeal cancer: Epidemiology and treatment outcomes</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<ab>This book focuses on functional treatment outcomes in head and neck cancer patients from the perspective of experts from around the world in medical and allied health fields. Recent advances in management strategies are presented as they relate to functional preservation and quality of life. Clinical and research knowledge is organized in an approachable manner by means of short chapters, key point tables, and high-quality illustrations and graphics. This method of presentation is very effective for busy clinical practitioners and researchers. Information is provided on site-specific epidemiology and treatment outcome, the impact of different treatment techniques and toxicities on quality of life, and the relationship of toxicity prevention, rehabilitation, and supportive care to quality of life after treatment. Among literature on the treatment of head and neck cancer, this book is unique because of the outstanding list of contributors and the specific focus on functional preservation and quality of life..</ab>
<no>ID: 551425983</no>
<a2>Harari,Paul M.</a2><a2> Connor,Nadine P.</a2><a2> Grau,Cai</a2><a2>Amdur,Robert J.</a2>
<t2>Functional preservation and quality of life in head and neck radiotherapy</t2>
<ed>1</ed>
<pb>Springer-Verlag</pb>
<pp>Berlin</pp>
<sn>3540732322 9783540732327</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1680</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Laryngeal squamous cell carcinoma: Treatment options and outcomes</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<no>ID: 429588898</no>
<a2>Nemecek,O.</a2><a2> Mares,V.</a2>
<t2>Laryngeal diseases : symptoms, diagnosis and treatments</t2>
<pb>Nova Science</pb>
<pp>Hauppauge, NY</pp>
<sn>9781608761074 160876107X</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1679</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Pfister,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Treatment of head and neck cancers</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>Chapter 36, Section 2</is>
<sp>809</sp>
<op>809-876</op>
<k1>Cancer</k1>
<k1>Oncology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms</k1>
<no>editors, Vincent T. DeVita, Jr., Theodore S. Lawrence, Steven A. Rosenberg ; associate scientific advisors, Robert A. Weinberg, Ronald A. DePinho ; with 421 contributing authors. : editors, Vincent T. DeVita, Jr., Theodore S. Lawrence, Steven A. Rosenberg ; associate scientific advisors, Robert A. Weinberg, Ronald A. DePinho ; with 421 contributing authors.; Uniform Title: Cancer, principles &amp;amp; practice of oncology.; Alternate title: Cancer; 50011 Rev. ed. of: Cancer, principles &amp;amp; practice of oncology. 7th ed. c2005.; 50412 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>DeVita,Vincent T.</a2><a2> Lawrence,Theodore S.</a2><a2>Rosenberg,Steven A.</a2>
<t2>DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg&amp;#39;s cancer : principles &amp;amp; practice of oncology</t2>
<ed>8</ed>
<pb>Wolters Kluwer/Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia</pp>
<sn>0781772079 (alk. paper); 9780781772075 (alk. paper)</sn>
<lk>Publisher description http://www.loc.gov/catdir/enhancements/fy0811/2008006079-d.html</lk>
<cn>QZ200.C21537 2008 (Jacksonville UFHSCL Borland Reference); QZ200.C21537 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY Reference)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1639</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Grobmyer,S. R.</a1>
<a1>George,T. J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Hochwald,S. N.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Adjuvant radiotherapy for cutaneous melanoma</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar 15</fd>
<vo>112</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1189</sp>
<op>1196</op>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Melanoma/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</k1>
<k1>Skin Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<ab>The purpose of the current study was to discuss the efficacy of adjuvant radiotherapy (RT) in the treatment of melanoma by reviewing the pertinent literature. The risk of locoregional recurrence after surgery alone for locally advanced melanoma is relatively high. The likelihood of a positive sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) exceeds 20% for melanomas&amp;gt;2 mm thick and approximately&amp;gt;or=20% of those patients with positive SLNB will be found to have residual positive lymph nodes on completion lymph node dissection. Patients with positive regional lymph nodes have an approximately&amp;gt;or=20% risk of regional recurrence after surgery alone, particularly if multiple lymph nodes are involved and/or extracapsular extension is present. Postoperative adjuvant RT results in locoregional control rates of 85% to 90% or higher in high-risk patients with a modest risk of complications. The impact of adjuvant RT on survival is likely minimal.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright (c) 2008; JID: 0374236; RF: 54; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendwm@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18260153</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.23306</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18260153</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1678</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Management of the neck including unknown primary tumor</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>46</is>
<sp>1035</sp>
<op>1035-1054</op>
<k1>Cancer -- Radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms -- radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Radiometry</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy -- methods</k1>
<ab>Contents: 01 The discipline of radiation oncology -- Biologic basis of radiation therapy -- Molecular cancer and radiation biology -- Molecular pathophysiology of tumors -- Principles of radiologic physics, dosimetry, and treatment planning -- Photon external-beam dosimetry and treatment planning -- Electron-beam therapy: dosimetry, planning, and techniques -- Three-dimensional conformal radiation therapy: physics, treatment planning, and clinical aspects -- Intensity-modulated radiation treatment techniques and clinical applications -- Image-guided radiation therapy -- Altered fractionation schedules -- Late effects of cancer treatment on normal tissues -- Methodology of clinical trials -- Total-body and hemibody irradiation -- Stereotactic radiosurgery and radiotherapy -- Sterotatic irradiation of tumors outside the central nervous system -- Intraoperative radiotherapy -- Particle beam radiotherapy -- Physics and biology of brachytherapy --^; Contents: 02 ^^ Clinical applications of brachytherapy: low-dose-rate and pulse-dose-rate -- The physics and dosimetry of high-dose-rate brachytherapy -- Clinical aspects and applications of high-dose-rate brachytherapy -- Radioimmunoglobulins and nonsealed radionuclide therapy -- Photodynamic therapy -- Radiation oncology in the developing world -- Chemical modifiers of radiation response -- Oncologic imaging/oncologic anatomy -- Hyperthermia -- Basic concepts of chemotherapy and irradiation interaction -- Skin -- Malignant neoplasms associated with the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome -- Primary intracranial neoplasms -- Pituitary -- Spinal canal -- Eye and orbit -- Ear -- The role of combined radiotherapy and chemotherapy in the management of locally advanced squamous carcinoma of the head and neck -- Nasopharynx -- Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses -- Salivary glands -- Oral cavity cancer -- Oropharynx -- Hypopharynx cancer -- Larynx -- Unusual nonepithelial tumors of the head and neck --^; Contents: 03 ^^ Management of the neck including unknwon primary tumor -- Thyroid -- Lung -- Mediastinum and trachea --; Contents: 04 Esophageal cancer -- Tumors of the heart and great vessels -- Breast: stage tis -- Early stage breast cancer -- Breast cancer: locally advanced and recurrent disease, postmastectomy radiation, and systemic therapies -- Stomach -- Cancer of the pancreas -- Liver and hepatobiliary tract -- Colon and rectum -- Anal cancer -- Kidney, renal pelvis, and ureter -- Bladder -- Low-risk prostate cancer -- Intermediate- and high-risk prostate cancer -- Testis -- Penis and male urethra -- Uterine cervix -- Endometrium -- Ovary -- Fallopian tube -- Vagina -- Female urethra -- Carcinoma of the vulva -- Retroperitoneum -- Adrenal gland -- Hodgkin lymphoma -- Non-Hodgkin&amp;#39;s lymphoma -- Cutaneous T-cell lymphoma -- Leukemia -- Plasma cell myeloma and plasmacytoma -- Osteosarcoma -- Soft tissue sarcomas (excluding retroperitoneum) -- Central nervous system tumors in children -- Wilms&amp;#39; tumor -- Neuroblastoma -- Rhabdomyosarcoma -- Ewing tumor -- Lymphomas in children -- Unusual tumors in childhood -- Radiotherapy of non-malignant diseases -- Endovascular brachytherapy -- Palliation of brain and spinal cord metastases -- Palliation of bone metastases -- Palliation of visceral recurrences and metastases -- Pain management -- Supportive care and quality of life -- Technology assessment, cost benefit, outcome analysis research and evidence-based radiation oncology -- Ethics, professional values, and legal considerations in radiation oncology -- The economics of radiation oncology.</ab>
<no>editors, Edward C. Halperin, Carlos A. Perez, Luther W. Brady ; associate editors, David E. Wazer, Carolyn Freeman, Leonard R. Prosnitz. : editors, Edward C. Halperin, Carlos A. Perez, Luther W. Brady ; associate editors, David E. Wazer, Carolyn Freeman, Leonard R. Prosnitz.; Uniform Title: Principles and practice of radiation oncology.; Alternate title: Principles and practice of radiation oncology; 50011 Rev. ed. of: Principles and practice of radiation oncology / editors, Carlos A. Perez ... [et al.]. c2004.; 50412 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Brady,Luther W.</a2><a2> Halperin,Edward C.</a2><a2>Perez,Carlos A.</a2>
<t2>Perez and Brady&amp;#39;s principles and practice of radiation oncology</t2>
<ed>5</ed>
<pb>Wolters Kluwer Health/Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia</pp>
<sn>078176369X; 9780781763691</sn>
<lk>Publisher description http://www.loc.gov/catdir/enhancements/fy0730/2007027840-d.html</lk>
<cn>QZ269.P957 2008 (Jacksonville UFHSCL Borland)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1648</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Skin cancer of the head and neck with perineural invasion</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>93</sp>
<op>96</op>
<k1>Brain Neoplasms/pathology</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Invasiveness</k1>
<k1>Nervous System Neoplasms/pathology</k1>
<k1>Skin Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy</k1>
<ab>Perineural invasion occurs in 2% to 6% of cutaneous basal and squamous cell carcinomas of the head and neck and is associated with midface location, recurrent tumors, high histologic grade, and increasing tumor size. Patients may be asymptomatic with perineural invasion appreciated on pathologic examination of the surgical specimen (incidental) or may present with cranial nerve deficits (clinical). The cranial nerves most commonly involved are the 5th and 7th nerves. Magnetic resonance imaging is obtained to detect and define the extent of perineural invasion; computed tomography is used to detect regional lymph node metastases. Patients with apparently resectable cancers undergo surgery usually followed by postoperative radiotherapy. Patients with incompletely resectable cancers are treated with definitive radiotherapy. The 5-year local control, cause-specific survival, and overall survival rates are approximately 87%, 65%, and 50%, respectively, for patients with incidental perineural invasion compared with 55%, 59%, and 55%, respectively, for those with clinical perineural invasion.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 33; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17278901; 00000421-200702000-00016 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000251224.16075.60</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17278901</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1642</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Head and neck mucosal melanoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>626</sp>
<op>630</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunotherapy</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melanoma/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mouth Mucosa/pathology</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Mucous Membrane/pathology</k1>
<k1>Nasal Mucosa/pathology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Palatal Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: The purpose of this article is to discuss the optimal treatment and outcomes for head and neck mucosal melanoma. METHODS: Review the pertinent literature. RESULTS: Head and neck mucosal melanoma is a rare entity comprising less than 1% for all Western melanomas. It usually arises in the nasal cavity, paranasal sinuses, and oral cavity. The optimal treatment is surgery. The likelihood of local recurrence after resection is approximately 50%. Radiotherapy (RT) reduces the likelihood of local failure but probably does not enhance survival, which is primarily impacted by advanced T stage and the presence of regional metastases. The 5-year survival rates vary from approximately 20 to 50%. Although the median time to relapse is roughly 1 year or less, late failures are common and cause-specific survival continues to decline after 5 years. CONCLUSION: The optimal treatment is surgery. Postoperative RT improves local-regional control but may not impact survival. Definitive RT may occasionally cure patients with unresectable local-regional disease or at least provide long-term palliation.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 25; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16317276; 00000421-200512000-00017 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16317276</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1672</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Carcinoma of the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>899</sp>
<op>906</op>
<k1>Carcinoma/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nasal Cavity/pathology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: To determine the outcomes after radiotherapy (RT) alone or combined with surgery at the University of Florida for patients with carcinomas of the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. METHODS: Between November 1964 and June 2005, 109 patients were treated with curative intent. Patients with maxillary sinus carcinomas were excluded. Fifty-six patients were treated with definitive RT, and 53 patients received surgery and preoperative (eight patients) or postoperative (45 patients) RT. Median follow-up was 4.3 years (range, 0.2-35.9 years). Median follow-up on living patients was 9.4 years (range, 2.0-35.9 years). RESULTS: The 5-year local control rates were: T1-T3, 82%; T4, 50%; and overall, 63%. Local control at 5 years was 43% after definitive RT versus 84% after surgery and adjuvant RT (P &amp;lt; .0001). Multivariate analysis of local control revealed that both overall stage and treatment group (definitive RT versus surgery and adjuvant RT) significantly impacted this endpoint. Cause-specific survival rates were: stages I to III, 81%; stage IV, 54%; and overall, 62%. Multivariate analysis revealed that T-stage, N-stage, and treatment group significantly influenced this endpoint. Thirty-one (20%) of 109 patients sustained severe complications; 17 of 56 patients (16%) after definitive RT and 14 of 53 patients (25%) after surgery and adjuvant RT. CONCLUSIONS: The probability of local control and cause-specific survival is better after surgery and RT compared with definitive RT. There is a modest increase in the risk of complications after surgery and RT. Thus, the preferred treatment is surgery combined with preoperative or postoperative RT.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendwm@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19358246</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/lary.20196</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19358246</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1668</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Lansford,C. D.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Postoperative radiotherapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck</t1>
<jf>Clinical medicine &amp; research</jf>
<jo>Clin.Med.Res.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>200</sp>
<op>208</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/drug therapy/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/drug therapy/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>This review discusses the role of postoperative radiotherapy (RT) for patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Patients with unfavorable pathologic features have a high-risk of local-regional recurrence and a decreased likelihood of survival after surgery alone. Postoperative RT reduces the risk of local-regional failure and probably improves survival. Patients who are at high risk for recurrence may benefit from more aggressive altered fractionation schedules to decrease the overall time from surgery to the completion of RT. Adjuvant cisplatin-based chemotherapy also appears to improve the probability of cure in high-risk patients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 101175887; RF: 40; OID: NLM: PMC1570489; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1539-4182; 1539-4182</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16988100; 4/3/200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16988100</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1570489</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1650</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Inverted papilloma of the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>560</sp>
<op>563</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Papilloma/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To discuss the treatment and outcomes of inverted papilloma of the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. METHODS: Review of the pertinent literature. RESULTS: Inverted papilloma is a benign, locally aggressive neoplasm that arises in the nasal cavity and is associated with squamous cell carcinoma in approximately 5% of patients. Squamous cell carcinoma may be present with inverted papilloma at the initial diagnosis or it may occur metachronously after prior treatment. Surgery is the primary treatment of inverted papilloma. The likelihood of local recurrence varies from less than 5% to over 50%, depending on the extent of resection. There is likely no significant difference in the risk of local recurrence after open compared with endoscopic resection. The probability of local recurrence and/or death from tumor is increased if inverted papilloma is associated with squamous cell carcinoma. The likelihood of cure is approximately 50% when malignancy is present and postoperative radiotherapy should be considered for the majority of patients. A small subset of patients with inverted papilloma present with incompletely resectable disease. Definitive radiotherapy using doses between 65 and 70 Gy will locally control gross disease in the majority of patients. CONCLUSION: The preferred treatment of inverted papilloma is surgery; postoperative radiotherapy is added if it is associated with squamous cell carcinoma. The likelihood of local recurrence after surgery for inverted papilloma may be substantial and varies with the extent of resection. Definitive radiotherapy may be used to successfully treat patients with incompletely resectable inverted papilloma.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 21; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17921720; 00000421-200710000-00017 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e318064c711</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17921720</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1669</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Multidisciplinary management of laryngeal carcinoma</t1>
<jf>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Radiat.Oncol.Biol.Phys.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>2 Suppl</is>
<sp>S12</sp>
<op>4</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Glottis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<ab>The management of head and neck cancer has evolved into a multidisciplinary approach in which patients are evaluated before treatment and decisions depend on prospective multi-institutional trials, as well as retrospective outcome studies. The choice of one or more modalities to use in a given case varies with the tumor site and extent, as exemplified in the treatment of laryngeal squamous cell carcinomas. The goals of treatment include cure, laryngeal voice preservation, voice quality, optimal swallowing, and minimal xerostomia. Treatment options include transoral laser excision, radiotherapy (both definitive and postoperative), open partial laryngectomy, total laryngectomy, and neck dissection. The likelihood of local control and preservation of laryngeal function is related to tumor volume. Patients who have a relatively high risk of local recurrence undergo follow-up computed tomography scans every 3-4 months for the first 2 years after radiotherapy. Patients with suspicious findings on computed tomography might benefit from fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography to differentiate post-radiotherapy changes from tumor.</ab>
<no>JID: 7603616; RF: 10; 2007/02/28 [received]; 2007/04/24 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0360-3016; 0360-3016</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17848278; S0360-3016(07)00961-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ijrobp.2007.05.036</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17848278</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1654</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Salivary gland pleomorphic adenoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>95</sp>
<op>99</op>
<k1>Adenoma, Pleomorphic/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/diagnosis/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Salivary Gland Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>We discuss the optimal treatment and outcomes for pleomorphic adenoma of the salivary glands by reviewing the pertinent literature. Pleomorphic adenoma is the most common benign salivary gland neoplasm. It is found mostly in the parotid gland in middle-aged women. It progresses slowly and, left untreated, can produce significant morbidity and, rarely, death. The optimal treatment is superficial or total parotidectomy with facial nerve preservation, which results in local control rates of 95% or higher. Radiotherapy (RT) is useful to obtain local control in patients with positive margins, unresectable tumors, and multifocal recurrences after prior resection. Local control rates after RT for microscopic and gross residual tumor are approximately 80% to 85% and 40% to 60%, respectively. The main complication is surgically induced 7th nerve injury. Surgery is the mainstay of treatment and results in a very high cure rate. RT increases the likelihood of local control in the small subset of patients with incompletely resectable tumors and/or multifocal recurrences.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 25; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA. mendwm@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18376235; 00000421-200802000-00016 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e3181595ae0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18376235</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1646</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Reith,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Cutaneous angiosarcoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>524</sp>
<op>528</op>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Hemangiosarcoma/diagnosis/etiology/mortality/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Skin Neoplasms/diagnosis/etiology/mortality/therapy</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To discuss the treatment and outcomes for cutaneous angiosarcoma. METHODS: Review of the pertinent literature. RESULTS: Cutaneous angiosarcoma is a rare, aggressive malignancy with a poor prognosis. It usually arises in the scalp or face and is locally advanced at presentation. Patients are most often white, male, and elderly. A subset of patients presents with multifocal disease and/or positive regional nodes. Although the optimal treatment is surgery followed by wide-field radiotherapy (RT), the disease is frequently so extensive at diagnosis that it is not completely resectable. Even after optimal local-regional treatment, there is a relatively high likelihood of a local recurrence at the margins of the RT fields. The probability of hematogenous dissemination is relatively high. Limited data suggest that chemotherapy may be useful for palliation with progression-free survival rates ranging from 1 to 5 months. The 5-year local-regional control rates are approximately 40% to 50%, the 5-year distant metastasis-free survival rates range from 20% to 40%, and the 5-year survival rates range from 10% to 30%. CONCLUSION: Cutaneous angiosarcoma is a rare, aggressive malignancy that is optimally treated with resection and wide-field postoperative RT. The likelihood of local-regional failure is high, as is the risk of distant relapse. Chemotherapy may be useful for short-term palliation.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 27; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17023791; 00000421-200610000-00019 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000227544.01779.52</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17023791</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1661</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Riggs,C. E.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Adult head and neck soft tissue sarcomas</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>916</sp>
<op>922</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Sarcoma/therapy</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The purpose was to determine the optimal treatment for adult patients with head and neck soft tissue sarcomas. METHODS: We conducted a review of the pertinent literature. RESULTS: Local control after surgery alone or combined with radiotherapy was obtained in approximately 60% to 70% of the patients. The probability of local control is influenced by histologic grade, tumor size, and surgical margins. Patients with high-grade tumors and/or positive margins have improved local control if adjuvant radiotherapy is used. Distant metastases occurred in 10% to 30% of patients. The 5-year overall and cause-specific survival rates varied from approximately 60% to 70% and are affected by age, histologic grade, previous treatment of tumor, invasion of deep structures, and adequacy of surgery. CONCLUSIONS: The optimal treatment for adult head and neck soft tissue sarcomas is surgery. Adjuvant radiotherapy improves outcomes for those with high-grade tumors and/or positive margins. Radiotherapy alone will cure a small subset of patients with unresectable tumors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; JID: 8902541; RF: 26; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, P. O. Box 100385, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16136585</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20249</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16136585</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1645</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Lansford,C. D.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy for tonsillar squamous cell carcinoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>290</sp>
<op>297</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Lymph Node Excision</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Tonsillar Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: The purpose of this study is to update our experience with definitive radiotherapy (RT) for carcinoma of the tonsillar area. PATIENTS AND METHODS: There were 503 patients treated between October 1964 and May 2003 (potential follow-up for at least 2 years). Of these, 198 patients underwent a planned neck dissection and 57 patients received induction (18 patients) or concomitant (39 patients) chemotherapy. RESULTS: The 5-year local control rates were as follows: T1, 88%; T2, 84%; T3, 78%; and T4, 61%. Multivariate analysis revealed that local control was significantly influenced by T stage, primary site, and fractionation. Local control after RT for early stage cancers was higher for tonsillar fossa/posterior pillar tumors than for those arising from the anterior tonsillar pillar. The 5-year cause-specific survival rates were as follows: I, 100%; II, 86%; III, 84%; IVA, 73%; and IVB, 46%. Multivariate analysis revealed that cause-specific survival was significantly influenced by T stage, overall stage, neck dissection, race, and gender. The incidence of severe late complications was 9%. CONCLUSION: Based on our data and a review of the literature, definitive RT provides cure rates that are as good as those after surgery, and is associated with a lower rate of severe complications. Patients with lateralized tumors may be safely treated with ipsilateral field arrangements. Our limited experience with intensity modulated radiotherapy suggests that it is as efficacious as conventional RT.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16755183; 00000421-200606000-00012 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000209510.19360.f9</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16755183</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1643</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the base of tongue</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>39</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To evaluate definitive radiotherapy (RT) for treatment of base of tongue cancer. METHODS: There were 333 patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the base of tongue treated with definitive RT and had follow-up from 0.2 to 26.2 years. Follow-up on living patients ranged from 1.2 to 26.2 years (median, 6.6 years). RESULTS: Local control rates at 5 years were: T1, 98%; T2, 92%; T3, 82%; and T4, 53%. The 5-year rates of local-regional control rates were: I-II, 100%; III, 82%; IVA, 87%; and IVB, 58%. The rates of absolute and cause-specific survival at 5 years were as follows: I-II, 67% and 91%; III, 66% and 77%; IVA, 67% and 84%; and IVB, 33% and 45%. Severe complications developed in 52 patients (16%). CONCLUSION: Our data and review of the pertinent literature reveal that the local-regional control rates and survival rates after RT were comparable to those after surgery, and the morbidity associated with RT was less.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16462500; 00000421-200602000-00008 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.coc.0000189680.60262.eb</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16462500</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1659</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Radiotherapy alone or combined with surgery for adenoid cystic carcinoma of the head and neck</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>154</sp>
<op>162</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Adenoid Cystic/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The purpose of this study was to analyze the results of radiotherapy (RT) alone or combined with surgery for adenoid cystic carcinoma. METHODS: Between September 1966 and November 2001, 101 previously untreated patients were treated with curative intent with RT alone or combined with surgery. Follow-up ranged from 0.4 to 30.6 years (median, 6.6 years). All living patients had follow-up for at least 1 year. RESULTS: The 5- and 10-year rates of local control were as follows: RT alone, 56% and 43%; surgery and RT, 94% and 91%; and overall, 77% and 69%. Multivariate analysis of local control revealed that T stage (p=.0101) and treatment group (p=.0008) significantly influenced this endpoint. The 5- and 10-year rates of distant metastases-free survival were 80% and 73%. The 5- and 10-year absolute survival rates were as follows: RT alone, 57% and 42%; surgery and RT, 77% and 55%; and overall, 68% and 49%. Multivariate analysis of absolute survival revealed that T stage (p=.0043) and clinical nerve invasion (p=.0011) significantly influenced this endpoint. The 5- and 10-year cause-specific survival rates were as follows: RT alone, 65% and 48%; surgery and RT, 81% and 71%; and overall, 74% and 61%. Multivariate analysis revealed that T stage (p=.0008) and clinical nerve invasion (p=.0005) significantly influenced cause-specific survival. CONCLUSIONS: The optimal treatment for patients with adenoid cystic carcinoma is surgery and adjuvant RT. A significant proportion of patients with incompletely resectable disease are cured after RT alone. Improvements in locoregional control are offset, in part, by the relatively high incidence of distant metastases.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2004; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc. Head Neck 26: 154-162, 2004</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, University of Florida Health Science Center, P O Box 100385, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 14762884</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.10380</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14762884</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1637</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Radiotherapy alone or combined with surgery for salivary gland carcinoma</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun 15</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2544</sp>
<op>2550</op>
<k1>Adenocarcinoma/metabolism/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Adenoid Cystic/metabolism/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Mucoepidermoid/metabolism/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoadjuvant Therapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Salivary Gland Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The authors analyzed the outcomes of patients treated with radiotherapy (RT) alone or combined with surgery for carcinoma of the salivary glands. METHODS: Between October 1964 and June 2003, 224 previously untreated patients were treated with curative intent with RT alone (n = 64) or combined with surgery (n = 160) at the University of Florida College of Medicine (Gainesville, FL). The median follow-up period was 5.0 years (range, 0.4-31.6 years). RESULTS: The 10-year local control rate was 75%. Multivariate analysis of local control revealed that T classification (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) and treatment group (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) impacted this end point. Patients treated with surgery and adjuvant RT had improved local control compared with patients treated with RT alone. The 10-year locoregional control rate was 68%. Multivariate analysis of locoregional control revealed that overall stage (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) and treatment group (P = 0.0002) significantly influenced this end point. The 10-year distant metastasis-free survival rate was 68%. Multivariate analysis of distant metastasis-free survival revealed that overall stage (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) significantly influenced this end point. The 10-year cause-specific and overall survival rates were 57% and 44%, respectively. Multivariate analysis of cause-specific survival revealed that overall stage (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) significantly impacted this end point. Twenty-three patients (10%) experienced severe complications. CONCLUSIONS: A substantial proportion of patients with salivary gland carcinoma were cured with surgery combined with adjuvant RT. RT alone was used for patients with unresectable tumors and cured approximately 20% of those with advanced-stage disease. The probability of cure was influenced by the extent of disease and treatment group.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright 2005; JID: 0374236; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15880750</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.21083</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15880750</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1635</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Retromolar trigone squamous cell carcinoma treated with radiotherapy alone or combined with surgery</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>2320</sp>
<op>2325</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Treatment outcomes were analyzed for retromolar trigone squamous cell carcinoma. METHODS: Between June 1966 and August 2003, 99 patients were treated with radiotherapy alone (35 patients) or radiotherapy combined with surgery (64 patients). Followup ranged from 0.2 to 23.8 years (median, 3.3 yrs). All living patients had followup for at least 1 year. RESULTS: The 5-year local-regional control rates after definitive radiotherapy versus surgery and radiotherapy were as follows: Stages I-III, 51% and 87%; Stage IV, 42% and 62%; and overall, 48% and 71%, respectively. The 5-year cause-specific survival rates after definitive radiotherapy compared with surgery and radiotherapy were as follows: Stages I-III, 56% and 83%; Stage IV, 50% and 61%; and overall, 52% and 69%, respectively. Multivariate analyses revealed that the likelihood of cure was better with surgery and radiotherapy compared with definitive radiotherapy. CONCLUSIONS: The likelihood of cure after treatment for retromolar trigone squamous cell carcinoma was influenced by the extent of disease and treatment. Patients treated with surgery and radiotherapy had a better outcome than those treated with radiotherapy alone.</ab>
<no>JID: 0374236; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Departments of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15825160</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.21038</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15825160</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1666</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Riggs,C. E.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Altered fractionation and adjuvant chemotherapy for head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>939</sp>
<op>945</op>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The aim of this review was to discuss the role of altered fractionation and adjuvant chemotherapy for patients treated with definitive radiotherapy (RT) for head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC). METHODS: This review explores the pertinent literature and discusses the optimal management of previously untreated patients with stage III-stage IVA and/or -B HNSCCs. RESULTS: Depending on the schedule, altered fractionation improves locoregional control and survival. Both hyperfractionation and concomitant boost RT improve locoregional control and are associated with improved overall survival (OS). Adjuvant chemotherapy improves OS; the greatest impact is observed after concomitant versus induction or maintenance chemotherapy. Monochemotherapy appears to be equivalent to polychemotherapy. Drugs associated with the greatest survival benefit include fluorouracil and cisplatin. Intraarterial chemotherapy offers no advantage over intravenous chemotherapy. Concomitant cetuximab and RT results in improved outcomes similar to those observed after concomitant cisplatin-based chemotherapy and RT. CONCLUSIONS: Altered fractionation and/or concomitant chemotherapy result in improved outcomes compared with conventionally fractionated definitive RT alone for stage III-stage IV HNSCC. The optimal combination of RT fractionation and chemotherapy remains unclear. (c) 2009 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. Head Neck, 2009.</ab>
<no>JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1097-0347; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19894219</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.21261</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19894219</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1652</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Fernandes,R.</a1>
<a1>Malyapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,N. P.</a1>
<t1>Ameloblastoma</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>645</sp>
<op>648</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Ameloblastoma/diagnosis/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Jaw Neoplasms/diagnosis/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>The purpose of this article is to review the pertinent literature and discuss the optimal treatment and outcomes for patients with ameloblastoma. Ameloblastoma is an uncommon benign, locally aggressive odontogenic neoplasm that usually occurs in the vicinity of the mandibular molars or ramus. Uncontrolled, ameloblastoma may cause significant morbidity and occasionally death. The median age is approximately 35 years and males and females are equally affected. The majority of ameloblastomas are multicystic, which are more difficult to eradicate than the unicystic and peripheral varieties. Although surgery is the mainstay of treatment, the extent of resection is controversial. Radical resections, including marginal and segmental mandibulectomy, result in local control rates exceeding 90%. In contrast, conservative procedures such as enucleation and/or curettage result in local control rates of approximately 80% and 50% for unicystic and multicystic ameloblastomas, respectively. Limited experience with radiotherapy indicates that it may reduce the risk of progression and result in long-term local control in the occasional patient with incompletely resectable disease. The optimal treatment for ameloblastoma is wide en bloc resection. Radiotherapy may improve the likelihood of local control in the occasional patient with incompletely resectable tumor.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; RF: 27; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mendwm@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18091060; 00000421-200712000-00013 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e3181573e59</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18091060</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1634</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Management of T1-T2 glottic carcinomas</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>May 1</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1786</sp>
<op>1792</op>
<k1>Biopsy, Needle</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Glottis/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Laryngectomy/methods</k1>
<k1>Laser Therapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>T1-T2 glottic carcinomas may be treated with conservative surgery or radiotherapy. The goals of treatment are cure and laryngeal voice preservation. The aim of the current study was to review the pertinent literature and discuss the optimal management of early-stage laryngeal carcinoma. Literature review indicated that the local control, laryngeal preservation, and survival rates of patients were similar after transoral laser resection, open partial laryngectomy, and radiotherapy. Voice quality depended on the extent of resection for patients undergoing surgery; results for patients undergoing laser resection for limited lesions were comparable to the corresponding results for patients receiving radiotherapy, whereas open partial laryngectomy yielded poorer results. Costs were similar for laser resection and radiotherapy, but open partial laryngectomy was more expensive. Patients with well defined lesions suitable for transoral laser excision with a good functional outcome were treated with either laser or radiotherapy. The remaining patients were optimally treated with radiotherapy. Open partial laryngectomy was reserved for patients with locally recurrent tumors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; CI: Copyright 2004; JID: 0374236; RF: 27; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15112257</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Review; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.20181</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15112257</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1662</id>
<a1>Newlin,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Plasma cell granuloma of the maxillary sinus: a case report and literature review</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>722</sp>
<op>728</op>
<k1>Adrenal Cortex Hormones/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Biopsy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Granuloma, Plasma Cell/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Maxillary Sinus Neoplasms/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Radiosurgery</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Plasma cell granulomas are rare and heterogeneous tumor-like lesions of mixed inflammatory cell infiltrates of unknown etiology. Although they have the potential to occur in sites throughout the body, their occurrence in the paranasal sinuses and nasal cavity is uncommon and often associated with unique clinical characteristics and natural history. METHODS: We present a case of an aggressive plasma cell granuloma of the maxillary sinus and a review of the literature (28 cases). RESULTS: The patient was treated with definitive radiotherapy (45 Gy in 25 fractions) and experienced a local recurrence 2 years later. The lesion initially responded to corticosteroids and then progressed. Resection was performed and was followed by another recurrence. The patient was treated with radiosurgery and is disease free 8 years after initial treatment. CONCLUSIONS: Review of the literature indicates that the optimal first line of treatment is high-dose corticosteroids. Surgery is indicated if the lesion fails to respond. Radiotherapy is indicated if complete resection is not feasible.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2005; JID: 8902541; 0 (Adrenal Cortex Hormones); RF: 29; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, University of Florida Health Science Center, P. O. Box 100385, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15880393</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20196</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15880393</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1655</id>
<a1>Prabhu,R.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Indelicato,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Vaysberg,M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Squamous cell carcinoma of the external auditory canal: long-term clinical outcomes using surgery and external-beam radiotherapy</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>401</sp>
<op>404</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Disease-Free Survival</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Radiation</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/pathology</k1>
<k1>Ear Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kaplan-Meiers Estimate</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Invasiveness/pathology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/mortality/pathology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Probability</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Statistics, Nonparametric</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Squamous cell carcinoma (SCCA) of the external auditory canal (EAC) is often treated with a combination of surgery and radiotherapy (RT) to optimize the chance of achieving locoregional control. This retrospective review describes a 27-year experience of treating these tumors at the University of Florida. METHODS: Thirty patients with histologically confirmed SCCA of the EAC received external-beam radiation (RT) alone or combined with surgical resection between 1976 and 2003. Seven patients were treated with RT alone, 22 with postoperative RT, and 1with preoperative RT. Patients were grouped according to nodal status (N0/N1) and the Stell staging system for tumors of the EAC and middle ear. Early stage was defined as T1/T2 (n = 12) and advanced stage as T3 (n = 18). Median follow-up was 2 years (range, 0.1-19.4 years) with no patients lost to follow-up. RESULTS: The 5-year actuarial probabilities for local control, locoregional control, and cause-specific survival for patients with early stage (T1/T2) versus advanced-stage (T3) tumors were 74% and 55% (P = 0.27), 63% and 38% (P = 0.16), and 70% and 41% (P = 0.04), respectively. The regional control rate was 83% (P = 0.6). There were 12 local recurrences and 4 neck recurrences as the first site of failure. One failure was successfully salvaged with surgery. Five of 23 (21%) patients undergoing surgery had significant complications (grade 3 or 4), whereas 2 of 30 (7%) patients receiving RT experienced grade 3 complications. CONCLUSION: Patients with early stage disease achieved better local control, locoregional control, and cause-specific survival than those with advanced tumors. Less than half of the patients (13 of 30; 43%) were cured without significant complications, suggesting a suboptimal therapeutic ratio, using current treatment methods.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19398900</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e31818f2d48</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19398900</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1670</id>
<a1>Rabbani,A.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy for T1-T2 squamous cell carcinoma of pyriform sinus</t1>
<jf>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Radiat.Oncol.Biol.Phys.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Oct 1</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>351</sp>
<op>355</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/radiotherapy/secondary/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Laryngectomy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To report the long-term results after definitive radiotherapy (RT) for T1-T2 pyriform sinus squamous cell carcinoma. PATIENTS AND METHODS: The data from 123 patients with T1-T2 pyriform sinus squamous cell carcinoma treated with RT with or without neck dissection between November 1964 and June 2003 were analyzed. The median follow-up for all patients was 3.2 years, and the median follow-up for living patients was 10.7 years. RESULTS: The 5-year local control, locoregional control, freedom from distant metastasis, cause-specific survival, and overall survival rate was 85%, 70%, 75%, 61%, and 35%, respectively. The ultimate local control rate, including successful salvage of RT failure, for T1 and T2 cancer patients was 96% and 94%, respectively. The overall local control rate with a functional larynx was 83%. Pretreatment computed tomography tumor volume data were available for 55 patients. The median computed tomography tumor volume was 4.2 cm(3) (range, 0-22.4). Local control was worse for patients with a tumor volume &amp;gt;6.5 cm(3) compared with those with a smaller tumor volume. Of the 123 patients, 16% developed moderate to severe acute (2%), late (9%), or postoperative (5%) complications. CONCLUSIONS: Local control with larynx preservation after definitive RT for T1-T2 pyriform sinus squamous cell carcinoma likely results in local control and survival similar to that after total laryngectomy or larynx-conserving surgery. Two-thirds of our living patients retained a functional larynx.</ab>
<no>JID: 7603616; 2007/12/17 [received]; 2008/01/03 [revised]; 2008/01/03 [accepted]; 2008/04/18 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0360-3016; 0360-3016</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18395359; S0360-3016(08)00032-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ijrobp.2008.01.003</do>
<wp>20080418</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18395359</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1629</id>
<a1>Saccogna,P. W.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Setrakian,S.</a1>
<a1>Strauss,M.</a1>
<t1>Lipoinjection in the paralyzed feline vocal fold: study of graft survival</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>117</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>465</sp>
<op>470</op>
<k1>Adipose Tissue/pathology/transplantation</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biocompatible Materials/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Graft Survival</k1>
<k1>Injections, Intralesional</k1>
<k1>Laryngoscopy</k1>
<k1>Larynx/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Longitudinal Studies</k1>
<k1>Photography</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Implantation</k1>
<k1>Recurrent Laryngeal Nerve/injuries/surgery</k1>
<k1>Tissue Survival</k1>
<k1>Transplantation, Autologous</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Video Recording</k1>
<k1>Vocal Cord Paralysis/pathology/surgery</k1>
<ab>Six adult domestic strain cats were used to study the long-term histologic outcome of injected autologous fat for augmentation of the paralyzed vocal fold. Each animal had surgically induced left vocal cord paralysis via sectioning of the recurrent laryngeal nerve, followed by injection of 0.1 to 0.2 ml of autologous fat into the paralyzed vocal fold. The animals were killed at 6 weeks, and at 4, 6, 8, and 12 months after the injection. Photographic and videolaryngoscopic data were obtained. Histologic studies of the larynges were performed. The results documented histologic viability and persistence of a portion of the injected adipose tissue graft at 8 months after the injection, but only minimal graft survival at 12 months. The outcome suggests that autologous lipoinjection has potential use for short-term (several months) augmentation of the paralyzed vocal cord. Further investigation is warranted before recommending this technique for such use or as an alternative to currently available long-term injectable laryngeal biomaterials.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Biocompatible Materials); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9374168; S0194599897002738 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9374168</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1630</id>
<a1>Senchenkov,A.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Staren,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Radiographic assessment of the infiltrating retropharyngeal lipoma</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>125</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>658</sp>
<op>660</op>
<k1>Airway Obstruction/etiology</k1>
<k1>Deglutition Disorders/etiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lipoma/complications/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retroperitoneal Neoplasms/complications/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive/etiology</k1>
<k1>Snoring/etiology</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, Medical College of Ohio, 3065 Arlington Avenue, Toledo, OH 43614-5807, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11743474; S0194-5998(01)04728-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1067/mhn.2001.120395</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11743474</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1664</id>
<a1>Tanzler,E. D.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Orlando,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Management of sinonasal undifferentiated carcinoma</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>595</sp>
<op>599</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoadjuvant Therapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Our aim was to report the outcomes of treatment for sinonasal undifferentiated carcinoma (SNUC). METHODS: Between September 1992 and October 2005, 15 patients were treated with curative intent with surgery (n=1), surgery and adjuvant radiotherapy (n=9), and definitive radiotherapy (RT) (n=5). Follow-up ranged from 11 to 151 months (median, 30); follow-up on living patients ranged from 12 to 151 months (median, 22). No patient was lost to follow-up. RESULTS: Seven patients (47%) developed a recurrence from 3 to 50 months (median, 9) after treatment. The 3-year outcomes were: local control, 78%; locoregional control, 65%; distant metastasis-free survival, 82%; cause-specific survival, 77%, and survival, 67%. The local control rates versus treatment modality were: surgery, 0/1 (0%); surgery and postoperative RT, 7/7 (100%); preoperative RT and surgery, 2/2 (100%); and definitive RT, 2/5 (40%). One patient (7%) treated with surgery and postoperative RT sustained a fatal complication. CONCLUSIONS: Combined surgery and adjuvant RT likely offer the best chance of cure compared with either modality alone. The impact of adjuvant chemotherapy is unclear.</ab>
<no>JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18383526</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20748</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18383526</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1653</id>
<a1>Wagner,M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Mucosal melanoma of the head and neck</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>43</sp>
<op>48</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melanoma/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mucous Membrane/pathology/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Outcomes after radiotherapy for head and neck mucosal melanoma (MMHN). METHODS: From 1974 to 2005, 17 patients with primary MMHN were treated with radiotherapy. Primary sites included nasal cavity, paranasal sinuses, and oral cavity or oropharynx. Thirteen patients received surgery and postoperative radiotherapy; 4 received definitive radiotherapy. RESULTS: Local control was 79% at 1 and 5 years for 13 of 13 patients treated with surgery and postoperative radiotherapy compared with 1 of 4 patients treated with definitive radiotherapy. Three patients recurred in the neck; 13 patients developed distant metastases. Disease-free survival was 23% at 1 year and 18% at 5 years. Absolute and cause-specific survivals were identical (53% and 28% at 1 and 5 years). CONCLUSION: Locoregional control is relatively high after surgery and adjuvant radiotherapy, but most patients recur in distant sites; approximately one fourth of patients are cured at 5 years. Patients with unresectable tumor may be controlled with definitive radiotherapy.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18376227; 00000421-200802000-00008 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e318134ee88</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18376227</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1651</id>
<a1>Wallace,A.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Kirwan,J.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Radiotherapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule</t1>
<jf>American journal of clinical oncology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>612</sp>
<op>616</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Brachytherapy</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/secondary/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the efficacy of radiotherapy (RT) alone or combined with surgery for the treatment of the nasal vestibule squamous cell carcinomas. METHODS: Seventy-one patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule were treated with definitive RT at the University of Florida, and 8 patients with advanced T4 cancers were treated with combined surgery and RT. Patients were followed from 4 months to 27.7 years (mean 9.0 years, median 7.9 years). Follow-up on living patients ranged from 6 months to 27.7 years (mean 10.0 years, median 8.1 years). RESULTS: The 5-year outcomes were: local control, 87%; local-regional control, 77%; freedom from distant metastases, 94%; cause-specific survival, 90%; and survival, 76%. The 5-year local control rates for patients treated with definitive RT were: T1-T2, 95%; T4, 71%; and overall, 86% (P = 0.0046). Local control was achieved in 8 of 8 patients treated with surgery and RT. CONCLUSION: RT results in a high cure rate for T1-T2 and favorable T4 tumors. Surgery and RT result in an improved likelihood of cure for patients with extensive T4.</ab>
<no>JID: 8207754; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-453X; 0277-3732</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18091056; 00000421-200712000-00009 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/COC.0b013e31815aff1f</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18091056</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1658</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Byers,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Novas,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Roberts,D.</a1>
<t1>Preoperative assessment for and outcomes of mandibular conservation surgery</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1024</sp>
<op>1030</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mandibular Neoplasms/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Invasiveness</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<ab>INTRODUCTION: The role of marginal mandibulectomy and other conservative resective procedures for patients with early cortical mandibular invasion from squamous carcinoma of the oral cavity remains poorly defined. The purpose of this retrospective study was to evaluate the efficacy of preoperative assessment for bone invasion and the outcomes of different mandibular resective procedures that preserve mandibular continuity. METHODS: The charts of 222 patients treated at the University of Texas M. D. Anderson Cancer Center between 1960 and 1990 were reviewed. All patients had a biopsy-confirmed diagnosis of squamous carcinoma involving either the lower gingiva, floor of mouth, oral tongue, or retromolar trigone. All patients had a surgical resection that involved removing less than a segment of the mandible. Patient data were analyzed to determine the usefulness of preoperative assessment and outcomes of therapy. RESULTS: Clinical evaluation of mandibular bone invasion was more sensitive than radiologic evaluation, whereas radiologic assessment was more specific and had a higher reliability index. The overall local and regional recurrence and distant metastasis rates for all T stages were 14.4%, 18.0%, and 2.7%, respectively. Sixty-nine point eight percent of all patients were without evidence of disease 2 years after treatment. CONCLUSIONS: Mandibular conservation surgery is oncologically safe for patients with early mandibular invasion. Accurate preoperative assessment that combines clinical examination and radiographic evaluation is better than either modality alone, but clinical judgment is still necessary for proper patient selection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2001; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Medical College of Ohio, 3065 Arlington Avenue, Toledo, Ohio 43614, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11774386; 10.1002/hed.10031 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11774386</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1627</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Downey,N. M.</a1>
<a1>Brinker,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Khuder,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Davis,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Rubin,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Elsamaloty,H. M.</a1>
<t1>The impact of osteoporosis on patients with maxillofacial trauma</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>130</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>353</sp>
<op>356</op>
<k1>Accidental Falls</k1>
<k1>Accidents, Traffic</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Bone Density</k1>
<k1>Costs and Cost Analysis</k1>
<k1>Facial Bones/injuries</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Linear Models</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Maxillary Fractures/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Maxillofacial Injuries/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Morbidity</k1>
<k1>Osteoporosis/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Skull Fractures/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Although maxillofacial injuries in the elderly population frequently result from falls and motor vehicle crashes, the association between osteoporosis and fractures of the maxillofacial region remains poorly defined. OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the relationship between osteoporosis and maxillofacial trauma in the elderly. DESIGN, SETTING, AND MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: A retrospective review of 59 patients 60 years or older treated for maxillofacial fractures at a trauma center between 1989 and 2000 was performed. The severity of osteoporosis was graded by evaluating the radiographic appearance of the vertebral bodies of each trauma patient using the Saville index. The number of maxillofacial fractures and the severity of osteoporosis in each patient was assessed to determine whether an association between osteoporosis and maxillofacial trauma exists. RESULTS: Of the 59 patients evaluated, 51% were injured by falls and 46% were involved in motor vehicle crashes. Seventy-three percent of the patients had multiple facial fractures. As the severity of osteoporosis worsened, patients were more likely to sustain a greater number of maxillofacial fractures (P=.01). The mechanism of injury had no impact on the relationship between osteoporosis and the number of fractures. CONCLUSIONS: Osteoporosis is an independent risk factor for the development of maxillofacial fractures. Since more than half of these patients are injured by falls, safety measures must be instituted to prevent fall-related maxillofacial injuries in the home and the community.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060328; JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA. wernijw@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15023847; 130/3/353 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archotol.130.3.353</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15023847</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1626</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Heard,D.</a1>
<a1>Pagano,C.</a1>
<a1>Khuder,S.</a1>
<t1>Elective management of the clinically negative neck by otolaryngologists in patients with oral tongue cancer</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>83</sp>
<op>88</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Health Care Surveys</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Node Excision</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otolaryngology</k1>
<k1>Physician&#39;s Practice Patterns</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/pathology/surgery</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The treatment of patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck who have a clinically negative (cN0) neck remains controversial. Furthermore, the treatment delivered to patients with a cN0 neck by practicing otolaryngologists is not known. OBJECTIVE: To determine the variability in the management of the cN0 neck in the otolaryngology community. DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS: A random survey of 763 board-certified otolaryngologists in the United States. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Physician respondents&amp;#39; preferences for observation vs treatment of the cN0 neck and the treatment modalities chosen. RESULTS: Forty-one percent of the surveyed physicians responded. Nearly 10% of the respondents observed all patients with a cN0 neck. Otolaryngologists who treat 35 or more new patients with cancer each year were more likely to perform elective treatment of the neck for a T2 lesion of the oral tongue than those who treat 10 or fewer patients each year (P =.03). They were also more likely to treat patients with a cN0 neck when the risk of occult cervical metastases was greater than 15% to 20% (P =.04). A comprehensive neck dissection was the preferred lymphadenectomy procedure for 21% of the otolaryngologists surveyed. CONCLUSIONS: Variations in the treatment of the cN0 neck are associated with differences in the frequency of treatment of patients with head and neck cancer by otolaryngologists. Uniformity of care must be established within the otolaryngology community by developing widely accepted evidence-based guidelines and referring patients to surgeons who routinely treat head and neck cancer.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060328; JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Rd, Room M-228, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. wernijw@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12525200; ooa20130 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12525200</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1623</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Anderson,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Biomechanical assessment of a new adhesive bone cement for otologic surgery</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>269</sp>
<op>276</op>
<k1>Adhesives</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biomechanics</k1>
<k1>Bone Cements/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Bone and Bones/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Boranes/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Ear/surgery</k1>
<k1>Methacrylates/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Methylmethacrylate</k1>
<k1>Methylmethacrylates/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Tibia/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Titanium/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>The adhesion of metallic prostheses to bone is a major problem in otologic surgery. Conventional bone cements lack significant adhesive strength, which predisposes the cemented prosthesis to loosening. The advent of surgically implantable hearing devices is one example where an adhesive cement to secure metal to bone would be useful. The biomechanical properties of a new cement, 4-META/MMA-TBB opaque resin, were evaluated in an animal model. The cement is composed of 4-methacryloyloxyethyl trimellitate anhydride (4-META) and methyl methacrylate (MMA) as monomers and tri-n-butyl borane (TBB) as an initiator. Titanium disks were cemented to the tibias of rabbits, which were sacrificed at 0 and 90 days. Tensile and shear bond strengths between bone and metal were tested at both times. The mean baseline tensile and shear bond strengths were 8.92 MPa and 11.96 MPa, respectively. Adhesive failure occurred at the bone-cement interface. The decrease in bond strength at 90 days was minimal. Thus, 4-META/MMA-TBB cement is a promising new metal-to-bone adhesive that may be useful for the surgical fixation of metallic prostheses in otologic surgery.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01 DC-0153-02/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7909513; 0 (Adhesives); 0 (Bone Cements); 0 (Boranes); 0 (Methacrylates); 0 (Methylmethacrylates); 70293-55-9 (4-methacryloxyethyltrimellitic acid anhydride); 7440-32-6 (Titanium); 80-62-6 (Methylmethacrylate); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8588618</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8588618</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1625</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Preston,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Khuder,S.</a1>
<t1>Physician specialty is associated with differences in the evaluation and management of acute bacterial rhinosinusitis</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>128</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>123</sp>
<op>130</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Infections/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Community-Acquired Infections/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Data Collection</k1>
<k1>Family Practice</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Internal Medicine</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otolaryngology</k1>
<k1>Outcome Assessment (Health Care)</k1>
<k1>Physician&#39;s Practice Patterns</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Rhinitis/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Sinusitis/radiography/therapy</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Acute bacterial rhinosinusitis (ABRS) is a common illness that is routinely managed by physicians from several different specialties. However, the actual diagnostic and treatment preferences of physicians from these different specialties are not known. OBJECTIVE: To determine whether the radiographic evaluation and management of community-acquired ABRS differs according to medical specialty. DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS: Randomized survey of 450 board-certified physicians in the United States from family medicine, general internal medicine, and otolaryngology. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Responding physicians&amp;#39; use of diagnostic radiography as well as choice and duration of antimicrobial and adjunctive treatments of ABRS. RESULTS: Otolaryngologists were more likely to use supportive diagnostic radiography (P =.04). They were also more likely to treat patients with adjunctive therapy, such as topical decongestants (P =.01), guaifenesin (P =.01), and saline nasal irrigation (P =.01), in addition to antibiotics. Otolaryngologists prescribed more medications to treat patients with ABRS than primary care physicians (P =.01). There were no significant differences in diagnosis and management by family physicians and general internists. CONCLUSIONS: Otolaryngologists use more health care resources to diagnose and treat ABRS than primary care physicians despite an absence of evidence that such tests and treatments lead to better outcomes. Otolaryngologists typically treat a patient population with a higher prevalence of ABRS and frequently see referred patients with recurrent acute sinusitis and chronic rhinosinusitis, which may explain their tendency to treat patients more aggressively. Nevertheless, these survey results illustrate a lack of consensus within the medical community regarding the evaluation and management of community-acquired ABRS, suggesting that widely accepted evidence-based practice guidelines need to be developed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Medical College of Ohio, 3065 Arlington Ave, Toledo, OH 43614-5807, USA. jwwerning@netscape.net</ad>
<an>PMID: 11843718; ooa10045 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11843718</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1624</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Stepnick,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Jafri,A.</a1>
<a1>Megerian,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Antunez,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Zaidi,S. I.</a1>
<t1>Metoclopramide enhances the effect of photodynamic therapy on xenografted human squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>783</sp>
<op>789</op>
<k1>1,2-Dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/drug therapy/pathology</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</k1>
<k1>Drug Carriers</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/drug therapy/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Indoles/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacokinetics</k1>
<k1>Liposomes</k1>
<k1>Metoclopramide/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Nude</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Transplantation</k1>
<k1>Organosilicon Compounds/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacokinetics</k1>
<k1>Photochemotherapy/methods</k1>
<k1>Photosensitizing Agents/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacokinetics</k1>
<k1>Remission Induction</k1>
<k1>Silanes</k1>
<k1>Transplantation, Heterologous</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Photodynamic therapy (PDT) is a promising new treatment modality for head and neck cancer that is based on the uptake of a systemically administered photosensitizer in tumor tissue and local illumination of the lesion by a high-intensity visible light source, typically a tunable argon-pumped dye laser. We developed a new photosensitizer named silicon phthalocyanine [SiPc(OH) OSi(CH3)2(CH2)3N(CH3)2, abbreviated as SiPc IV], which yields superior PDT responses in vitro and in vivo compared with other clinically used photosensitizers. However, tumor regrowth following SiPc IV-based PDT is still a therapeutic problem. The benzamide derivatives, for example, have been shown to enhance tumor ablation when used during radiotherapy and chemotherapy. Therefore, we used metoclopramide hydrochloride, a benzamide derivative, to evaluate its effects on PDT response. DESIGN: Intradermally injected human squamous cell carcinoma cells were grown to 40 to 80 mm3 in athymic nude mice and irradiated with 675-nm light (75 J/cm2, 75 mW/cm2) 24 hours after the intraperitoneal injection of SiPc IV (1.0 mg/kg). Metoclopramide hydrochloride (2 to 48 mg/kg) was injected intraperitoneally 1 hour before and 24 and 48 hours after irradiation. RESULTS: Tumors exposed to PDT alone showed 80% to 90% tumor regression with regrowth in most animals within 20 days. Tumors treated with metoclopramide hydrochloride (48 mg/kg) plus PDT demonstrated 100% tumor regression without regrowth up to the time of killing (150 days). No observable toxic effects were clinically apparent with the high doses of metoclopramide. CONCLUSIONS: Our results show that administering metoclopramide in combination with PDT may be a promising approach to the management of head and neck cancer.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8603209; 0 (Drug Carriers); 0 (Indoles); 0 (Liposomes); 0 (Organosilicon Compounds); 0 (Photosensitizing Agents); 0 (Silanes); 135719-28-7 (silicon phthalocyanine); 2644-64-6 (1,2-Dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine); 364-62-5 (Metoclopramide); 92396-88-8 (bis(tri-n-hexylsiloxy)(2,3-naphthalocyaninato)silicon); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7598858</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7598858</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1674</id>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Zaidi,S. I. A.</a1>
<a1>Megerian,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Drago,P.</a1>
<a1>Maniglia,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Stepnick,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Cisplatin-Fluorouracil enhances the effect of PDR on xenografted human squamous cell carcinoma (HSCC) of the head and neck</t1>
<jf>Photochemistry and Photobiology</jf>
<jo>Photochem.Photobiol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>57</vo>
<sp>98S</sp>
<k1>Abstract from 21st Annual Meeting of the American Society for Photobiology Chicago, Illinios June 26-30, 1993</k1>
<pb>American Society for Photobiology</pb>
<pp>Augusta, GA</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1677</id>
<a1>Werning,John W.</a1>
<t1>Oral cancer : diagnosis, management, and rehabilitation</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>354</sp>
<k1>Mouth -- Cancer</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms -- diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms -- rehabilitation</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms -- therapy</k1>
<ab>Contents: 01 Epidemiology of oral cancer -- Oral precancer -- Malignant lesions of the oral cavity -- Evaluation of oral premalignant lesions -- Anatomic considerations -- Imaging of patients with oral cancer -- Staging of oral cancer -- Pretreatment dental evaluation and management of the oral cancer patient -- Cancer of the lip -- Cancer of the buccal mucosa -- Cancer of the oral tongue and floor of mouth -- Cancer of the lower alveolar ridge and retromolar trigone -- Cancer of the hard palate and upper alveolar ridge -- Management of the neck -- Reconstruction of the lips -- Reconstruction of the cheek -- Reconstruction of the tongue -- Reconstruction of the mandible -- Reconstruction of the maxilla -- Radiation therapy -- Chemotherapy -- Oral rehabilitation with osseointegrated implants -- Dental implant imaging -- Oral prosthetic rehabilitation -- Xerostomia and mucositis -- Osteoradionecrosis -- Speech and swallowing following treatment for oral cancer -- Temporomandibular disorder and orofacial pain -- Chemoprevention -- Novel therapeutics for head and neck cancer -- Medical/legal issues.</ab>
<no>[edited by] John W. Werning. : [edited by] John W. Werning.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Werning,J. W.</a2>
<ed>1</ed>
<pb>Thieme Medical Publishers</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<sn>1588903095; 3131358114; 9781588903099; 9783131358110</sn>
<cn>WU280O632 2007 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1638</id>
<a1>Yeung,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Liauw,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Lymph node-positive head and neck cancer treated with definitive radiotherapy: can treatment response determine the extent of neck dissection?</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar 1</fd>
<vo>112</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1076</sp>
<op>1082</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/radiography/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiography/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymphatic Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The purpose was to determine if postradiotherapy (RT) neck dissection can be limited to the neck levels of residual adenopathy on post-RT computed tomography (CT). METHODS: In all, 274 patients with lymph node-positive head and neck squamous cell carcinoma were treated with definitive RT. All patients had a contrast-enhanced CT performed 4 weeks after completing RT to evaluate tumor response. Two hundred eleven heminecks were dissected, either planned pre-RT or because of residual adenopathy on post-RT CT. CT images were reviewed to determine the presence and location of residual adenopathy. Radiographic complete response (rCR) was defined as lymph node size  or =95% for each neck level. This suggests that limiting neck dissection based on post-RT CT is safe.</ab>
<no>JID: 0374236; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18186495</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.23279</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18186495</pmid></reference></refworks>
