<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3462</id>
<t1>Mosquitoes unlimited.</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<is>7</is>
<sp>88</sp>
<k1>MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology</k1>
<k1>Behaviour</k1>
<k1>ecology</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>behavior</k1>
<k1>general account</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>This special issue of this semi-popular magazine is devoted to mosquitoes. It contains articles, many attractively illustrated, on their ecology, behaviour and medical importance by authors such as J.D. Edman, J.O. Washburn, J.R. Anderson, W. Bradshaw, C. Holzapfel, D.S. Taylor, L. Blaustein, W.A. Foster, R.M. Taylor, L.P. Lounibos, M.J. Klowden, J.F. Day, W.A. Hawley, R.L. Nagel, L.E. Munstermann and others.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Diptera; NR: many ref.</no>
<a2>Nielsen,L. T.</a2>
<ad>University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19920510688</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2261</id>
<a1>Allan,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Visual ecology of biting flies</t1>
<jf>Annual Review of Entomology</jf>
<jo>Annu.Rev.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<sp>297</sp>
<op>316</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blood</k1>
<k1>Culicidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Diptera/physiology</k1>
<k1>Ecology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Simuliidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vision, Ocular</k1>
<ab>Many of the similarities in visual ecology between the Nematocera and Brachycera and within the Cyclorrhapha may reflect the evolution of blood-feeding in these groups. In Nematocera and Brachycera, blood-feeding is thought to have evolved from predatory or nectar-feeding behavior (138). Only females feed on hosts, and association with hosts generally occurs when hosts are close to the aquatic or semiaquatic habitats of the immatures. Flies feed on nectar, make appetitive flights, disperse, or migrate prior to blood-feeding, and then oviposit in water. Many species are nocturnal or crepuscular. In Cyclorrhapha, flies are closely associated with hosts. They may have arisen from compost-feeding flies that developed a larval dependence on vertebrate-produced microhabitats. Both sexes blood-feed, and mating occurs on or near hosts. Flies generally emerge in the proximity of hosts and maintain close contact with them. These species are diurnal, and their visual systems are well developed. Comparisons between closely related blood-feeding and non-blood-feeding species may provide insight into the visual ecology of blood-feeding species. Despite the different origins of hematophagy, there appears to be a convergence of morphology and behavior that is related to ecology rather than to phylogenetic relationships. This is clearly seen in host-location strategies by tsetse and tabanids. Even within groups such as mosquitoes, species that are active at the same time of day and in the same habitat have more in common than closely related species in different habitats. For this reason, an ecological review would be more cohesive than this phylogenetic discussion. However, because of the disproportionate amount of literature on a small number of groups, the phylogenetic approach is the most practical for this subject. However, this review does point out the great need for research on the less well-studied groups and behaviors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: AI-20983/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372367; RF: 151; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0066-4170; 0066-4170</sn>
<an>PMID: 2880551</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1146/annurev.en.32.010187.001501</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2880551</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3191</id>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<t1>West Nile Virus Affects the Rate of Blood Digestion in Culex Pipiens Quinquefasciatus Say (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>NOV 2009</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>5, Suppl. S</is>
<sp>112</sp>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Blood and Lymphatics (Transport and Circulation)</k1>
<k1>Digestive System (Ingestion and Assimilation)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>14004, Digestive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>15002, Blood - Blood and lymph studies</k1>
<k1>15004, Blood - Blood cell studies</k1>
<k1>33502, Virology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Diptera] [Culicidae] [Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus</k1>
<k1>(disease vector)]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>(parasite)]</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus infection</k1>
<k1>viral disease</k1>
<k1>transmission</k1>
<k1>Sella scale</k1>
<k1>mathematical and computer techniques</k1>
<k1>leg/midgut</k1>
<k1>digestive system</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV201000140052; CT: 58th Annual Meeting of the American-Society-of-Tropical-Medicine-and-Hygiene; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: November 18 -22, 2009; SP: Amer Soc Trop Med &amp;amp; Hyg</no>
<sn>0002-9637(print); 1476-1645(electronic)</sn>
<ad>Anderson, Sheri L. ; Univ Florida, Vero Beach, FL USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3464</id>
<a1>Bentley,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Chemical ecology and behavioral aspects of mosquito oviposition.</t1>
<jf>Annual Review of Entomology</jf>
<jo>Annu.Rev.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<sp>401</sp>
<op>421</op>
<k1>MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology LL600 Animal Physiology and Biochemistry (Excluding Nutrition) LL300 Animal Behaviour HH500 Repellents and Attractants</k1>
<k1>behaviour</k1>
<k1>Breeding places</k1>
<k1>Insect attractants</k1>
<k1>oviposition</k1>
<k1>oviposition attractant pheromones</k1>
<k1>Oviposition attractants</k1>
<k1>Oviposition deterrents</k1>
<k1>Pheromones</k1>
<k1>reviews</k1>
<k1>Semiochemicals</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>behavior</k1>
<k1>breeding habitats</k1>
<k1>breeding sites</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>Mosquito oviposition behaviour is reviewed under the following headings: perspectives and overview; oviposition behaviour in nature; selection of an oviposition site; oviposition attractants and stimulants (interaction of chemical and physical factors, substances of larval, puparial and egg origin, substances from other sources); and oviposition deterrents and repellents (salinity, fatty acids, phytochemicals, insecticides). It is suggested that more field experiments need to be done to increase knowledge of this aspect of mosquito ecology.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Diptera; NR: 123 ref.</no>
<sn>0066-4170</sn>
<ad>Department of Chemistry, University of Maine, Orono, ME 04469, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19910599998</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3484</id>
<a1>Benton,A. H.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal changes in the flea fauna of nests of the southern flying squirrel.</t1>
<yr>1980</yr>
<sp>401</sp>
<op>403</op>
<k1>LL820 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Animals (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>seasonal abundance</k1>
<k1>Orchopeas howardii</k1>
<k1>Siphonaptera</k1>
<k1>Conorhinopsylla stanfordi</k1>
<k1>Epitedia</k1>
<k1>Epitedia faceta</k1>
<k1>faceta, Epitedia</k1>
<k1>Glaucomys volans</k1>
<k1>Glaucomys volans nests</k1>
<k1>howardii, Orchopeas</k1>
<k1>Opisodasys</k1>
<k1>Opisodasys pseudarctomys</k1>
<k1>pseudarctomys, Opisodasys</k1>
<k1>Siphonaptera in nests</k1>
<k1>stanfordi, Conorhinopsylla</k1>
<k1>United States of</k1>
<k1>America</k1>
<ab>Opisodasys pseudarctomys (Baker), Orchopeas howardii (Baker), Epitedia faceta (Roths.) and Conorhinopsylla stanfordi Stewart regularly infest the nests of Glaucomys volans in the north-eastern USA. Between November 1976 and May 1977, more than 1000 fleas were collected from these nests and the seasonal changes were studied. The preliminary data indicate that the life-cycles of the dominant species are adjusted to maximise success and minimise competition. The position of the nest also appears to influence the distribution of the parasites.</ab>
<no>GE: USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Orchopeas; Ceratophyllidae; Siphonaptera; insects; Hexapoda;&lt;br&gt;   arthropods; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Hystrichopsyllidae;&lt;br&gt;   Glaucomys; Sciuridae; rodents; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata;&lt;br&gt;   squirrels; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries</no>
<a2>Traub,R. Starcke,H.</a2>
<t2>Fleas. Proceedings of the International Conference on Fleas, Ashton Wold, Peterborough, UK, 21-25 June 1977.; Fleas. Proceedings of the International Conference on Fleas, Ashton Wold, Peterborough, UK, 21-25 June 1977.</t2>
<pb>A.A. Balkema.</pb>
<pp>Rotterdam Netherlands</pp>
<ad>State University College, Fredonia, New York, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19810581684</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2368</id>
<a1>Bidlingmayer,WL</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Evans,DG</a1>
<t1>Effect of wind velocity on suction trap catches of some Florida mosquitoes</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>295</sp>
<op>301</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: sampling</k1>
<k1>wind</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<ab>The correlations between wind velocity and suction trap catches of mosquitoes when taken at 15-min intervals during the night were studied at 2 locations. Although normal mosquito flight speeds are approximately 1 m/sec, trap catches were reduced about 50% by winds of 0.5 m/sec and 75% at 1.0 m/sec. Trap catches were inversely related to winds of all velocities and even the lightest winds reduced trap catches. No evidence was found for a threshold below which wind velocity had no effect.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomology Lab., IFAS, Univ. Florida, 200 9th St. S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>3864302</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05205 Populations &amp; general ecology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3250</id>
<a1>Bressler,D. S.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Boyd,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Rollin,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Ksiazek,T. G.</a1>
<t1>Identification and serological characterization of a virus isolated from a cotton mouse from Florida</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sept., 1999</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>3 SUPPL.</is>
<sp>409</sp>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>Rodentia, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Rodents, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Cricetidae [86310]</k1>
<k1>[Peromyscus gossypinus</k1>
<k1>cotton mouse</k1>
<k1>(disease vector, host, isolate)]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>viral infection</k1>
<k1>Virus Diseases (MeSH)</k1>
<k1>viral disease</k1>
<k1>sera</k1>
<k1>blood and lymphatics</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900499725&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 48th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; CL: Washington, D.C., USA; CY: November 28-December 2, 1999; SP: American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Bressler, D. S. ; Special Pathogens Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3421</id>
<a1>Darsie,R. F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Almasi,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Studies of the genus Culex Linnaeus in Florida: III. Redescription of the fourth-stage larva of Culex salinarius Coquillett and comparison with that of Cx. nigripalpus Theobald.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>184</op>
<k1>VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY100 Anatomy and Morphology (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>larvae</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>redescriptions</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culex salinarius</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The larva of Culex salinarius is completely described and illustrated, except for the mouth parts, and compared with the morphologically similar larva of Cx. nigripalpus. At least 8 characters have been found to separate larvae of the two species of which 7 give 90% or higher divergence while the remaining character gives 87% separation.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Culex; Culicidae; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods;&lt;br&gt;   invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 48 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Mount Laurel USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20063162328</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.2987/8756-971X(2006)22[179:SOTGCL]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3417</id>
<a1>Darsie,R. F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Redescription of the pupa of Culex restuans and a comparison with Culex nigripalpus.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>95</sp>
<op>98</op>
<k1>VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY100 Anatomy and Morphology (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000) ZZ380 Taxonomy and Evolution</k1>
<k1>animal anatomy</k1>
<k1>body parts</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>pupae</k1>
<k1>redescriptions</k1>
<k1>taxonomy</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culex restuans</k1>
<k1>body components</k1>
<k1>systematics</k1>
<ab>The pupa of Culex restuans is redescribed in detail with a chaetotaxal table and a full illustration. The chaetotaxy of the pupa of Cx. restuans is compared with that of Cx. nigripalpus, the primary vector of St. Louis encephalitis and West Nile virus in Florida.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Delaware; Georgia; New York; Pennsylvania&lt;br&gt;BD: Culex; Culicidae; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods;&lt;br&gt;   invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Southeastern States of USA; Middle Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Northeastern States of USA; NR: 15 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Mount Laurel USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20073218330</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.2987/8756-971X(2007)23[95:ROTPOC]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3428</id>
<a1>Darsie,R. F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Redescription of the pupa of Culex (Culex) declarator Dyar and Knab (Diptera, Culicidae), with amendments to key to the Culex pupae of the Eastern United States.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>128</sp>
<op>130</op>
<k1>PP710 Biological Resources (Animal) YY100 Anatomy and Morphology (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000) ZZ380 Taxonomy and Evolution</k1>
<k1>animal anatomy</k1>
<k1>body parts</k1>
<k1>geographical distribution</k1>
<k1>keys</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>new geographic records</k1>
<k1>pupae</k1>
<k1>redescriptions</k1>
<k1>taxonomy</k1>
<k1>Culex</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>body components</k1>
<k1>Culex declarator</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>systematics</k1>
<k1>United</k1>
<k1>States of America</k1>
<ab>The pupa of Culex declarator was partially described and illustrated by Lane. This species was recently discovered in Florida, USA for the first time, and a series of individual rearings have resulted in a number of pupae and an opportunity to redescribe it fully, with a complete illustration. Amendment to the key to the Culex pupae of the eastern United States is provided.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Culicidae; Culex; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD&lt;br&gt;   Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 10 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Eatontown USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 20 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20053148435</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.2987/8756-971X(2005)21[128:ROTPOC]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3429</id>
<a1>Darsie,R. F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Studies of the genus Culex in Florida. II. Redescription of the fourth instar of Culex nigripalpus.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>110</sp>
<op>114</op>
<k1>VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY100 Anatomy and Morphology (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>animal anatomy</k1>
<k1>body parts</k1>
<k1>illustrations</k1>
<k1>larvae</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>redescriptions</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>body components</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The fourth instar of C. nigripalpus collected in Florida, USA is described in detail and completely illustrated for the first time as compared with previous descriptions of the larva of C. nigripalpus. Certain important features are shown in the figure.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Culex; Culicidae; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD&lt;br&gt;   Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 35 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Eatontown USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20043123618</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3207</id>
<a1>Darsie,Richard F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Almasi,James R.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<t1>Studies of the genus Culex Linnaeus in Florida - III. Redescription of the fourth-stage larva of Culex salinarius Coquillett and comparison with that of Cx. nigripalpus Theobald</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>JUN 2006</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>184</op>
<k1>Biogeography (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>Morphology</k1>
<k1>Systematics and Taxonomy</k1>
<k1>00504, General biology - Taxonomy, nomenclature and terminology</k1>
<k1>07502, Ecology: environmental biology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>11102, Anatomy and Histology - Gross anatomy</k1>
<k1>25502, Development and Embryology - General and descriptive</k1>
<k1>62800, Animal distribution</k1>
<k1>63574, Invertebrata: general and systematic - Insecta: Diptera</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Culex] [Culex salinarius</k1>
<k1>(larva</k1>
<k1>description)] [Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>(larva)]</k1>
<ab>The larva of Cidex salinarius is completely described and illustrated, except for the mouth parts, and compared with the morphologically similar larva of Cx. nigripalpus. At least 8 characters have been found to separate larvae of the two species of which 7 give 90% or higher divergence while the remaining character gives 87% separation.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200600530080; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region ER</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Darsie, Richard F., Jr. ; Florida Med Entomol Lab, 200 9th St SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962 USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3206</id>
<a1>Darsie,Richard F.,Jr.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<t1>Redescription of the pupa of Culex salinarius coquillett and comparison with Culex nigripalpus theobald</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP 2006</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>547</sp>
<op>549</op>
<k1>Systematics and Taxonomy</k1>
<k1>00504, General biology - Taxonomy, nomenclature and terminology</k1>
<k1>11102, Anatomy and Histology - Gross anatomy</k1>
<k1>25502, Development and Embryology - General and descriptive</k1>
<k1>63574, Invertebrata: general and systematic - Insecta: Diptera</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Culex salinarius</k1>
<k1>(pupa</k1>
<k1>description)] [Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>(pupa)] ER</k1>
<ab>The pupa of Culex salinarius is redescribed with updated chaetotaxal nomenclature and a full illustration. The pupal chaetotaxy of Cx. salinarius and the similar species Culex nigripalopus is compared.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200700030764</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Darsie, Richard F., Jr. ; Univ Florida, Inst Food and Agr Sci, Florida Med Entomol Lab, 200 9th St SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962 USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article; LT: Taxonomic Key</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2343</id>
<a1>Darsie,RF,Jr</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Studies of the Genus Culex Linnaeus in Florida I. Redescription of the Pupae of Culex nigripalpus Theobald and Cx. tarsalis Coquillett, Vectors of St. Louis Encephalitis, and a Key to Pupae of Culex species in the Eastern United States (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</jf>
<jo>Proc.Entomol.Soc.Wash.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>100</sp>
<op>107</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Identification keys</k1>
<k1>Life cycle</k1>
<k1>Morphology</k1>
<k1>Pupae</k1>
<k1>Taxonomy</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex nigripalpis</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culex tarsalis</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA</k1>
<k1>USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>The pupal stages of Culex nigripalpus and Cx. tarsalis are redescribed and illustrated. A key to the pupae of 15 species of Culex in the eastern United States is included.</ab>
<no>TR: CS0729874&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of Washington</pb>
<sn>0013-8797</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory. University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA, [mailto:rfd@mail.ifas.ufl.edu]</ad>
<an>5861709</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05122 Diptera; Q1 01303 Taxonomy and morphology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>ASFA: Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries Abstracts</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2351</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Zhang,JT</a1>
<a1>Winner,R.</a1>
<a1>Parsons,RE</a1>
<t1>Distribution of St. Louis encephalitis virus in Sentinel chickens from Sarasota County, Florida</t1>
<jf>Diversity &#39;88-Entomological Society of America National Conference and Exhibition</jf>
<fd>4-8 Dec 1988</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 884 0712); Availability: Conference proceedings will not be published&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Louisville, KY (USA)</ed>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., 200 9th St. SE, Univ. Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962; Entomological Society of America (ESA)</ad>
<an>2009765</an>
<cl>U 2000 BIOLOGY GENERAL</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3422</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Host-seeking strategies of mosquito disease vectors.</t1>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4(Supplement)</is>
<sp>17</sp>
<op>22</op>
<k1>VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY500 Behaviour (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>behaviour</k1>
<k1>dengue</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>haematophagous arthropods</k1>
<k1>host-seeking behaviour</k1>
<k1>malaria</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Aedes aegypti</k1>
<k1>Anopheles gambiae</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>behavior</k1>
<k1>bloodsucking arthropods</k1>
<k1>hematophagous arthropods</k1>
<k1>host-seeking behavior</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>Disease transmission by arthropods normally requires at least 2 host contacts. During the first, a pathogen (nematode, protozoan, or virus) is acquired along with the blood from an infected vertebrate host. The pathogen penetrates the vector&amp;#39;s midgut and infects a variety of tissues, where replication may occur during an extrinsic incubation period lasting 3-30, days depending on vector and parasite physiology and ambient temperature. Following salivary-gland infection, the pathogen is usually transmitted to additional susceptible vertebrate hosts during future probing or blood feeding. The host-seeking strategies used by arthropod vectors can, in part, affect the efficiency of disease transmission. Vector abundance, seasonal distribution, habitat and host preference, and susceptibility to infection are all important components of disease-transmission cycles. Examples of 3 mosquito vectors of human disease are presented here to highlight the diversity of host seeking and to show how specific behaviors may influence disease-transmission cycles. In the African tropics, Anopheles gambiae s.s. is an efficient vector of human malaria due to its remarkably focused preference for human blood. Aedes aegypti is the main vector of dengue viruses in the New and Old World tropics and subtropics. This mosquito has evolved a domestic lifestyle and shares human habitations throughout much of its range. It prospers in settings where humans are its main source of blood. In south Florida, Culex nigripalpus is the major vector of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) and West Nile (WN) viruses. This mosquito is opportunistic and blood feeds on virtually any available vertebrate host. It serves as an arboviral vector, in part, due to its ability to produce large populations in a short period of time. These 3 host-seeking and blood-feeding strategies make the specialist, as well as the opportunist, equally dangerous disease vectors.</ab>
<no>BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Aedes; Culicidae; Anopheles; Culex; NR: 40 ref.</no>
<a2>Duhrkopf,R. E.</a2>
<t2>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association; Current trends in repellent technology: papers presented at a symposium on repellents at the 2002 Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association.</t2>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Eatontown USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.; JFDay@mail.ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20063024067</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Journal article, Conference paper</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3440</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Predicting St. Louis encephalitis virus epidemics: lessons from recent, and not so recent, outbreaks.</t1>
<jf>Annual Review of Entomology</jf>
<jo>Annu.Rev.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>46</vo>
<sp>111</sp>
<op>138</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>epidemics</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>outbreaks</k1>
<k1>reviews</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>St. Louis encephalitis virus was first identified as the cause of human disease in North America after a large urban epidemic in St. Louis, Missouri, during the summer of 1933. Since then, numerous outbreaks of St. Louis encephalitis have occurred throughout the continent. In south Florida, a 1990 epidemic lasted from August 1990 through January 1991 and resulted in 226 clinical cases and 11 deaths in 28 counties. This epidemic severely disrupted normal activities throughout the southern half of the state for 5 months and adversely impacted tourism in the affected region. The accurate forecasting of mosquito-borne arboviral epidemics will help minimize their impact on urban and rural population centres. Epidemic predictability would help focus control efforts and public education about epidemic risks, transmision patterns, and elements of personal protection that reduce the probability of arboviral infection. Research associated with arboviral outbreaks has provided an understanding of the strengths and weaknesses associated with epidemic prediction. The purpose of this paper is to review lessons from past arboviral epidemics and determine how these observations might aid our ability to predict and respond to future outbreaks.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; Missouri; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; West North Central States of USA; North Central States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Corn Belt States of USA; NR: 121 ref.</no>
<pb>Annual Reviews Inc</pb>
<pp>Palo Alto USA</pp>
<sn>0066-4170; 0-8243-0146-3</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20013063240</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.1146/annurev.ento.46.1.111</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3454</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>A review of the 1990 St. Louis encephalitis virus epidemic in Indian River County, Florida.</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>39</op>
<k1>VV200 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Humans (Discontinued March 2000) HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General)</k1>
<k1>arboviruses</k1>
<k1>control programmes</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>epidemics</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>control programs</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>From July 28, 1990, to January 1991, a widespread epidemic of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus, transmitted by Culex nigripalpus, swept through the human population of southern Florida, USA. Indian River County, located on the Atlantic coast of central Florida was the epidemic epicentre. The Index Case of the 1990 epidemic occurred in northern Indian River County with onset of symptoms on July 28. A total of 19 clinical cases and 1 death was reported in the County. Ample early warning of impending epidemic activity was provided through an intensive, long-term surveillance programme run by personnel from the Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, the Indian River Mosquito Control District and the Epidemiology Research Center in Tampa.</ab>
<no>GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Culex; Culicidae; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods;&lt;br&gt;   invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae;&lt;br&gt;   positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses;&lt;br&gt;   South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North&lt;br&gt;   America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southeastern States of USA; SU: Proceedings - 78th Annual Meeting, New Jersey Mosquito Control Association, Inc. Atlantic City, New Jersey, April 3-5, 1991.; NR: 7 ref.</no>
<t2>Proceedings - Annual Meeting, New Jersey Mosquito Control Association</t2>
<ad>IFAS, University of Florida, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19950506501</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Journal article, Conference paper</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3466</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>The use of sentinel chickens for arbovirus surveillance in Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Florida Anti-Mosquito Association</jf>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>60</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>56</sp>
<op>61</op>
<k1>VV200 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Humans (Discontinued March 2000) MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology LL820 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Animals (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>arboviruses</k1>
<k1>DISEASE SURVEYS</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Human diseases</k1>
<k1>monitoring</k1>
<k1>Mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>Sentinel animals</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Eastern equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Fowls</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>disease surveillance</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>surveillance systems</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Controversy has recently surrounded the practice of using sentinel chickens to monitor Florida counties for mosquito-borne arboviruses, the most important of which are St. Louis encephalitis and eastern equine encephalomyelitis viruses, both of which can infect humans. The purpose of this report is to review the Florida sentinel chicken arbovirus surveillance programme and to evaluate its strengths and weaknesses. Data for 1978-88 were analysed for Charlotte, East Volusia, Indian River and Sarasota Counties.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Gallus gallus; Gallus; Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds; vertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   Chordata; animals; poultry; eukaryotes; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae;&lt;br&gt;   positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses;&lt;br&gt;   equine encephalomyelitis virus; Alphavirus; Togaviridae; Diptera;&lt;br&gt;   insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; North America; America;&lt;br&gt;   Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 15 ref.</no>
<ad>IFAS, University of Florida, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19910504724</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3301</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Benton,A. H.</a1>
<t1>Population Dynamics and Co Evolution of Adult Siphonapteran Parasites of the Southern Flying Squirrel Glaucomys-Volans-Volans</t1>
<jf>American Midland Naturalist</jf>
<jo>Am.Midl.Nat.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>333</sp>
<op>338</op>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Evolution and Adaptation</k1>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>01500, Evolution</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Siphonaptera [75346]/Rodentia, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Rodents, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Sciuridae [86405]</k1>
<ab>One possible outcome of the competitive interaction of 2 or more species for a limited resource is the development of 1 or more strategies which allow all species involved to use the resource that is limiting. This study suggests that 4 spp. of fleas which inhabit the nest of the southern flying squirrel (G. v. volans) have coevolved life history strategies which allow them to cycle asynchronously. By being in the adult stage during different months of the year the 4 flea species [Conorhinopsylla stanfordi Stewart, Epitedia faceta (Rothschild), Opisodasys pseudarctomys (Baker) and Orchopeas howardi howardi (Baker)] apparently do not place undue parasitic pressure on the host squirrels.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198070032201</no>
<sn>0003-0031</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; DEP ENTOMOL, UNIV MASS, AMHERST, MASS 01003, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3476</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Carlson,D. B.</a1>
<t1>The importance of autumn rainfall and sentinel flock location to understanding the epidemiology of St Louis encephalitis virus in Indian River County, Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>305</sp>
<op>309</op>
<k1>LL820 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Animals (Discontinued March 2000) HH700 Other Control Measures EE100 Economics (General) VV200 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Humans (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>arboviruses</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>encephalitis</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>infections</k1>
<k1>mosquito nets</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>transmission</k1>
<k1>vectors</k1>
<k1>viral diseases</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>fowls</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>encephalomyelitis</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United</k1>
<k1>States of America</k1>
<k1>viral infections</k1>
<ab>Culex nigripalpus adults were collected from sentinel chickens at 4 sites in Indian River Co. (IRC) Florida. Chickens located in well drained, open habitats attracted fewer Cx. nigripalpus than did those located in a moist, forested area, but the number of mosquitoes collected in the open habitats increased significantly with heavy autumn rainfall. All St Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) seroconversions (11/674) during a 7-year period were from chickens located in open, well drained habitats. A comparison of monthly rainfall during years of known SLE activity in IRC with the 22-year average showed that virus activity was significantly associated with years in which rainfall was unusually low in either September or October. Sentinal chickens in areas with large vector populations may not be the most reliable indicators of local SLE activity and autumn rainfall in September and October may influence yearly SLE patterns in southern Florida. ASADDITIONAL ABSTRACT:Sentinel chickens located in well drained open habitats in Florida attracted fewer adults of Culex nigripalpus than did those located in a moist forested area, but the number of mosquitoes collected in the open habitats increased significantly with heavy autumn rainfall. All the St. Louis encephalitis virus seroconversions during a 7-year period (1977-84) were from chickens in open well drained habitats. Virus activity was significantly associated with years in which rainfall was unusually low in September or October. Sentinel chickens may not be the most reliable indicators of local St. Louis encephalitis activity, and autumn rainfall in September and October may influence yearly patterns in southern Florida.; Culex nigripalpus adults were collected from sentinel chickens at 4 sites in Indian River Co. (IRC) Florida. Chickens located in well drained, open habitats attracted fewer Cx. nigripalpus than did those located in a moist, forested area, but the number of mosquitoes collected in the open habitats increased significantly with heavy autumn rainfall. All St Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) seroconversions (11/674) during a 7-year period were from chickens located in open, well drained habitats. A comparison of monthly rainfall during years of known SLE activity in IRC with the 22-year average showed that virus activity was significantly associated with years in which rainfall was unusually low in either September or October. Sentinal chickens in areas with large vector populations may not be the most reliable indicators of local SLE activity and autumn rainfall in September and October may influence yearly SLE patterns in southern Florida. AS</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   RNA viruses; viruses; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; eukaryotes; Diptera; Culex; Culicidae; Gallus gallus; Gallus;&lt;br&gt;   Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds; vertebrates; Chordata; poultry; North&lt;br&gt;   America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; SU: 1 fig.; NR: 16 ref.</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA 01003, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19862026686</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3471</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Curtis,G. A.</a1>
<t1>Influence of rainfall on Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae) blood-feeding behavior in Indian River County, Florida.</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>37</op>
<k1>LL300 Animal Behaviour MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology</k1>
<k1>Arboviruses</k1>
<k1>Behaviour</k1>
<k1>blood-meals</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>ecology</k1>
<k1>environmental factors</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Feeding behaviour</k1>
<k1>Population ecology</k1>
<k1>Rain</k1>
<k1>Seasonal abundance</k1>
<k1>vectors</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>America (North)</k1>
<k1>behavior</k1>
<k1>feeding behavior</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>rainfall</k1>
<k1>rainfall effects</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Culex nigripalpus Theobald abundance was monitored by ground aspirator collections taken three times a week at a site in Indian River County, Florida from January 1985 through December 1987. Aspirator collections allowed daily surveillance of fluctuations in mosquito abundance and changes in blood-feeding behavior. A Time Series Analysis of the 3-yr period revealed a significant cross correlation between C. nigripalpus engorgement and daily rainfall. This was especially pronounced in 1985, when St Louis encephalitis virus was common in Indian River County, but was much less pronounced in 1987, when no virus activity was recorded. Rainfall in July, August, and September strongly influenced mosquito abundance during the autumn and early winter when virus transmission was most common. Dry conditions during July and August 1987 reduced mosquito abundance drastically during the following autumn. ASADDITIONAL ABSTRACT:The abundance of C. nigripalpus was monitored by ground aspirator (&amp;#39;pooter&amp;#39;) collections taken 3 times a week at a site in Indian River County, Florida, from January 1985 to December 1987. Aspirator collections allowed daily surveillance of fluctuations in mosquito abundance and changes in blood-feeding behaviour. A Time Series Analysis of the 3-year period revealed a significant cross correlation between C. nigripalpus engorgement and daily rainfall. This was especially pronounced in 1985, when St. Louis encephalitis virus was common in Indian River County, but was much less pronounced in 1987, when no virus activity was recorded. Rainfall in July, August and September strongly influenced mosquito abundance during the autumn and early winter when virus transmission was most common. Dry conditions during July and August 1987 reduced abundance drastically during the following autumn.; Culex nigripalpus Theobald abundance was monitored by ground aspirator collections taken three times a week at a site in Indian River County, Florida from January 1985 through December 1987. Aspirator collections allowed daily surveillance of fluctuations in mosquito abundance and changes in blood-feeding behavior. A Time Series Analysis of the 3-yr period revealed a significant cross correlation between C. nigripalpus engorgement and daily rainfall. This was especially pronounced in 1985, when St Louis encephalitis virus was common in Indian River County, but was much less pronounced in 1987, when no virus activity was recorded. Rainfall in July, August, and September strongly influenced mosquito abundance during the autumn and early winter when virus transmission was most common. Dry conditions during July and August 1987 reduced mosquito abundance drastically during the following autumn. AS</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Culex; Culicidae; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods;&lt;br&gt;   invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; Flavivirus; North&lt;br&gt;   America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; NR: 20 ref.</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., IFAS-Univ. Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19902069314</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3293</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Curtis,G. A.</a1>
<t1>Opportunistic Blood Feeding on Egg Laying Sea Turtles Caretta-Caretta-Caretta by Salt Marsh Mosquitoes Diptera Culicidae</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>359</sp>
<op>360</op>
<k1>Behavior</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>07003, Behavioral biology - Animal behavior</k1>
<k1>07517, Ecology: environmental biology - Water research and fishery biology</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>13002, Metabolism - General metabolism and metabolic pathways</k1>
<k1>13202, Nutrition - General studies, nutritional status and methods</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]/Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Vertebrata [85150]/Reptilia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Reptiles, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Chelonia [85402]/Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Mammalia [85700]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198426050602</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; FLORIDA MED ENTOMOL LAB, VERO BEACH, FLA 32960, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2256</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Curtis,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Rainfall-directed oviposition behavior of Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae) and its influence on St. Louis encephalitis virus transmission in Indian River County, Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>43</sp>
<op>50</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis, St. Louis/transmission</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Insect Vectors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Oviposition/physiology</k1>
<k1>Rain</k1>
<ab>Resting Culex nigripalpus Theobald were collected with a ground aspirator three times a week in Indian River County, Fla., from January 1985 through December 1987. The number of green (newly emerged), empty, blood-fed, and gravid females in each collection was counted; up to 100 empty females were dissected to estimate the abundance of empty, parous females in the population. In general, this species was uncommon during the dry season from January through June but increased during the wet season in July and remained abundant through early winter. During the wet season, green, parous, and gravid females were periodically abundant. Time series analysis demonstrated that green and parous mosquitoes were positively associated through time and that gravid females were associated negatively with daily rainfall. The strongest correlations were recorded in 1985, a year during which St. Louis encephalitis virus was detected with increased frequency in Indian River County. Laboratory experiments in a large outdoor wind tunnel confirmed that high relative humidity was important for the initiation and successful completion of oviposition by gravid, field-collected Cx. nigripalpus mosquitoes. Thus, intermittent rainfall during autumn may serve to delay oviposition, increase longevity, synchronize blood feeding, and enhance transmission of St. Louis encephalitis virus by infected mosquitoes in the field.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-20983/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Vero Beach 32962.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2299655</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2299655</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3294</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Ebert,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Feeding Pattern of Mosquitoes Diptera Culicidae Simultaneously Exposed to Malarious and Healthy Mice Including a Method for Separating Blood Meals from Conspecific Hosts</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>120</sp>
<op>127</op>
<k1>Behavior</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>06504, Radiation biology - Radiation and isotope techniques</k1>
<k1>07003, Behavioral biology - Animal behavior</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10064, Biochemistry studies - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>13002, Metabolism - General metabolism and metabolic pathways</k1>
<k1>13202, Nutrition - General studies, nutritional status and methods</k1>
<k1>22100, Routes of immunization, infection and therapy</k1>
<k1>34502, Immunology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>35000, Immunology, parasitological</k1>
<k1>37052, Public health: epidemiology - Communicable diseases</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>60504, Parasitology - Medical</k1>
<k1>64002, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Protozoa</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Protozoa, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Invertebrates, Microorganisms, Protozoans</k1>
<k1>Sporozoa [35400]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]/Rodentia, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Rodents, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Muridae [86375]</k1>
<k1>ESTRADIOL</k1>
<k1>50-28-2</k1>
<ab>A method involving injection of anti-estradiol into mice and subsequently assaying this Ig in the blood meal radio-immunologically was developed to mark conspecific animals for mosquito feeding experiments. Mosquitoes released into cages containing 1 uninfected mouse and 1 mouse infected with either Plasmodium chabaudi or P. berghei engorged almost exclusively on the infected animal. Engorgement success depended on rodent defensive behavior, which was significantly modified by malaria infection. Mosquitoes successfully obtained blood from P. chabaudi-infected mice on day 9-13 postinfection. Mice infected with P. berghei were most vulnerable to mosquito engorgement on day 6-8 and 17-20 postinfection. When cages contained 2 uninfected mice, mosquitoes rarely engorged. Mosquitoes in cages containing 2 malaria-infected mice had engorgement profiles similar to those in cages containing an infected and uninfected mouse.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198376059233</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; FLORIDA MED ENTOMOL LAB, P O BOX 520, VERO BEACH, FLORIDA 32960, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3296</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Ebert,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Age of Murine Hosts Determined by Binding of Estradiol to Mosquito Blood Meals</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>357</sp>
<op>360</op>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Endocrine System (Chemical Coordination and Homeostasis)</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Metabolism</k1>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>01012, Methods - Photography</k1>
<k1>06504, Radiation biology - Radiation and isotope techniques</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10064, Biochemistry studies - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>13008, Metabolism - Sterols and steroids</k1>
<k1>13012, Metabolism - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>16504, Reproductive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>17004, Endocrine - Adrenals</k1>
<k1>17006, Endocrine - Gonads and placenta</k1>
<k1>25000, Pediatrics -</k1>
<k1>25508, Development and Embryology - Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>33506, Virology - Animal host viruses</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>60504, Parasitology - Medical</k1>
<k1>64002, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Protozoa</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>64078, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: pathology</k1>
<k1>Negative Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Negative Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Bunyaviridae [03506]/Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses [03600]/Protozoa, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Invertebrates, Microorganisms, Protozoans</k1>
<k1>Flagellata [35200]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]/Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Mammalia [85700]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]/Rodentia, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Mammals, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Nonhuman Mammals, Rodents, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Muridae [86375]</k1>
<k1>ESTRADIOL</k1>
<k1>50-28-2</k1>
<ab>Steroid-binding proteins (e.g., .alpha.-fetoprotein) are found in blood of many mammalian neonates, where they serve to bind and clear maternal steroid hormones. Detectable amounts of steroid-binding proteins (SBP) were found in mosquito blood meals obtained from suckling laboratory mice. Mosquitoes fed on suckling mice were easily differentiated from those fed on adults by testing blood meals for binding of radiolabeled estradiol (3H-E2). Binding of 3H-E2 in blood meals remained detectable for up to 18 h after ingestion. Binding of radiolabeled steroids to blood meals can be used to determine the relative age of host rodents. Potential field applications and limitations of this technique are discussed. [Rodents are important to cycling and maintenance of human and animal pathogens such as Leishmania, California encephalitis and Venezuelan equine encephalitis viruses.].</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198376040392</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; DEP ENTOMOL, UNIV MASS, AMHERST, MASS 01003, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2265</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>The importance of disease induced changes in mammalian body temperature to mosquito blood feeding</t1>
<jf>Comparative biochemistry and physiology.A, Comparative physiology</jf>
<jo>Comp.Biochem.Physiol.A.Comp.Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>447</sp>
<op>452</op>
<k1>Aedes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anopheles/physiology</k1>
<k1>Body Temperature</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology</k1>
<k1>Culicidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Enterovirus Infections/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Malaria/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Maus Elberfeld virus</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Plasmodium</k1>
<k1>Plasmodium berghei</k1>
<ab>Laboratory mice infected with rodent malaria (Plasmodium berghei or P. chabaudi) or St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) were not hyperthermic during the infection period. However, all infected animals displayed pathogen-specific periods of hypothermia. Hamsters infected with P. berghei were hyperthermic on day 7 postinfection (PI) but became hypothermic on day 8 PI and remained so until death, approximately 20 days PI. Body temperatures of mice infected with P. yoelii were not significantly different from those of uninfected control mice. Mosquitoes (Aedes aegypti, Anopheles stephensi and Culex quinquefasciatus) successfully engorged on restrained, uninfected mice, but were unable to engorge on unrestrained, uninfected mice due to the natural antimosquito behavior of the healthy rodents. Mosquitoes successfully engorged on unrestrained, malaria or SLE infected mice only during certain pathogen-specific periods of infection, but were able to engorge on all restrained, infected mice throughout the infection period regardless of the animal&amp;#39;s body temperature. Daily activity patterns of malaria infected mice followed pathogen-specific profiles which closely conformed to the observed mosquito-engorgement profiles.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081030; GR: AI 07109/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 13981/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 1276312; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0300-9629; 0300-9629</sn>
<an>PMID: 6142803</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6142803</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2264</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Mosquito engorgement on normally defensive hosts depends on host activity patterns</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Nov 29</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>732</sp>
<op>740</op>
<k1>Aedes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anopheles/physiology</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Cricetinae</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Host-Parasite Interactions</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Peromyscus</k1>
<k1>Restraint, Physical</k1>
<no>LR: 20071115; GR: AI-07109/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-13981/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0375400; OID: NASA: 85058010; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<an>PMID: 6502631</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM; S</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6502631</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2268</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Malaria renders mice susceptible to mosquito feeding when gametocytes are most infective</t1>
<jf>The Journal of parasitology</jf>
<jo>J.Parasitol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>163</sp>
<op>170</op>
<k1>Aedes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Malaria/parasitology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred A</k1>
<k1>Plasmodium berghei</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Mice infected with Plasmodium berghei, P. chabaudi, or P. yoelii became lethargic and ceased to display normal antimosquito behavior. Periods of reduced defensiveness corresponded with maximum mosquito engorgement and with periods of maximum gametocyte infectivity to mosquitoes. Increased feeding success of mosquitoes during periods of peak gametocyte infectivity may be important to the natural maintenance of these malaria parasites.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 13981/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7803124; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-3395; 0022-3395</sn>
<an>PMID: 6338190</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6338190</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2250</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Scott,T. W.</a1>
<t1>Reproductive fitness and survivorship of Aedes aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae) maintained on blood, with field observations from Thailand</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>611</sp>
<op>617</op>
<k1>Aedes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animal Nutritional Physiological Phenomena</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blood</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Reproduction</k1>
<k1>Thailand</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Daily survivorship and fecundity of Aedes aegypti mosquitoes were monitored for cohorts provided with five nutritional treatments: water, 2% sucrose, blood from a live chicken plus water, blood plus 2% sucrose, and blood alone. The median mortality time (LT50) for these females was 6, 54, 16, 12, and 29 d, respectively. There was no significant difference in the number of eggs laid by females in any of the treatments containing a host. Females maintained on blood alone laid as many or more eggs during their lifetime as females with access to sugar who had a greater life expectancy. Males maintained on sugar alone survived significantly longer than those in any of the other treatments. Large- and small-bodied, sugar-starved Ae. aegypti females that were marked, released, and recaptured in a Thai village survived as well as the replicate cohorts that received sugar or sugar plus blood during the 36 +/- 12 h period from emergence until their release. These results indicate that Ae. aegypti females live longer in the laboratory if they are provided a source of carbohydrate, but the increased survival associated with sugar feeding does not increase reproductive success.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: AI-22119/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, Vero Beach 32962.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7932609</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7932609</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3463</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Lewis,A. L.</a1>
<t1>An integrated approach to arboviral surveillance in Indian River County, Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Florida Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>62</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>46</sp>
<op>52</op>
<k1>VV200 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Humans (Discontinued March 2000) MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology</k1>
<k1>Arboviruses</k1>
<k1>Disease vectors</k1>
<k1>Epidemics</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Human diseases</k1>
<k1>Monitoring</k1>
<k1>Mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>sentinel animals</k1>
<k1>Surveillance</k1>
<k1>Viral diseases</k1>
<k1>Wild birds</k1>
<k1>Birds</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>Fowls</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>surveillance systems</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>viral infections</k1>
<ab>A long term surveillance programme was developed to monitor and predict the transmission of St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) in southern Florida, USA. This programme was tested from 1983 to 1990 in collaboration with the Indian River Mosquito Control District. Two types of surveillance data were collected. First, factors predicting the probability of annual SLE transmission were tracked year round. These included: annual and daily rainfall patterns throughout the county, vector (Culex nigripalpus) and amplification host population dynamics, wild bird immunity to SLE, and viral isolation from vector mosquitoes. Second, factors that proved virus transmission was occurring were monitored. These included: viral isolation from avian amplification hosts, the detection of recently acquired antibody from sentinel chickens and wild birds, and the incidence of suspected, presumptive and confirmed human SLE cases.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   viruses; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; eukaryotes; vertebrates; Chordata; Flavivirus; Homo;&lt;br&gt;   Hominidae; Primates; mammals; Culex; Culicidae; Gallus gallus; Gallus;&lt;br&gt;   Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds; poultry; North America; America;&lt;br&gt;   Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 17 ref.</no>
<sn>1055-355X</sn>
<ad>Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19920508585</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3278</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Ramsey,A. M.</a1>
<t1>Environmentally Mediated Seasonal Variation in Mosquito Body Size</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>469</sp>
<op>473</op>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10011, Biochemistry - Physiological water studies</k1>
<k1>10614, External effects - Temperature as a primary variable</k1>
<k1>13202, Nutrition - General studies, nutritional status and methods</k1>
<k1>15001, Blood - General and methods</k1>
<k1>16504, Reproductive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>23001, Temperature - General measurement and methods</k1>
<k1>25508, Development and Embryology - Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<ab>The mean adult body size of male and nonblood-fed female Culex nigripalpus Theobald mosquitoes showed a highly significant negative correlation with water temperature in the field. Large females were more successful in obtaining blood and developing eggs during an extended period of drought from March through September 1987. Small females emerged from field-collected pupae but were less successful in blood feeding and developing eggs in the field during the period of drought.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199090049387</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; FLA MED ENTOMOL, LAB INST FOOD AND AGRIC SCI, UNIV FLA, VERO BEACH, FLA 32962, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3413</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<t1>Severe winter freezes enhance St. Louis encephalitis virus amplification and epidemic transmission in Peninsular Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1498</sp>
<op>1506</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>reservoir hosts</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>West Nile fever</k1>
<k1>winter</k1>
<k1>birds</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Mosquito-borne arboviral epidemics tend to strike without warning. The driving force for these epidemics is a combination of biotic (vector, amplification host, and virus) and abiotic (meteorological conditions, especially rainfall and temperature) factors. Abiotic factors that facilitate the synchronization and interaction of vector and amplification host populations favor epidemic amplification and transmission. In Florida, epidemics of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus (family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus, SLEV) have been preceded by major freezes one or two winters before the onset of human cases. Here, we analyze the relationship between severe winter freezes and epidemic SLEV transmission in peninsular Florida and show that there is a significant relationship between the transmission of SLEV and these severe freezes. We propose that by killing cold-sensitive understory vegetation in the mid-peninsular region of Florida, freezes enhance the reproductive success of ground-feeding avian amplification hosts, especially mourning doves and common grackles. In conjunction with other appropriate environmental signals, increased avian reproductive success may enhance SLEV and West Nile (WN) virus amplification and result in SLE and WN epidemics during years when all of the biological cycles are properly synchronized. The knowledge that winter freezes in Florida may enhance the amplification and epidemic transmission of SLE and WN viruses facilitates arboviral tracking and prediction of human risk of SLE and WN infection during the transmission season.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: vertebrates; Chordata; animals; eukaryotes; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda;&lt;br&gt;   arthropods; invertebrates; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD&lt;br&gt;   Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; Homo;&lt;br&gt;   Hominidae; Primates; mammals; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense&lt;br&gt;   ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>CABI:20103030332</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://esa.publisher.ingentaconnect.com/content/esa/jme/2009/00000046/00 000006/art00038</lk>
<do>10.1603/033.046.0638</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3416</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<t1>Using hydrologic conditions to forecast the risk of focal and epidemic arboviral transmission in Peninsular Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>458</sp>
<op>465</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) LL823 Veterinary Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>amplification</k1>
<k1>arboviruses</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>drought</k1>
<k1>encephalitis</k1>
<k1>epidemics</k1>
<k1>monitoring</k1>
<k1>outbreaks</k1>
<k1>rain</k1>
<k1>temperature</k1>
<k1>vector-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>birds</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>viruses</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>encephalomyelitis</k1>
<k1>rainfall</k1>
<k1>surveillance systems</k1>
<k1>United States of</k1>
<k1>America</k1>
<ab>The accurate forecasting and tracking of arboviral transmission is becoming increasingly critical for the early recognition and management of arboviral epidemics. Meteorological factors, especially rainfall and temperature, drive arboviral epidemics, but monitoring rainfall and temperature alone is not predictive of increased levels of vector-borne disease transmission. In Florida, model simulations of water table depth (WTD) provide a measure of drought, and they have been shown to provide an accurate forecast of arboviral transmission. Here, we tracked WTD in two peninsular Florida regions where focal West Nile virus (family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus, WNV) transmission was reported during 2004 and 2005. We compared the resulting WTD profiles with historical WTD simulations for Indian River County (IRC), FL, where two peninsular Florida St. Louis encephalitis virus epidemics had their epicenters in 1977 and 1990. In both of the regions where focal WNV transmission was reported during 2004 and 2005, the local WTD profiles approached the 1977 and 1990 IRC WTD profiles; however, differences in the local temporal sequence of hydrologic conditions were observed. These differences seem in part to explain why the focal WNV transmission during 2004 and 2005 failed to reach epidemic levels in peninsular Florida. These findings suggest that hydrologic monitoring, specifically WTD, may help determine the geographic extent, timing, and intensity of WNV transmission. We speculate that a more precise sequence of drought and wetting, including a secondary summer drying and wetting cycle, as occurred in IRC during 1977 and 1990, may provide the optimal hydrologic conditions for the expansion of an arbovirus outbreak from focal to epidemic. This study documents that monitoring hydrologic conditions, along with vector, avian amplification host, and virus population data, increases our ability to track and predict significant levels of arboviral transmission.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: vertebrates; Chordata; animals; eukaryotes; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; Flaviviridae; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; Flavivirus</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>CABI:20093326922</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://esa.publisher.ingentaconnect.com/content/esa/jme/2008/00000045/00 000003/art00018</lk>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2008)45[458:UHCTFT]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2251</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Sjogren,R. D.</a1>
<t1>Vector control by removal trapping</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>6 Suppl</is>
<sp>126</sp>
<op>133</op>
<k1>Africa</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Australia</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Disease Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Muscidae</k1>
<k1>Pest Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Tsetse Flies</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<ab>The classic approach to vector control where large tracts of land are treated with an insecticide has many shortcomings. These include high cost, chemical resistance of target species to many of the widely used insecticides, a lack of public acceptance, and the detrimental effect of sprays on nontarget species. Removal trapping, the use of visual, auditory, and olfactory attractants to lure target species into small areas where they are killed, has recently received well-deserved attention as a possible alternative to the broadcast application of chemicals for vector control. We briefly review the histories of four successful removal trapping programs; Hippelates eye gnats in the United States, tsetse flies in Africa, Stomoxys calcitrans flies in Australia, and tabanids in the United States. We then review the future prospects of removal trapping and evaluate its potential as a viable method for vector control.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 0370507; RF: 34; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0002-9637; 0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, Vero Beach.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8024078</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8024078</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3441</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stark,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Frequency of Saint Louis encephalitis virus in humans from Florida, USA: 1990-1999.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>626</sp>
<op>633</op>
<k1>LL821 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Animals (NEW March 2000) VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>epidemics</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>outbreaks</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>fowls</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Four general frequencies of human St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus (epidemic, focal, sporadic), and no transmission occurred in Florida, USA between 1990 and 1999. An epidemic with 226 clinical cases and 11 deaths was reported from 28 Florida counties between July 1990 and January 1991. During the autumn of 1993, a focal outbreak was reported from Lee (5 cases) and Collier (3) Counties in southwest Florida. During the autumn of 1997, sporadic transmission to nine humans was reported from five Florida counties (Brevard, 1 case; Polk, 3; Charlotte, 1; Lee, 2; and Palm Beach, 2). Human infection with SLE virus depends on a number of variables that drive virus transmission. These include vector, virus, and avian host abundance, and meteorological events, especially rainfall. We monitored the abundance and serological status of wild avian amplification hosts, virus isolations from Culex nigripalpus females, and SLE virus transmission to sentinel chickens during 1990, 1993, and 1997. The epidemic of 1990 was characterized by conditions that produced an unusual abundance of vector mosquitoes and avian amplification hosts early in the year. We propose that epidemics may result when a specific combination of biotic and abiotic conditions favour SLE virus minimum field infection rates that approach 1 : 1000 in Cx. nigripalpus vectors.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Culex; Culicidae; Gallus gallus; Gallus; Phasianidae;&lt;br&gt;   Galliformes; birds; vertebrates; Chordata; poultry; Homo; Hominidae;&lt;br&gt;   Primates; mammals; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 20 ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20013136622</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2246</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stark,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Transmission patterns of St. Louis encephalitis and eastern equine encephalitis viruses in Florida: 1978-1993</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>132</sp>
<op>139</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bird Diseases/virology</k1>
<k1>Chickens/virology</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis Virus, Eastern Equine/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis Virus, St. Louis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<ab>Sentinel chickens were maintained at field sites in 40 Florida counties for varying periods between 1978 and 1993. For each county, the total number of St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) or eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) virus seroconversions were divided by the number of chickens exposed to calculate a mean annual seroconversion rate. These rates were used to evaluate the annual and geographical distributions of these viruses within Florida. For SLE, the rates in counties that reported human SLE cases during a widespread epidemic in 1990 were compared with adjusted mean annual seroconversion rates calculated by excluding the epidemic year seroconversion data. In general, actual rates were higher than adjusted rates in counties where human SLE cases were reported in 1990. Similar calculations were made for EEE virus that was unusually abundant in northern Florida during the spring and summer of 1991. In general, EEE virus was distributed in the panhandle and northern regions and SLE virus in the central and southern regions of the state. However, this distribution was not exclusive, and during years of high transmission, either virus can extend beyond its normal range. The annual distribution of SLE and EEE viruses was sporadic, ranging from years with little detectable activity to years with widespread, high-level transmission.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Vero Beach 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8906917</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8906917</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3287</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Van Handel,E.</a1>
<t1>Differences between the Nutritional Reserves of Laboratory-Maintained and Field-Collected Adult Mosquitoes</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>154</sp>
<op>157</op>
<k1>Behavior</k1>
<k1>Climatology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>01004, Methods - Laboratory methods</k1>
<k1>07003, Behavioral biology - Animal behavior</k1>
<k1>07504, Ecology: environmental biology - Bioclimatology and biometeorology</k1>
<k1>10066, Biochemistry studies - Lipids</k1>
<k1>10068, Biochemistry studies - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>12100, Movement</k1>
<k1>13004, Metabolism - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>13006, Metabolism - Lipids</k1>
<k1>13220, Nutrition - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>13222, Nutrition - Lipids</k1>
<k1>16501, Reproductive system - General and methods</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>GLYCOGEN</k1>
<k1>9005-79-2</k1>
<ab>Individual female mosquitoes from field populations of Aedes aegypti, Culex nigripalpus and Coquillettidia perturbans were analyzed for sugar, glycogen and lipids. Controls were maintained in the laboratory for 7 to 10 days on 2% and either 10 or 20% sucrose. Mosquitoes held in the laboratory had significnatly more glycogen and lipid than field-collected mosquitoes of the same species. Laboratory mosquitoes maintained on 10 or 20% sucrose contained more sugar than did field mosquitoes. Mosquitoes of the above species were collected at field sites in January, April, July and October and nutritional reserves were determined. Seasonal differences in reserves were documented in females of all species. However, even when reserves were at their highest in field-collected mosquitoes they rarely approached the reserves in mosquitoes of the same species maintained in the laboratory on 10 or 20% sucrose. Since laboratory-maintained mosquitoes are nutritionally different from those in the field, results of laboratory studies on flight performance, host attractancy, biting, disease transmission and oviposition behavior may be biased.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198783059198</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; INST FOOD AGRIC SCI, UIV FLORIDA, FLORIDA MED ENTOMOL LAB, 200 9TH ST SE, VERO BEACH, FLA 32962, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3276</id>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Winner,R.</a1>
<a1>Parsons,R. E.</a1>
<t1>Distribution of St. Louis Encephalitis Viral Antibody in Sentinel Chickens Maintained in Sarasota County Florida Usa 1978-1988</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>19</sp>
<op>23</op>
<k1>Cell Biology</k1>
<k1>Immune System (Chemical Coordination and Homeostasis)</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>Veterinary Medicine (Medical Sciences)</k1>
<k1>02506, Cytology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10064, Biochemistry studies - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>10068, Biochemistry studies - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>27002, Poultry production - General and methods</k1>
<k1>33506, Virology - Animal host viruses</k1>
<k1>34504, Immunology - Bacterial, viral and fungal</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>36504, Medical and clinical microbiology - Serodiagnosis</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>38004, Veterinary science - Pathology</k1>
<k1>38006, Veterinary science - Microbiology</k1>
<k1>Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses [03600]/Aves, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Galliformes [85536]</k1>
<ab>Sentinel chicken flocks monitored arboviral transmission at 12 sites in Sarasota County, Fla., from 1978 thorugh 1988. During this time, 3,452 serum samples were analyzed for hemagglutination inhibition antibody to St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) and eastern equine encephalomyelitis virus (EEE). Overal, 91 chickens seroconverted To SLE and three to EEE. The intensity of SLE transmission showed considerable year-to-year variation. Chickens from south-county flocks were more likely to seroconvert to SLE virus than chickens maintained at the north-country sites. The SLE seroconversion rate for midcounty sentinels was intermediate between north- and south-county sites. Chickens were caged in four habitat types: oak hammocks, slash pine-saw palmetto areas, pastures, and urban-residential areas. There was no significant difference in SLE seroconversion rates between habitats.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199192004790</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>DAY J F ; FLA MED ENTOMOL LAB, INST FOOD AGRIC SCI, UNIV FLA, 200 9TH ST SE, VERA BEACH, FLA 32962, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2328</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Avian population dynamics as a key factor in virus amplification</t1>
<jf>1996 Annual Meeting of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<fd>8-12 Dec 1996</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 964 5008); Availability: Entomological Society of America, 9301 Annapolis Road, Lanham, MD 20706-3115, Contact authors directly for individual papers. Paper No. 0502&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Louisville, KY (USA)</ed>
<ad>FMEL, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA; Entomological Society of America</ad>
<an>3287422</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 1000 Animal and Plant Science; U 2000 Biology</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2329</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Highlights of medical entomology</t1>
<jf>1997 Annual Meeting of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<fd>14-18 Dec 1997</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 974 5000); Availability: Entomological Society of America, 9301 Annapolis Road, Lanham, MD 20706-3115, Contact individual authors directly, or search abstracts at http://www.sheridan.com/entsoc/abs&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Nashville, TN (USA)</ed>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomology Lab., Univ. Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA; Entomological Society of America</ad>
<an>3347266</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 1000 Animal and Plant Science; U 2000 Biology</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2360</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Curtis,GA</a1>
<t1>Blood Feeding and Oviposition by Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae) Before, During, and After a Widespread St. Louis Encephalitis Virus Epidemic in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>176</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Blood meals</k1>
<k1>Disease transmission</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Feeding behavior</k1>
<k1>Feeding behaviour</k1>
<k1>Human diseases</k1>
<k1>Oviposition</k1>
<k1>Public health</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Viral diseases</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Freshwater</k1>
<ab>A widespread epidemic of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus was reported from central Florida from late July through December 1990 with 226 clinical cases and 11 deaths in humans. The abundance of blood-fed and gravid Culex nigripalpus Theobald females, the vector of SLE in Florida, was monitored at a resting site in Indian River County, FL, for the 3 yr before the epidemic, the epidemic year, and for 1 yr following the epidemic. Each study year was divided into four 3-mo periods that depict the subtropical SLE transmission cycle; a January-March maintenance phase, an April-June amplification phase, a July-September early transmission phase, and an October-December late transmission phase. The abundance of blood-fed and gravid females was significantly greater during the amplification, early transmission, and late transmission phases of the 1990 SLE epidemic when compared with the 3 pre-epidemic years. Throughout the study, Cx. nigripalpus blood feeding and oviposition was driven by epic (&amp;gt;50 mm) rainfall events. The abundance of gravid females decreased, whereas the number of blood-fed females increased following heavy rainfalls. Epizootic and epidemic transmission of SLE to sentinel chickens and humans in Indian River County was greatest immediately following heavy rainfalls that synchronized Cx. nigripalpus oviposition and blood feeding.</ab>
<no>TR: CS9912845&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>4501156</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; Y 25423 Insects; V 22123 Epidemiology; Q1 01425 Nutrition and feeding habits</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; Animal Behavior Abstracts; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>ASFA: Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries Abstracts</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2372</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Curtis,GA</a1>
<t1>When it rains, they soar -- and that makes Culex nigripalpus a dangerous mosquito</t1>
<jf>American Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Am.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>162</sp>
<op>167</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>biological vectors</k1>
<k1>public health</k1>
<k1>reviews</k1>
<k1>vector-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>viral diseases</k1>
<k1>viruses</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Freshwater</k1>
<ab>The purpose of this article is to review the natural history of Culex nigripalpis and, in so doing, identify the physiological and biological factors that make it the most dangerous mosquito in Florida.</ab>
<no>TR: CS9517280&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1046-2821</sn>
<ad>Univ. Florida&#39;s, Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>3762299</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; V 22160 Viral infections of invertebrates; Q1 01484 Species interactions: parasites and diseases</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>ASFA: Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries Abstracts</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2373</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Curtis,GA</a1>
<t1>Annual emergence patterns of Culex nigripalpus females before, during and after a widespread St. Louis encephalitis epidemic in South Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>249</sp>
<op>255</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>emergence</k1>
<k1>females</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>Freshwater</k1>
<ab>Resting Culex nigripalpus females were collected from the same site at least 3 times a week from January 1986 through December 1991. Newly emerged mosquitoes were used to monitor annual emergence patterns that were rainfall driven. Four of the years, 1986-89, preceded the 1990 St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) epidemic in south Florida. The pre-epidemic period averaged 4 emergences per year, with most occurring during July and August. The emergence patterns observed during the epidemic year were unusual in their early start in May and June and in the total number (11) observed. Adult mosquito emergences in 1991 were similar to those in 1990, with an early start and a total of 14 observed, yet no SLE transmission was recorded in Indian River County during 1991. A time series analysis of the 6-year data set showed a significant cross-correlation between the emergence of Cx. nigripalpus females and heavy (&amp;gt; 50 mm) rains. A significant adult emergence occurred 5-8 days and 12-15 days following a heavy rainfall event.</ab>
<no>TR: CS9401832&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., Inst. Food and Agric. Sci., Univ. Florida, 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>3509519</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; D 04659 Insects; Q1 01304 Reproduction and development; Q1 01485 Species interactions: pests and control</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; Ecology Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2363</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Duzak,D.</a1>
<a1>Braverman,Y.</a1>
<a1>Chizov-Ginzburg,A.</a1>
<a1>Linley,JR</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructure of the eggs of Culicoides circumscriptus, Culicoides gejgelensis, and Culicoides imicola (Diptera: Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>76</sp>
<op>83</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: eggs</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Ceratopogonidae</k1>
<k1>Culicoides circumscriptus</k1>
<k1>Culicoides gejgelensis</k1>
<k1>Culicoides imicola</k1>
<k1>Biting midges</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>No-see-ums</k1>
<k1>Punkies</k1>
<k1>ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Freshwater</k1>
<ab>The eggs of Culicoides circumscriptus Kieffer, Culicoides gejgelensis Dzhafarov, and Culicoides imicola Kieffer collected in Israel are described and illustrated by scanning electron micrographs. Eggs of all 3 species were morphologically similar, generally sausage- or cigar-shaped, with slight dorsal-ventral curvature and longitudinal rows of tubercle pillars covered with a thin adhesive layer. Tubercle pillars were scarce on C. circumscriptus and C. imicola eggs, but were common on C. gejgelensis eggs, forming longitudinal plastrons with an associated hydrofuge meshwork. All 3 species had micropyle domes and associated aeropyles at the anterior end of their eggs.</ab>
<no>TR: CS9720362&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., Inst. Food and Agric. Sci., Univ. Florida, 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>4113191</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05158 Eggs &amp; immature stages; Q1 01304 Reproduction and development</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>ASFA: Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries Abstracts</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2381</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Edman,JD</a1>
<t1>Host location, blood-feeding, and oviposition behavior of Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae): Their influence on St. Louis encephalitis virus transmission in southern Florida</t1>
<jo>Miscellaneous Publications of the Entomological Society of America [MISC.PUBL.ENTOMOL.SOC.AM</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<sp>]</sp>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>blood meals</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>feeding behavior</k1>
<k1>host location</k1>
<k1>oviposition</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida, South</k1>
<k1>relationship</k1>
<k1>vector-borne disease</k1>
<ab>Culex nigripalpus (Theobald) is a proven vector of St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLE) in southern Florida. It is an important vector for three reasons: its opportunistic blood-feeding behavior, its ability to forage and locate hosts in a variety of habitats, and its ability to retain eggs for long periods when suitable oviposition sites are unavailable. Results of laboratory and field observations documenting that Cx. nigripalpus fits the above criteria are presented.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<a2>Scott,T. W.</a2><a2> Grumstrup-Scott,J.</a2>
<t2>Symposium on the Role of Vector-Host Interactions in Disease Transmission, National Conference of the Entomological Society of America, Hollywood, FL (USA), 10 Dec 1985</t2>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., Univ. Florida, IFAS, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>1849835</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; Y 25503 Insects; V 22123 Epidemiology; Z 05199 Feeding; Z 05192 Reproductive behavior; V 22143 Epizootiology; V 22160 Viral infections of invertebrates</cl>
<sf>Book Monograph; Conference; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Animal Behavior Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2361</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Stark,LM</a1>
<t1>St. Louis encephalitis virus transmission to emus (Dromaius novaehollandiae) in Palm Beach County, Florida with evidence of western equine encephalitis virus antibody transport to Florida by emus infected in other states</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>104</sp>
<op>111</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Antibodies</k1>
<k1>Disease transmission</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination inhibition</k1>
<k1>Neutralization</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Arbovirus</k1>
<k1>Dromaius novaehollandiae</k1>
<k1>Eastern equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Western equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<ab>From November 1993 through January 1995, sera were collected from 59 domestic emus (Dromaius novaehollandiae) at a ranch in Palm Beach County, FL and tested for antibody evidence of arboviral infection. Hemagglutination inhibition (HI) and neutralizing (NT) antibodies to St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus were identified in sera collected each year. In addition, HI and NT antibodies to eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) virus and NT antibodies to western equine encephalitis (WEE) virus were detected in emus imported to and then maintained at the ranch.*</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>4355349</an>
<la>English; English; Spanish</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; V 22143 Epizootiology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2366</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Stark,LM</a1>
<a1>Zhang,Jin-tong</a1>
<a1>Ramsey,AM</a1>
<a1>Scott,TW</a1>
<t1>Antibodies to arthropod-borne encephalitis viruses in small mammals from southern Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of wildlife diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Wildl.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>431</sp>
<op>436</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: antibodies</k1>
<k1>seroepidemiology</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Peromyscus gossypinus</k1>
<k1>Sigmodon hispidus</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>arbovirus</k1>
<k1>eastern equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<ab>From 1987 through 1991, blood samples were collected from 10 species of small mammals in Indian River County, Florida (USA). Sera from 1,347 animals were analyzed for hemagglutination-inhibition (HI) antibody to St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) and eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) viruses. Of these, 75 (5.6%) were positive for HI antibody to SLE virus and 121 (9.0%) were positive for EEE antibody. Sera from five mammalian species were tested for neutralizing (NT) antibody to SLE, EEE, Highlands J (HJ, a member of the western equine encephalitis virus complex), or Everglades (EVE, a member of the Venezuelan equine encephalitis complex) viruses. By serum neutralization tests, 26 (46%) of 57 had SLE antibodies, 14 (24%) of 58 had EEE antibodies, two (3.2%) of 63 had HJ antibodies, and 9 (14%) of 63 had EVE antibodies. One Sigmodon hispidus and one Peromyscus gossypinus had NT antibodies both to EEE and HJ viruses. Blood samples from 512 mammals were tested for virus. Isolations of one EVE virus and two unidentified arenaviruses were made from P. gossypinus, and one EVE virus isolate was made from a S. hispidus.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0090-3558</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., Inst. Food and Agric. Sci., Univ. Florida, 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>3949596</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>V 22142 Symptomatology, pathology &amp; etiology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2367</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Storrs,EE</a1>
<a1>Stark,LM</a1>
<a1>Lewis,AL</a1>
<a1>Williams,S.</a1>
<t1>Antibodies to St. Louis encephalitis virus in armadillos from southern Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of wildlife diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Wildl.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>10</sp>
<op>14</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: antibodies</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Dasypus movemcinctus</k1>
<ab>From January 1990 through March 1991, 189 armadillos (Dasypus novemcinctus) were collected from Brevard and Glades Counties in southern Florida (USA). The sera were analyzed for hemagglutination-inhibition (HAI) antibodies against St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) and eastern equine encephalomyelitis (EEE) viruses. None of the armadillos had detectable HAI antibody to EEE virus, but 59 (31%) had antibodies against SLE virus. Sera from 31 of the HAI-positive armadillos contained significant levels of neutralizing (NT) antibody to SLE virus. Armadillos captured during the 1990 SLE human epidemic in south Florida had a greater prevalence of HAI and NT antibody to SLE virus than did animals captured before the start of the epidemic. This is evidence that armadillos were fed on by mosquitoes infected with SLE virus. We propose that armadillos may be involved in the SLE amplification and transmission cycles in Florida.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0090-3558</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomology Lab., Inst. Food and Agric. Sci., Univ. Florida, 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>3838768</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>V 22143 Epizootiology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2382</id>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Van Handel,E.</a1>
<t1>Differences in carbohydrate reserves between resting and flying Culex nigripalpus collected in the field</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>547</sp>
<op>548</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: carbohydrate composition</k1>
<k1>flight</k1>
<k1>resting behavior</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., Univ. Florida, IFAS, 200 9th St., S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>1926404</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>Z 05173 Biochemistry &amp; metabolism (incl. fat body)</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3252</id>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Stark,Lillian M.</a1>
<t1>Avian serology in a St. Louis encephalitis epicenter before, during, and after a widespread epidemic in south Florida, USA</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sept., 1999</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>614</sp>
<op>624</op>
<k1>Epidemiology (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>37056, Public health: epidemiology - Miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>15001, Blood - General and methods</k1>
<k1>16501, Reproductive system - General and methods</k1>
<k1>62518, Chordata: general and systematic - Aves</k1>
<k1>33502, Virology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>Aves, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Columbiformes [85524]</k1>
<k1>[Zenaida macroura</k1>
<k1>mourning dove</k1>
<k1>(host)]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis, St. Louis (MeSH)</k1>
<k1>nervous system disease, viral disease</k1>
<k1>blood</k1>
<k1>blood and lymphatics/serum</k1>
<k1>blood and lymphatics</k1>
<ab>Blood and serum from 3,915 wild and domestic birds (2,590 resident, 139 migrant, and 1,186 captive), representing 56 species collected in central Florida from 1989 through 1997, were analyzed for evidence of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus transmission. All sera were tested for SLE hemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibody. Selected sera and bloods were tested for SLE neutralizing (NT) antibody and virus. The reproductive success of resident birds was highest from 1990-1992 and lowest from 1994-1997. Transmission of SLE to resident birds, especially mourning doves (Zenaida macroura), peaked during the summer of 1990, a year during which a widespread SLE epidemic was recorded in central Florida. The SLE antibody-positive resident birds 1st appeared during September of the epidemic year. Some SLE, HI antibody-positive resident birds were captured throughout 1991, but only 5% were yearlings, compared with 36% in 1990. By 1993, wild resident birds expressing HI and NT antibodies to SLE had nearly disappeared. None of the migrant birds tested were SLE-positive. Sentinel chickens maintained in Indian River County during the epidemic year seroconverted to SLE starting in early July with peak seroconversion rates in August, September, and October. High (gtoreq50%) SLE seroconversion rates in sentinel chickens preceded those in wild birds by 10 wk and preceded peak human SLE transmission by at least 8 wk. Major SLE epidemics in south Florida depend on abundant wild bird populations, especially during the amplification phase of the transmission cycle. We propose that hard winter freezes along the temperate-subtropical climatic zone interface in central Florida, at apprxeq27degree30&amp;#39; North Latitude, opens foraging and nesting habitats for ground-feeding birds, resulting in high reproductive success and an abundance of seronegative individuals that rapidly amplify the SLE later in the year.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900478717&lt;br&gt;ME: print; GE: South Florida; Florida, USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Day, Jonathan F. ; Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL, 32962, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3258</id>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Stark,Lillian M.</a1>
<t1>Eastern equine encephalitis transmission to emus (Dromaius novaehollandiae) in Volusia County, Florida: 1992 through 1994</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>1996</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>3 PART 1</is>
<sp>429</sp>
<op>436</op>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>12510, Pathology - Necrosis</k1>
<k1>22100, Routes of immunization, infection and therapy</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Aves, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Casuariiformes [85516]</k1>
<k1>[emu] [Dromaius novaehollandiae]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Anopheles crucians] [Culex erraticus] [Culex nigripalpus]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Togaviridae [03616]</k1>
<k1>[Eastern equine encephalitis virus]</k1>
<ab>From May 1992 through October 1994, sera were collected from 204 domestic emus (Dromaius novaehollandiae) at a ranch in Volusia County, FL, and tested for antibody evidence of arboviral infection. Hemagglutination-inhibition (FE) and neutralizing (NT) antibodies to eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) virus were identified in sera collected during each year. In addition, HI and NT antibodies to St. Louis encephalitis virus were detected in 3 naturally infected emus. Isolations of EEE virus were made from emu blood and tissues collected in 1992 and 1994, when EEE-related mortality in emus was 14% and 1%, respectively. A total of 259 mosquito pools was collected and tested for arboviruses during the 3-year study. The EEE virus was isolated from 4 of 140 mosquito pools (2 Anopheles crucians and 2 Culex erraticus pools) in 1992 and 3 of 10 pools (all Culex nigripalpus) in 1994. Emus vaccinated against EEE virus showed evidence of short-term HI antibody acquisition. Evidence of EEE antibody transfer from naturally infected hens to their offspring is reported.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199699233158; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region/USA; North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Day, Jonathan F. ; Fla. Med. Entomology Lab., Inst. Food Agricultural Sciences, Univ. Fla., 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3427</id>
<a1>Douglas,H. D.,III</a1>
<a1>Co,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Jones,T. H.</a1>
<a1>Conner,W. E.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Chemical odorant of colonial seabird repels mosquitoes.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>647</sp>
<op>651</op>
<k1>HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) YY700 Pathogens, Parasites and Infectious Diseases (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>aldehydes</k1>
<k1>ectoparasites</k1>
<k1>ectoparasitoses</k1>
<k1>insect repellents</k1>
<k1>odours</k1>
<k1>Aethia</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Aethia cristatella</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>odors</k1>
<k1>smells</k1>
<ab>The crested auklet, Aethia cristatella, emits a class of aldehydes shown to be potent invertebrate repellents when used by heteropterans against their predators. Our aim was to determine the efficacy of these aldehydes against mosquitoes in the laboratory. Synthetic analogues of the auklet odorant were strongly repellent to mosquitoes in controlled laboratory trials. Furthermore, the efficacy was similar to previous reports for commercial mosquito repellents. These results, in combination with a previously published study, show that constituents of the aldehyde odourant are broad spectrum in efficacy against ectoparasitic arthropods of birds. Our report is the first empirical evidence for an endogenous mosquito repellent in birds.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Alcidae; Charadriiformes; birds; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   Aethia; NR: 39 ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Institute of Marine Science, University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, AK 99775, USA.; douglas@ims.uaf.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053183244</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2005)042[0647:COOCSR]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3290</id>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Walker,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Field Confirmation of Laboratory Observations on the Differential Antimosquito Behavior of Herons</t1>
<jf>Condor</jf>
<jo>Condor</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>86</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>91</sp>
<op>92</op>
<k1>Behavior</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Morphology</k1>
<k1>07003, Behavioral biology - Animal behavior</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>11304, Chordate body regions - Head</k1>
<k1>12100, Movement</k1>
<k1>13202, Nutrition - General studies, nutritional status and methods</k1>
<k1>20504, Nervous system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>21003, Psychiatry - Psychophysiology</k1>
<k1>64074, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: morphology, comparative</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]/Aves, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Ciconiiformes [85520]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198528036783</no>
<sn>0010-5422</sn>
<ad>EDMAN J D ; DEP ENTOMOLOGY, UNIV MASS, AMHERST, MASS 01003, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3437</id>
<a1>Fradin,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Comparative efficacy of insect repellents against mosquito bites.</t1>
<jf>New England Journal of Medicine</jf>
<jo>N.Engl.J.Med.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>347</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>13</sp>
<op>18</op>
<k1>HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) SS200 Non-food/Non-feed Plant Products VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>insect bites</k1>
<k1>insect repellents</k1>
<k1>volunteers</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Background: The worldwide threat of arthropod-transmitted diseases, with their associated morbidity and mortality, underscores the need for effective insect repellents. Multiple chemical, botanical, and &amp;quot;alternative&amp;quot; repellent products are marketed to consumers. We sought to determine which products available in the USA provide reliable and prolonged complete protection from mosquito bites. Methods: We conducted studies involving 15 volunteers to test the relative efficacy of seven botanical insect repellents; four products containing N,N-diethyl-m-toluamide, now called N,N-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide (DEET); a repellent containing IR3535 (ethyl butylacetylaminopropionate); three repellent-impregnated wristbands; and a moisturizer that is commonly claimed to have repellent effects. These products were tested in a controlled laboratory environment in which the species of the mosquitoes, their age, their degree of hunger, the humidity, the temperature, and the light-dark cycle were all kept constant. Results: DEET-based products provided complete protection for the longest duration. Higher concentrations of DEET provided longer-lasting protection. A formulation containing 23.8 percent DEET had a mean complete-protection time of 301.5 minutes. A soyabean-oil-based repellent protected against mosquito bites for an average of 94.6 minutes. The IR3535-based repellent protected for an average of 22.9 minutes. All other botanical repellents we tested provided protection for a mean duration of less than 20 minutes. Repellent-impregnated wristbands offered no protection. Conclusions: Currently available non-DEET repellents do not provide protection for durations similar to those of DEET-based repellents and cannot be relied on to provide prolonged protection in environments where mosquito-borne diseases are a substantial threat.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; NR: 40 ref.</no>
<pb>Massachusetts Medical Society</pb>
<pp>Waltham USA</pp>
<sn>0028-4793</sn>
<ad>Chapel Hill Dermatology, 891 Willow Dr., Suite 1, Chapel Hill, NC 27514, USA.; mark_fradin@med.unc.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20023102561</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.1056/NEJMoa011699</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3237</id>
<a1>Fradin,Mark S.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<t1>The authors reply</t1>
<jf>New England Journal of Medicine</jf>
<jo>N.Engl.J.Med.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>November 21, 2002</fd>
<vo>347</vo>
<is>21</is>
<sp>1720</sp>
<op>1721</op>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60016, Economic entomology - Chemical control and apparatus</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human]/Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Insecta [75300]</k1>
<k1>[insect</k1>
<k1>(pest)]</k1>
<k1>Bayrepel</k1>
<k1>119515-38-7</k1>
<k1>(insecticide)/DEET</k1>
<k1>N,N-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide</k1>
<k1>(insecticide)/insect repellents</k1>
<k1>(insecticide)/vitamin B-1</k1>
<k1>59-43-8</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200200623166&lt;br&gt;ME: print</no>
<sn>0028-4793</sn>
<ad>Fradin, Mark S. ; Chapel Hill Dermatology, Chapel Hill, NC, 27514, USA; mark_fradin@med.unc.edu</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Letter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3438</id>
<a1>Fukuda,T.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>An iridescent virus and a microsporidium in the biting midge Culicoides barbosai from Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>128</sp>
<op>130</op>
<k1>VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY700 Pathogens, Parasites and Infectious Diseases (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>histopathology</k1>
<k1>larvae</k1>
<k1>mortality</k1>
<k1>Culicoides barbosai</k1>
<k1>Nosema</k1>
<k1>death rate</k1>
<k1>iridescent viruses</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>An iridescent virus and a microsporidium (Nosema sp.) were found infecting the larvae of the biting midge C. barbosai collected in Boynton Beach, Palm Beach County, Florida, USA. Larvae were extracted from mud collected weekly during a 22-month period from March 1998 to December 1999. Virus-infected larvae were present in 4 collections made in March, April, and May 1998 and the average infection level was 4.7% (range 2.3-7.1%). The virus infected the fat body and produced an iridescent blue colour in larvae because of the crystalline arrays of the particles. These virus particles were hexagonal, measured 99 nm from side to side, and had an electron-dense inner core. The site of infection of the Nosema sp. also was the fat body of the larva, which became opaque white. These opaque areas were the result of masses of oval binucleate spores measuring 2.70.1*4.40.3 m (n=25). The Nosema sp. was present in larvae of 14 collections made during the 22-month period, with an average infection level of 6.1% (range 0.3-21.4%). Although individual larvae infected with the iridescent virus and Nosema sp. occurred in 4 collections, no dual infections were observed. Larvae patently infected with the iridescent virus and Nosema sp. died before pupation.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Culicoides; Ceratopogonidae; Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods;&lt;br&gt;   invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Iridoviridae; dsDNA viruses; DNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; viruses; Nosematidae; Microspora; Protozoa; South Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America;&lt;br&gt;   Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; NR: 11 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Eatontown USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Center for Medical, Agricultural and Veterinary Entomology, PO Box 14565, Gainesville, FL 32604, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20023094678</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2340</id>
<a1>Garvin,MC</a1>
<a1>Tarvin,KA</a1>
<a1>Stark,LM</a1>
<a1>Woolfenden,GE</a1>
<a1>Fitzpatrick,JW</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Arboviral Infection in Two Species of Wild Jays (Aves: Corvidae): Evidence for Population Impacts</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>41</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>215</sp>
<op>225</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Disease control</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Disease reservoirs</k1>
<k1>Survival</k1>
<k1>Control</k1>
<k1>Sex</k1>
<k1>Age</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Antibodies</k1>
<k1>Viruses</k1>
<k1>Viral diseases</k1>
<k1>Biological vectors</k1>
<k1>Aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>Serological studies</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Arbovirus</k1>
<k1>Highlands j virus</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Eastern equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Aves</k1>
<k1>Cyanocitta cristata</k1>
<k1>Aphelocoma coerulescens</k1>
<k1>Corvidae</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>Birds</k1>
<k1>Blue jay</k1>
<k1>Florida Scrub-jay</k1>
<k1>Scrub Jay</k1>
<k1>Freshwater</k1>
<ab>We examined the prevalence of antibodies to three mosquito-borne arboviruses in blue jays, Cyanocitta cristata, and Florida scrub-jays, Aphelocoma coerulescens, to identify the effects on host survival, the influence of sex and age on infection, and the temporal patterns of antibody prevalence. Blood samples from 306 blue jays and 219 Florida scrub-jays were collected at Archbold Biological Station (Lake Placid, FL) from April 1994 through December 1995. Sera were analyzed for hemagglutination-inhibition antibody to eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) and St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) viruses, and neutralizing antibodies to EEE, Highlands J (HJ), and SLE viruses. Overall, 31.4% of blue jay samples and 22.1% of scrub-jay samples had antibodies to EEE. Antibodies to HJ were detected in slightly &amp;gt;15% of samples in each jay species, and SLE was detected in &amp;lt;3% of the samples in each jay species. A single EEE virus isolation was made from the blood of an 11-d-old scrub-jay nestling. Survival of adult blue jays seropositive to EEE was significantly lower than that of seronegative birds based on resight rates, but infection did not seem to affect survival of adult or juvenile Florida scrub-jays.</ab>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Infection status; Nutritional independence; Relationship between brood survival; Object Statistical Terms: Degrees of Freedom; P-value; TR: CS0514929&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 10. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00015%2Fi0022-2585-041-02-0215%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-041-02-0215-t10.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=e8381fe57e36bf1dd43e4ad7a167ae61&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 10. Relationship between brood survival and infection status at nutritional independence in Florida scrub-jays&lt;br&gt;M1: Table&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Relationship between brood survival; Nutritional independence; Infection status; Object Statistical Terms; Degrees of Freedom; P-value</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Archbold Biological Station, 123 Main Dr., Venus, FL 33960</ad>
<an>5902574</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; V 22141 Diagnosis; Q1 01484 Species interactions: parasites and diseases; Q5 01524 Public health, medicines, dangerous organisms; Q1 01301 General</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; 1B; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; ASFA 3: Aquatic Pollution &amp; Environmental Quality; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts; OB</sf>
<lk>http://journals.allenpress.com/jrnlserv/?request=get-abstract&amp;issn=0022-2585&amp;volume=41&amp;page=215</lk>
<do>10.1043/0022-2585(2004)041(0215:AIITSO)2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3486</id>
<a1>Guthrow,C. E.</a1>
<a1>Morris,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Thorpe,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Baynes,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Enhanced nonenzymatic glucosylation of human serum albumin in diabetes mellitus.</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>4258</sp>
<op>4261</op>
<k1>VV130 Nutrition-related Disorders and Therapeutic Nutrition</k1>
<k1>albumins</k1>
<k1>diabetes</k1>
<k1>Man</k1>
<k1>nonenzymic glucosylation of serum albumin in diabetes</k1>
<ab>Nonenzymically glucosylated serum albumin was greater in patients with poorly controlled diabetes mellitus than in controls. Several patients apparently in good control based on glycosylated haemoglobin estimations had increased glucosylated albumin. Because albumin has a shorter circulating half-life than the human erythrocyte, the plasma concentration of glucosylated albumin should be expected to reflect short-term control of hyperglycaemia in diabetes. Glucosylated albumin may be a sensitive indicator of moderate hyperglycaemia and of early glucose intolerance.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; NR: 10 ref.</no>
<sn>0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Dep. Medicine, Duke Univ. Medical Center, Durham, N.C. 27710, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19791495697</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2379</id>
<a1>Handel,E.</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Correlation between wing length and protein content of mosquitoes</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>180</sp>
<op>182</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: protein composition</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>correlation</k1>
<k1>length</k1>
<k1>wings</k1>
<ab>Wing length and protein content were compared in individual specimens of male and nonbloodfed, nongravid female mosquitoes. The following groups were tested: field-collected and colonized Aedes aegypti ; field-collected Culex nigripalpus and Aedes vexans ; and colonized Culex quinquefasciatus and Psorophora columbiae . The correlation coefficient varied from 0.91 in Ae. aegypti males to 0.98 in Ae. vexans females, and in each group the P value was less than 0.001. This close correlation suggests that both wing length and protein measurement are reliable expressions of size in adult mosquitoes.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., 200 9th St. SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<an>2094529</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05159 Adults; Z 05173 Biochemistry &amp; metabolism (incl. fat body)</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3461</id>
<a1>Handel,E. van</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>A day in the life of Culex nigripalpus.</t1>
<yr>1993</yr>
<sp>288</sp>
<op>293</op>
<k1>LL300 Animal Behaviour MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology</k1>
<k1>behaviour</k1>
<k1>Blood</k1>
<k1>Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>Ecology</k1>
<k1>Feeding behaviour</k1>
<k1>Fructose</k1>
<k1>Haematophagy</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>physiology</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>sugar feeding</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Fowls</k1>
<k1>behavior</k1>
<k1>blood feeding</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>feeding</k1>
<k1>fruit sugar</k1>
<k1>hematophagy</k1>
<k1>ketohexose</k1>
<k1>laevulose</k1>
<k1>levulose</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>saccharides</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The feeding habits of C. nigripalpus were traced over a 24-h period (3-4 November 1992) near Vero Beach, Florida, USA. Total carbohydrate content was used as the principal criterion for short-term changes in nutritional status.</ab>
<no>GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Diptera; Gallus gallus; Gallus; Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds;&lt;br&gt;   vertebrates; Chordata; poultry; Culex; Culicidae; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; NR: 9 ref.</no>
<a2>Borovsky,D. Spielman,A.</a2>
<t2>Host regulated developmental mechanisms in vector arthropods: Proceedings of the Third Symposium, Vero Beach, Florida, February 8-11, 1993.; Host regulated developmental mechanisms in vector arthropods: Proceedings of the Third Symposium, Vero Beach, Florida, February 8-11, 1993.</t2>
<pb>University of Florida - IFAS, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory</pb>
<pp>Vero Beach, Florida USA</pp>
<ad>IFAS-University of Florida, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, 200 9th Street S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19930517473</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper</sf>
<cn>57-48-7</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3469</id>
<a1>Handel,E. van</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Assay of lipids, glycogen and sugars in individual mosquitoes: correlations with wing length in field collected Aedes vexans.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>549</sp>
<op>550</op>
<k1>ZZ900 Techniques and Methodology MM300 Aquatic Biology and Ecology LL600 Animal Physiology and Biochemistry (Excluding Nutrition)</k1>
<k1>assays</k1>
<k1>biochemistry</k1>
<k1>carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>Ecology</k1>
<k1>Glycogen</k1>
<k1>Lipids</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>size</k1>
<k1>Sugar feeding</k1>
<k1>Sugars</k1>
<k1>Techniques</k1>
<k1>Trehalose</k1>
<k1>Aedes vexans</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>lipins</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>saccharides</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>A protocol for separating lipids and sugars from glycogen from the same mosquito is given, a modification of previously reported methods [see E. van Handel (1985) Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association, 1: 299-301, 302-304]. Using field-collected females of A. vexans, captured in Florida, it was found that there was a strong correlation between lipid content and wing length (p &amp;lt; 0.01), a parameter of body size, and between glycogen and wing length (p &amp;lt; 0.01); however, there was no correlation between wing length and sugar (e.g. trehalose, glucose, fructose and sucrose) content.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Diptera; Aedes; Culicidae; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 10 ref.</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, IFAS, 200 9th Street, S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19900594389</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>9005-79-2; 99-20-7</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2335</id>
<a1>Harbison,JE</a1>
<a1>Mathenge,EM</a1>
<a1>Misiani,GO</a1>
<a1>Mukabana,WR</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>A Simple Method for Sampling Indoor-Resting Malaria Mosquitoes Anopheles Gambiae and Anopheles Funestus (Diptera: Culicidae) in Africa</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>473</sp>
<op>479</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Malaria</k1>
<k1>Methodology</k1>
<k1>Sampling</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Traps</k1>
<k1>Greenhouses</k1>
<k1>Aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>Human diseases</k1>
<k1>Surveillance and enforcement</k1>
<k1>Entomology</k1>
<k1>Spray</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Anopheles funestus</k1>
<k1>Anopheles gambiae</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: Africa</k1>
<k1>Kenya</k1>
<k1>Mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>Sampling indoor resting African malaria vectors is traditionally done by hand catches with oral or mechanical aspirators and pyrethrum spray catches (PSCs). In this study, we designed and briefly evaluated an inexpensive but practical alternative by using a cloth resting box or wicker resting basket and a ceiling net. Evaluations were performed in greenhouse and field situations in rural Kenya by comparing capture rates of Anopheles gambiae s.l. and Anopheles funestus (Giles) in these traps to hand collections and PSCs. A resting box and a ceiling net when used together collected more mosquitoes than a single collector using a hand-held aspirator but only one-third the number collected by PSCs. At sites where PSCs are impractical, a resting box and ceiling net can be effectively used as an alternative to hand catches in malaria surveillance.</ab>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Bed net; Cardboard box; Cloth box; Cloth resting box; Hand collection; Percentage of mosquitoes found (%); Percentage of total mosquitoes collected (%); Percentage of total number of mosquitoes collected (%); Resting bed-net hung in hut; Resting net; Trap tested; Wicker basket resting box; Object Taxonomic Terms: Anopheles funestus; Anopheles gambiae; Object Statistical Terms: Degrees of Freedom; F-Test; Mean; P-value; Standard Error; TR: CS0728634&lt;br&gt;IF: Figure 1. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00068%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473-f01.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=e18cae90070b27f9c5e60127f89f4ce2&lt;br&gt;C1: Figure 1. Cloth resting box (left) and the wicker basket resting box (right)&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Cloth resting box; Wicker basket resting box; Object Taxonomic Terms; Anopheles funestus; Anopheles gambiae&lt;br&gt;IF: Figure 2. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00068%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473-f02.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=47bbf82e6bd21abe419a00175e06090a&lt;br&gt;C1: Figure 2. Resting bed-net hung in hut&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Resting bed-net hung in hut; Object Taxonomic Terms; Anopheles funestus; Anopheles gambiae&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 1. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00068%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473-t01.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=e7057df4e288655abc48f811a0c70dae&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 1. Percentage of total number of mosquitoes (437) collected from each location&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Bed net; Percentage of total number of mosquitoes collected (%); Object Taxonomic Terms; Anopheles funestus; Anopheles gambiae&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 2. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00068%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473-t02.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=1a6f0c35a51926c8dbcd8281daed23f1&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 2. Percentage of the overall number of mosquitoes found in each dwelling over the 27 test dates for the three methods tested&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Cardboard box; Cloth box; Hand collection; Percentage of mosquitoes found (%); Object Taxonomic Terms; Anopheles gambiae; Object Statistical Terms; Degrees of Freedom; F-Test; Mean; P-value; Standard Error&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 3. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00068%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-43-3-473-t03.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=bca742bf4c34fe7f9d0e39e96ba7e5c9&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 3. Percentage of the total mosquitoes collected by each trap tested the Latin Square&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Cardboard box; Percentage of total mosquitoes collected (%); Resting net; Trap tested; Object Taxonomic Terms; Anopheles funestus; Anopheles gambiae</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Department of Entomology and Nematology, Gainesville, FL 32611</ad>
<an>7002009</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05156 Techniques; Q1 01422 Environmental effects; Q5 01524 Public health, medicines, dangerous organisms</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; ASFA 3: Aquatic Pollution &amp; Environmental Quality; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; 1B; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<lk>http://journals.allenpress.com/jrnlserv/?request=get-abstract&amp;issn=0022-2585&amp;volume=43&amp;issue=3&amp;page=473</lk>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2006)43[473:ASMFSI]2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2249</id>
<a1>Linley,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Benton,A. H.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructure of the eggs of seven flea species (Siphonaptera)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>813</sp>
<op>832</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chorion/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fleas/classification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Ovum/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Eggs of seven flea species representing five families, Ctenocephalides felis (Bouche) (Pulicidae), Orchopeas leucopus (Baker) and Aetheca wagneri (Baker) (Ceratophyllidae), Conorhinopsylla stanfordi Stewart and Epitedia faceta (Rothschild) (Hystrichopsyllidae), Sternopsylla distincta texana (C. Fox) (Ischnopsyllidae), and Craneopsylla minerva (Rothschild) (Stephanocircidae), were examined with a scanning electron microscope and are described from the resulting micrographs. In the Pulicidae and Ceratophyllidae the individual outer chorionic cells are not visible; the egg surfaces are covered uniformly with small, nodular tubercles. In contrast, the Hystrichopsyllidae and Ischnopsyllidae have a prominent, raised reticulum, very heavily constructed in the latter, delineating the chorionic cells. The single representative of the Stephanocircidae has only a faintly embossed chorionic reticulum. All of the species examined except E. faceta and C. minerva (both with a single micropylar opening) have multiple micropyles at the posterior end. C. felis, O. leucopus, A. wagneri, and C. stanfordi also have multiple aeropyles at the anterior end (these are lacking in S. d. texana). Lateral aeropyles, consisting of small groups of pores often associated with small mounds in the chorion, are present (maximum of two seen on any one egg) in all species except E. faceta, C. stanfordi, and C. minerva.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, IFAS University of Florida, Vero Beach 32962.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7815392</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7815392</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3457</id>
<a1>Linley,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Benton,A. H.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Ultrastructure of the eggs of seven flea species (Siphonaptera).</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>813</sp>
<op>827</op>
<k1>LL820 Parasites, Vectors, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Animals (Discontinued March 2000) ZZ310 Anatomy, Morphology and Structure (General) (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>eggs</k1>
<k1>morphology</k1>
<k1>morphotaxonomy</k1>
<k1>ova</k1>
<k1>scanning electron microscopy</k1>
<k1>taxonomy</k1>
<k1>Ceratophyllidae</k1>
<k1>Ctenocephalides felis</k1>
<k1>Hystrichopsyllidae</k1>
<k1>Ischnopsyllidae</k1>
<k1>Orchopeas leucopus</k1>
<k1>Pulicidae</k1>
<k1>Siphonaptera</k1>
<k1>Aetheca</k1>
<k1>Aetheca wagneri</k1>
<k1>cat flea</k1>
<k1>Conorhinopsylla</k1>
<k1>stanfordi</k1>
<k1>Craneopsylla</k1>
<k1>Craneopsylla minerva</k1>
<k1>Epitedia</k1>
<k1>faceta</k1>
<k1>Stephanocircidae</k1>
<k1>Sternopsylla</k1>
<k1>Sternopsylla distincta</k1>
<k1>Sternopsylla distincta texana</k1>
<k1>systematics</k1>
<ab>Eggs of 7 flea species representing 5 families, Ctenocephalides felis (Pulicidae), Orchopeas leucopus and Aetheca wagneri (Ceratophyllidae), Conorhinopsylla stanfordi and Epitedia faceta (Hystrichopsyllidae), Sternopsylla distincta texana (Ischnopsyllidae) and Craneopsylla minerva (Stephanocircidae), were examined and described using scanning electron microscopy. In the Pulicidae and Ceratophyllidae the individual outer chorionic cells are not visible; the egg surfaces are covered uniformly with small, nodular tubercles. In contrast, the Hystrichopsyllidae and Ischnopsyllidae have a prominent, raised reticulum, very heavily constructed in the latter, delineating the chorionic cells. The single representative of the Stephanocircidae has only a faintly embossed chorionic reticulum. All of the species examined except E. faceta and C. minerva (both with a single micropylar opening) have multiple micropyles at the posterior end. Ctenocephalides felis, O. leucopus, A. wagneri and Conorhinopsylla stanfordi also have multiple aeropyles at the anterior end (these are lacking in S. d. texana). Lateral aeropyles, consisting of small groups of pores often associated with small mounds in the chorion, are present (maximum of 2 seen on any one egg) in all species except E. faceta, C. stanfordi and Craneopsylla minerva.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Siphonaptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Ctenocephalides; Pulicidae; Orchopeas; Ceratophyllidae;&lt;br&gt;   Hystrichopsyllidae; Ischnopsyllidae; NR: 6 ref.</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, IFAS University of Florida, 200 9th Street S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19950502540</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2323</id>
<a1>Lord,CC</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Modeling arboviruses in Florida: Impact of bird mortality</t1>
<jf>ASTMH 49th Annual Meeting</jf>
<fd>29 Oct-2 Nov 2000</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 000 5172); Availability: American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, 3088 Briarcliff Rd., Ste. 11A, Atlanta, GA 30329, USA&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Houston, Texas (USA)</ed>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomology Lab, Univ. Florida - IFAS, Vero Beach, FL, USA; American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</ad>
<an>3547693</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 7000 Multidisciplinary</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2330</id>
<a1>Lord,CC</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Simulation studies of the epidemiology of St. Louis encephalitis and Culex nigripalpus in Florida</t1>
<jf>1997 Annual Meeting of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<fd>14-18 Dec 1997</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 974 5000); Availability: Entomological Society of America, 9301 Annapolis Road, Lanham, MD 20706-3115, Contact individual authors directly, or search abstracts at http://www.sheridan.com/entsoc/abs. Poster Paper No. D394&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Nashville, TN (USA)</ed>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomology Lab., Univ. Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA; Entomological Society of America</ad>
<an>3347572</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 1000 Animal and Plant Science; U 2000 Biology</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2231</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Simulation studies of St. Louis encephalitis and West Nile viruses: the impact of bird mortality</t1>
<jf>Vector borne and zoonotic diseases (Larchmont, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Winter</fd>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>317</sp>
<op>329</op>
<k1>Aging</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bird Diseases/mortality/transmission/virology</k1>
<k1>Birds/virology</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis Virus, St. Louis</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis, St. Louis/mortality/transmission/veterinary</k1>
<k1>Insect Vectors/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Logistic Models</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Prevalence</k1>
<k1>Seasons</k1>
<k1>West Nile Fever/mortality/transmission/veterinary</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<ab>West Nile virus (WNv) has spread through much of the eastern United States following its introduction in 1999, and arrived in Florida in 2001. Prior to its arrival, we anticipated that its transmission cycle was likely to be similar to that of St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLEv). However, high levels of avian mortality have been reported for WNv in the northeastern United States, and it was unknown how this would impact the transmission dynamics of WNv. Simulation models were used to compare the two viruses by considering the impact of bird mortality on the transmission dynamics of arboviruses in south Florida. Transmission models without disease-induced mortality (SLEv) were compared with models including disease-induced mortality (WNv). Disease-induced mortality depressed transmission, eliminating epizootics in two of 14 simulations that were epizootic without the additional mortality. In both models, the most important factor in the likelihood of epizootics was mosquito population size; the mosquito mortality rate was also important. The additional avian mortality altered the factors most important in the size and timing of epizootics, although it did not always directly affect the outcome of the simulations. In some cases, low-level transmission occurred prior to the epizootic peak. When disease-induced avian mortality was included in the simulations, appreciable numbers of dead birds occurred prior to high levels of infection in mosquitoes. This has implications for the use of dead birds as a surveillance tool monitoring the spread and transmission of WNv.</ab>
<no>LR: 20031114; JID: 100965525; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1530-3667; 1530-3667</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida-Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA. clord@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12653130</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12653130</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2232</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Simulation studies of St. Louis encephalitis virus in south Florida</t1>
<jf>Vector borne and zoonotic diseases (Larchmont, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Winter</fd>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>299</sp>
<op>315</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bird Diseases/virology</k1>
<k1>Birds/virology</k1>
<k1>Chickens/virology</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Culex/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis Virus, St. Louis</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis, St. Louis/epidemiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior/physiology</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Insect Vectors/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Population Dynamics</k1>
<k1>Prevalence</k1>
<k1>Seasons</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<ab>Two simulation models were used to investigate the epidemiology of St. Louis encephalitis virus (SLEv) in south Florida, one including sentinel hosts (chickens) and amplification hosts (wild birds), while the other one included age structure in the amplification host population. The overall population size of the vector, Culex nigripalpus, was a major factor in the likelihood of epizootics for both models, but the seasonal dynamics of the vector alone did not explain variation in transmission. Interactions between seasonal factors in the mosquito and reproduction in the wild amplification avian hosts appeared to be important in the likelihood of epizootics. Biased feeding between sentinel and amplification hosts affected the time course of virus prevalence and may have implications for the interpretation of sentinel data. The time of virus introduction strongly affected the timing of outbreaks but did not affect the likelihood of epizootics. In most cases, the outbreak occurred immediately after virus introduction; however, in some cases the outbreak was delayed until the mosquito population increased. This has implications for the timing of control strategies directed against mosquito populations.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI142162/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100965525; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1530-3667; 1530-3667</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida-Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA. clord@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12653129</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12653129</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3443</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Attractiveness of chickens and bobwhite quail for Culex nigripalpus.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>271</sp>
<op>273</op>
<k1>LL120 Meat-producing Animals LL130 Egg-producing Animals LL823 Veterinary Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) HH500 Repellents and Attractants VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>attractants</k1>
<k1>baits</k1>
<k1>host preferences</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>trapping</k1>
<k1>Colinus virginianus</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>fowls</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<ab>An experiment to determine if wild C. nigripalpus preferentially enter lard-can traps baited with chickens or Colinus virginianus was conducted. A strong preference for the chicken-baited trap was observed.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Gallus gallus; Gallus; Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds; vertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   Chordata; animals; poultry; eukaryotes; Culex; Culicidae; Diptera;&lt;br&gt;   insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; Colinus; Odontophoridae; NR: 13 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Milltown USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida-IFAS, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20003028961</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3442</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>First record of Amblyomma auricularium (Acari: Ixodidae) in the United States.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>977</sp>
<op>978</op>
<k1>YY700 Pathogens, Parasites and Infectious Diseases (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000) ZZ380 Taxonomy and Evolution</k1>
<k1>geographical distribution</k1>
<k1>new geographic records</k1>
<k1>Amblyomma</k1>
<k1>Dasypus novemcinctus</k1>
<k1>Amblyomma auricularium</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>A survey of 9-banded armadillos (Dasypus novemcinctus) was conducted in Glades and Brevard Counties, Florida, USA. Armadillos were collected between January 1990 and March 1991 along canal banks (Brevard County) or in cattle pastures (Glades County). Collected animals were examined for ectoparasites, which were removed and preserved. 13 ticks were collected from one adult female armadillo collected in Glades County. No ticks were found on the rest of the armadillos collected (140 in Glades County, 49 in Brevard). All (11 males and 2 females) were identified as A. auricularium. This is the first record of this species in the USA.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Ixodidae; Metastigmata; Acari; Arachnida; arthropods; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; eukaryotes; Dasypus; Dasypodidae; Edentata; mammals;&lt;br&gt;   vertebrates; Chordata; Amblyomma; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 9 ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida - IFAS, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20013167408</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3246</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Modeling arboviruses in Florida: Impact of bird mortality</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>March, 2000</fd>
<vo>62</vo>
<is>3 Supplement</is>
<sp>373</sp>
<op>374</op>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>33506, Virology - Animal host viruses</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37052, Public health: epidemiology - Communicable diseases</k1>
<k1>37056, Public health: epidemiology - Miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>37057, Public health: disease vectors - General</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Aves [85500]</k1>
<k1>[bird]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[mosquito</k1>
<k1>(vector)]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>(model, pathogen, transmission)] [West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen, transmission)]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human]/Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Viruses [03000]</k1>
<k1>[arbovirus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen, transmission)]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200100014496&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 49th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; CL: Houston, Texas, USA; CY: October 29-November 02, 2000; SP: American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Lord, C. C. ; Day, J. F.; Florida Medical Entomology Lab, University of Florida - IFAS, Vero Beach, FL, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3251</id>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Modeling St. Louis encephalitis in Florida: What factors affect yearly variation in transmission?</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sept., 1999</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>3 SUPPL.</is>
<sp>396</sp>
<op>397</op>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Nervous System (Neural Coordination)</k1>
<k1>36001, Medical and clinical microbiology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>20501, Nervous system - General and methods</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Aves [85500]</k1>
<k1>[wild birds</k1>
<k1>(host)]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>(viral transmission model)]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]/Aves, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Galliformes [85536]</k1>
<k1>[chicken</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis, St. Louis (MeSH)</k1>
<k1>nervous system disease, viral disease</k1>
<k1>modeling, yearly transmission variation factors</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900499707&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 48th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; CL: Washington, D.C., USA; CY: November 28-December 2, 1999; SP: American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Lord, C. C. ; Day, J. F.; Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, Vero Beach, FL, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3226</id>
<a1>Lord,Cynthia C.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<t1>Modeling of arboviruses in Florida.</t1>
<jf>Ecological Society of America Annual Meeting Abstracts</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<sp>210</sp>
<op>211</op>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Models and Simulations (Computational Biology)</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>04500, Mathematical biology and statistical methods</k1>
<k1>10515, Biophysics - Biocybernetics</k1>
<k1>33502, Virology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37057, Public health: disease vectors - General</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Aves [85500]</k1>
<k1>[bird</k1>
<k1>(disease vector)]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[mosquito</k1>
<k1>(disease vector</k1>
<k1>mortality, outbreaks)]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)] [West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]</k1>
<k1>sensitivity analysis</k1>
<k1>mathematical and computer techniques/simulation modeling</k1>
<k1>mathematical and computer techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300528055&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 88th Annual Meeting of the Ecological Society of America held jointly with the International Society for Ecological Modeling - North American Chapter; CL: Savannah, Georgia, USA; CY: August 03-08, 2003; SP: Ecological Society of America; International Society for Ecological Modeling - North American Chapter; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<ad>Lord, Cynthia C. ; Day, Jonathan F.; University of Florida - IFAS, Vero Beach, FL, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3193</id>
<a1>McCann,Sean</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Allan,Sandra</a1>
<a1>Lord,Cynthia C.</a1>
<t1>Age modifies the effect of body size on fecundity in Culex quinquefasciatus Say (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vector Ecology</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>DEC 2009</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>174</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>Models and Simulations (Computational Biology)</k1>
<k1>Aging</k1>
<k1>04500, Mathematical biology and statistical methods</k1>
<k1>10515, Biophysics - Biocybernetics</k1>
<k1>15002, Blood - Blood and lymph studies</k1>
<k1>15004, Blood - Blood cell studies</k1>
<k1>24500, Gerontology</k1>
<k1>25502, Development and Embryology - General and descriptive</k1>
<k1>33502, Virology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>37057, Public health: disease vectors - General</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Diptera] [Culicidae] [Culex quinquefasciatus</k1>
<k1>(larva, pupa, mature, egg</k1>
<k1>disease vector</k1>
<k1>female)]/Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Viruses [03000]</k1>
<k1>[Arbovirus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]</k1>
<k1>multiple linear regression model</k1>
<k1>mathematical and computer techniques</k1>
<k1>blood</k1>
<k1>blood and lymphatics</k1>
<ab>Fecundity of mosquitoes can vary with many factors and can have a strong effect on population growth. This study reports the effects of body size, blood meal size, and age on the reproductive output of nulliparous Culex quinquefasciatus, a vector of arboviruses and other pathogens. Mated adult female mosquitoes from a colony were reared under standard conditions and fed on chickens at different ages post-eclosion. Blood meal size and wing length were recorded, as well as the number of eggs in the first-cycle egg raft. Each of these factors had a significant influence on fecundity considered in a simple regression context. Multiple regression analysis revealed a significant interaction effect between age and body size on fecundity. Up to 13 days of age, fecundity was positively correlated with body size, but in mosquitoes older than 13 days, this relationship was not significantly different from zero. These results are discussed in terms of the known physiology of this and other species.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV201000083582</no>
<sn>1081-1710</sn>
<ad>McCann, Sean ; Simon Fraser Univ, Dept Biol Sci, 8888 Univ Dr, Burnaby, BC V5A 1S6, Canada</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3426</id>
<a1>Pettit,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Meng,Y. H.</a1>
<a1>Herald,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Knight,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Antineoplastic agents. 553. The Texas grasshopper Brachystola magna.</t1>
<jf>Journal of natural products</jf>
<jo>J.Nat.Prod.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1256</sp>
<op>1258</op>
<k1>VV600 Non-communicable Human Diseases and Injuries VV730 Pharmacology (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>antineoplastic agents</k1>
<k1>cell lines</k1>
<k1>crystals</k1>
<k1>leukaemia</k1>
<k1>neoplasms</k1>
<k1>blood cancer</k1>
<k1>Brachystola</k1>
<k1>Brachystola magna</k1>
<k1>cancers</k1>
<k1>cytotoxic</k1>
<k1>agents</k1>
<k1>leucaemia</k1>
<k1>leukemia</k1>
<k1>narciclasine</k1>
<k1>pancratistatin</k1>
<k1>ungeremine</k1>
<ab>Bioassay (P388 lymphocytic leukaemia cell line and human cancer cell lines) guided separation of an extract prepared from the previously chemically uninvestigated Texas grasshopper Brachystola magna led to isolation of the cancer cell growth inhibitory pancratistatin, narciclasine, and ungeremine. Pancratistatin was first isolated from the bulbs of Hymenocallis littoralis, and the original crystal structure was deduced by X-ray analysis of a monomethyl ether derivative. In the present study pancratistatin was isolated from an extract of B. magna, which led to the X-ray crystal structure of this anticancer drug. Since these isoquinoline derivatives are previously known only as constituents of amaryllidaceous plants, some of the interesting implications of their rediscovery in the grasshopper B. magna that does not appear to utilize amaryllis family plants were discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Acrididae; Orthoptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; eukaryotes; NR: 21 notes and ref.</no>
<pb>American Chemical Society</pb>
<pp>Washington USA</pp>
<sn>0163-3864</sn>
<ad>Cancer Research Institute, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ 85287-2404, USA.; bpettit@asu.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053166080</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://pubs.acs.org/journals/jnprdf/index.html</lk>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3414</id>
<a1>Rios,L. M. V.</a1>
<a1>Sheu,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Maruniak,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Seino,K.</a1>
<a1>Zaretsky,H.</a1>
<a1>Long,M. T.</a1>
<t1>Environmental risk factors associated with West Nile virus clinical disease in Florida horses.</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>357</sp>
<op>366</op>
<k1>LL821 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Animals (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>disease prevalence</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>risk factors</k1>
<k1>horses</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The objective of this study was to examine the extrinsic risk factors of West Nile virus (WNV) clinical disease in Florida horses as established from confirmed and negative horses tested within the state from 2001 to 2003. An Arboviral Case Information Form (ACF) was submitted by a referring veterinarian at the time of testing to the Florida Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services on every horse suspected of a viral encephalitis in Florida. A follow-up survey that focused on arbovirus prevention and farm ecology was created and mailed to the owner of each tested horse. Data from the follow-up survey indicated peak WNV prevalence in the late summer months in Florida. Quarter horses were the most commonly affected breed. The WNV vaccine was highly protective and natural water on the property also had a protective association. Factors that increased the risk of WNV to horses were the use of fans and a stable construction of solid wood or cement. Some risk indicators were dead birds on the property and other ill animals on the property. Data from this retrospective study have helped identify factors associated with WNV transmission in equines in Florida. Horses that have not been vaccinated and show clinical signs of arboviral infection from June to November should be tested for WNV. Horses that have been vaccinated and show clinical signs should be tested when the vaccination was administered within 1 month or greater than 6 months prior to the onset of clinical symptoms associated with WN infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North&lt;br&gt;   America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southeastern States of USA; Equus; Equidae; Perissodactyla;&lt;br&gt;   mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals; ungulates; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   RNA viruses; viruses; NR: 37 ref.</no>
<pb>Blackwell Publishing</pb>
<pp>Oxford UK</pp>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.; bug_lady8@yahoo.com</ad>
<an>CABI:20093343083</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/loi/mve</lk>
<do>10.1111/j.1365-2915.2009.00821.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3435</id>
<a1>Rutledge,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Stark,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>West Nile virus infection rates in Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae) do not reflect transmission rates in Florida.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>258</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>We describe the first documented field transmission of West Nile (WN) virus by a North American mosquito. WN was first detected in northern Florida, USA in 2001. An intensive mosquito trapping and surveillance programme was conducted in this region for four nights to assess mosquito transmission of WN. Four mosquito traps, each with a single sentinel chicken, were placed at five different locations on each of four nights. A total of 11 948 mosquitoes was collected, and 14 mosquito pools were found to contain WN, giving a minimum infection rate between 1.08 and 7.54 per 1000. Only one of the 80 sentinel chickens seroconverted to WN, demonstrating a single mosquito transmission event during the study and a mosquito transmission rate of between 0.8 and 1 per 1000. Culex nigripalpus was responsible for WN transmission to the sentinel chicken, although both C. nigripalpus and C. quinquefasciatus were found infected with WN. Mosquito transmission rates are reported in this study for the first time for a WN outbreak. This information is essential to determine risk of human and animal infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Culex; Culicidae; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense&lt;br&gt;   ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America;&lt;br&gt;   Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; NR: 20 ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20033109610</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3256</id>
<a1>Scott,Thomas W.</a1>
<a1>Naksathit,Amara</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Kittayapong,Pattamaporn</a1>
<a1>Edman,John D.</a1>
<t1>A fitness advantage for Aedes aegypti and the viruses it transmits when females feed only on human blood</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>1997</fd>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>235</sp>
<op>239</op>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Reproductive System (Reproduction)</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>16501, Reproductive system - General and methods</k1>
<k1>36001, Medical and clinical microbiology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>37057, Public health: disease vectors - General</k1>
<k1>64072, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: general</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Aedes aegypti]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human]</k1>
<k1>SUCROSE</k1>
<k1>57-50-1</k1>
<ab>Literature on arthropod-borne diseases has traditionally supported the notion that mosquito vectors maintain a feeding duality that includes vertebrate blood meals for egg development and sugar meals from plants for the synthesis of Right and survival energy reserves. Aedes aegypti was found to deviate from that feeding pattern by obtaining a reproductive advantage when feeding only on human blood. Female mosquitoes fed human blood alone had a greater net replacement rate and intrinsic rate of growth during all phases of their reproductive life than conspecifics fed human blood plus sucrose. Feeding frequently on human hosts during each gonotrophic cycle is necessary to avoid death due to starvation and increases exponentially the spread of Ae. aegypti-borne disease. Our results help explain why Ae. aegypti is such an unusually efficient vector of human disease; frequent biting of humans results in a high reproductive rate for vectors as well as the viruses they transmit.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199799744283</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Scott, Thomas W. ; Dep. Entomol., Univ. Calif., Davis, CA 95616, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2213</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Reproductive phase locking of mosquito populations in response to rainfall frequency</t1>
<jf>PloS one</jf>
<jo>PLoS One</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Mar 28</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>e331</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Climate</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Culicidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Global Warming</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Population Dynamics</k1>
<k1>Rain</k1>
<k1>Reproduction/physiology</k1>
<ab>The frequency of moderate to heavy rainfall events is projected to change in response to global warming. Here we show that these hydrologic changes may have a profound effect on mosquito population dynamics and rates of mosquito-borne disease transmission. We develop a simple model, which treats the mosquito reproductive cycle as a phase oscillator that responds to rainfall frequency forcing. This model reproduces observed mosquito population dynamics and indicates that mosquito-borne disease transmission can be sensitive to rainfall frequency. These findings indicate that changes to the hydrologic cycle, in particular the frequency of moderate to heavy rainfall events, could have a profound effect on the transmission rates of some mosquito-borne diseases.</ab>
<no>JID: 101285081; OID: NLM: PMC1824708; GN: NLM: Original DateCompleted: 20070726; 2006/08/07 [received]; 2007/03/06 [accepted]; 2007/03/28 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1932-6203; 1932-6203</sn>
<ad>College of Oceanic and Atmospheric Sciences, Oregon State University, Corvallis, Oregon, United States of America. jshaman@coas.oregonstate.edu.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17396162</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1371/journal.pone.0000331</do>
<wp>20070328</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17396162</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1824708</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3424</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Achieving operational hydrologic monitoring of mosquitoborne disease.</t1>
<jf>Emerging Infectious Diseases</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1343</sp>
<op>1350</op>
<k1>PP500 Meteorology and Climate VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) ZZ332 Animal Ecology</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>rain</k1>
<k1>reviews</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>West Nile fever</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>rainfall</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Mosquitoes and mosquitoborne disease transmission are sensitive to hydrologic variability. If local hydrologic conditions can be monitored or modelled at the scales at which these conditions affect the population dynamics of vector mosquitoes and the diseases they transmit, a means for monitoring or modelling mosquito populations and mosquitoborne disease transmission may be realized. We review how hydrologic conditions have been associated with mosquito abundances and mosquitoborne disease transmission and discuss the advantages of different measures of hydrologic variability. We propose that the useful application of any measure of hydrologic conditions requires additional consideration of the scales for both the hydrologic measurement and the vector control interventions that will be used to mitigate an outbreak of vector-borne disease. Our efforts to establish operational monitoring of St. Louis encephalitis virus and West Nile virus transmission in Florida are also reviewed.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 40 ref.</no>
<pb>National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</pb>
<pp>Atlanta USA</pp>
<sn>1080-6040</sn>
<ad>College of Oceanic and Atmospheric Sciences, Oregon State University, 104 Admin Building, Corvallis, OR 97331, USA.; jshaman@coas.oregonstate.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053170620</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3432</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,M.</a1>
<t1>The spatial-temporal distribution of drought, wetting, and human cases of St. Louis encephalitis in Southcentral Florida.</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>251</sp>
<op>261</op>
<k1>PP800 Natural Disasters VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV500 Human Health and the Environment</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>drought</k1>
<k1>epidemiology</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>risk factors</k1>
<k1>spatial distribution</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>wetting</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>temporal distribution</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Using a dynamic hydrology model, we simulated land surface wetness conditions at 42 sites in 28 counties in southcentral Florida, USA from 1990 to 1998 and compared these simulations with the incidence of human cases of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) within these counties. Within counties, drought four months prior and wetting one-half month prior were significantly associated with human cases of SLE. Simulated land surface wetness conditions resolved transmission loci in both space and time, and May drought was significantly associated with the subsequent occurrence of human SLE cases. These findings are consistent with previous results associating simulated land surface wetness conditions with the transmission of SLE virus as measured in sentinel chickens, and support our working hypothesis that springtime drought facilitates SLE virus amplification in mosquito and wild bird populations.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 16 ref.</no>
<pb>American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</pb>
<pp>Northbrook USA</pp>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA.; jshaman@fas.harvard.edu; JFDA@mail.ifas. ufl.edu; marc@ldeo.columbia.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20043169646</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3434</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,M.</a1>
<t1>St. Louis encephalitis virus in wild birds during the 1990 South Florida epidemic: the importance of drought, wetting conditions, and the emergence of Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae) to arboviral amplification and transmission.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>547</sp>
<op>554</op>
<k1>PP500 Meteorology and Climate VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) YY700 Pathogens, Parasites and Infectious Diseases (Wild Animals) (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>antibodies</k1>
<k1>autumn</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>drought</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>serological surveys</k1>
<k1>seroprevalence</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>summer</k1>
<k1>wild birds</k1>
<k1>zoonoses</k1>
<k1>birds</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>fall</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>seroepidemiology</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>zoonotic</k1>
<k1>infections</k1>
<ab>We analysed the prevalence of haemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibodies to St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) virus in wild birds during the 1990 SLE epidemic in Indian River County, Florida, USA. The initial presence of SLE HI antibody was associated significantly with modelled drought 15 weeks prior, wetting conditions one week prior, and the emergence of the Florida SLE virus vector, Culex nigripalpus, 5 weeks prior. Three factors conspired to create the 1990 epidemic: (1) a large population of susceptible wild birds; (2) severe springtime drought, which facilitated amplification of the SLE virus among the C. nigripalpus and a portion of the wild bird population; and (3) continued rainfall and wetting of the land surface in the summer and early fall, which sustained a large, host-seeking C. nigripalpus population. The continued biting and reproductive activity of C. nigripalpus maintained epizootic transmission throughout the summer and early fall in Indian River County. The high level of SLE virus amplification resulted in spillover transmission to humans. We hypothesize that without the continued reproductive activity of the vector mosquito, brought about by excessive summer and fall wetness, the unprecedented SLE virus amplification and consequent transmission to humans would not have been realized in 1990.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; vertebrates; Chordata; Culex; Culicidae; Homo; Hominidae;&lt;br&gt;   Primates; mammals; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 21 ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences, Columbia University, Palisades, NY 10964, USA.; jshaman@ldeo.columbia.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20033158071</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3439</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Drought-induced amplification of Saint Louis encephalitis virus, Florida.</t1>
<jf>Emerging Infectious Diseases</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>575</sp>
<op>580</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) VV500 Human Health and the Environment</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>drought</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>mosquito-borne diseases</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>wild birds</k1>
<k1>birds</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>We used a dynamic hydrology model to simulate water table depth (WTD) and quantify the relationship between Saint Louis encephalitis virus (SLEV) transmission and hydrological conditions in Indian River County, Florida, USA, during 1986-91, a period with an SLEV epidemic. Virus transmission followed periods of modelled drought (specifically low WTDs 12 to 17 weeks before virus transmission, followed by a rising of the water table 1 to 2 weeks before virus transmission). Further evidence from collections of Culex nigripalpus (the major mosquito vector of SLEV in Florida) suggests that during extended spring droughts, vector mosquitoes and nestling, juvenile, and adult wild birds congregate in selected refuges, facilitating epizootic amplification of SLEV. When the drought ends and habitat availability increases, the SLEV-infected C. nigripalpus and wild birds disperse, initiating an SLEV transmission cycle. These findings demonstrate a mechanism by which drought facilitates the amplification of SLEV and its subsequent transmission to humans.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; vertebrates; Chordata; Culex; Culicidae; Homo; Hominidae;&lt;br&gt;   Primates; mammals; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 26 ref.</no>
<pb>National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</pb>
<pp>Atlanta USA</pp>
<sn>1080-6040</sn>
<ad>Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory, Columbia University, Oceanography, Room 103, Route 9W, Palisades, New York, NY 10964, USA.; jshaman@ldeo.columbia.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20023086888</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3431</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,M.</a1>
<a1>Zebiak,S.</a1>
<a1>Cane,M.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal forecast of St. Louis encephalitis virus transmission, Florida.</t1>
<jf>Emerging Infectious Diseases</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>802</sp>
<op>809</op>
<k1>PP500 Meteorology and Climate VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) ZZ900 Techniques and Methodology</k1>
<k1>climate</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>forecasting</k1>
<k1>models</k1>
<k1>prediction</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>weather</k1>
<k1>weather forecasting</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Disease transmission forecasts can help minimize human and domestic animal health risks by indicating where disease control and prevention efforts should be focused. For disease systems in which weather-related variables affect pathogen proliferation, dispersal, or transmission, the potential for disease forecasting exists. We present a seasonal forecast of St. Louis encephalitis virus transmission in Indian River County, Florida, USA. We derive an empiric relationship between modelled land surface wetness and levels of SLEV transmission in humans. We then use these data to forecast SLEV transmission with a seasonal lead. Forecast skill is demonstrated, and a real-time seasonal forecast of epidemic SLEV transmission is presented. This study demonstrates how weather and climate forecast skill-verification analyses may be applied to test the predictability of an empiric disease forecast model.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   RNA viruses; viruses; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; USA; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries;&lt;br&gt;   Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 16 ref.</no>
<pb>National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</pb>
<pp>Atlanta USA</pp>
<sn>1080-6040</sn>
<ad>Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Harvard University, 207 Hoffman Laboratories, 20 Oxford Street, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA.; jshaman@fas.harvard.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20043078997</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2331</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Komar,N.</a1>
<t1>Hydrologic Conditions Describe West Nile Virus Risk in Colorado</t1>
<jf>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Environ.Res.Public Health</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>494</sp>
<op>508</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Abundance</k1>
<k1>Aquatic insects</k1>
<k1>Disease transmission</k1>
<k1>Drought</k1>
<k1>Droughts</k1>
<k1>Hosts</k1>
<k1>Human Diseases</k1>
<k1>Hydrologic Models</k1>
<k1>Hydrology</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Models</k1>
<k1>Mosaics</k1>
<k1>Mountains</k1>
<k1>Population dynamics</k1>
<k1>Public Health</k1>
<k1>Risk</k1>
<k1>Variability</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Culex tarsalis</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Colorado</k1>
<ab>We examine the relationship between hydrologic variability and the incidence of human disease associated with West Nile virus (WNV; family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus) infection (hereafter termed &amp;quot;human WN cases&amp;quot;) in Colorado from 2002 to 2007. We find that local hydrologic conditions, as simulated by the Mosaic hydrology model, are associated with differences in human WN cases. In Colorado&amp;#39;s eastern plains, wetter spring conditions and drier summer conditions predict human WN cases. In Colorado&amp;#39;s western mountains, drier spring and summer conditions weakly predict human WN cases. These findings support two working hypotheses: (1) wet spring conditions increase the abundance of Culex tarsalis vectors in the plains, and (2) dry summer conditions, and respondent irrigational practices during such droughts, favor Cx. pipiens and Cx. tarsalis abundance throughout Colorado. Both of these processes potentially increase the local vector-to-host ratio, favoring WNV amplification among competent avian hosts and bridging to humans.</ab>
<no>TR: CS1022375</no>
<sn>1660-4601</sn>
<an>12658881</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Q5 01524 Public health, medicines, dangerous organisms; Q1 01484 Species interactions: parasites and diseases; V 22400 Human Diseases; Z 05350 Medical, Veterinary, and Agricultural Entomology; AQ 00008 Effects of Pollution</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts; Sustainability Science Abstracts; Risk Abstracts; ASFA 1: Biological Sciences &amp; Living Resources; ASFA 3: Aquatic Pollution &amp; Environmental Quality; Aqualine Abstracts</sf>
<do>10.3390/ijerph7020494</do>
<db>Environmental Sciences and Pollution Mgmt</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2338</id>
<a1>Shaman,J.</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,M.</a1>
<t1>Drought-Induced Amplification and Epidemic Transmission of West Nile Virus in Southern Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>134</sp>
<op>141</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Disease transmission</k1>
<k1>Droughts</k1>
<k1>Epidemics</k1>
<k1>Encephalitis</k1>
<k1>Epizootics</k1>
<k1>Vectors</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<ab>We show that the spatial-temporal variability of human West Nile (WN) cases and the transmission of West Nile virus (WNV) to sentinel chickens are associated with the spatial-temporal variability of drought and wetting in southern Florida. Land surface wetness conditions at 52 sites in 31 counties in southern Florida for 2001-2003 were simulated and compared with the occurrence of human WN cases and the transmission of WNV to sentinel chickens within these counties. Both WNV transmission to sentinel chickens and the occurrence of human WN cases were associated with drought 2-6 mo prior and land surface wetting 0.5-1.5 mo prior. These dynamics are similar to the amplification and transmission patterns found in southern Florida for the closely related St. Louis encephalitis virus. Drought brings avian hosts and vector mosquitoes into close contact and facilitates the epizootic cycling and amplification of the arboviruses within these populations. Southern Florida has not recorded a severe, widespread drought since the introduction of WNV into the state in 2001. Our results indicate that widespread drought in the spring followed by wetting during summer greatly increase the probability of a WNV epidemic in southern Florida.</ab>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Human WN cases; Springtime drought; Object Geographic Terms: USA, Florida; Object Statistical Terms: Average; Mean&lt;br&gt;IF: Figure 2. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00015%2Fi0022-2585-042-02-0134%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-042-02-0134-f02.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=c401fd09b2ca1c4913c027def0543832&lt;br&gt;C1: Figure 2. Maps of mean local WTD as simulated by the TBH model at 52 sites in southern Florida for May 2001, 2002, and 2003. Springtime drought, loosely represented by the May average, is not widespread in the years since introduction of WNV into southern Florida. 2003 was a particularly wet year&lt;br&gt;M1: Map&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Springtime drought; Object Statistical Terms; Mean; Average&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 1. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00015%2Fi0022-2585-042-02-0134%2Fobj%2Fi0022-2585-042-02-0134-t01.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=c566ae2727f20ff2af29cd5bfad36db0&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 1. Reported human WN cases by month of onset in southern Florida for 31 counties in southern Florida, 2001a2003&lt;br&gt;M1: Table&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Human WN cases; Object Geographic Terms; USA, Florida</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962</ad>
<an>6180509</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05206 Medical &amp; veterinary entomology; V 22143 Epizootiology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; 1B; Virology &amp; AIDS Abstracts; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<lk>http://journals.allenpress.com/jrnlserv/?request=get-abstract&amp;issn=0022-2585&amp;volume=42&amp;page=134</lk>
<do>10.1043/0022-2585(2005)042&lt;0134:DAAETO&gt;2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3208</id>
<a1>Shaman,Jeffrey</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Stieglitz,Marc</a1>
<a1>Zebiak,Stephen</a1>
<a1>Cane,Mark</a1>
<t1>An ensemble seasonal forecast of human cases of St. Louis encephalitis in Florida based on seasonal hydrologic forecasts</t1>
<jf>Climatic Change</jf>
<jo>Clim.Change</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>APR 2006</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>495</sp>
<op>511</op>
<k1>Nervous System (Neural Coordination)</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Climatology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>05500, Social biology and human ecology</k1>
<k1>07504, Ecology: environmental biology - Bioclimatology and biometeorology</k1>
<k1>20504, Nervous system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>20506, Nervous system - Pathology</k1>
<k1>33502, Virology - General and methods</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37052, Public health: epidemiology - Communicable diseases</k1>
<k1>37054, Public health: epidemiology - Organic diseases and neoplasms</k1>
<k1>37056, Public health: epidemiology - Miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[St. Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>St. Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>nervous system disease, viral disease</k1>
<k1>transmission, epidemiology</k1>
<ab>We present a method for the ensemble seasonal prediction of human St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) incidence and SLE virus transmission in Florida. We combine empirical relationships between modeled land surface wetness and the incidence of human clinical cases of SLE and modeled land surface wetness and the occurrence of SLE virus transmission throughout south Florida with a previously developed method for generating ensemble, seasonal hydrologic forecasts. Retrospective seasonal forecasts of human SLE incidence are made for Indian River County, Florida, and forecast skill is demonstrated for 2-4 months. A sample seasonal forecast of human SLE incidence is presented. This study establishes the skill of a potential component of an operational SLE forecast system in south Florida, one that provides information well in advance of transmission and may enable early interventions that reduce transmission. Future development of this method and operational application of these forecasts are discussed. The methodology also will be applied to West Nile virus monitoring and forecasting.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200600465372; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0165-0009</sn>
<ad>Shaman, Jeffrey ; Oregon State Univ, Coll Ocean and Atmospher Sci, 104 COAS Adm Bldg, Corvallis, OR 97331 USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2327</id>
<a1>Shroyer,DA</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<t1>Accumulation and persistence of males in resting adult populations of Culex nigripalpus</t1>
<jf>Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<fd>19-23 Mar 1995</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 951 0400); Availability: American Mosquito Control Association, 2200 E. Prien Lake Road, PO Box 5416, Lake Charles, LA 70606-5416&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Portland, OR (USA)</ed>
<ad>Indian River Mosquito Control Dist., Vero Beach, FL, USA; American Mosquito Control Association</ad>
<an>3160405</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 1000 Animal and Plant Science; U 2000 Biology</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2224</id>
<a1>Spielman,A.</a1>
<a1>Andreadis,T. G.</a1>
<a1>Apperson,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Cornel,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Fish,D.</a1>
<a1>Harrington,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Kiszewski,A. E.</a1>
<a1>Lampman,R.</a1>
<a1>Lanzaro,G. C.</a1>
<a1>Matuschka,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Munstermann,L. E.</a1>
<a1>Nasci,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Norris,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Novak,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Pollack,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Reisen,W. K.</a1>
<a1>Reiter,P.</a1>
<a1>Savage,H. M.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Wesson,D. M.</a1>
<t1>Outbreak of West Nile virus in North America</t1>
<jf>Science (New York, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov 26</fd>
<vo>306</vo>
<is>5701</is>
<sp>1473</sp>
<op>5; author reply 1473-5</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Culex/genetics/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Disease Outbreaks</k1>
<k1>Europe/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Insect Vectors/genetics/physiology/virology</k1>
<k1>North America/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>West Nile Fever/epidemiology/transmission/virology</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus/pathogenicity</k1>
<no>LR: 20070319; JID: 0404511; CON: Science. 2004 Mar 5;303(5663):1535-8. PMID: 15001783; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1095-9203; 0036-8075</sn>
<an>PMID: 15567836; 306/5701/1473c [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comment; Letter; IM</sf>
<do>10.1126/science.306.5701.1473c</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15567836</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2255</id>
<a1>Van Handel,E.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Nectar-feeding habits of Aedes taeniorhynchus</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>270</sp>
<op>273</op>
<k1>Aedes/analysis/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Flight, Animal</k1>
<k1>Fructose/analysis</k1>
<k1>Glucose/analysis</k1>
<k1>Glycogen/analysis</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<ab>Aedes taeniorhynchus were collected on the wing at several times during the day and night, in Indian River and Brevard County, Florida. Nonblooded females were individually analyzed for fructose and glycogen. Fructose content of mosquitoes collected early in the morning and held without food during the day diminished to approximately the same level as in mosquitoes collected late in the afternoon. However, fructose content of mosquitoes collected before sunset and held without food overnight diminished greatly, whereas that of mosquitoes collected in the morning always exceeded that of evening collections. Maximum fructose content occurred within one or 2 hours after sunset. Apparently, these mosquitoes take little or no nectar during the day, and feed soon after the onset of darkness.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 20983/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 8511299; 30237-26-4 (Fructose); 50-99-7 (Glucose); 9005-79-2 (Glycogen); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>IFAS-University of Florida, Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, Vero Beach 32962.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2370536</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2370536</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3268</id>
<a1>Van Handel,E.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Scott,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Clark,G. G.</a1>
<a1>Reiter,P.</a1>
<a1>Lynn,H. C.</a1>
<t1>Plant-sugar, glycogen, and lipid assay of Aedes aegypti collected in urban Puerto Rico and rural Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>2 PART 1</is>
<sp>149</sp>
<op>153</op>
<k1>Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10066, Biochemistry studies - Lipids</k1>
<k1>10068, Biochemistry studies - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Aedes aegypti]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae [03615]</k1>
<k1>[Flaviviridae]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human]</k1>
<k1>GLYCOGEN</k1>
<k1>9005-79-2</k1>
<ab>Between 50 and 75% of male and female Aedes aegypti collected at a rural tire dump near Veto Beach, FL, in March 1992, and males collected inside inhabited houses in San Juan, PR, in October 1991 and January 1992, were fructose positive. In contrast, only 5 of 231 females in the San Juan collections contained fructose. Gravid females in January 1992 contained 3 times more lipid than those in October 1991.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497402057</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Van Handel, E. ; Day, J. F. ; Lynn, H. C.; Inst. Food and Agric. Sciences, Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., 200 9th Street S.E., Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3275</id>
<a1>Van Handel,E.</a1>
<a1>Scott,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Reiter,P.</a1>
<t1>Sugar feeding habits of Aedes aegypti females from San Juan, Puerto Rico</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>311</sp>
<k1>Behavior</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>07003, Behavioral biology - Animal behavior</k1>
<k1>10068, Biochemistry studies - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>13214, Nutrition - General dietary studies</k1>
<k1>13220, Nutrition - Carbohydrates</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>62800, Animal distribution -</k1>
<k1>64078, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: pathology</k1>
<k1>Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Aedes aegypti]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Togaviridae [03616]</k1>
<k1>[Togaviridae]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199344020430; CT: 58th Annual Meeting of the American Mosquito Control Association, Corpus Christi, Texas, USA, March 17, 1992. J AM MOSQ CONTROL ASSOC</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Van Handel, E. ; Univ. Fla., Vero Beach, Fla, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3415</id>
<a1>Vitek,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Richards,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Mores,C. N.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<t1>Arbovirus transmission by Culex nigripalpus in Florida, 2005.</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>483</sp>
<op>493</op>
<k1>LL822 Protozoan, Helminth, Mollusc and Arthropod Parasites of Animals (NEW March 2000) LL823 Veterinary Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) HH600 Host Resistance and Immunity</k1>
<k1>arboviruses</k1>
<k1>disease transmission</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>encephalitis</k1>
<k1>poultry</k1>
<k1>risk</k1>
<k1>seroconversion</k1>
<k1>transmission</k1>
<k1>traps</k1>
<k1>vectors</k1>
<k1>Culex</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Flaviviridae</k1>
<k1>Flavivirus</k1>
<k1>fowls</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>viruses</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>chickens</k1>
<k1>domesticated birds</k1>
<k1>encephalomyelitis</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>United</k1>
<k1>States of America</k1>
<ab>Understanding the transmission patterns of West Nile and St. Louis encephalitis viruses (family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus, WNV and SLEV) could result in an increased ability to predict transmission risk to humans. To examine transmission patterns between vector and host, we trapped mosquitoes in three Florida counties from June to November 2005 by using chicken-baited lard can mosquito traps. These traps were used to monitor for presence of WNV and SLEV in mosquitoes and subsequent transmission of these viruses to chickens. In total, 166,615 female mosquitoes were sorted into 4,009 pools based on species and bloodfed status, and they were tested for presence of WNV and SLEV. Sera from 209 chickens were tested for WNV and SLEV antibodies. We detected eight WNV-positive Culex nigripalpus Theobald mosquito pools; SLEV was not detected in any pools. Six positive pools were collected in August and September from Duval County, one pool in September from Manatee County, and one pool in November from Indian River County. Of the eight chickens potentially exposed to WNV, antibodies were detected in only one chicken, indicating a low rate of transmission relative to the observed mosquito infection rates. Low virus transmission rates relative to infection rates would suggest that using sentinel chicken seroconversion data as a means of arbovirus surveillance may underestimate the prevalence of WNV in the mosquito population. However, using mosquito infection rates may overestimate the risk of arboviral transmission. A variety of factors might account for the observed low level of transmission including a lack of viral dissemination in mosquito vectors.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Gallus gallus; Gallus; Phasianidae; Galliformes; birds; vertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   Chordata; animals; poultry; eukaryotes; Culicidae; Diptera; insects;&lt;br&gt;   Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; Culex; positive-sense ssRNA&lt;br&gt;   viruses; ssRNA viruses; RNA viruses; viruses; Flaviviridae; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals;&lt;br&gt;   Flavivirus; NR: many ref.</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>Lanham USA</pp>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Florida Medical Entomology Laboratory, University of Florida, Institute of Food and Agricultural Science, 200 9th Street SE, Vero Beach, FL 32962, USA.; cjvitek@uss.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20093326926</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://docserver.ingentaconnect.com/deliver/connect/esa/00222585/v45n3/s 22.pdf?expires=1258070897&amp;id=0000&amp;titleid=10266&amp;checksum=E594D968212902B 54EBBCD71C6B25E17</lk>
<do>10.1603/0022-2585(2008)45[483:ATBCNI]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3418</id>
<a1>Vlach,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Hall,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Curtis,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Hribar,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Fussell,E. M.</a1>
<t1>Interisland dispersal of the black salt marsh mosquito, Ochlerotatus taeniorhynchus (Diptera: Culicidae) in the Florida keys.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>615</sp>
<op>621</op>
<k1>PP710 Biological Resources (Animal) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>dispersal</k1>
<k1>zoogeography</k1>
<k1>Aedes taeniorhynchus</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>animal geography</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>Ochlerotatus</k1>
<k1>taeniorhynchus</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Mark-release-recapture experiments were conducted in 2001 and 2002 to determine whether Ochlerotatus taeniorhynchus, black salt marsh mosquitoes, were dispersing from uninhabited islands in the Key Deer National Wildlife Refuge to inhabited islands within Monroe County, Florida. An estimated 1,658,000 mosquitoes were marked during 2001, and an estimated 300,000 mosquitoes were marked during 2002. Recapture rates were 0.0061% and 0.0117%, respectively. Oc. taeniorhynchus disperse from uninhabited islands to other uninhabited islands and also to inhabited islands, namely, Big Pine Key and No Name Key.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA;&lt;br&gt;   North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; Culicidae; Aedes; NR: 33 ref.</no>
<pb>American Mosquito Control Association, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Mount Laurel USA</pp>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Florida Keys Mosquito Control District, 5224 College Road, Key West, FL 33040, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20073034501</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<do>10.2987/8756-971X(2006)22[615:IDOTBS]2.0.CO;2</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3269</id>
<a1>Vodkin,Michael H.</a1>
<a1>McLaughlin,Gerald L.</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan F.</a1>
<a1>Shope,Robert E.</a1>
<a1>Novak,Robert J.</a1>
<t1>A rapid diagnostic assay for eastern equine encephalomyelitis viral RNA</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>1993</fd>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>772</sp>
<op>776</op>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Enzymology (Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics)</k1>
<k1>Epidemiology (Population Studies)</k1>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Molecular Genetics (Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics)</k1>
<k1>Neurology (Human Medicine, Medical Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Public Health (Allied Medical Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Vector Biology</k1>
<k1>Veterinary Medicine (Medical Sciences)</k1>
<k1>10062, Biochemistry studies - Nucleic acids, purines and pyrimidines</k1>
<k1>10064, Biochemistry studies - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>10300, Replication, transcription, translation</k1>
<k1>10804, Enzymes - Methods</k1>
<k1>12508, Pathology - Inflammation and inflammatory disease</k1>
<k1>12512, Pathology - Therapy</k1>
<k1>20506, Nervous system - Pathology</k1>
<k1>36006, Medical and clinical microbiology - Virology</k1>
<k1>37001, Public health - General and miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>37052, Public health: epidemiology - Communicable diseases</k1>
<k1>37058, Public health: disease vectors - Animate</k1>
<k1>37400, Public health: microbiology - Public health microbiology</k1>
<k1>38006, Veterinary science - Microbiology</k1>
<k1>60012, Economic entomology - Animal pests</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Birds, Chordates, Nonhuman Vertebrates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Aves [85500]</k1>
<k1>[bird] [Aves]/Insecta, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Diptera [75314]</k1>
<k1>[Diptera]/Primates, Mammalia, Vertebrata, Chordata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Chordates, Humans, Mammals, Primates, Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Hominidae [86215]</k1>
<k1>[human]/Positive Sense ssRNA Viruses, Viruses, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Microorganisms, Positive Sense Single-Stranded RNA Viruses, Viruses</k1>
<k1>Togaviridae [03616]</k1>
<k1>[Togaviridae]</k1>
<ab>Eastern equine encephalomyelitis virus (EEEV) has been a low-frequency, but serious human and veterinary health problem. Increased frequency of this mosquito-borne virus is anticipated as wetlands are maintained and re-established. Control of EEEV has depended on mosquito abatement in response to increasing frequency of EEEV in the environment. A coupled reverse transcription/polymerase chain reaction assay was designed to rapidly, sensitively, and specifically detect EEEV RNA. The assay successfully detected the viral RNA in a single-blind study of a set of field samples composed of either pooled mosquitoes or bird tissue. These results suggest that it would be practical to use this assay for deciding when and where to implement mosquito abatement.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497130968</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<ad>Vodkin, Michael H. ; Dep. Vet. Pathobiol., Purdue Univ., West Lafayette, IN 47907, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3241</id>
<a1>Wilkinson,Adam</a1>
<a1>Day,Jonathan</a1>
<a1>Bowater,Richard</a1>
<t1>Bacterial DNA ligases</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>June, 2001</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1241</sp>
<op>1248</op>
<k1>Enzymology (Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics)</k1>
<k1>Molecular Genetics (Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics)</k1>
<k1>03502, Genetics - General</k1>
<k1>10062, Biochemistry studies - Nucleic acids, purines and pyrimidines</k1>
<k1>10802, Enzymes - General and comparative studies: coenzymes</k1>
<k1>31000, Physiology and biochemistry of bacteria</k1>
<k1>31500, Genetics of bacteria and viruses</k1>
<k1>Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Bacteria, Eubacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Aerobic Helical or Vibrioid Gram-Negatives [06210]</k1>
<k1>[Campylobacter jejuni]/Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Archaeobacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Archaeobacteria [09400]</k1>
<k1>[Archaeobacteria]/Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Bacteria [05000]</k1>
<k1>[Pseudoaltermonas haloplanktis] [bacteria]/Aerobic Chemolithotrophs and Similar Bacteria, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Chemolithotrophic Hydrogen Bacteria [08130]</k1>
<k1>[Aquifex aeolicus]/Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Endospore-forming Gram-Positives [07810]</k1>
<k1>[Bacillus stearothermophilus] [Bacillus subtilis]/Facultatively Anaerobic Gram-Negative Rods, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Enterobacteriaceae [06702]</k1>
<k1>[Escherichia coli]/Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Facultatively Anaerobic Gram-Negative Rods [06700]</k1>
<k1>[Zymomonas mobilis]/Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Gram-Negative Aerobic Rods and Cocci [06500]</k1>
<k1>[Rhodothermus marinus] [Thermus filiformis] [Thermus scotoductus] [Thermus species] [Thermus thermophilus]/Mycobacteria, Actinomycetes and Related Organisms, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Mycobacteriaceae [08881]</k1>
<k1>[Mycobacterium tuberculosis]/Gram-Negative Aerobic Rods and Cocci, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Neisseriaceae [06507]</k1>
<k1>[Neisseria meningitidis]/Facultatively Anaerobic Gram-Negative Rods, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Pasteurellaceae [06703]</k1>
<k1>[Haemophilus influenzae]/Gram-Negative Aerobic Rods and Cocci, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonadaceae [06508]</k1>
<k1>[Pseudomonas aeruginosa]/Facultatively Anaerobic Gram-Negative Rods, Eubacteria, Bacteria, Microorganisms</k1>
<k1>Vibrionaceae [06704]</k1>
<k1>[Vibrio cholerae]</k1>
<k1>ATP</k1>
<k1>56-65-5Q, 42530-29-0Q, 94587-45-8Q, 111839-44-2Q/DNA</k1>
<k1>(phosphodiester backbone)/DNA ligase</k1>
<k1>9015-85-4Q, 37259-52-2Q</k1>
<k1>(NAD-plus dependent)</k1>
<ab>DNA ligases join breaks in the phosphodiester backbone of DNA molecules and are used in many essential reactions within the cell. All DNA ligases follow the same reaction mechanism, but they may use either ATP or NAD+ as a cofactor. All Bacteria (eubacteria) contain NAD+-dependent DNA ligases, and the uniqueness of these enzymes to Bacteria makes them an attractive target for novel antibiotics. In addition to their NAD+-dependent enzymes, some Bacteria contain genes for putative ATP-dependent DNA ligases. The requirement for these different isozymes in Bacteria is unknown, but may be related to their utilization in different aspects of DNA metabolism. The putative ATP-dependent DNA ligases found in Bacteria are most closely related to proteins from Archaea and viruses. Phylogenetic analysis suggests that all NAD+-dependent DNA ligases are closely related, but the ATP-dependent enzymes have been acquired by Bacterial genomes on a number of separate occasions.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200100344563&lt;br&gt;ME: print</no>
<sn>0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Bowater, Richard; Molecular Biology Sector, School of Biological Sciences, University of East Anglia, Norwich, NR4 7TJ, UK; r.bowater@uea.ac.uk</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Letter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2326</id>
<a1>Zhang,JT</a1>
<a1>Day,JF</a1>
<a1>Lewis,A.</a1>
<a1>Scott,T.</a1>
<t1>Eastern equine encephalitis virus from small mammals in southern Florida</t1>
<jf>Diversity &#39;88-Entomological Society of America National Conference and Exhibition</jf>
<fd>4-8 Dec 1988</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 884 0712); Availability: Conference proceedings will not be published Poster Paper&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Louisville, KY (USA)</ed>
<ad>Florida Med. Entomol. Lab., 200 9th St. SE, Univ. Florida, Vero Beach, FL 32962; Entomological Society of America (ESA)</ad>
<an>2011041</an>
<cl>U 2000 BIOLOGY GENERAL</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3436</id>
<a1>Zyzak,M.</a1>
<a1>Loyless,T.</a1>
<a1>Cope,S.</a1>
<a1>Wooster,M.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal abundance of Culex nigripalpus Theobald and Culex salinarius Coquillett in north Florida, USA.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vector Ecology</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>155</sp>
<op>162</op>
<k1>VV210 Prion, Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Pathogens of Humans (NEW March 2000) VV230 Public Health Pests, Vectors and Intermediate Hosts (NEW March 2000) ZZ332 Animal Ecology</k1>
<k1>disease vectors</k1>
<k1>human diseases</k1>
<k1>seasonal variation</k1>
<k1>spring</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis</k1>
<k1>viral diseases</k1>
<k1>West Nile fever</k1>
<k1>winter</k1>
<k1>Culex nigripalpus</k1>
<k1>Culex salinarius</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>eastern equine encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>man</k1>
<k1>St Louis encephalitis virus</k1>
<k1>West Nile virus</k1>
<k1>mosquitoes</k1>
<k1>seasonal changes</k1>
<k1>seasonal fluctuations</k1>
<k1>viral infections</k1>
<ab>North Florida is a transition zone between widespread Culex nigripalpus populations to the south and focal Culex salinarius populations to the north. Culex nigripalpus is a vector of St. Louis encephalitis (SLE) and eastern equine encephalitis (EEE) viruses in south Florida, while C. salinarius is a suspected New World vector of West Nile (WN) virus. Abundant vector populations are often a prerequisite for epidemic and epizootic transmission of arboviruses. Extensive SLE transmission has never been reported from north Florida, but sporadic WN transmission was reported there during the summer of 2001. The disparate flavivirus transmission patterns observed in north and south Florida may be due, in part, to the local geographical and seasonal distribution of Culex vectors. Here we report that between May 1991 and April 1994, C. salinarius was most commonly observed during the winter and spring in northeast Florida (Duval County), whereas C. nigripalpus was most abundant during the summer and autumn. An unusually mild spring in 1991 allowed C. nigripalpus to reproduce early in the year, resulting in a summer population that emerged more than 8 weeks earlier than in 1992 and 1993. The 1991 C. nigripalpus population persisted through October, when SLE transmission was detected by sentinel chickens. Transmission of SLE was not detected in Duval County in 1992 or 1993. These data indicate that mild winter and spring conditions in north Florida may favour increased abundance and survival of C. nigripalpus in a region where this species is normally not abundant. A seasonal shift in population structure may increase the transmission risk of arboviruses for which C. nigripalpus is a competent vector, including SLE, WN, and EEE.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida&lt;br&gt;BD: Diptera; insects; Hexapoda; arthropods; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Culex; Culicidae; equine encephalomyelitis virus;&lt;br&gt;   Alphavirus; Togaviridae; positive-sense ssRNA viruses; ssRNA viruses;&lt;br&gt;   RNA viruses; viruses; Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   Chordata; Flavivirus; Flaviviridae; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 25 ref.</no>
<pb>Society for Vector Ecology</pb>
<pp>Corona USA</pp>
<sn>1081-1710</sn>
<ad>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, Department of Preventative Medicine and Biometrics, 4301 Jones Bridge Road, Bethesda, MD 20814, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20023118212</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
