
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3954</id>
<a1>Carlson,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Obryan,P. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>A Review of Current Salt-Marsh Management Issues in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>83</sp>
<op>88</op>
<ab>For the past decade, salt marsh management in Florida has been a central issue in attempts to reconcile mosquito control and natural resource interests. Progress has been made in trying to maintain effective mosquito control while protecting and enhancing salt marsh resources primarily due to: 1) efforts by the Florida Coordinating Council on Mosquito Control and its Subcommittee on Managed Marshes, which are committees comprised of agencies responsible for wetlands resources, those mandated to provide mosquito control, and research institutions; and 2) funding of research to investigate ecosystem effects of marsh management techniques. Research and management experience have demonstrated that Rotational Impoundment Management (RIM) and rotary ditching can provide ecologically sound source reduction benefits. Salt marsh ownership, management of state lands and mariculture remain controversial salt marsh management issues.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>A1991FG76800017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3953</id>
<a1>Carlson,D. B.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Bryan,P. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Florida&amp;#39;s salt-marsh management issues: 1991-98</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>186</sp>
<op>193</op>
<ab>During the 1990s, Florida has continued to make important strides in managing salt marshes for both mosquito control and natural resource enhancement. The political mechanism for this progress continues to be interagency cooperation through the Florida Coordinating Council on Mosquito Control and its Subcommittee on Managed Marshes (SOMM). Continuing management experience and research has helped refine the most environmentally. acceptable source reduction methods, which typically are Rotational Impoundment Management or Open Marsh Water Management. The development of regional marsh management plans for salt marshes within the Indian River Lagoon by the SOMM has helped direst the implementation of the best management practices for these marshes. Controversy occasionally occurs concerning that management technique is most appropriate for individual marshes. The most common disagreement is over the benefits of maintaining an impoundment in an &amp;quot;open&amp;quot; vs. &amp;quot;closed&amp;quot; condition, with the &amp;quot;closed&amp;quot; condition, allowing for summer mosquito control flooding or winter waterfowl management. New federal initiatives influencing salt-marsh management have included the Indian River Lagoon-National Estuary Program and the Pesticide Environmental Stewardship Program. A neu Florida initiative is the Florida Department of Environmental Protection&amp;#39;s Ecosystem Management Program with continuing involvement by the Surface Water Improvement and Management program. A developing mitigation banking program has the potential to benefit mal-sh management but mosquito control interests may suffer if not handled properly. Larvicides remain as an important salt-marsh integrated pest management tool with the greatest acreage being treated with temephos. followed by Bacillus thuringensis israelensis and methoprene. However, over the past 14 years, use of biorational larvicides has increased greatly.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000081219900011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3952</id>
<a1>Lounibos,L. P.</a1>
<a1>Suarez,S.</a1>
<a1>Menendez,Z.</a1>
<a1>Nishimura,N.</a1>
<a1>Escher,R. L.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Does temperature affect the outcome of larval competition between Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus?</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vector Ecology</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>86</sp>
<op>95</op>
<ab>The superior larval competitive ability of Aedes albopictus has been proposed to explain the recent displacement of Aedes aegypti by the former species in parts of the southeastern U.S. Ae. aegypti persists, however, in sympatry with Ae. albopictus in urban areas of southern Louisiana, Florida, and Texas, and the impact of larval competition between these species has not been investigated at higher temperatures that may be characteristic of these urban environments. We compared growth and survivorship of the two species at controlled temperatures of 24degrees and 30degreesC in water-containing tires under conditions of intra- and interspecific competition and with or without leaf litter. When other variables were controlled statistically, the estimated finite rate of increase (lambda&amp;#39;) was significantly higher for both species at the higher temperature, and the proportional increases in lambda&amp;#39; did not differ between species. Therefore, our experiment predicts that by itself, temperatures between 24degrees and 30degreesC would not alter the outcome of larval competition. Overall, response measures of Ae. albopictus were more sensitive than those of Ae. aegypti to the litter and species/density variables, although the development of Ae. aegypti females was uniquely retarded by a high density of its own species.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1081-1710</sn>
<an>000176627700012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3955</id>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Terrestrial Arthropods of Northwest Florida Salt Marshes - Hymenoptera (Insecta)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>70</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>90</sp>
<op>97</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1987G518000010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3958</id>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>The Biogeography of Herbivorous Arthropods - Species Accrual on Tropical Crops</t1>
<jf>Ecological Entomology</jf>
<jo>Ecol.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>305</sp>
<op>313</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0307-6946</sn>
<an>A1983RB55400007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3961</id>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Patterns of Abundance, Distribution, and Alary Polymorphism among the Salt-Marsh Delphacidae (Homoptera, Fulgoroidea) of Northwest Florida</t1>
<jf>Ecological Entomology</jf>
<jo>Ecol.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>285</sp>
<op>291</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0307-6946</sn>
<an>A1981MA91800006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3960</id>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Terrestrial Arthropods of Northwest Florida Salt Marshes - Coleoptera</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>405</sp>
<op>411</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1981MM24100004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3962</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Correction</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>972</sp>
<op>972</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1979HT85900040</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3956</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Terrestrial Arthropods of Northwest Florida Salt Marshes - Diptera (Insecta)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>197</sp>
<op>205</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1986C464600025</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3957</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Terrestrial Arthropods of Northwest Florida Salt Marshes - Araneae and Pseudoscorpiones (Arachnida)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>497</sp>
<op>503</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1983SE70700012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3959</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Terrestrial Arthropods of Northwest Florida Salt Marshes - Hemiptera and Homoptera (Insecta)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>241</sp>
<op>248</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1982PE76900006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3963</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Mccoy,E. D.</a1>
<t1>Application of Island Biogeographic Theory to Pests of Cultivated Crops</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>577</sp>
<op>582</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1979HJ49900001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3951</id>
<a1>Rey,J. R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,S.</a1>
<a1>Suarez,S.</a1>
<a1>Menendez,Z.</a1>
<a1>Lounibos,L. P.</a1>
<a1>Byer,G.</a1>
<t1>Laboratory and field studies of Macrocyclops albidus (Crustacea : Copepoda) for biological control of mosquitoes in artificial containers in a subtropical environment</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vector Ecology</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>124</sp>
<op>134</op>
<ab>The cyclopoid copepod Macrocyclops albidus (Jurine) was tested as a potential biological control agent of mosquitoes in laboratory microcosms, in controlled field conditions, and in a 22-mo field experiment using discarded tires. The predator was highly efficient in controlling mosquitoes in all three settings, reaching close to 90% reduction in larval survival under field conditions and exceeding the recommended predation rates for effective mosquito control in laboratory experiments. The predator was most effective on 1-4-d-old larvae. Alternate food and habitat structure significantly influenced the predation rates on mosquito larvae. Once established, the copepod was able to maintain reproducing populations in the field for the duration of the experiments. However, the predator failed to establish populations at four of the experimental field sites. Two of the failures can be attributed to characteristics of the individual tires, such as leaching chemicals, whereas the other two were probably due to site-specific factors. This copepod species is a promising candidate for control of mosquito larvae because it is a widespread and highly effective predator that is capable of establishing and maintaining populations under a wide variety of field conditions. Additionally, M albidus is relatively easy to culture, maintain, and deliver to the target areas.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1081-1710</sn>
<an>000222528600015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3948</id>
<a1>Rey,Jorge R.</a1>
<a1>Nishimura,Naoya</a1>
<a1>Wagner,Billi</a1>
<a1>Braks,Marieta A. H.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,Sheila M.</a1>
<a1>Lounibos,L. Philip</a1>
<t1>Habitat segregation of mosquito arbovirus vectors in south Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1134</sp>
<op>1141</op>
<ab>Oviposition traps set in rural to urban environments in three south Florida counties were colonized predominantly by Culex quinquefasciatus Say (35.1%), Aedes albopictus (Skuse) (34.5%), Aedes aegypti (L.) (23.8%), and Culex nigripalpus Theobald (6.6%) during I yr of monthly sampling. Significant differences were detected among counties for abundances of Cx. quinquefasciatus and for percentage composition of that species and Ae. albopictus. Aerial images of habitats around each collection site were digitized, and coverages by each of 16 habitat variables were recorded. Abundances of Ae. aegypti were positively related to habitat variables associated with urbanization and negatively correlated to those reflecting rural characteristics. Multiple regression models of habitat selection explained similar proportions of variances in abundance of Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus, but signs of significant variables were opposite for these two species. No consistent trends of habitat associations were observed among counties for the two Culex spp. Co-occurrences of the four species in individual traps depended on container type (tub versus cup), and, for Aedes spp. with Culex spp., county. The results underscore the importance of scale in evaluating habitat selection and the utility of quantifiable habitat characteristics of intermediate scale to identify site characteristics favored by the arboviral vectors Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000241931200005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3947</id>
<a1>Rey,Jorge R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Meara,George F.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,Sheila A.</a1>
<a1>Cutwa-Francis,Michele M.</a1>
<t1>Factors affecting mosquito production from stormwater drains and catch basins in two Florida cities</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vector Ecology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>334</sp>
<op>343</op>
<ab>Mosquito production from drains and catch basins in the cities of Vero Beach and Key West, FL were monitored from May 2004 through August 2005. A total of 48,787 mosquitoes were captured during the study. Of these, over 99% belonged to two species, Culex nigripalpus Theobald (2,630) and Culex quinquefasciatus Say (45,946). Other species collected included Culex restuans Theobald, Culex salinarius Coquillett, Aedes aegypti (L.), Aedes albopictus (Skuse), and Uranotaenia lowii Theobald. Significantly greater numbers of Cx. nigripalpus were collected at Vero Beach than at Key West, but no significant differences in numbers of Cx. quinquefasciatus and in total numbers of mosquitoes between the two cities were evident. Rainfall, salinity, type of structure, structure setting, and presence or absence of predators or competitors influenced the numbers of mosquitoes collected and/or the frequency of positive, negative, dry, or flooded samples.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1081-1710</sn>
<an>000243418000015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3950</id>
<a1>Rey,Jorge R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Meara,George F.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,Sheila M.</a1>
<a1>Cutwa-Francis,Michele M.</a1>
<t1>Mosquito production from four constructed treatment wetlands in peninsular Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>198</sp>
<op>205</op>
<ab>Several techniques were used to sample adult and immature mosquitoes in 4 constructed treatment wetlands in Florida. Adults of 19 species (7 genera) of mosquitoes were collected, and immatures of the most abundant species and of 60% of all species also were collected. Few significant differences between sites and stations in the numbers of mosquitoes collected were discovered. Culex nigripalpus Theobald was the most abundant mosquito found in adult (carbon dioxide-baited suction traps) and ovitrap collections, whereas Mansonia spp. and Uranotaenia spp. were most common in pump-dip-grab samples. The roles of rooted and floating vegetation and of water quality in determining mosquito production from these areas are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000238900900004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3949</id>
<a1>Rey,Jorge R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Meara,George F.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Connell,Sheila M.</a1>
<a1>Darsie,Richard F.</a1>
<t1>Variation in the number and position of siphonal setae in Culex quinquefasciatus from Key West and Vero Beach, Florida, USA</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>355</sp>
<op>357</op>
<ab>Variations in diagnostic siphonal characters of Culex quinquefasciatus larvae collected in Key West and Vero Beach, FL, are described. We observed specimens with 3, 4, and 5 sets of siphonal setae and also observed frequent variation in the insertion point of the proximal and subapical setae.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000241120700001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
