<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1126</id>
<a1>Alteri,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Hess,S.</a1>
<a1>Caballero-Olin,G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Friedman,R. L.</a1>
<t1>Mycobacterium tuberculosis produces pili during human infection</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Mar 20</fd>
<vo>104</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5145</sp>
<op>5150</op>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin G/blood</k1>
<k1>Laminin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mycobacterium tuberculosis/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Subunits/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tuberculosis/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Mycobacterium tuberculosis is responsible for nearly 3 million human deaths worldwide every year. Understanding the mechanisms and bacterial factors responsible for the ability of M. tuberculosis to cause disease in humans is critical for the development of improved treatment strategies. Many bacterial pathogens use pili as adherence factors to colonize the host. We discovered that M. tuberculosis produces fine (2- to 3-nm-wide), aggregative, flexible pili that are recognized by IgG antibodies contained in sera obtained from patients with active tuberculosis, indicating that the bacilli produce pili or pili-associated antigen during human infection. Purified M. tuberculosis pili (MTP) are composed of low-molecular-weight protein subunits encoded by the predicted M. tuberculosis H37Rv ORF, designated Rv3312A. MTP bind to the extracellular matrix protein laminin in vitro, suggesting that MTP possess adhesive properties. Isogenic mtp mutants lost the ability to produce Mtp in vitro and demonstrated decreased laminin-binding capabilities. MTP shares morphological, biochemical, and functional properties attributed to bacterial pili, especially with curli amyloid fibers. Thus, we propose that MTP are previously unidentified host-colonization factors of M. tuberculosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI45537-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Immunoglobulin G); 0 (Laminin); 0 (Protein Subunits); OID: NLM: PMC1817835; 2007/03/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, 1501 North Campbell Avenue, LSN 649, Tucson, AZ 85724, USA. alteri@umich.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17360408; 0602304104 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0602304104</do>
<wp>20070308</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17360408</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1817835</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1138</id>
<a1>Andrade,A.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Amhaz,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Trabulsi,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Martinez,M. B.</a1>
<t1>Expression and characterization of flagella in nonmotile enteroinvasive Escherichia coli isolated from diarrhea cases</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>70</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>5882</sp>
<op>5886</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Enterobacteriaceae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Flagella/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Movement/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>We report that enteroinvasive Escherichia coli (EIEC) serotypes considered to be nonmotile produce an unusually large (77 kDa) flagellin that is assembled into functional flagellum filaments that allow the bacteria to swim in modified motility agar. The EIEC flagellin showed N-terminal identity to most common enterobacterial flagellins, especially those of the E. coli H7 serotype. These data are important in terms of the epidemiology, evolution, and biology of EIEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); OID: NLM: PMC128341; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Analises Clinicas e Toxicologicas, Faculdade de Ciencias Farmaceuticas, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12228323</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12228323</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC128341</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1110</id>
<a1>Avelino,F.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Islam,S.</a1>
<a1>Monteiro-Neto,V.</a1>
<a1>Dall&#39;agnol,M.</a1>
<a1>Eslava,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>The majority of enteroaggregative Escherichia coli strains produce the E. coli common pilus when adhering to cultured epithelial cells</t1>
<jf>International journal of medical microbiology : IJMM</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Med.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May 6</fd>
<ab>Enteroaggregative Escherichia coli (EAEC) have emerged as a significant worldwide cause of chronic diarrhea in the pediatric population and in HIV patients. The vast majority of EAEC strains do not produce the aggregative adherence fimbriae I-III (AAFs) so far reported and thus, what adherence factors are present in these strains remains unknown. Here, we investigated the prevalence of the chromosomal E. coli common pilus (ECP) genes and ECP production amongst 130 EAEC strains of diverse origin as well as the role of ECP in EAEC adherence. Through multiplex PCR analysis we found that 96% of EAEC strains contained the ecpA structural pilin gene whereas only 3.1% and 5.4% were positive for AAF fimbrial genes aggA or aafA, respectively. Among the ecpA(+) strains, 63% produced ECP when adhering to cultured epithelial cells. An ecpA mutant derived from prototypic strain 042 (AAF/II(+)) was not altered in adherence suggesting that the AAF/II, and not ECP, plays a major role in this strain. In contrast, strain 278-1 (AAF(-)) deleted of the ecpA gene was significantly reduced in adherence to cultured epithelial cells. In all, these data indicate a potential role of ECP in adherence for EAEC strains lacking the known AAFs and that in association with other adhesive determinants, ECP may contribute to their survival and persistence within the host and in the environment.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright (c) 2010; JID: 100898849; 2009/10/04 [received]; 2010/01/22 [revised]; 2010/02/20 [accepted]; aheadofprint</no>
<pb>Elsevier GmbH</pb>
<sn>1618-0607; 1438-4221</sn>
<ad>Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Puebla, Pue 72000, Mexico.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20452276; S1438-4221(10)00032-9 [pii]</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ijmm.2010.02.002</do>
<wp>20100506</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20452276</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1184</id>
<a1>Baseman,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Lange,M.</a1>
<a1>Criscimagna,N. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Thomas,C. A.</a1>
<t1>Interplay between mycoplasmas and host target cells</t1>
<jf>Microbial pathogenesis</jf>
<jo>Microb.Pathog.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>105</sp>
<op>116</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Fractionation</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Flow Cytometry/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lung/cytology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Confocal</k1>
<k1>Mycoplasma penetrans/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mycoplasma pneumoniae/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<ab>The infectious pattern of mycoplasmas (Mycoplasma penetrans, Mycoplasma pneumoniae and Mycoplasma genitalium) in mammalian cells was examined using confocal microscopy and flow cytometry combined with cell fractionation and mycoplasma viability determinations. Within 2 h postinfection mycoplasmas parasitize cell surfaces, enter the intracellular spaces and locate throughout the cytoplasmic and perinuclear regions. These mycoplasmas can be cultivated from cytoplasmic and nuclear fractions 96 h later and continue to persist intracellularly for at least 7 days, suggesting a much more active intracellular role for mycoplasmas than had been considered previously.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 287873/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 32829/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8606191; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0882-4010; 0882-4010</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio 78284-7758, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8577234; S0882401085700502 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8577234</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1115</id>
<a1>Blackburn,D.</a1>
<a1>Husband,A.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Nada,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Klena,J.</a1>
<a1>Qadri,F.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Distribution of the Escherichia coli common pilus among diverse strains of human enterotoxigenic E. coli</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1781</sp>
<op>1784</op>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Flow Cytometry</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Immunoelectron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<ab>The Escherichia coli common pilus (ECP) is produced by commensal and pathogenic E. coli strains. This pilus is unrelated to any of the known colonization factors (CFs) of enterotoxigenic E. coli (ETEC). In this study, we investigated the distribution and production of ECP among a collection of 136 human CF-positive and CF-negative ETEC strains of different geographic origins. The major pilus subunit gene, ecpA, was found in 109 (80%) of these strains, suggesting that it is widely distributed among ETEC strains. Phenotypic analysis of a subset of 43 strains chosen randomly showed that 58% of them produced ECP independently of the presence or absence of CFs, a percentage even higher than that of the most prevalent CFs. These data suggest an important role for ECP in the biology of ETEC, particularly in CF-negative strains, and in human infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091230; GENBANK/FJ210911; GENBANK/FJ210912; GR: AI66012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505564; 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC2691072; 2009/04/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-660X; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19357209; JCM.00260-09 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JCM.00260-09</do>
<wp>20090408</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19357209</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2691072</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1130</id>
<a1>Castaneda-Roldan,E. I.</a1>
<a1>Avelino-Flores,F.</a1>
<a1>Dall&#39;Agnol,M.</a1>
<a1>Freer,E.</a1>
<a1>Cedillo,L.</a1>
<a1>Dornand,J.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Adherence of Brucella to human epithelial cells and macrophages is mediated by sialic acid residues</t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>435</sp>
<op>445</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Brucella abortus/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Brucella melitensis/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/metabolism/microbiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Extracellular Matrix Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/cytology/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>N-Acetylneuraminic Acid/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Neuraminidase/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Periodic Acid/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Trypsin/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The basis for the interaction of Brucella species with the surface of epithelial cells before migration in the host within polymorphonuclear leucocytes is largely unknown. Here, we studied the ability of Brucella abortus and Brucella melitensis to adhere to cultured epithelial (HeLa and HEp-2) cells and THP-1-derived macrophages, and to bind extracellular matrix proteins (ECM). The brucellae adhered to epithelial cells forming localized bacterial microcolonies on the cell surface, and this process was inhibited significantly by pretreatment of epithelial cells with neuraminidase and sodium periodate and by preincubation of the bacteria with heparan sulphate and N-acetylneuraminic acid. Trypsinization of epithelial cells yielded increased adherence, suggesting unmasking of target sites on host cells. Notably, the brucellae also adhered to cultured THP-1 cells, and this event was greatly reduced upon removal of sialic acid residues from these cells with neuraminidase. B. abortus bound in a dose-dependent manner to immobilized fibronectin and vitronectin and, to a lesser extent, to chondroitin sulphate, collagen and laminin. In sum, our data strongly suggest that the adherence mechanism of brucellae to epithelial cells and macrophages is mediated by cellular receptors containing sialic acid and sulphated residues. The recognition of ECM (fibronectin and vitronectin) by the brucellae may represent a mechanism for spread within the host tissues. These are novel findings that offer new insights into understanding the interplay between Brucella and host cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100883691; 0 (Enzyme Inhibitors); 0 (Extracellular Matrix Proteins); 10450-60-9 (Periodic Acid); 131-48-6 (N-Acetylneuraminic Acid); 7790-28-5 (metaperiodate); EC 3.2.1.18 (Neuraminidase); EC 3.4.21.4 (Trypsin); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5814; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Edificio 76, Complejo de Ciencias, Puebla, Mexico.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15056214; CMI372 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-5822.2004.00372.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15056214</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1129</id>
<a1>Castaneda-Roldan,E. I.</a1>
<a1>Ouahrani-Bettache,S.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Avelino,F.</a1>
<a1>Rendon,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Dornand,J.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of SP41, a surface protein of Brucella associated with adherence and invasion of host epithelial cells</t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1877</sp>
<op>1887</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/chemistry/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/blood/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Brucella/chemistry/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Brucellosis/immunology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/chemistry/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Brucella is an invasive organism that multiplies and survives within eukaryotic cells. The brucellae are able to adhere to the surface of cultured epithelial cells, a mechanism that may facilitate penetration and dissemination to other host tissues. However, no adhesins that allow the bacteria to interact with the surface of epithelial cells before migration within polymorphonuclear leukocytes, monocytes and macrophages have been described. Here, we show that Brucella surface proteins (SPs) with apparent molecular masses of 14, 18 and 41 kDa bound selectively to HeLa cells. However, only antibodies directed against the 41 kDa surface protein (SP41) inhibited in dose-response manner, bacterial adherence and invasion of HeLa cells. HeLa cells treated with neuraminidase did not bind SP41, suggesting the involvement of cellular sialic acid residues in this interaction. Biochemical analysis of SP41 revealed that this protein is the predicted product of the ugpB locus, which showed significant homology to the glycerol-3-phosphate-binding ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter protein found in several bacterial species. SP41 appears to be exposed on the bacterial surface as determined by immunofluorescence and immunogold labelling with anti-SP41 antibody. An isogenic DeltaugpB mutant showed a significant inhibitory effect on Brucella adherence and invasion of human cultured epithelial cells and this effect could be reversed by restoration of the ugpB on a plasmid. Lastly, we also show that most of the sera from individuals with acute brucellosis, but not sera obtained from healthy donors or patients with chronic brucellosis, mount antibody reactivity against SP41, suggesting that this protein is produced in vivo and that it elicits an antibody immune response. These data are novel findings that offer new insights into understanding the interplay between this bacterium and host target cells, and identify a new target for vaccine development and prevention of brucellosis.</ab>
<no>JID: 100883691; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Membrane Proteins); 2006/07/04 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5814; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Ciudad Universitaria, Puebla 72570, Mexico.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16817909; CMI754 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-5822.2006.00754.x</do>
<wp>20060704</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16817909</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1133</id>
<a1>de Oliveira-Garcia,D.</a1>
<a1>Dall&#39;Agnol,M.</a1>
<a1>Rosales,M.</a1>
<a1>Azzuz,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Alcantara,N.</a1>
<a1>Martinez,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Fimbriae and adherence of Stenotrophomonas maltophilia to epithelial cells and to abiotic surfaces</t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>625</sp>
<op>636</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Gram-Negative Bacterial Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<ab>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia is an emerging nosocomial bacterial pathogen associated with several infectious diseases and opportunistic infections, especially in immunocompromised patients. These bacteria adhere avidly to medical implants and catheters forming a biofilm that confers natural protection against host immune defences and different antimicrobial agents. The nature of the bacterial surface factors involved in biofilm formation on inert surfaces and in adherence of S. maltophilia to epithelial cells is largely unknown. In this study, we identified and characterized fimbrial structures produced by S. maltophilia grown at 37 degrees C. The S. maltophilia fimbriae 1 (SMF-1) are composed of a 17 kDa fimbrin subunit which shares significant similarities with the N-terminal amino acid sequences of several fimbrial adhesins (G, F17, K99 and 20K) found in Escherichia coli pathogenic strains and the CupA fimbriae of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. All of the clinical S. maltophilia isolates tested produced the 17 kDa fimbrin. Antibodies raised against SMF-1 fimbriae inhibited the agglutination of animal erythrocytes, adherence to HEp-2 cells and biofilm formation by S. maltophilia. High resolution electron microscopy provided evidence of the presence of fimbriae acting as bridges between bacteria adhering to inert surfaces or to cultured epithelial cells. This is the first characterization of fimbriae in this genus. We provide compelling data suggesting that the SMF-1 fimbriae are involved in haemagglutination, biofilm formation and adherence to cultured mammalian cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100883691; 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5814; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio Clinico do Instituto Dante Pazzanese de Cardiologia, Departamento de Microbiologia do Instituto de Ciencias Biomedicas, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12925132; 306 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12925132</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1140</id>
<a1>de Oliveira-Garcia,D.</a1>
<a1>Dall&#39;Agnol,M.</a1>
<a1>Rosales,M.</a1>
<a1>Azzuz,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Martinez,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of flagella produced by clinical strains of Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</t1>
<jf>Emerging infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>Emerg.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>918</sp>
<op>923</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Flagella/genetics/immunology/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Plastics</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia/genetics/immunology/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia is an emerging nosocomial pathogen associated with opportunistic infections in patients with cystic fibrosis, cancer, and HIV. Adherence of this organism to abiotic surfaces such as medical implants and catheters represents a major risk for hospitalized patients. The adhesive surface factors involved in adherence of these bacteria are largely unknown, and their flagella have not yet been characterized biochemically and antigenically. We purified and characterized the flagella produced by S. maltophilia clinical strains. The flagella filaments are composed of a 38-kDa subunit, SM(FliC), and analysis of its N-terminal amino acid sequence showed considerable sequence identity to the flagellins of Serratia marcescens (78.6%), Escherichia coli, Proteus mirabilis, Shigella sonnei (71.4%), and Pseudomonas aeruginosa (57.2%). Ultrastructural analysis by scanning electron microscopy of bacteria adhering to plastic showed flagellalike structures within the bacterial clusters, suggesting that flagella are produced as the bacteria spread on the abiotic surface.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 9508155; 0 (Plastics); OID: NLM: PMC2732543; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1080-6040; 1080-6040</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio Clinico do Instituto Dante Pazzanese de Cardiologia, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12194767</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12194767</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2732543</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1141</id>
<a1>del C Rocha-Gracia,R.</a1>
<a1>Castaneda-Roldan,E. I.</a1>
<a1>Giono-Cerezo,S.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Brucella sp. bind to sialic acid residues on human and animal red blood cells</t1>
<jf>FEMS microbiology letters</jf>
<jo>FEMS Microbiol.Lett.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Aug 6</fd>
<vo>213</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>219</sp>
<op>224</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigen-Antibody Reactions</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Brucella/immunology</k1>
<k1>Brucella abortus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Chondroitin Sulfates/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cricetinae</k1>
<k1>Erythrocytes/drug effects/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination Tests</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>N-Acetylneuraminic Acid/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Neuraminidase/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Cell Surface/metabolism</k1>
<ab>We report that Brucella abortus and Brucella melitensis agglutinate human (A+ and B+), hamster and rabbit erythrocytes, a heretofore undescribed feature in this genus. This activity was associated with a 29-kDa surface protein (SP29) that bound selectively to these erythrocytes and this binding was inhibited by rabbit anti-SP29 antibodies. Hemagglutination was inhibited by pretreatment of erythrocytes with neuraminidase and by preincubation of B. abortus with chondroitin sulfate, N-acetylneuraminic acid and N-acetylneuramin-lactose.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7705721; 0 (Receptors, Cell Surface); 0 (sialic acid receptor); 131-48-6 (N-Acetylneuraminic Acid); 9007-28-7 (Chondroitin Sulfates); EC 3.2.1.18 (Neuraminidase); ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0378-1097; 0378-1097</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Edificio 76, Complejo de Ciencias, Cd. Universitaria, Pue. C.P. 72000, Puebla, Mexico</ad>
<an>PMID: 12167541; S0378109702008170 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12167541</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1195</id>
<a1>Donnenberg,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Nataro,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>A plasmid-encoded type IV fimbrial gene of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli associated with localized adherence</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>3427</sp>
<op>3437</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Escherichia coli</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) form adherent microcolonies on the surface of tissue culture cells in a pattern termed localized adherence. Localized adherence requires the presence of a large EPEC adherence factor (EAF) plasmid. Recently a bundle-forming pilus has been described in EPEC possessing the EAF plasmid. An analysis of 22 non-invasive EPEC TnphoA mutants revealed that seven have insertions in the EAF plasmid and are incapable of localized adherence. We report here the mapping of the TnphoA insertions in these mutants. The nucleotide sequence of the gene interrupted in these TnphoA mutants (bfpA) was determined and found to correspond to the N-terminal amino acid sequence of the major structural protein of the bundle-forming pilus. The bfpA gene bears sequence similarities to members of the type IV fimbrial gene family and encodes a potential site for processing by a prepilin peptidase. A plasmid containing bfpA as the only open reading frame directs the synthesis of a protein recognized by antiserum raised against the bundle-forming pilus. TnphoA mutants at this locus are unable to synthesize BfpA, but synthesis is restored by introduction of a plasmid containing the cloned gene. The minimum fragment of DNA required to restore localized adherence is considerably greater than that required to restore BfpA synthesis. BfpA expression, as assessed by alkaline phosphatase activity in bfpA::TnphoA mutants, is affected by temperature and growth medium. These studies describe an EPEC plasmid-encoded fimbrial gene, a candidate for the elusive EPEC adherence factor responsible for localized adherence.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/Z12295; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Adhesins, Escherichia coli); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (BfpA protein, E coli); 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Veterans&#39; Affairs Medical Center, Baltimore, Maryland 21201.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1362446</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1362446</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1151</id>
<a1>Elliott,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Shin,S.</a1>
<a1>Mellies,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Wainwright,L.</a1>
<a1>Hutcheson,S. W.</a1>
<a1>McDaniel,T. K.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>The locus of enterocyte effacement (LEE)-encoded regulator controls expression of both LEE- and non-LEE-encoded virulence factors in enteropathogenic and enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>6115</sp>
<op>6126</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Regulation of virulence gene expression in enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) and enterohemorrhagic E. coli (EHEC) is incompletely understood. In EPEC, the plasmid-encoded regulator Per is required for maximal expression of proteins encoded on the locus of enterocyte effacement (LEE), and a LEE-encoded regulator (Ler) is part of the Per-mediated regulatory cascade upregulating the LEE2, LEE3, and LEE4 promoters. We now report that Ler is essential for the expression of multiple LEE-located genes in both EPEC and EHEC, including those encoding the type III secretion pathway, the secreted Esp proteins, Tir, and intimin. Ler is therefore central to the process of attaching and effacing (AE) lesion formation. Ler also regulates the expression of LEE-located genes not required for AE-lesion formation, including rorf2, orf10, rorf10, orf19, and espF, indicating that Ler regulates additional virulence properties. In addition, Ler regulates the expression of proteins encoded outside the LEE that are not essential for AE lesion formation, including TagA in EHEC and EspC in EPEC. delta ler mutants of both EPEC and EHEC show altered adherence to epithelial cells and express novel fimbriae. Ler is therefore a global regulator of virulence gene expression in EPEC and EHEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI41325/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC97688; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development and Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11035714</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11035714</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC97688</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1124</id>
<a1>Erdem,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Avelino,F.</a1>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Host protein binding and adhesive properties of H6 and H7 flagella of attaching and effacing Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>189</vo>
<is>20</is>
<sp>7426</sp>
<op>7435</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cell Aggregation</k1>
<k1>Erythrocytes/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/classification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Extracellular Matrix Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Flagella/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Horses</k1>
<k1>Intestines/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mucins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mucus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<ab>It had been suggested that the flagella of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) and enterohemorrhagic E. coli (EHEC) might contribute to host colonization. In this study, we set out to investigate the adhesive properties of H7 and H6 flagella. We studied the abilities of EHEC EDL933 (O157:H7) and EPEC E2348/69 (O127:H6) flagella to bind to bovine mucus, host proteins such as mucins, and extracellular matrix proteins. Through several approaches, we found that H6 and H7 flagella and their flagellin monomers bind to mucins I and II and to freshly isolated bovine mucus. A genetic approach showed that EHEC and EPEC fliC deletion mutants were significantly less adherent to bovine intestinal tissue than the parental wild-type strains. In addition, we found that EPEC bacteria and H6 flagella, but not EHEC, bound largely, in a dose-dependent manner, to collagen and to a lesser extent to laminin and fibronectin. We also report that EHEC O157:H7 strains agglutinate rabbit red blood cells via their flagella, a heretofore unknown phenotype in this pathogroup. Collectively, our data demonstrate that the H6 and H7 flagella possess adhesive properties, particularly the ability to bind mucins, that may contribute to colonization of mucosal surfaces.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI60211/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI66012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Extracellular Matrix Proteins); 0 (FliC protein, E coli); 0 (Mucins); OID: NLM: PMC2168434; 2007/08/10 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17693516; JB.00464-07 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.00464-07</do>
<wp>20070810</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17693516</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2168434</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1203</id>
<a1>Frankel,G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Valmassoi,J.</a1>
<a1>Schoolnik,G. K.</a1>
<t1>Multi-gene amplification: simultaneous detection of three virulence genes in diarrhoeal stool</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1729</sp>
<op>1734</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>DNA Probes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Feces/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Amplification</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Shigella/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) and Shigella account for a substantial proportion of acute diarrhoeal illnesses among Third-World children. Rapid detection of these infectious agents in faeces followed by the prompt implementation of public health measures could help reduce their spread during the early phase of epidemics. Towards this end, three pairs of synthetic oligonucleotide primers were prepared and shown to hybridize specifically to the genes encoding the heat-stable (ST) and the heat-labile (LT) enterotoxins of ETEC and to invasion-associated loci (ial) of the large Shigella virulence plasmid. When the three primer pairs were used together in the polymerase chain reaction (PCR), the three corresponding genetic loci could be simultaneously amplified using DNA extracted directly from stool; the amplified products were readily detected by ST-, LT- and ial-specific, alkaline phosphatase-labelled oligonucleotide probes (AP probes). The performance of this system was evaluated in a Mayan community in southeastern Mexico, where diarrhoeal illnesses are a common cause of childhood morbidity and mortality. Using only simple and inexpensive laboratory equipment, multigene amplification with these primers and probes led to the identification of ETEC and/or Shigella in the stools of 20 out of 71 children with diarrhoea; the procedure could be completed in seven hours and was more sensitive than conventional diagnostic tests or DNA probes used without amplification.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8712028; 0 (DNA Probes); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, Stanford University School of Medicine, California 94305.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2695745</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2695745</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1201</id>
<a1>Frankel,G.</a1>
<a1>Riley,L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Valmassoi,J.</a1>
<a1>Friedmann,A.</a1>
<a1>Strockbine,N.</a1>
<a1>Falkow,S.</a1>
<a1>Schoolnik,G. K.</a1>
<t1>Detection of Shigella in feces using DNA amplification</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>161</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1252</sp>
<op>1256</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Dysentery, Bacillary/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Agar Gel</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Feces/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Probes</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Predictive Value of Tests</k1>
<k1>Shigella/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Shigella flexneri/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<ab>A rapid diagnostic method employing a polymerase chain reaction procedure (PCR) was used to identify Shigella and enteroinvasive Escherichia coli. This procedure amplified a region of the invasive-associated locus (ial) from a crude DNA extract of feces. A synthetic 21-base oligonucleotide corresponding to the ial gene sequence was shown to specifically hybridize only with enteroinvasive E. coli (EIEC) strains and Shigella species. Upon PCR amplification, a 320-base pair fragment was generated in DNA extracted from feces reconstituted with EIEC or Shigella flexneri but not in DNA from 70 normal stools lacking these organisms and could be readily detected by the ial probe. For identifying Shigella and EIEC, the PCR assay was 10(5)- and 10(2)-fold more sensitive than standard biochemical tests and the macrocolony hybridization assay, respectively. These findings demonstrate a novel methodology for rapid, sensitive, and culture-independent diagnosis of diarrhea caused by these pathogens and underscores the utility of PCR in the diagnostic laboratory.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0413675; 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Oligonucleotide Probes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1899; 0022-1899</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, Stanford University, CA 94305.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2189008</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2189008</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1682</id>
<a1>Giono-Cerezo,S.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Aguirre,E.</a1>
<a1>Escobar,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Escamilla,E.</a1>
<t1>Evaluacion de antisueros grupo y tipo especificos para la tipificacion en Mexico de infecciones estreptococcicas</t1>
<jo>Bol. Med. Hosp. Inf. Mex.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>43</vo>
<sp>470</sp>
<op>476</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2806</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Fimbriae of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli.</t1>
<jo>Rev. Microbiol. (Sao Paulo)</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>27</vo>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>154</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1621</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Role of flagella in mucosal colonization</t1>
<yr>2005</yr>
<sp>213</sp>
<op>235</op>
<k1>Mucous membrane -- Microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mucous membrane -- Immunology</k1>
<k1>Immunity, Mucosal -- physiology</k1>
<k1>Immunologie</k1>
<k1>Mikroorganismus</k1>
<k1>Schleimhaut</k1>
<k1>Internet resource (url)</k1>
<ab>I. General Considerations. Structure and function of mucosal surfaces / Jeff P. Pearson and Iain A. Brownlee -- Defensins and other antimicrobial peptides: innate defense of mucosal surfaces / Alexander M. Cole and Tomas Ganz -- Mechanisms of adaptive immunity that prevent colonization at mucosal surfaces / Marcela F. Pasetti, Rosangela Salerno-Gonçalves and Marcelo B. Sztein -- In situ monitoring of bacterial presence and activity / Claus Sternberg ... [et al.] -- II. Colonization of the respiratory tract. Role of phosphorylcholine in respiratory tract colonization / Jeffrey N. Weiser -- Sialylation of the gram-negative bacterial cell surface / Michael A. Apicella and Paul A. Jones -- Competitive and cooperative interactions in the respiratory microflora / Adam J. Ratner -- Bacterial adherence and tropism in the human respiratory tract / Mumtaz Virji -- Immunoglobulin A1 proteases of pathogenic and commensal bacteria of the respiratory tract / Mogens Kilian and Jesper Reinholdt --; Genetic exchange in the respiratory tract / Christopher G. Dowson -- Regulation in response to environmental conditions / Peggy A. Cotter -- III. Colonization of the gastrointestinal tract. Microbiota of mucosal surfaces in the gut of monogastric animals / Gerald W. Tannock -- Interactions of commensal flora with the human gastrointestinal tract / James P. Nataro -- Quorum sensing in the gastrointestinal tract / James B. Kaper, Christopher Pritchett and Jane Michalski -- Role of the mucous layer in bacterial colonization of the intestine / David C. Laux, Paul S. Cohen and Tyrrell Conway -- Role of flagella in mucosal colonization / Jorge A. Girón -- Tissue tropism in intestinal colonization / Elizabeth L. Hartland ... [et al.] -- Aggregation and dispersal on mucosal surfaces / James P. Nataro and Angela Jansen -- Signal transduction in the intestinal mucosa / Beth A. McCormick --; Pathogen gene expression during intestinal infection / Susan M. Butler, Anna D. Tischler and Andrew Camilli -- Mechanisms of Salmonella enterica serotype typhimurium intestinal colonization / Caleb W. Dorsey ... [et al.] -- Colonization and invasion of humans by Entamoeba histolytica / Kristine M. Peterson and William A. Petri, Jr -- IV. Colonization of the genitourinary tract. Role of phase and antigenic variation in Neisseria gonorrhoeae colonization / Amy N. Simms and Ann E. Jerse -- Allelic variation of the FimH lectin of Escherichia coli type 1 fimbriae and uropathogenesis / David L. Hasty ... [et al.] -- Fimbriae, signaling, and host response to urinary tract infection / Niamh Roche ... [et al.] -- Urease, urolithiasis, and colonization of the urinary tract / Harry L.T. Mobley -- Polymicrobial bacteriuria: biofilm formation on foreign bodies and colonization of the urinary tract / David J. Stickler -- Colonization of the vagina and urethral mucosa / Gregor Reid.</ab>
<no>xi; ill. ; 29 cm.; Note(s): Includes bibliographical references and index.; General Info: Other format available: Online version:; Colonization of mucosal surfaces.; Washington, D.C. : ASM Press, c2005; Online version:; Colonization of mucosal surfaces.; Washington, D.C. : ASM Press, c2005; Responsibility: edited by James P. Nataro ... [et al.]. More Records: Show record information Vendor Info: Baker &amp;amp; Taylor Baker and Taylor YBP Library Services Ingram (BKTY BTCP YANK INGR) 119.95 Status: active; Date of Entry: 20041007; Update: 20100530</no>
<a2>Nataro,James P.</a2>
<t2>Colonization of mucosal surfaces</t2>
<pb>ASM Press</pb>
<pp>Washington, D.C</pp>
<sn>1555813232; 9781555813239; National Library: 101231516; LCCN: 2004-23760</sn>
<an>56733159</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>WorldCat; Book; Internet Resource; OCLC; WorldCat</sf>
<lk>http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip052/2004023760.html; Materials specified: Table of contents http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip052/2004023760.html http://bvbm2.bib-bvb.de:8993/F?func=service&amp;doc_library=BVB01&amp;doc_number=012954429&amp;line_number=0001&amp;func_code=DB_RECORDS&amp;service_type=MEDIA Note: Inhaltsverzeichnis</lk>
<cn>LC: QR185.9.M83; Dewey: 616.9/201; NLM: 2005 D-008; QS 532.5.M8</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1181</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Expression of flagella and motility by Shigella</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>63</sp>
<op>75</op>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>Dysentery, Bacillary/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Flagella/genetics/immunology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/genetics/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Movement</k1>
<k1>Shigella/genetics/immunology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Since the discovery of Shigella as the aetiologic agent of acute dysentery almost 100 years ago, this organism has been described as a non-motile and nonflagellated organism that invades the human colonic mucosa. In this study, the production of flagella by prototypic strains of all four Shigella species and, moreover, by fresh clinical isolates was demonstrated by electron microscopy. The flagellum of Shigella (flash) is approximately 10 microns long and 12-14 nm in diameter and is typically seen emanating from one pole of the bacterium. Flash is composed of a putative structural polypeptide subunit of 33-38 kDa that shares immunological similarities with Escherichia coli, Salmonella spp., and Proteus mirabilis flagellins, and with the recently described recombinant Shigella flagellins (FliCSS and FliCSF) expressed in E. coli K-12. A fliCSS-specific oligo probe hybridized with all four Shigella species, while a fliCSF probe hybridized with all Shigella flexneri and Shigella dysenteriae strains, but not with all Shigella sonnei or Shigella boydii strains, indicating genetic divergence among their flagellin genes. Shigella exhibits motility in low-concentration motility agar under physiological growth conditions. The expression of flash and motility appears to be strictly regulated by unidentified genetic and environmental factors. These heretofore undescribed features may allow the bacteria to circumvent the natural intestinal mucosal defences leading to bacterial colonization and disease. The motility of shigellae may represent an evolutionary adaptation important for bacterial survival.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8712028; 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 127384-62-7 (ipaB protein, Shigella); 127384-63-8 (IpaC protein, Shigella); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8596461</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8596461</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1192</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Donnenberg,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Martin,W. C.</a1>
<a1>Jarvis,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Distribution of the bundle-forming pilus structural gene (bfpA) among enteropathogenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>168</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1037</sp>
<op>1041</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Probes</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) express an inducible bundle-forming pilus (BFP) associated with the presence of the EPEC adherence factor (EAF) plasmid and localized adherence (LA) on HEp-2 cells. The cloned structural gene (bfpA) encoding BFP was found to be specific for EPEC, as homologous sequences were found only in EPEC and not in other enteropathogens. The bfpA probe was slightly more sensitive than the EAF probe; among EPEC strains with LA, the bfpA and EAF probes hybridized with 99% and 96% of the strains, respectively. Immunoblotting of whole cell lysates of BFP-positive, EAF-positive or -negative, and LA-positive or -negative EPEC strains revealed variations in the size (18,500-21,000) of the expressed structural subunit of BFP, suggesting differences in processing that may account for discrepancies between the bfpA, EAF, and LA. Because the bfpA probe consists primarily of sequences encoding an important EPEC virulence factor, in contrast to the unknown function of sequences contained in the EAF probe, the bfpA probe may be useful in epidemiologic studies to detect EPEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0413675; 0 (DNA Probes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1899; 0022-1899</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland, Baltimore.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8104225</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8104225</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1170</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Gomez-Duarte,O. G.</a1>
<a1>Jarvis,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Longus pilus of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli and its relatedness to other type-4 pili--a minireview</t1>
<jf>Gene</jf>
<jo>Gene</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Jun 11</fd>
<vo>192</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>39</sp>
<op>43</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/metabolism/pathogenicity/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/chemistry/classification/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<ab>Longus is a long pilus produced by human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) which shares significant structural and biochemical features with class-B type-4 pili. These pili include the toxin-coregulated pilus (TCP) of Vibrio cholerae, the bundle-forming pilus (BFP) of enteropathogenic E. coli and both longus and the colonization factor antigen III (CFA/III) of ETEC. These pili are produced under defined growth conditions indicating that they are under the control of different regulatory elements. While TCP is chromosomally encoded, the remaining pili are encoded on large virulence plasmids. Longus and CFA/III are closely related pili although certain DNA and protein differences also exist between them. This may account for the differences in the regulation, surface presentation, antigenicity, and prevalence of these two pilins among ETEC. Neighboring lngA, a second open reading frame termed lngB was found which encodes a protein with significant homology to proteins which are part of a type-II secretory system such as XcpV, OutC, and PulO of Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Erwinia chrysanthemi, and Klebsiella pneumoniae, respectively. This suggests that lngB may be an accessory gene involved in biogenesis of longus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 7706761; 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); RF: 28; ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0378-1119; 0378-1119</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Pue, Mexico. jgiron@siu.cen.buap.mx</ad>
<an>PMID: 9224872; S0378-1119(97)00039-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9224872</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1191</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Ho,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Schoolnik,G. K.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of fimbriae produced by enteropathogenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>175</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>7391</sp>
<op>7403</op>
<k1>ABO Blood-Group System</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/analysis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Extracellular Matrix Proteins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination Inhibition Tests</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Immunoelectron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Urinary Tract Infections/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) express rope-like bundles of filaments, termed bundle-forming pili (BFP) (J. A. Giron, A. S. Y. Ho, and G. K. Schoolnik, Science 254:710-713, 1991). Expression of BFP is associated with localized adherence to HEp-2 cells and the presence of the EPEC adherence factor plasmid. In this study, we describe the identification of rod-like fimbriae and fibrillae expressed simultaneously on the bacterial surface of three prototype EPEC strains. Upon fimbrial extraction from EPEC B171 (O111:NM), three fimbrial subunits with masses of 16.5, 15.5, and 14.7 kDa were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. Their N-terminal amino acid sequence showed homology with F9 and F7(2) fimbriae of uropathogenic E. coli and F1845 of diffuse-adhering E. coli, respectively. The mixture of fimbrial subunits (called FB171) exhibited mannose-resistant agglutination of human erythrocytes only, and this activity was not inhibited by alpha-D-Gal(1-4)-beta-Gal disaccharide or any other described receptor analogs for P, S, F, M, G, and Dr hemagglutinins of uropathogenic E. coli, which suggests a different receptor specificity. Hemagglutination was inhibited by extracellular matrix glycoproteins, i.e., collagen type IV, laminin, and fibronectin, and to a lesser extent by gangliosides, fetuin, and asialofetuin. Scanning electron microscopic studies performed on clusters of bacteria adhering to HEp-2 cells revealed the presence of structures resembling BFP and rod-like fimbriae linking bacteria to bacteria and bacteria to the eukaryotic cell membrane. We suggest a role of these surface appendages in the interaction of EPEC with eukaryotic cells as well as in the overall pathogenesis of intestinal disease caused by EPEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: DK 38707/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (ABO Blood-Group System); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Extracellular Matrix Proteins); 0 (Macromolecular Substances); OID: NLM: PMC206884; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University, California 94305.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7901197</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7901197</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC206884</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1198</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Ho,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Schoolnik,G. K.</a1>
<t1>An inducible bundle-forming pilus of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Science (New York, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Nov 1</fd>
<vo>254</vo>
<is>5032</is>
<sp>710</sp>
<op>713</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intestine, Small/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC), a cause of childhood diarrhea, grow on the surface of the small intestine and on cultured epithelial cells as colonies of adherent bacteria. When propagated on solid medium containing blood or attached to HEp-2 cells, EPEC express ropelike bundles of filaments, termed bundle-forming pili (BFP), that create a network of fibers that bind together the individual organisms. BFP were found to be expressed by five EPEC serogroups, each harboring a approximately 92-kilobase plasmid previously known to be important for virulence in humans. When two of these strains were cured of this plasmid, they neither expressed BFP nor grew as adherent colonies. An antiserum to BFP reduced the capacity of EPEC to infect cultured epithelial cells. BFP are composed of a repeating subunit of 19,500 daltons, the amino-terminal amino acid sequence of this subunit is homologous to that of the toxin-coregulated pilin of Vibrio cholerae.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: DK 38707/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0404511; 0 (Macromolecular Substances); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0036-8075; 0036-8075</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Beckman Center, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University, CA 94305.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1683004</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1683004</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1200</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Jones,T.</a1>
<a1>Millan-Velasco,F.</a1>
<a1>Castro-Munoz,E.</a1>
<a1>Zarate,L.</a1>
<a1>Fry,J.</a1>
<a1>Frankel,G.</a1>
<a1>Moseley,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Baudry,B.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Diffuse-adhering Escherichia coli (DAEC) as a putative cause of diarrhea in Mayan children in Mexico</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>163</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>507</sp>
<op>513</op>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Case-Control Studies</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>DNA Probes/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/ethnology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/diagnosis/ethnology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Indians, North American</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Mexico/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<ab>Diarrhea is a major cause of infantile morbidity and mortality in developing countries. A community-based, case control study was conducted in a southern Mexican Mayan village for 3 weeks during the peak diarrhea period to prospectively identify the infectious agents associated with childhood diarrheal disease. Several enteropathogens were isolated from stools of 34 of 58 cases, although none was significantly associated with diarrhea. For the 24 cases from which no enteropathogens were isolated, diffuse-adhering Escherichia coli (DAEC) strains were significantly associated with diarrheal disease (P less than .02; odds ratio = 6; 95% confidence limit, 1.08-99.0). DAEC were highly heterogeneous with respect to plasmid content and serotype. Three DNA probes designed to differentiate E. coli exhibiting localized, diffuse, or aggregative adherence were compared with results from a standard HeLa cell binding assay to assess the utility of these probes in the field. This study provides evidence for the potential pathogenic capacity of DAEC and underscores the variety of diarrheal agents operating within a community.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0413675; 0 (DNA Probes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1899; 0022-1899</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Stanford University, CA 94305.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1995723</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1995723</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1176</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Lange,M.</a1>
<a1>Baseman,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Adherence, fibronectin binding, and induction of cytoskeleton reorganization in cultured human cells by Mycoplasma penetrans</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>197</sp>
<op>208</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Cytoskeleton/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells</k1>
<k1>Epithelium/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fibronectins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique, Indirect</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Immunoelectron</k1>
<k1>Mycoplasma penetrans/immunology/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Tissue Fixation</k1>
<ab>Mycoplasma penetrans adhered to cultured human cells, forming clusters that localized to specific areas of the host cell surface. Adherence and cluster formation were inhibited by anti-M. penetrans antibodies, suggesting the involvement of specific adhesin-receptor interactions. Ultrastructural studies showed that after 2 h of infection, mycoplasmas attach to and penetrate the host cell surface. M. penetrans bound selectively to immobilized fibronectin, an interaction which was not inhibited by a 70-kDa fragment containing a heparin-gelatin-binding domain of fibronectin, other matrix glycoproteins, or an RGD tripeptide, suggesting the recognition of other specific binding sites on the fibronectin molecule. A ca. 65-kDa fibronectin-binding protein of M. penetrans was eluted following Sepharose-fibronectin affinity chromatography. Confocal, light, and immunofluorescence microscopy demonstrated that the interaction of M. penetrans with target cells triggers a signal that causes recruitment of several cytoskeletal components, including tubulin and alpha-actinin, and aggregation of phosphorylated proteins. Detergent-soluble mycoplasma proteins with apparent molecular masses of 18, 28, 32, 36, 39, and 41 kDa selectively bound to glutaraldehyde-fixed HEp-2 cells. Our findings offer new insights into understanding the interaction of this human mycoplasma with host target cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 27873/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 32829/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Fibronectins); 0 (fibronectin-binding protein, Bacteria); OID: NLM: PMC173746; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio 78284-7758, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8557340</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8557340</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC173746</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1189</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Levine,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Longus: a long pilus ultrastructure produced by human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>71</sp>
<op>82</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/pathogenicity/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) causes an acute cholera-like diarrhoea in both humans and animals. We describe a new pilus termed longus produced by ETEC, which can extend for over 20 microns from the cell surface. Longus is composed of a repeating subunit of 22 kDa and its NH2-terminal amino acid sequence revealed homology with the toxin-coregulated pilus of Vibrio cholerae, the bundle-forming pilus of enteropathogenic E. coli and type IV pilins of some Gram-negative bacterial pathogens. The longus structural gene (lngA) is encoded in a large plasmid and was cloned in a 5 kb fragment, which proved to be sufficient for pilus production and assembly in E. coli K-12. The presence of lngA was restricted to human ETEC strains. In contrast to other ETEC pili, lngA was widely distributed among ETEC strains independent of their geographical origin, serotype, toxin production, or other pili antigens expressed. Longus is a new member of the type IV pili family, which may represent a highly conserved intestinal colonization factor of ETEC. Common antigenic determinants exist among longus and their pilin subunits, produced by heterologous ETEC. Longus could be significant in the immunoprophylaxis of diarrhoeal disease caused by ETEC, especially against those strains in which no colonization factors have been identified and that produce heat-stable toxin only.</ab>
<no>LR: 20080820; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Enterotoxins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (heat stable toxin (E coli)); 0 (heat-labile enterotoxin, E coli); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore 21201.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7914665</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7914665</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1178</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Qadri,F.</a1>
<a1>Azim,T.</a1>
<a1>Jarvis,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Albert,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Monoclonal antibodies specific for the bundle-forming pilus of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>4949</sp>
<op>4952</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/diagnostic use/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/diagnostic use/immunology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/immunology/isolation &amp; purification/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/immunology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<ab>The bundle-forming pilus (BFP) produced by enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) is associated with the presence of a large EPEC adherence factor plasmid and the formation of localized adherence clusters on tissue culture cells. Three mouse monoclonal antibodies (ICA2, ICA3, and ICA4) were produced against BFP purified from EPEC B171 (O111:NM). These monoclonal antibodies reacted in immunoblots with different epitopes of the 19.5-kDa bundlin subunit of BFP of heterologous EPEC. These reagents could serve as diagnostic tools for the identification of EPEC as well as for studying the role of BfpA in the interaction of EPEC with eukaryotic cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); OID: NLM: PMC173713; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7591164</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7591164</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC173713</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1144</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Torres,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Freer,E.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>The flagella of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli mediate adherence to epithelial cells</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>361</sp>
<op>379</op>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Culture Media, Conditioned</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Flagella/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis</k1>
<k1>Serotyping</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) utilizes a type III protein secretion system to target effector molecules into the host cell leading to effacement of the intestinal mucosa. This secretion apparatus shares many structural features of the flagellar type III export system involved in flagella assembly and motility. We report here that fliC insertional mutants constructed in two wild-type EPEC strains were markedly impaired in adherence and microcolony formation on cultured cells. An E. coli K-12 strain harbouring the EPEC H6 fliC gene on a plasmid showed discrete adhering clusters on HeLa cells, albeit to less extent than the wild-type EPEC strain. Flagella purified from EPEC bound to cultured epithelial cells and antiflagella antibodies blocked adherence of several EPEC serotypes. We determined that eukaryotic cells in culture stimulate expression of flagella by motile and non-motile EPEC. Isogenic strains mutated in perA (a transcriptional activator), bfpA (a type IV pilin), luxS (a quorum-sensing autoinducer gene) and in the type III secretion genes were reduced for motility in Dulbecco&amp;#39;s modified Eagle medium (DMEM) motility agar and produced none or few flagella when associated with epithelial cells. Growth of these mutants in preconditioned tissue culture medium restored motility and their ability to produce flagella, suggesting the influence of a signal provided by mammalian cells that triggers flagella production. This study shows for the first time that the flagella of EPEC are directly involved in the adherence of these bacteria and supports the existence of a molecular relationship between the two existing type III secretion pathways of EPEC, the EPEC adherence factor (EAF) plasmid-encoded regulator, quorum sensing and epithelial cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Culture Media, Conditioned); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Mexico. jagiron@yahoo.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 11972776; 2899 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11972776</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1182</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Viboud,G. I.</a1>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Gomez-Duarte,O. G.</a1>
<a1>Maneval,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Albert,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Levine,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Prevalence and association of the longus pilus structural gene (lngA) with colonization factor antigens, enterotoxin types, and serotypes of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>4195</sp>
<op>4198</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/analysis</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/analysis</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/classification/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Serotyping</k1>
<ab>Human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) produces a plasmid-encoded type IV pilus termed longus (for long pilus). Regardless of the geographic origins of ETEC strains, the longus structural gene lngA was found to have the highest level of association with ETEC producing colonization factor antigen (CFA) CFA/II, followed by ETEC producing CFA/I and CFA/IV. ETEC bearing the less prevalent CFA/III and putative colonization factors and ETEC negative for CFA and putative colonization factor also contained lngA-related sequences. lngA was found in a considerable number of ETEC serotypes and was more often associated with ETEC producing heat-stable enterotoxins than with ETEC producing both heat-labile and heat-stable enterotoxins or heat-labile enterotoxin alone. lngA was found more often in strains isolated from children with diarrhea than in strains from healthy children, suggesting an association with intestinal disease. We conclude that longus is a widely distributed antigenic determinant in ETEC that is highly associated with known plasmid-encoded virulence factors, namely, CFAs and enterotoxins. A longus-specific probe may be a helpful epidemiological tool to assist in the identification of ETEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Enterotoxins); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC173594; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7558343</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7558343</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC173594</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1185</id>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Xu,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Gonzalez,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Hone,D.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Levine,M. M.</a1>
<t1>Simultaneous expression of CFA/I and CS3 colonization factor antigens of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli by delta aroC, delta aroD Salmonella typhi vaccine strain CVD 908</t1>
<jf>Vaccine</jf>
<jo>Vaccine</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>939</sp>
<op>946</op>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Epitopes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/growth &amp; development/immunology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhi/genetics/growth &amp; development/immunology</k1>
<ab>Among the known colonization factors of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC), CFA/I and CS3 (the common antigen in the CFA/II family of fimbrial antigens) are two of the most prevalent fimbrial antigens found in clinical isolates but are never expressed by the same wild-type strain. We manipulated the genetic determinants encoding CS3 and CFA/I fimbriae so that these two important colonization factors are expressed simultaneously in attenuated Salmonella typhi live oral vaccine strain CVD 908, including after growth in liquid medium (CFA/I is poorly expressed by wild-type ETEC in broth culture). The recombinant fimbrial structures produced by CVD 908 are morphologically indistinguishable from the CS3 fibrillae and CFA/I rod-like fimbriae produced by ETEC, and are recognized by monospecific CS3 and CFA/I antibodies. This prototype construct may prove useful in investigating the live vector approach to immunoprophylaxis of ETEC diarrheal disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01 A129471/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 8406899; 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Epitopes); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0264-410X; 0264-410X</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7483768; 0264410X9500003J [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7483768</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1143</id>
<a1>Gismero-Ordonez,J.</a1>
<a1>Dall&#39;Agnol,M.</a1>
<a1>Trabulsi,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Expression of the bundle-forming pilus by enteropathogenic Escherichia coli strains of heterologous serotypes</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2291</sp>
<op>2296</op>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Culture Media</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/classification/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Serotyping</k1>
<ab>The production of the bundle-forming pilus subunit BfpA was investigated in 44 enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) diarrheal isolates after growth on several conventional bacteriological media. In all, the use of brucella agar supplemented with 4.5 mM sodium bisulfite resulted in a higher detection of BfpA-producing EPEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505564; 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (BfpA protein, E coli); 0 (Culture Media); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC130815; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0095-1137; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Microbiologia, Universidade de Sao Paulo, and Instituto Butanta, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12037114</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12037114</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC130815</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1121</id>
<a1>Gomez-Duarte,O. G.</a1>
<a1>Chattopadhyay,S.</a1>
<a1>Weissman,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Sokurenko,E. V.</a1>
<t1>Genetic diversity of the gene cluster encoding longus, a type IV pilus of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>189</vo>
<is>24</is>
<sp>9145</sp>
<op>9149</op>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Multigene Family</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<ab>Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) strains produce a type IV pilus named Longus. We identified a 16-gene cluster involved in the biosynthesis of Longus that has 57 to 95% identity at the protein level to CFA/III, another type IV pilus of ETEC. Alleles of the Longus structural subunit gene lngA demonstrate a diversity of 12 to 19% at the protein level with strong positive selection for point replacements and horizontal transfer.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/EF595770; GENBANK/EU107087; GENBANK/EU107088; GENBANK/EU107089; GENBANK/EU107090; GENBANK/EU107091; GENBANK/EU107092; GENBANK/EU107093; GENBANK/EU107094; GENBANK/EU107095; GENBANK/EU107096; GENBANK/EU107097; GENBANK/EU107098; GENBANK/EU107099; GENBANK/EU107100; GENBANK/EU107101; GENBANK/EU107102; GENBANK/EU107103; GENBANK/EU107104; GENBANK/EU107105; GENBANK/EU107106; GENBANK/EU107107; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM60731/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (LngA protein, E coli); OID: NLM: PMC2168600; 2007/10/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5530; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, University of Iowa Children&#39;s Hospital, 200 Hawkins Drive, Iowa City, IA 52242, USA. oscar-gomez@uiowa.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17951389; JB.00722-07 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.00722-07</do>
<wp>20071019</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17951389</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2168600</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2805</id>
<a1>Gomez-Duarte,O. G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Donnenberg,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>PerA regulates the expression of genes coding for intimate adherence and localized adherence in enteropathogenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jo>Plasmid</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<sp>357</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1159</id>
<a1>Gomez-Duarte,O. G.</a1>
<a1>Ruiz-Tagle,A.</a1>
<a1>Gomez,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Viboud,G. I.</a1>
<a1>Jarvis,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Identification of lngA, the structural gene of longus type IV pilus of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Microbiology (Reading, England)</jf>
<jo>Microbiology</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>145 ( Pt 7)</vo>
<is>Pt 7</is>
<sp>1809</sp>
<op>1816</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/classification/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<ab>Human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) produces a type IV pilus termed longus which is encoded on large plasmids in association with colonization factor antigens (CFAs) and enterotoxins. A plasmid-derived 7 kbp BamHI DNA fragment hybridizing with an oligonucleotide probe designed from the amino-terminal amino acid sequence of the denatured 22 kDa structural longus pilin subunit was subcloned and sequenced. DNA sequencing analysis revealed an open reading frame, designated lngA, whose predicted amino acid sequence matched perfectly the N-terminal sequence of LngA obtained by Edman degradation. lngA is the first gene described of the longus gene cluster. Cloned lngA encoded and expressed a prepilin protein of 236 residues with a calculated mass of 25.17 kDa. The prepilin is apparently processed into a mature pilin of 206 residues with a calculated mass of 21.5 kDa. The predicted peptide sequence of lngA showed 78.8 and 37% identity to CFA/III pilin (CofA) of ETEC and the toxin-coregulated pilus (TcpA) of Vibrio cholerae. Peptide sequence homology between lngA and cofA was more prominent towards the amino terminus than within the carboxy region. Like other type IV pilins, LngA contains two cysteine residues towards the carboxy-terminal region. Transmission electron microscopy and immunoblot analysis of ETEC strains expressing either longus or CFA/III detected antigenic differences between native and denatured epitopes of these pili. In addition, differential regulation of pilus expression was identified when ETEC strains were grown in different media. Our data indicate that longus and CFA/III are two distinct but yet highly related type IV pili of ETEC.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/AF004308; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9430468; 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Enterotoxins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (LngA protein, E coli); 0 (TcpA protein, Vibrio cholerae); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1350-0872; 1350-0872</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10439420</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10439420</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1155</id>
<a1>Gutierrez-Cazarez,Z.</a1>
<a1>Qadri,F.</a1>
<a1>Albert,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Identification of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli harboring longus type IV pilus gene by DNA amplification</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1767</sp>
<op>1771</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins</k1>
<k1>Bangladesh</k1>
<k1>Chile</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Gene Amplification</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<ab>DNA amplification of lngA, the structural gene of longus type IV pilus produced by human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) was achieved by the use of specific oligonucleotide primers designed from the nucleotide sequence of lngA. A 630-bp fragment representing the entire lngA gene was amplified in eight prototype strains previously characterized as longus positive. Five ETEC strains producing colonization factor antigen III (CFA III) (also a type IV pilus) were also positive by PCR, confirming the DNA homology between CFA III and longus. None of the non-ETEC and non-E. coli enteropathogens studied showed the 0.63-kbp amplicon. The procedure thus detected only ETEC strains harboring type IV pili genes with or without other colonization factors. Except for five lngA PCR-positive, probe-positive strains, all lngA PCR-positive strains produced the pilin as demonstrated by immunoblotting. To test the amplification procedure in a clinical setting, a collection of 264 fresh clinical E. coli strains isolated from 88 Mexican children with diarrhea was screened by PCR. Among 82 ETEC isolates found, 30 (36.5%) were lngA PCR-positive. Twenty-seven percent of the children shed ETEC that possessed lngA. In parallel with DNA probes or PCR protocols to detect enterotoxin genes, the lngA PCR method may prove useful for detection of ETEC harboring type IV pilus genes in epidemiological studies.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505564; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (LngA protein, E coli); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC86583; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0095-1137; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Puebla, Mexico.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10790096</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10790096</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC86583</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1183</id>
<a1>Jarvis,K. G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Jerse,A. E.</a1>
<a1>McDaniel,T. K.</a1>
<a1>Donnenberg,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli contains a putative type III secretion system necessary for the export of proteins involved in attaching and effacing lesion formation</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Aug 15</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>7996</sp>
<op>8000</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Epithelium/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Intestines/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Rabbits/immunology</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Shigella flexneri/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Yersinia/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) causes a characteristic histopathology in intestinal epithelial cells called the attaching and effacing lesion. Although the histopathological lesion is well described the bacterial factors responsible for it are poorly characterized. We have identified four EPEC chromosomal genes whose predicted protein sequences are similar to components of a recently described secretory pathway (type III) responsible for exporting proteins lacking a typical signal sequence. We have designated the genes sepA, sepB, sepC, and sepD (sep, for secretion of E. coli proteins). The predicted Sep polypeptides are similar to the Lcr (low calcium response) and Ysc (yersinia secretion) proteins of Yersinia species and the Mxi (membrane expression of invasion plasmid antigens) and Spa (surface presentation of antigens) regions of Shigella flexneri. Culture supernatants of EPEC strain E2348/69 contain several polypeptides ranging in size from 110 kDa to 19 kDa. Proteins of comparable size were recognized by human convalescent serum from a volunteer experimentally infected with strain E2348/69. A sepB mutant of EPEC secreted only the 110-kDa polypeptide and was defective in the formation of attaching and effacing lesions and protein-tyrosine phosphorylation in tissue culture cells. These phenotypes were restored upon complementation with a plasmid carrying an intact sepB gene. These data suggest that the EPEC Sep proteins are components of a type III secretory apparatus necessary for the export of virulence determinants.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/Z49933; GENBANK/Z49972; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI32074/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Antibodies); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (SepB protein, E coli); OID: NLM: PMC41273; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, Department of Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Baltimore, MD, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7644527</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7644527</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC41273</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1147</id>
<a1>Khursigara,C.</a1>
<a1>Abul-Milh,M.</a1>
<a1>Lau,B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Lingwood,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Barnett Foster,D. E.</a1>
<t1>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli virulence factor bundle-forming pilus has a binding specificity for phosphatidylethanolamine</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>6573</sp>
<op>6579</op>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/biosynthesis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Liposomes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phosphatidylethanolamines/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>The bundle-forming pilus (BFP) of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC), an established virulence factor encoded on the EPEC adherence factor (EAF) plasmid, has been implicated in the formation of bacterial autoaggregates and in the localized adherence of EPEC to cultured epithelial cells. While understanding of the pathogenic mechanism of this organism is rapidly improving, a receptor ligand for BFP has not yet been identified. We now report, using both solid-phase and liposome binding assays, that BFP expression correlates with phosphatidylethanolamine (PE) binding. In a thin-layer chromatogram overlay assay, specific recognition of PE was documented for BFP-expressing strains, including E2348/69, a wild-type EPEC clinical isolate, as well as a laboratory strain, HB101, transformed with a bfp-carrying plasmid. Strains which did not express BFP did not bind PE, including a bfpA disruptional mutant of E2348/69, EAF plasmid-cured E2348/69, and HB101. E2348/69 also aggregated PE-containing liposomes but not phosphatidylcholine- or phosphatidylserine-containing liposomes, while BFP-negative strains did not produce aggregates with any tested liposomes. Purified BFP preparations bound commercial PE standards as well as a PE-containing band within lipid extracts from human epithelial cells and from E2348/69. Our results therefore indicate a specific interaction between BFP and PE and suggest that PE may serve as a BFP receptor for bacterial autoaggregation and may promote localized adherence to host cells, both of which contribute to bacterial pathogenesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (BfpA protein, E coli); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Liposomes); 0 (Phosphatidylethanolamines); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC100029; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Chemistry, Biology and Chemical Engineering, Ryerson University, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11598024</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/IAI.69.11.6573-6579.2001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11598024</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC100029</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1620</id>
<a1>Levine,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Noriega,F.</a1>
<t1>Ch. 18 Fimbrial Vaccines</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<sp>255-</sp>
<op>270</op>
<k1>Pili (Microbiology)</k1>
<k1>Pili, Sex</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae</k1>
<k1>Pili</k1>
<k1>Bacteria</k1>
<ab>Introduction: A Historical Perspective / James P. Duguid and David C. Old -- Ch. 1. Type 1 Fimbriae of Escherichia coli / Per Klemm and Karen Angeliki Krogfelt -- Ch. 2. S and FIC Fimbriae / Jorg Hacker and Joachim Morschhauser -- Ch. 3. Structure, Function, and Biogenesis of Escherichia coli P Pili / Meta J. Kuehn, David Haslam, Staffan Normark and Scott J. Hultgren -- Ch. 4. Fimbriae of Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli / Frits K. de Graaf and Wim Gaastra -- Ch. 5. Nonfimbrial Adhesins of Escherichia coli / M. Alexander Schmidt -- Ch. 6. Type 3 Fimbriae of the Enterobacteriaceae / Steven Clegg, Timo K. Korhonen, Douglas B. Hornick and Ann-Mari Tarkkanen -- Ch. 7. Salmonella Fimbriae / Steven Clegg and Dana L. Swenson -- Ch. 8. Bordetella pertussis Fimbriae / Frits R. Mooi -- Ch. 9. Type 4 Fimbriae / Jan M. Tennent and John S. Mattick -- Ch. 10. Pili (Fimbriae) of Neisseria gonorrhoeae / John K. Davies, J. Michael Koomey and H. Steven Seifert.</ab>
<no>viii; ill. ; 26 cm.; Note(s): Includes bibliographical references and index.; Responsibility: edited by Per Klemm. More Records: Show record information Vendor Info: Baker and Taylor YBP Library Services Baker &amp;amp; Taylor (BTCP YANK BKTY) 379.95 Status: active; Entry: 19931123; Update: 20100530</no>
<a2>Klemm,Per</a2>
<t2>Fimbriae : adhesion, genetics, biogenesis, and vaccines</t2>
<pb>CRC Press</pb>
<pp>Boca Raton</pp>
<sn>0849348943; 9780849348945; National Library: 9439029 LCCN: 93-44580</sn>
<an>29469391</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>WorldCat; Book; OCLC; WorldCat</sf>
<cn>LC: QR78.5; Dewey: 589.9/5; NLM: 1994 I-338; QR 78.5; NAL: QR78.5.F55</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1162</id>
<a1>Martinez,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Taddei,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Ruiz-Tagle,A.</a1>
<a1>Trabulsi,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Antibody response of children with enteropathogenic Escherichia coli infection to the bundle-forming pilus and locus of enterocyte effacement-encoded virulence determinants</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>179</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>269</sp>
<op>274</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins</k1>
<k1>Case-Control Studies</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/immunology/microbiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/immunology/microbiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin G/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Intestines/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) express a plasmid-encoded type IV pilus termed bundle-forming pilus, which is associated with the formation of bacterial microcolonies on cultured epithelial cells. Bacterial attachment and effacement of the enterocyte brush border membrane is attributed to a surface outer membrane protein adhesin termed intimin and EPEC-secreted proteins EspA, EspB, and EspD. Except for intimin, production in vivo or antibody response against these virulence determinants during natural EPEC infections in young children has not been demonstrated. Antibody responses against BfpA, intimin, EspA, and EspB were investigated in Brazilian children naturally infected with EPEC. Generally, IgG antibodies against BfpA and EspB were the most commonly found, followed by anti-EspA and intimin antibodies. Thus, bundle-forming pilus and locus of enterocyte attachment-encoded products are produced in vivo during natural EPEC infections and elicit an immune response against heterologous EPEC virulence determinants. These findings have important implications in the immunoprophylaxis against EPEC infections.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0413675; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (BfpA protein, E coli); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (EaeB protein, E coli); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (EspA protein, E coli); 0 (Immunoglobulin G); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1899; 0022-1899</sn>
<ad>Faculdade de Ciencias Farmaceuticas, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Brazil. mbmartin@usp.br</ad>
<an>PMID: 9841853; JID980365 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1086/314549</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9841853</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1134</id>
<a1>Monteiro-Neto,V.</a1>
<a1>Bando,S. Y.</a1>
<a1>Moreira-Filho,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of an outer membrane protein associated with haemagglutination and adhesive properties of enteroaggregative Escherichia coli O111:H12</t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>533</sp>
<op>547</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutination</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<ab>Diarrhoeagenic Escherichia coli strains of serotype O111:H12 are characterized by their aggregative pattern of adherence on cultured epithelial cells and thus are considered enteroaggregative E. coli (EAEC). We have previously shown that these EAEC strains lack the genes encoding the aggregative fimbriae I and II described in other heterologous EAEC strains. In this paper, we show compelling data suggesting that a plasmid-encoded outer membrane 58 kDa protein termed aggregative protein 58 (Ap58) produced by EAEC O111:H12 strains, is associated with the adherence capabilities and haemagglutination of animal red blood cells. This conclusion is supported by several lines of evidence: (i) adherent O111:H12 strains are able to produce Ap58; (ii) non-adherent O111:H12 strains are unable to produce Ap58; (iii) antibodies raised against Ap58 inhibited adherence and haemagglutination of epithelial and bovine red blood cells, respectively; (iv) a non-adherent E. coli K-12 host strain containing the ap58 gene determinant on plasmid pVM15 displayed abundant adherence to cultured HEp-2 cells; and (v) the purified Ap58 bound specifically to HEp-2 and bovine red blood cells. Our findings indicate that the aggregative adherence in the O111:H12 strains may be also mediated by non-fimbrial adhesins. We believe our data contribute to the understanding of the adherence mechanisms of these organisms.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100883691; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5814; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Microbiologia, Instituto de Ciencias Biomedicas, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12864813; 299 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12864813</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1194</id>
<a1>Nataro,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Yikang,D.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Savarino,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Kothary,M. H.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R.</a1>
<t1>Aggregative adherence fimbria I expression in enteroaggregative Escherichia coli requires two unlinked plasmid regions</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1126</sp>
<op>1131</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<ab>Adherence to HEp-2 cells by many enteroaggregative Escherichia coli (EAggEC) strains is associated with the expression of flexible, bundle-forming fimbriae 2 to 3 nm in diameter, designated aggregative adherence fimbriae I (AAF/I). We have previously reported the molecular cloning and TnphoA mutagenesis of AAF/I genes from the large plasmid of prototype EAggEC strain 17-2 (J. P. Nataro, Y. Deng, D. R. Maneval, A. L. German, W. C. Martin, and M. M. Levine, Infect. Immun. 60:2297-2304, 1992). Here, we report that further mapping and subcloning of AAF/I regions suggest that expression of the fimbriae requires two separate plasmid regions (designated regions 1 and 2). Approximately 9 kb of DNA unnecessary for fimbrial expression separates the two regions; this intervening segment encodes the EAggEC heat-stable enterotoxin (EAST1). Neither region was capable of conferring aggregative HEp-2 adherence (AA) when cloned individually; when the two regions were cloned as a single fragment or when each was cloned into a different vector and introduced into the same E. coli HB101 cell, AA was restored. AA-positive constructs also expressed human erythrocyte hemagglutination, autoagglutination in broth cultures, and the production of AAF/I as detected by immunogold electron microscopy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 1R29-AI-33096/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-AI-15096/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (AggA protein, E coli); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC302849; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore 21201.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8094379</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8094379</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC302849</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1136</id>
<a1>Negrete-Abascal,E.</a1>
<a1>Reyes,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Garcia,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Vaca,S.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Garcia,O.</a1>
<a1>Zenteno,E.</a1>
<a1>De La Garza,M.</a1>
<t1>Flagella and Motility in Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>185</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>664</sp>
<op>668</op>
<k1>Actinobacillus Infections/veterinary</k1>
<k1>Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae/genetics/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Culture Media</k1>
<k1>Flagella/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Movement</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Swine Diseases/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae has been considered nonmotile and nonflagellate. In this work, it is demonstrated that A. pleuropneumoniae produces flagella composed of a 65-kDa protein with an N-terminal amino acid sequence that shows 100% identity with those of Escherichia coli, Salmonella, and Shigella flagellins. The DNA sequence obtained through PCR of the fliC gene in A. pleuropneumoniae showed considerable identity (93%) in its 5&amp;#39; and 3&amp;#39; ends with the DNA sequences of corresponding genes in E. coli, Salmonella enterica, and Shigella spp. The motility of A. pleuropneumoniae was observed in tryptic soy or brain heart infusion soft agar media, and it is influenced by temperature. Flagella and motility may be involved in the survival and pathogenesis of A. pleuropneumoniae in pigs.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/AF515472; GENBANK/AF515473; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Culture Media); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); OID: NLM: PMC145319; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Mexico. negretee@yahoo.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 12511514</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12511514</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC145319</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1142</id>
<a1>Nishimura,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Nunes,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Guth,B. E.</a1>
<t1>Prevalence of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli strains harboring the longus pilus gene in Brazil</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>2606</sp>
<op>2608</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Brazil</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/classification/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Serotyping</k1>
<ab>The longus type IV pilus gene (lngA) was highly prevalent (32.8%) among Brazilian enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli strains producing both heat-labile and heat-stable enterotoxins and bearing the CFA/I, CS1CS3, or CS6 antigen. Furthermore, lngA was more often found in strains isolated from children with diarrhea than in strains isolated from children without diarrhea.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505564; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Enterotoxins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (LngA protein, E coli); 0 (heat stable toxin (E coli)); 0 (heat-labile enterotoxin, E coli); OID: NLM: PMC120555; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0095-1137; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Microbiologia, Imunologia e Parasitologia, Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo Escola Paulista de Medicina, UNIFESP, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12089285</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12089285</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC120555</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1152</id>
<a1>Parissi-Crivelli,A.</a1>
<a1>Parissi-Crivelli,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Recognition of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli virulence determinants by human colostrum and serum antibodies</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>2696</sp>
<op>2700</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/analysis/blood</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins</k1>
<k1>Colostrum/immunology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/immunology/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/immunology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Human colostra and sera collected from Mexican mothers and their children at birth and 6 months thereafter were studied for the presence of antibodies against the bundle-forming pilus and several chromosomal virulence gene products (intimin and secreted proteins EspA and EspB) of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC). Among 21 colostrum samples studied, 76, 71.5, 57, and 47% of them contained immunoglobulin A (IgA) antibodies against EspA, intimin, EspB, and BfpA, respectively. Interestingly, there was a difference in IgG response to EPEC antigens between the sera from neonates and sera from the same children 6 months later. While the number of neonates reacting to Esps and intimin diminished when they reached 6 months of age, those reacting with BfpA increased from 9 to 71%. Intimin from an enterohemorrhagic E. coli strain was also recognized by most of the samples reacting with EPEC intimin. These data suggest that Bfp and Esps elicit an antibody response during the early days of life of neonates and support the value of breast-feeding in areas of the world where bacterial diarrheal infections are endemic.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505564; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (BfpA protein, E coli); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (EspA protein, E coli); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC87001; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0095-1137; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Centro de Investigaciones en Ciencias Microbiologicas, Instituto de Ciencias, Benemerita Autonoma Universidad de Puebla, Puebla, Mexico.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10878066</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10878066</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC87001</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1618</id>
<a1>Payne,Claire M.</a1>
<a1>Fass,Ronnie</a1>
<a1>Bernstein,Harris</a1>
<a1>Giron,Jorge</a1>
<a1>Bernstein,Carol</a1>
<a1>Dvorak,Katerina</a1>
<a1>Garewal,Harinder</a1>
<t1>Pathogenesis of diarrhea in the adult: diagnostic challenges and life-threatening conditions</t1>
<jo>Eur. J. Gastroenterol. Hepatol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>18</vo>
<sp>1047</sp>
<op>1051</op>
<no>[Article]</no>
<sf>Leading Articles</sf>
<lk>http://ovidsp.ovid.com/ovidweb.cgi?T=JS&amp;NEWS=N&amp;PAGE=fulltext&amp;AN=00042737-200610000-00003&amp;D=ovfth</lk>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1161</id>
<a1>Pelayo,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Scaletsky,I. C.</a1>
<a1>Pedroso,M. Z.</a1>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Frankel,G.</a1>
<a1>Trabulsi,L. R.</a1>
<t1>Virulence properties of atypical EPEC strains</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>41</sp>
<op>49</op>
<k1>Actins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/classification/genetics/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cytotoxins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/drug effects/metabolism/pathogenicity/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gentamicins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Hemolysin Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hemolysis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immune Sera/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Virulence/physiology</k1>
<ab>Virulence properties of 31 atypical enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) strains isolated from cases of diarrhoea were examined. All except two strains adhered to HEp-2 cells in a localised adherence-like (LAL) pattern. With the exception of two strains, all were fluorescent actin staining (FAS) positive. Gentamicin HEp-2 invasion assay studies showed that all strains were invasive. Transmission electron microscopy of infected HEp-2 cells showed the characteristic attaching and effacing lesion and invasion of the cultured cells. Of the nine strains that hybridised with a DNA probe for alpha-haemolysin, five were haemolytic within 3 h of incubation, while the remaining strains were haemolytic only after incubation for 24 h. Three strains produced enterohaemolysin on blood agar. None of the 31 strains of E. coli induced fluid accumulation in the rabbit intestinal loop assay or displayed cytotoxic effects in HeLa and Vero cells. All the strains belonging to serotypes O26:H11, O26:H- and 0119:H2 expressed intimin beta, whereas all the strains from serotype O55:H7 expressed intimin gamma. The strains belonging to serogroup O111 expressed a non-typable intimin. The participation of intimin in LAL was supported by adhesion inhibition experiments in which antibodies to intimin significantly reduced the level of LAL.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0224131; 0 (Actins); 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Cytotoxins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Gentamicins); 0 (Hemolysin Proteins); 0 (Immune Sera); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-2615; 0022-2615</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Microbiologia, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9920124</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9920124</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1684</id>
<a1>Phillips,A. D.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J.</a1>
<a1>Hicks,S.</a1>
<a1>Dougan,G.</a1>
<a1>Frankel,G.</a1>
<t1>Intimin from enteropathogenic Escherichia coli mediates remodelling of the eukaryotic cell surface</t1>
<jf>Microbiology (Reading, England)</jf>
<jo>Microbiology</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>146 ( Pt 6)</vo>
<is>Pt 6</is>
<sp>1333</sp>
<op>1344</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Caco-2 Cells</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Culture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intestines/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Microvilli/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Virulence/physiology</k1>
<ab>Adhesion to cultured epithelial cells by enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) is associated with extensive rearrangement of the host cell cytoskeleton. Evidence has been presented that EPEC adhesion is associated with activation of signal transduction pathways leading to production of a characteristic histopathological feature known as the attaching and effacing (A/E) lesion. A/E lesion formation requires intimin, an EPEC adhesion molecule and several EPEC secreted proteins (EspA, B, D and Tir) involved in cell signalling and protein translocation. In this study it is shown that HEp-2 cells respond during the early stages of infection with two wild-type EPEC strains (B171 and E2348/69) by producing microvillus-like processes (MLP) at the site of initial bacterial adherence. Intimin appears to play a key role in MLP elongation. At later stages of infection with these wild-type EPEC strains, when A/E lesions have formed, the MLP were reduced in number and length to appear as at time zero, and the cell surface in the vicinity of bacterial clusters appeared unaffected. In contrast, infection with EspA- or EspB-negative, but intimin-positive, EPEC strains (UMD872 and UMD864, respectively) resulted in enhanced MLP proliferation and formation of &amp;#39;cage-like&amp;#39; structures engulfing the bacteria. Inoculating HEp-2 cells with intimin-coated latex spheres induced similar &amp;#39;cage-like&amp;#39; structures. Caco-2 cells did not show intimin-induced microvillus elongation in response to EPEC infection, although microvillus effacement and reduction in number occurred. Similar phenomena appeared on B171 and E2348/69 infection of paediatric intestine using in vitro organ culture, i.e. elongated microvilli were seen in association with small colonies and at the periphery of large localized colonies, along with evidence of microvillus breakdown and debris in the colony centre. These results show that intimin activates signal transduction pathways involved in the remodelling of the eukaryotic cell surface, probably via binding to a receptor encoded by the host cell.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9430468; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1350-0872; 1350-0872</sn>
<ad>University Department of Paediatric Gastroenterology, Royal Free Hospital, London NW3 2QG, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10846212</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10846212</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1145</id>
<a1>Pichel,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Binsztein,N.</a1>
<a1>Qadri,F.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Type IV longus pilus of enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli: occurrence and association with toxin types and colonization factors among strains isolated in Argentina</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>694</sp>
<op>697</op>
<k1>Australia/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Enterotoxins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Prevalence</k1>
<k1>Serotyping</k1>
<ab>The longus type IV pilus structural gene (lngA) was sought among 217 clinical enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC) strains isolated in Argentina. lngA was present in 20.7% of the isolates and was highly associated with ETEC producing heat-stable toxin and the most common colonization factors. The prevalence of longus among ETEC strains in Argentina was comparable to that of colonization factor antigen I (CFA/I), CFA/II, and CFA/IV in other regions of the world.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505564; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Enterotoxins); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (LngA protein, E coli); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC153402; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0095-1137; 0095-1137</sn>
<ad>Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Infecciosas, ANLIS &quot;Carlos G. Malbran,&quot; Buenos Aires, Argentina.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11826000</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11826000</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC153402</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1154</id>
<a1>Qadri,F.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Helander,A.</a1>
<a1>Begum,Y. A.</a1>
<a1>Asaduzzaman,M.</a1>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Negrete,E.</a1>
<a1>Albert,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Human antibody response to longus type IV pilus and study of its prevalence among enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli in Bangladesh by using monoclonal antibodies</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>181</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2071</sp>
<op>2074</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/biosynthesis/blood</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibody Specificity</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/analysis</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<ab>Mouse monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) were derived against longus (CS20), a type IV pilus expressed by human enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC). One MAb (ICA39) detected longus in 56 (8.5%) of 662 ETEC isolates obtained from a routine surveillance of diarrheal stools from children and adults. Five patients with diarrhea from whom longus-positive ETEC were isolated were also recruited. Of these 61 isolates, 50 were positive for other colonization factors (CFs; 61% for CFA/II and 21% for CFA/I), and 11 were negative for any of the other 8 CFs that were tested. They were either positive for the heat-stable enterotoxin (ST; n=29) or for the heat-labile enterotoxin (LT) and ST (n=32). All longus-positive ETEC were confirmed by polymerase chain reaction to harbor lngA, the longus structural pilin gene. Sera and/or fecal extracts from the patients reacted with the 22-kDa pilin polypeptide in immunoblots and ELISA. These studies show that longus is prevalent among ETEC in Bangladesh and that longus gives rise to IgA antibody responses in patients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0413675; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (colonization factor antigens); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); 1999/11/02 [received]; 2000/01/31 [revised]; 2000/05/16 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1899; 0022-1899</sn>
<ad>Laboratory Sciences Division, ICDDR, B, Dhaka 1000, Bangladesh. fqadri@icddrb.org</ad>
<an>PMID: 10837196; JID991330 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1086/315507</do>
<wp>20000516</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10837196</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1125</id>
<a1>Rendon,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Erdem,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Monteiro-Neto,V.</a1>
<a1>Vazquez,A.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Puente,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Commensal and pathogenic Escherichia coli use a common pilus adherence factor for epithelial cell colonization</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jun 19</fd>
<vo>104</vo>
<is>25</is>
<sp>10637</sp>
<op>10642</op>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular/microbiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intestinal Mucosa/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Liver Neoplasms/microbiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Symbiosis</k1>
<ab>Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) O157:H7 is a food-borne pathogen that causes hemorrhagic colitis and the hemolytic uremic syndrome. Colonization of the human gut mucosa and production of potent Shiga toxins are critical virulence traits of EHEC. Although EHEC O157:H7 contains numerous putative pili operons, their role in the colonization of the natural bovine or accidental human hosts remains largely unknown. We have identified in EHEC an adherence factor, herein called E. coli common pilus (ECP), composed of a 21-kDa pilin subunit whose amino acid sequence corresponds to the product of the yagZ (renamed ecpA) gene present in all E. coli genomes sequenced to date. ECP production was demonstrated in 121 (71.6%) of a total of 169 ecpA+ strains representing intestinal and extraintestinal pathogenic as well as normal flora E. coli. High-resolution ultrastructural and immunofluorescence studies demonstrated the presence of abundant peritrichous fibrillar structures emanating from the bacterial surface forming physical bridges between bacteria adhering to cultured epithelial cells. Isogenic ecpA mutants of EHEC O157:H7 or fecal commensal E. coli showed significant reduction in adherence to cultured epithelial cells. Our data suggest that ECP production is a common feature of E. coli colonizing the human gut or other host tissues. ECP is a pilus of EHEC O157:H7 with a potential role in host epithelial cell colonization and may represent a mechanism of adherence of both pathogenic and commensal E. coli.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI66012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC1890562; 2007/06/11 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17563352; 0704104104 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0704104104</do>
<wp>20070611</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17563352</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1890562</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1116</id>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Erdem,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Schuller,S.</a1>
<a1>Okeke,I. N.</a1>
<a1>Lucas,M.</a1>
<a1>Sivananthan,A.</a1>
<a1>Phillips,A. D.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Puente,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>The Escherichia coli common pilus and the bundle-forming pilus act in concert during the formation of localized adherence by enteropathogenic E. coli</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>191</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3451</sp>
<op>3461</op>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli/genetics/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Flow Cytometry</k1>
<k1>HT29 Cells</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Transmission</k1>
<ab>Although the bundle-forming pilus (BFP) of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) mediates microcolony formation on epithelial cells, the adherence of BFP-deficient mutants is significantly abrogated, but the mutants are still adherent due to the presence of intimin and possibly other adhesins. In this study we investigated the contribution of the recently described E. coli common pilus (ECP) to the overall adherence properties of EPEC. We found that ECP and BFP structures can be simultaneously observed in the course (between zero time and 7 h during infection) of formation of localized adherence on cultured epithelial cells. These two pilus types colocalized at different levels of the microcolony topology, tethering the adhering bacteria. No evidence of BFP disappearance was found after prolonged infection. When expressed from a plasmid present in nonadherent E. coli HB101, ECP rendered this organism highly adherent at levels comparable to those of HB101 expressing the BFP. Purified ECP bound in a dose-dependent manner to epithelial cells, and the binding was blocked with anti-ECP antibodies, confirming that the pili possess adhesin properties. An ECP mutant showed only a modest reduction in adherence to cultured cells due to background expression levels of BFP and intimin. However, isogenic mutants not expressing EspA or BFP were significantly less adherent when the ecpA gene was also deleted. Furthermore, a DeltaespA DeltaecpA double mutant (unable to translocate Tir and to establish intimate adhesion) was at least 10-fold less adherent than the DeltaespA and DeltaecpA single mutants, even in the presence of BFP. A Delta bfp DeltaespA DeltaecpA triple mutant showed the least adherence compared to the wild type and all the isogenic mutant strains tested, suggesting that ECP plays a synergistic role in adherence. Our data indicate that ECP is an accessory factor that, in association with BFP and other adhesins, contributes to the multifactorial complex interaction of EPEC with host epithelial cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091230; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI66012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (EspA protein, E coli); 147680-16-8 (Fimbriae Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC2681888; 2009/02/13 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5530; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, 1501 N. Campbell Ave., Tucson, Arizona 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19218393; JB.01539-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.01539-08</do>
<wp>20090213</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19218393</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2681888</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1117</id>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Avelino,F.</a1>
<a1>Phillips,A. D.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Puente,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Synergistic role of curli and cellulose in cell adherence and biofilm formation of attaching and effacing Escherichia coli and identification of Fis as a negative regulator of curli</t1>
<jf>Environmental microbiology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>992</sp>
<op>1006</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cellulose/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Factor For Inversion Stimulation Protein/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Dosage</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics</k1>
<ab>Curli are adhesive fimbriae of Escherichia coli and Salmonella enterica. Expression of curli (csgA) and cellulose (bcsA) is co-activated by the transcriptional activator CsgD. In this study, we investigated the contribution of curli and cellulose to the adhesive properties of enterohaemorragic (EHEC) O157:H7 and enteropathogenic E. coli (EPEC) O127:H6. While single mutations in csgA, csgD or bcsA in EPEC and EHEC had no dramatic effect on cell adherence, double csgAbcsA mutants were significantly less adherent than the single mutants or wild-type strains to human colonic HT-29 epithelial cells or to cow colon tissue in vitro. Overexpression of csgD (carried on plasmid pCP994) in a csgD mutant, but not in the single csgA or bscA mutants, led to significant increase in adherence and biofilm formation in EPEC and EHEC, suggesting that synchronized over-production of curli and cellulose enhances bacterial adherence. In line with this finding, csgD transcription was activated significantly in the presence of cultured epithelial cells as compared with growth in tissue culture medium. Analysis of the influence of virulence and global regulators in the production of curli in EPEC identified Fis (factor for inversion stimulation) as a, heretofore unrecognized, negative transcriptional regulator of csgA expression. An EPEC E2348/69Deltafis produced abundant amounts of curli whereas a double fis/csgD mutant yielded no detectable curli production. Our data suggest that curli and cellulose act in concert to favour host colonization, biofilm formation and survival in different environments.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100412; GR: AI063211/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI066012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI063211-04/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100883692; 0 (CsgD protein, E coli); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Factor For Inversion Stimulation Protein); 0 (Fis protein, E coli); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (csgA protein, E coli); 9004-34-6 (Cellulose); NIHMS91917; OID: NLM: NIHMS91917; OID: NLM: PMC2672964; 2009/11/14 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-2920; 1462-2912</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, 1501 N. Tucson, AZ 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19187284; EMI1824 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01824.x</do>
<wp>20091114</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19187284</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2672964</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1114</id>
<a1>Samadder,P.</a1>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Jordan,D.</a1>
<a1>Tarr,P. I.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>The Escherichia coli ycbQRST operon encodes fimbriae with laminin-binding and epithelial cell adherence properties in Shiga-toxigenic E. coli O157:H7</t1>
<jf>Environmental microbiology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar 10</fd>
<ab>Summary The human pathogen Shiga-toxigenic Escherichia coli (STEC) O157:H7 contains a ycbQRST fimbrial-like operon, which shares significant homology to the family of F17 fimbrial biogenesis genes f17ADCG found in enterotoxigenic E. coli. We report that growth of STEC O157:H7 strain EDL933 in minimal Minca medium at 37 degrees C and during adherence to epithelial cells led to the production of fine peritrichous fimbriae, which were found to be composed of a major subunit of 18 kDa whose N-terminal amino acid sequence matched the predicted protein product of the ycbQ gene; and showed significant homology to the F17a-A fimbrin. Similar to the F17 fimbriae, the purified STEC fimbriae and the recombinant YcbQ protein fused to a His peptide tag bound laminin, but not fibronectin or collagen. Thus, we propose the name E. coli YcbQ laminin-binding fimbriae (ELF) to designate the fimbriae encoded by the ycbQRST operon. The role of ELF as an adherence factor of STEC to cultured epithelial cells was investigated. We provide compelling evidence demonstrating that ELF contributes to adherence of STEC to human intestinal epithelial cells and to cow and pig gut tissue in vitro. Deletion in the fimbrin subunit gene elfA (or ycbQ) in STEC strain EDL933 led to an isogenic strain, which showed significant reduction (60%) in adherence to HEp-2 cells in comparison with the parental strain. In addition, antibodies against the purified ELF also partially blocked adherence of two STEC O157:H7 strains. These observations suggest that ELF functions as an accessory adherence factor that, along with other known redundant adhesins, contributes to the overall adhesive properties of STEC O157:H7 providing these organisms with ecological advantages to survive in different hosts and in the environment.</ab>
<no>JID: 100883692; aheadofprint</no>
<sn>1462-2920; 1462-2912</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19508558; EMI1906 [pii]</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01906.x</do>
<wp>20090310</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19508558</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1118</id>
<a1>Schuller,S.</a1>
<a1>Lucas,M.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Phillips,A. D.</a1>
<t1>The ex vivo response of human intestinal mucosa to enteropathogenic Escherichia coli infection</t1>
<jf>Cellular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Cell.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>521</sp>
<op>530</op>
<k1>Enteropathogenic Escherichia coli/growth &amp; development/immunology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Intestinal Mucosa/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Organ Culture Techniques/methods</k1>
<k1>Toll-Like Receptor 5/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>In vitro organ culture (IVOC) represents a gold standard model to study enteropathogenic E. coli (EPEC) infection of human intestinal mucosa. However, the optimal examination of the bacterial-host cell interaction requires a directional epithelial exposure, without serosal or cut surface stimulation. A polarized IVOC system (pIVOC) was developed in order to overcome such limitations: apical EPEC infection produced negligible bacterial leakage via biopsy edges, resulted in enhanced colonization compared with standard IVOC, and showed evidence of bacterial detachment, as in natural rabbit EPEC infections. Examination of mucosal innate immune responses in pIVOC showed both interleukin (IL)-8 mRNA and protein levels were significantly increased after apical EPEC infection. Increased IL-8 levels mainly depended on flagellin expression as fliC-negative EPEC did not elicit a significant IL-8 response despite increased mucosal colonization compared with wild-type EPEC. In addition, apical application of purified flagella significantly increased IL-8 protein levels over non-infected controls. Immunofluorescence staining of EPEC-infected small intestinal biopsies revealed apical and basolateral distribution of Toll-like receptor (TLR) 5 on epithelium, suggesting that EPEC can trigger mucosal IL-8 responses by apical flagellin/TLR5 interaction ex vivo and does not require access to the basolateral membrane as postulated in cell culture models.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100302; GR: R01 DK058957-07/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DK058957-09/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37 AI021657-22/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37 AI021657-23/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R37AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100883691; 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (FliC protein, E coli); 0 (Interleukin-8); 0 (TLR5 protein, human); 0 (Toll-Like Receptor 5); NIHMS105491; OID: NLM: NIHMS105491; OID: NLM: PMC2676445; 2008/12/30 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-5822; 1462-5814</sn>
<ad>Centre for Paediatric Gastroenterology, UCL Medical School, Royal Free Campus, London, UK. s.schuller@medsch.ucl.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 19134113; CMI1275 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-5822.2008.01275.x</do>
<wp>20081230</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19134113</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2676445</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1173</id>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Bailey,C.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>DiRita,V. J.</a1>
<a1>Silveira,W. D.</a1>
<a1>Vettore,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Cloning and characterization of the gene encoding the OmpU outer membrane protein of Vibrio cholerae</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5406</sp>
<op>5409</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Vibrio cholerae/genetics</k1>
<ab>The OmpU outer membrane protein is a member of the ToxR regulon of Vibrio cholerae and has recently been shown to be a potential adherence factor for this species. Using PCR and degenerate oligonucleotide primers based on internal peptide sequences of purified OmpU, we have cloned and sequenced the gene encoding OmpU. The ompU gene is predicted to encode a 36,646-molecular-weight protein which is present in both cholera toxin-positive and -negative V. cholerae O1 and O139 strains.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/U73751; GR: AI19716/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI31645/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (OmpU protein, Vibrio cholerae); OID: NLM: PMC174538; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8945596</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8945596</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC174538</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1179</id>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Silveira,W. D.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>The OmpU outer membrane protein, a potential adherence factor of Vibrio cholerae</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>4433</sp>
<op>4438</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/chemistry/immunology</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/chemistry/immunology</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Cholera/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells</k1>
<k1>Fibronectins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Immunization, Passive</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Vibrio cholerae/chemistry/immunology</k1>
<ab>Expression of the OmpU outer membrane protein of Vibrio cholerae is positively regulated by toxR, which also regulates critical virulence factors such as cholera toxin and the toxin-coregulated pilus colonization factor. In this study, we have characterized the 38-kDa OmpU protein and investigated its role in the adhesion of V. cholerae to mammalian cells. The amino-terminal sequence of OmpU has similarity with the sequences of Haemophilus influenzae HMW1 and HMW2 adhesins, which, in turn, also have similarity with the sequence of Bordetella pertussis filamentous hemagglutinin. A monoclonal antibody directed against FHA recognized both V. cholerae OmpU and Escherichia coli OmpA, and polyclonal anti-OmpU antibodies recognized FHA and E. coli OmpA, suggesting the existence of common epitopes among these proteins. OmpU was strongly recognized by convalescent-phase serum from volunteers experimentally infected with virulent V. cholerae strains, indicating that OmpU is immunogenic and produced in vivo. OmpU selectively bound to fibronectin and to an arginine-glycine-asparagine (RGD) tripeptide but not to other matrix glycoproteins tested such as collagen or laminin. Antibodies directed against OmpU or their F(ab)2 fragments completely inhibited adhesion of several V. cholerae strains to HeLa, HEp-2, Caco-2, and Henle 407 epithelial cells and also inhibited intestinal colonization and conferred protection in newborn mice against both biotypes (El Tor and classical) of V. cholerae O1. Collectively, these data indicate that OmpU has adhesive properties which may play a role in the pathogenesis of cholera.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI19716/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Fibronectins); 0 (OmpU protein, Vibrio cholerae); OID: NLM: PMC173631; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7591082</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7591082</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC173631</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1148</id>
<a1>Sperandio,V.</a1>
<a1>Torres,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Quorum sensing is a global regulatory mechanism in enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>183</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>5187</sp>
<op>5197</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Carbon-Sulfur Lyases</k1>
<k1>Down-Regulation</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Flagella/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Up-Regulation</k1>
<ab>Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) O157:H7 is responsible for outbreaks of bloody diarrhea and hemolytic-uremic syndrome in many countries. EHEC virulence mechanisms include the production of Shiga toxins (Stx) and formation of attaching and effacing (AE) lesions on intestinal epithelial cells. We recently reported that genes involved in the formation of the AE lesion were regulated by quorum sensing through autoinducer-2, which is synthesized by the product of the luxS gene. In this study we hybridized an E. coli gene array with cDNA synthesized from RNA that was extracted from EHEC strain 86-24 and its isogenic luxS mutant. We observed that 404 genes were regulated by luxS at least fivefold, which comprises approximately 10% of the array genes; 235 of these genes were up-regulated and 169 were down-regulated in the wild-type strain compared to in the luxS mutant. Down-regulated genes included several involved in cell division, as well as ribosomal and tRNA genes. Consistent with this pattern of gene expression, the luxS mutant grows faster than the wild-type strain (generation times of 37.5 and 60 min, respectively, in Dulbecco modified Eagle medium). Up-regulated genes included several involved in the expression and assembly of flagella, motility, and chemotaxis. Using operon::lacZ fusions to class I, II, and III flagellar genes, we were able to confirm this transcriptional regulation. We also observed fewer flagella by Western blotting and electron microscopy and decreased motility halos in semisolid agar in the luxS mutant. The average swimming speeds for the wild-type strain and the luxS mutant are 12.5 and 6.6 microm/s, respectively. We also observed an increase in the production of Stx due to quorum sensing. Genes encoding Stx, which are transcribed along with lambda-like phage genes, are induced by an SOS response, and genes involved in the SOS response were also regulated by quorum sensing. These results indicate that quorum sensing is a global regulatory mechanism for basic physiological functions of E. coli as well as for virulence factors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI41325/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); EC 4.4.- (Carbon-Sulfur Lyases); EC 4.4.1.21 (LuxS protein, Bacteria); OID: NLM: PMC95396; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development and Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11489873</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11489873</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC95396</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1139</id>
<a1>Torres,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Perna,N. T.</a1>
<a1>Burland,V.</a1>
<a1>Blattner,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Avelino-Flores,F.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Identification and characterization of lpfABCC&amp;#39;DE, a fimbrial operon of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>70</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>5416</sp>
<op>5427</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enteritis/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/genetics/pathogenicity/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics/immunology/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<ab>The mechanisms underlying the adherence of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and other enterohemorrhagic E. coli (EHEC) strains to intestinal epithelial cells are poorly understood. We have identified a chromosomal region (designated lpfABCC&amp;#39;DE) in EHEC O157:H7 containing six putative open reading frames that was found to be closely related to the long polar (LP) fimbria operon (lpf) of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium, both in gene order and in conservation of the deduced amino acid sequences. We show that lpfABCC&amp;#39;DE is organized as an operon and that its expression is induced during the exponential growth phase. The lpf genes from EHEC strain EDL933 were introduced into a nonfimbriated (Fim(-)) E. coli K-12 strain, and the transformed strain produced fimbriae as visualized by electron microscopy and adhered to tissue culture cells. Anti-LpfA antiserum recognized a ca. 16-kDa LpfA protein when expressed under regulation of the T7 promoter system. The antiserum also cross-reacted with the LP fimbriae in immunogold electron microscopy and Western blot experiments. Isogenic E. coli O157:H7 lpf mutants derived from strains 86-24 and AGT300 showed slight reductions in adherence to tissue culture cells and formed fewer microcolonies compared with their wild-type parent strains. The adherence and microcolony formation phenotypes were restored when the lpf operon was introduced on a plasmid. We propose that LP fimbriae participate in the interaction of E. coli O157:H7 with eukaryotic cells by assisting in microcolony formation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI41325/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); OID: NLM: PMC128367; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development and Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12228266</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12228266</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC128367</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1127</id>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Lyons,S.</a1>
<a1>Chaparro,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Hernandez,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Ledesma,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Rendon,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Gewirtz,A. T.</a1>
<a1>Klose,K. E.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Identification of proinflammatory flagellin proteins in supernatants of Vibrio cholerae O1 by proteomics analysis</t1>
<jf>Molecular &amp; cellular proteomics : MCP</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Proteomics</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2374</sp>
<op>2383</op>
<k1>Culture Media, Conditioned/chemistry/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/biosynthesis/chemistry/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>HT29 Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation Mediators/analysis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/analysis/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Organisms, Genetically Modified</k1>
<k1>Proteomics/methods</k1>
<k1>Vibrio cholerae O1/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>The genome of Vibrio cholerae contains five flagellin genes that encode proteins (FlaA-E) of 39-41 kDa with 61-82% identity among them. Although the existing live oral attenuated vaccine strains against cholera are protective in humans, there is an intrinsic residual cytotoxic and inflammatory component associated with these candidate vaccine strains. Bacterial flagellins are known to be potent inducers of proinflammatory molecules via activation of Toll-like receptor 5. Here we found that purified flagella from wild type V. cholerae 395 induced significant release of interleukin (IL)-8 from cultured HT-29 human colonic epithelial cells. Furthermore we found that filtered supernatants of KKV90, a DeltaflaA isogenic strain unable to produce flagella, were still able to activate production of IL-8 albeit to significantly lower levels than the wild type, suggesting that other activators of proinflammatory molecules were still present in these supernatants. A comparative proteomics analysis of secreted proteins of V. cholerae 395 and KKV90 identified additional proteins with potential to induce IL-8 release in HT-29 cells. Secreted proteins in the range of 30-45 kDa identified by two-dimensional electrophoresis and mass spectrometry revealed the presence of two additional flagellins, FlaC and FlaD, that appeared to be secreted 3- and 6-fold more, respectively, in the mutant compared with the wild type. Double isogenic mutants flaAC and flaAD were unable to trigger IL-8 release from HT-29 cells. In sum, we have shown that purified flagella and secreted flagellin proteins (FlaC and FlaD) are inducers of IL-8 release from epithelial cells via Toll-like receptor 5. This observation may explain, in part, the observed reactogenicity of cholera vaccine strains in humans.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: AI43486/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA02307-26/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: ES06694/ES/NIEHS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DK061417/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101125647; 0 (Culture Media, Conditioned); 0 (Inflammation Mediators); 0 (Interleukin-8); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); 133606-66-3 (flaA protein, bacteria); 2006/09/22 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1535-9476; 1535-9476</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16998199; M600228-MCP200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1074/mcp.M600228-MCP200</do>
<wp>20060922</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16998199</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1122</id>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Monteiro-Neto,V.</a1>
<a1>Ledesma,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Jordan,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Francetic,O.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Puente,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Intestinal adherence associated with type IV pili of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7</t1>
<jf>The Journal of clinical investigation</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Invest.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>117</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3519</sp>
<op>3529</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/cytology/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/cytology/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Hemolytic-Uremic Syndrome/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intestinal Mucosa/cytology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Protein Subunits/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Cell Surface/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<ab>Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) O157:H7 causes hemorrhagic colitis and hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) by colonizing the gut mucosa and producing Shiga toxins (Stx). The only factor clearly demonstrated to play a role in EHEC adherence to intestinal epithelial cells is intimin, which binds host cell integrins and nucleolin, as well as a receptor (Tir) that it injects into the host cell. Here we report that EHEC O157:H7 produces adhesive type IV pili, which we term hemorrhagic coli pilus (HCP), composed of a 19-kDa pilin subunit (HcpA) that is encoded by the hcpA chromosomal gene. HCP were observed as bundles of fibers greater than 10 microm in length that formed physical bridges between bacteria adhering to human and bovine host cells. Sera of HUS patients, but not healthy individuals, recognized HcpA, suggesting that the pili are produced in vivo during EHEC infections. Inactivation of the hcpA gene in EHEC EDL933 resulted in significantly reduced adherence to cultured human intestinal and bovine renal epithelial cells and to porcine and bovine gut explants. An escN mutant, which is unable to translocate Tir, adhered less than the hcpA mutant, suggesting that adherence mediated by intimin-Tir interactions is a prelude to HCP-mediated adherence. An hcpA and stx1,2 triple mutant and an hcpA mutant had similar levels of adherence to bovine and human epithelial cells while a stx1,2 double mutant had only a minor defect in adherence, indicating that HCP-mediated adherence and cytotoxicity are independent events. Our data establish that EHEC O157:H7 HCP are intestinal colonization factors that are likely to contribute to the pathogenic potential of this food-borne pathogen.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI061020-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI60211/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7802877; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Protein Subunits); 0 (Receptors, Cell Surface); 0 (Tir protein, E coli); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); EIN: J Clin Invest. 2008 Feb;118(2):820; OID: NLM: PMC2030454; 2006/10/23 [received]; 2007/08/13 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9738; 0021-9738</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17948128</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1172/JCI30727</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17948128</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2030454</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1119</id>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Monteiro-Neto,V.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Ledesma,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Puente,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>The type 4 pili of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli O157:H7 are multipurpose structures with pathogenic attributes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>191</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>411</sp>
<op>421</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor</k1>
<k1>Colon/microbiology</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Diarrhea/genetics/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Infections/genetics</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Food Microbiology</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Hemolytic-Uremic Syndrome/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Shiga Toxins/toxicity</k1>
<ab>Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) O157:H7 produces long bundles of polar type 4 pili (T4P) called HCP (for hemorrhagic coli pili) that form physical bridges between bacteria associating with human and animal epithelial cells. Here, we sought to further investigate whether HCP possessed other pathogenicity attributes associated with T4P production. Comparative studies performed with wild-type EHEC EDL933 and an isogenic hcpA mutant revealed that HCP play different roles in the biology of this organism. We found that in addition to promoting bacterial attachment to host cells, HCP mediate (i) invasion of epithelial cells, (ii) hemagglutination of rabbit erythrocytes, (iii) interbacterial connections conducive to biofilm formation, (iv) specific binding to host extracellular matrix proteins laminin and fibronectin but not collagen, and (v) twitching motility. Nonadherent laboratory E. coli strain HB101 complemented with hcpABC genes on plasmid pJX22, which specifies for HCP overproduction in EDL933, became hyperadherent and invasive and produced a thick biofilm, suggesting that the presence of HCP confers HB101(pJX22) new attributes otherwise not exhibited by HB101. Analogous to other bacteria in which T4P are involved in the pathogenesis of several infectious diseases, our data strongly suggest that HCP display multiple functions that may contribute to EHEC colonization of different hosts and to virulence, survival, and transmission of this food-borne pathogen.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI61020/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI63211-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (Shiga Toxins); OID: NLM: PMC2612451; 2008/10/24 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5530; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18952791; JB.01306-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.01306-08</do>
<wp>20081024</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18952791</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2612451</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>857</id>
<a1>Xicohtencatl-Cortes,J.</a1>
<a1>Sanchez Chacon,E.</a1>
<a1>Saldana,Z.</a1>
<a1>Freer,E.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Interaction of Escherichia coli O157:H7 with leafy green produce</t1>
<jf>Journal of food protection</jf>
<jo>J.Food Prot.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1531</sp>
<op>1537</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Consumer Product Safety</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli O157/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Flagella/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Food Contamination/analysis/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lettuce/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Plant Leaves/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Spinacia oleracea/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) is a foodborne pathogen responsible for human diarrheal disease. EHEC lives in the intestinal tract of cattle and other farm and wild animals, which may be the source of environmental contamination particularly of agricultural fields. Human infections are associated with consumption of tainted animal products and fresh produce. How the bacteria interact with the plant phyllosphere and withstand industrial decontamination remain to be elucidated. The goals of the present study were to investigate the environmental conditions and surface structures that influence the interaction of EHEC O157:H7 with baby spinach and lettuce leaves in vitro. Independently of the production of Shiga toxin, EHEC O157:H7 colonizes the leaf surface via flagella and the type 3 secretion system (T3SS). Ultrastructural analysis of EHEC-infected leafy greens revealed the presence of flagellated bacteria, and mutation of the fliC flagellin gene in EHEC EDL933 rendered the bacteria significantly less adherent, suggesting the involvement of flagella in the bacteria-leaf interaction. EDL933 mutated in the escN (ATPase) gene associated with the function of the T3SS but not in the eae (intimin adhesin) gene required for adherence to host intestinal cells had significantly reduced adherence compared with that of the parental strain. The data suggest a compelling role of flagella and the T3SS in colonization of leafy green produce. Colonization of salad leaves by EHEC strains may be a strategy that ensures survival of these bacteria in the environment and allows transmission to the human host.</ab>
<no>JID: 7703944; 0 (Adhesins, Escherichia coli); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0362-028X; 0362-028X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunobiology, University of Arizona, 1501 North Campbell Avenue, Tucson, Arizona 85724, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19681282</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19681282</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1135</id>
<a1>Zhou,X.</a1>
<a1>Giron,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Torres,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Crawford,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Negrete,E.</a1>
<a1>Vogel,S. N.</a1>
<a1>Kaper,J. B.</a1>
<t1>Flagellin of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli stimulates interleukin-8 production in T84 cells</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>2120</sp>
<op>2129</op>
<k1>Adhesins, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Colon/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Culture Media, Conditioned/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Flagella/immunology</k1>
<k1>Flagellin/chemistry/genetics/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interleukin-8/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase Kinases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>The type III secretion system (TTSS) of enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC) has been associated with the ability of these bacteria to induce secretion of proinflammatory cytokines, including interleukin-8 (IL-8), in cultured epithelial cells. However, the identity of the effector molecule directly involved in this event is unknown. In this study, we determined that the native flagellar filament and its flagellin monomer are activators of IL-8 release in T84 epithelial cells. Supernatants of wild-type EPEC strain E2348/69 and its isogenic mutants deficient in TTSS (escN) and in production of intimin (eae), grown in Luria-Bertani broth, elicited similar amounts of IL-8 secretion by T84 cells. In contrast, supernatants of EPEC fliC mutants and of B171, a nonflagellated EPEC strain, were defective in inducing IL-8 release, a phenotype that was largely restored by complementation of the fliC gene in the mutant lacking flagella. Purified flagella from E. coli K-12, EPEC serotypes H6 and H34, and enterohemorrhagic E. coli serotype H7 all induced IL-8 release in T84 cells. Induction of IL-8 by purified flagella or His-tagged FliC from EPEC strain E2348/69 was dose dependent and was blocked by a polyclonal anti-H6 antibody. Finally, the mitogen-activated protein kinases (Erk1 and -2 and Jnk) were phosphorylated in flagellin-treated T84 cells, and inhibition of the p38 and Erk pathways significantly decreased the IL-8 response induced by EPEC flagellin. Our data clearly indicate that FliC of EPEC is sufficient to induce IL-8 release in T84 cells and that activation of the Erk and p38 pathways is required for IL-8 induction.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: AI 010538 02/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 18797/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 21657/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK 58957/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Adhesins, Bacterial); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Culture Media, Conditioned); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Interleukin-8); 12777-81-0 (Flagellin); 147094-99-3 (eaeA protein, E coli); EC 2.7.12.2 (Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase Kinases); OID: NLM: PMC152053; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Center for Vaccine Development, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21201, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12654834</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12654834</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC152053</pmcid></reference></refworks>
