
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3401</id>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J.</a1>
<a1>Vitosh,M.</a1>
<a1>Chase,R.</a1>
<t1>Joint influence of nitrogen, phosphorus and Pratylenchus penetrans on the ontogeny of Solanum tuberosum.</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<sp>65</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH000 Pathogen, Pest and Parasite and Weed Management (General)</k1>
<k1>aldicarb</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>control methods</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>potatoes</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus penetrans</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene plus methyl isothiocyanate</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>inorganic</k1>
<k1>amendments</k1>
<k1>methyl isothiocyanate plus 1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<ab>In field trials, Pratylenchus penetrans was controlled and yields of S. tuberosum were significantly increased following application of aldicarb (2.2 kg/ha) or 1,3-D + MIC (941/ha). Phosphorus (84 or 168 kg P2O5/ha) in the absence of nematicides also increased tuber yield. Nitrogen (168 or 336 kg/ha) had no significant influence on ontogeny and tuber yield, except when nematicides were applied.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: Organization of Tropical American Nematologists: Partial list of abstracts of papers presented at the XII Annual Meeting of OTAN at Pointe-a-Pitre, Guadeloupe, August 17-21 1980.&lt;br&gt;BD: Pratylenchus; Pratylenchidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Solanum; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<ad>Dep. Entomol., Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, MI 48824, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19810883913</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>116-06-3</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3361</id>
<a1>Chandler,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Legard,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Performance of strawberry cultivars on fumigated and nonfumigated soil in Florida.</t1>
<jf>HortTechnology</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>69</sp>
<op>71</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) QQ050 Crop Produce QQ500 Food Composition and Quality</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>fruits</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>soil</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>strawberries</k1>
<k1>variety trials</k1>
<k1>weight</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Fragaria ananassa</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>cultivated varieties</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Five strawberry (Fragaria ananassa) cultivars (Sweet Charlie, Oso Grande, Selva, Carlsbad, and Rosa Linda) in the 1995-96 season and four cultivars (Sweet Charlie, Oso Grande, Selva and Camarosa) in the 1996-97 season were grown in the annual hill plasticulture system, with and without preplant soil fumigation (98% methyl bromide/2% chloropicrin at a rate of 240 lb/acre (269 kg/ha)). These trials were established on land that had been cropped with strawberries for 20 years. Significant cultivar by fumigation intereactions were not detected for either yield or average fruit weight. Plants grown in nonfumigated soil produced 54 and 68% of the yield obtained from the plants grown in fumigated soil in 1995-96 and 1996-97 respectively, and the average fruit weight from plants grown in nonfumigated soil was also reduced, compared to that of plants grown in fumigated soil. Plant mortality was 3% in the nonfumigated plots. These results indicate that strawberry productivity in Florida can be substantially reduced by growing plants in soil that has not been fumigated prior to planting, even in the absence of lethal pathogens.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Canada; Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Fragaria; Rosaceae; Rosales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; eukaryotes; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   Commonwealth of Nations; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 13 ref.</no>
<pb>American Society for Horticultural Science</pb>
<pp>Alexandria USA</pp>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 13138 Lewis Gallagher Road, Dover, FL 33527, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20013020507</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>76-06-2; 74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2769</id>
<a1>Duncan,LW</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Inserra,RN</a1>
<a1>Dunn,D.</a1>
<t1>Spatial patterns of Belonolaimus spp. among and within citrus orchards on Florida&amp;#39;s central ridge</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>352</sp>
<op>359</op>
<k1>Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>citrus</k1>
<k1>crop loss assessment</k1>
<k1>ecology</k1>
<k1>nematode</k1>
<k1>nematode survey</k1>
<k1>soil moisture</k1>
<k1>spatial distribution</k1>
<k1>spatial pattern</k1>
<k1>sting nematode</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus</k1>
<ab>A survey was initiated to determine the incidence of Belonolaimus spp. (sting nematodes) in citrus orchards in the central ridge region of Florida, following widespread damage by these nematodes to young trees replanted after freezing weather in 1989-90. Sting nematodes were detected in 50% of 210 samples and in 64% of 84 orchards surveyed. More orchards in Polk County were infested with sting nematodes (82%) than in counties to the north (36%) or south (48%). Principal component analysis of morphometric data separated six of seven sting nematode populations in northeastern Polk County from six populations in adjacent regions. Stylet:tail ratio for nematodes in northeastern Polk County tend to be greater than 1.0 and were less than 1.0 for all other populations. Patchiness of nematodes within an orchard was associated with stunted trees (23% smaller), reduced root mass density (25% lower), and low fruit yield (57% reduction). Soil texture did not vary among trees of different size in the orchard, but soil water potential between irrigation events was highest beneath small trees with low root mass density. Results of the survey indicate that the incidence of sting nematodes in orchards on the central ridge is much higher than previously estimated and that sting nematodes can cause substantial damage in replanted orchards. Further research is needed to evaluate the significance of sting nematode population variability and its relationships to citrus crop loss in Florida.</ab>
<no>CD: JONEB&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>L.W. Duncan, Citrus Research and Education Center, Food /Agricultural Sciences Institute, University of Florida, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, United States.</ad>
<an>1997011499</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>92.10.1.4 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Physiology: Soil science; 92.10.3.3 CROP SCIENCE: Tree Growth and Forest Management: Orchards, rootstocks and grafting; 92.11.1.7 PLANT PATHOLOGY AND SYMBIOSES: Plant Pathology: Nematodes; 92.13.1.2 ENVIRONMENTAL BIO(TRUNCATED)</cl>
<sf>Journal; Article; Plant Science</sf>
<db>Plant Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3389</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Ferguson,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Application of Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law to sample statistics of Tylenchulus semipenetrans in Florida citrus.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4 (supplement)</is>
<sp>707</sp>
<op>711</op>
<k1>LL300 Animal Behaviour ZZ900 Techniques and Methodology FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) PP710 Biological Resources (Animal)</k1>
<k1>ecology</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>sampling</k1>
<k1>Subtropical fruits</k1>
<k1>Techniques</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Tylenchulus semipenetrans</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>sampling techniques</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law was fit to T. semipenetrans population data obtained from individal trees in a survey of 50 Florida citrus orchards (geographic survey) and to data from individual trees within a single orchard collected at regular intervals for 2 years (temporal survey). No significant differences were detected between slope or intercept values when log variance was regressed against log mean for the geographic and temporal data sets. The geographic survey was divided into two subsets of data according to the perceived size of patches of T. semipenetrans. Subsets consisted of orchards which appeared to have numerous small patches of trees infected by the nematode (small patch) and orchards in which most of the trees were infected (large patch). The slope value for the orchards with smaller patches of nematodes was different from that from large-patch orchards. Assuming mean nematode levels of 1000 juveniles and males/100 cm soil, sample sizes (predicted standard error to mean ratio = 0.20) estimated from the relationships of variance to means were 12 trees in the geographic survey and 11 trees in the temporal. Omission of the small-patch data from the geographic survey resulted in a 17% reduction in optimum sample size. Sample size in sporadically infested orchards was estimated to be 69 trees. A data transformation of X0.23 was calculated from parameters of Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law fit to the survey data.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Tylenchulus; Tylenchulidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; SU: (/i Formerly called Annals of Applied Nematology/); NR: 10 ref.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, IFAS, Citrus Research and Education Center, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19901143126</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3386</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,D. T.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Maintaining barriers to the spread of Radopholus citrophilus in Florida citrus orchards.</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>71</sp>
<op>88</op>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) LL300 Animal Behaviour HH200 Environmental Pest Management</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>Cultural control</k1>
<k1>Methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>movement to roots</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>Spread</k1>
<k1>Temperate fruits</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Radopholus citrophilus</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Studies were conducted to determine methods to restrict inter-orchard spread of R. citrophilus. Experiments focused on the ability of a nematode to migrate in root-free soil and on methods to restrict the growth of citrus roots across root-free buffer zones. In migration trials, the nematode moved &amp;gt; 1.4 m in 1 year from infected to noninfected seedlings when host roots were permitted to grow toward one another. However, when citrus root growth was restricted by pruning, the nematode did not infect roots on seedlings growing 1.5 m distant from infected seedlings. In orchards, roots grew at an annual rate of &amp;gt; 0.90 m but  1.5 m until they grew beyond the 5 undercanopy area of the tree. Therefore, vertical hedging of trees to permit trenching near the trunk will significantly increase the number of major roots which are cut. Methyl bromide injected 60 cm deep in sandy soil at rates of 224 and 448 kg/ha penetrated at least 4.5 m in sufficient concentration to kill buried citrus seedlings.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Radopholus; Pratylenchidae; Nematoda; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA;&lt;br&gt;   North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 18 ref.</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, IFAS, Citrus Research and Education Center, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19912309788</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3362</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Agricultural sustainability and nematode integrated pest management.</t1>
<yr>1998</yr>
<sp>287</sp>
<k1>FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH300 Integrated Pest Management HH200 Environmental Pest Management HH100 Biological Control HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) HH600 Host Resistance and Immunity</k1>
<k1>biological control</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>conservation tillage</k1>
<k1>cover crops</k1>
<k1>cropping systems</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>decision making</k1>
<k1>fallow</k1>
<k1>integrated control</k1>
<k1>integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>monitoring</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>physical control</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>planting date</k1>
<k1>rotations</k1>
<k1>sanitation</k1>
<k1>soil amendments</k1>
<k1>sowing date</k1>
<k1>sustainability</k1>
<k1>yield losses</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>choice</k1>
<k1>crop rotation</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>fallowing</k1>
<k1>integrated plant</k1>
<k1>protection</k1>
<k1>IPM</k1>
<k1>rotational cropping</k1>
<k1>surveillance systems</k1>
<ab>Nematode management is considered in the context of sustainability and integrated pest management (IPM). The various methods currently used to limit or prevent nematode damage to crops are described in order to evaluate their potential as tactics to be used in IPM systems. Information is presented under the following headings: agricultural sustainability; nematode integrated pest management; integrated pest management decisions, including crop loss assessment, damage functions, cropping systems and biomonitoring; IPM strategies; IPM tactics, including sanitation, plant resistance, crop rotation, cover crops, planting date, fallowing and conservation tillage, soil amendments, physical methods of nematode control, biological control, and chemical control; and current and future considerations for IPM.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; NR: Many ref.</no>
<a2>Barker, K. R. Pederson, G. A. Windham,G.L.</a2>
<pb>American Society of Agronomy</pb>
<pp>Madison USA</pp>
<sn>0-89118-136-9</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Citrus Research and Education Center, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20013030265</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Book chapter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3177</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Modeling Population Dynamics of Tylenchulus-Semipenetrans in a Flatwoods Citrus Grove</t1>
<jf>Soil and Crop Science Society of Florida Proceedings</jf>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<sp>250</sp>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198936030722; CT: FORTY-SEVENTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOIL AND CROP SCIENCE SOCIETY OF FLORIDA, SARASOTA, FLORIDA, USA, OCTOBER 20-22, 1987. SOIL CROP SCI SOC FLA PROC.</no>
<sn>0096-4522</sn>
<ad>DUNCAN L W ; UNIV FLORIDA, IFAS, CITRUS RES AND EDUC CENTER, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3395</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The relationship between development of the citrus root system and infestation by Tylenchulus semipenetrans.</t1>
<jf>Revue de Nematologie</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>61</sp>
<op>65</op>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>damage</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pathology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Tropical fruits</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Tylenchulus semipenetrans</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>root growth</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Fibrous root growth and T. semipenetrans population development were monitored monthly on 100 citrus trees in a bedded grove on the Florida coast, USA. Fibrous root weights in individual samples were related to visual estimates of tree vigour. Nematode infestation levels (number of free living nematodes/g root) were inversely related to tree vigour. Proportional growth of fibrous roots of individual root systems was also inversely related to tree vigour. The mean proportion of young roots to total roots in a sample was 44% in healthy trees compared with 72% in trees in decline during the January sample period. In the present study, mature, vigorous citrus trees were less susceptible to population development by T. semipenetrans which only infect young roots.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Tylenchulus; Tylenchulidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 25 ref.</no>
<ad>Univ. Florida, IFAS, Citrus Res. &amp; Ed. Cent., 700 Exp. Sta. Rd., Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19870841825</an>
<la>English; French</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3181</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The Relationship between Development of the Citrus Root System and Infestation by Tylenchulus-Semipenetrans</t1>
<jf>Revue de Nematologie</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>61</sp>
<op>66</op>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>51000, Morphology, anatomy and embryology of plants</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<ab>Fibrous root growth and Tylenchulus semipenetrans population development were monitored monthly on 100 citrus trees in a bedded grove on the Florida[USA] coast. Fibrous root weights in individual samples were related (p = 0.01) to visual estimates of tree vigor. Nematode infestation levels (number of free living nematodes/g root) were inversely related to tree vigor (p = 0.01). Proportional growth of fibrous roots of individual root systems was also inversely related (p = 0.05) to tree vigor. The mean proportion of young roots to total roots in a sample was 44% in healthy trees compared with 72% (p = 0.05) in decline trees during the January sample period. In the present study, mature, vigorous citrus trees were less susceptible to population development by T. semipenetrans which only infect young roots.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198784028943</no>
<sn>0183-9187</sn>
<ad>DUNCAN L W ; UNIV FLORIDA, IFAS, CITRUS RES AND EDUCATION CENTER, 700 EXPERIMENT STATION ROAD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3184</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The Relationship between Citrus Tree Health and Tylenchulus-Semipenetrans Infestation Level</t1>
<jf>Revue de Nematologie</jf>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>295</sp>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54514, Phytopathology - Parasitism and resistance</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198732108397; CT: 18TH INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM OF THE EUROPEAN SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS, ANTIBES, FRANCE, SEPTEMBER 7-12, 1986. REV NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0183-9187</sn>
<ad>DUNCAN L W ; UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUC CENT, 700 EXPERIMENT STN ROAD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3185</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Resistance of Mature Healthy Citrus to Infestation by Tylenchulus-Semipenetrans</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>606</sp>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>16504, Reproductive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54514, Phytopathology - Parasitism and resistance</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198732041154; CT: 25TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>DUNCAN L W ; UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUCATION CENT, 700 EXPERIMENTAL STATION RD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3152</id>
<a1>Duncan,Larry W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<t1>Agricultural sustainability and nematode integrated pest management</t1>
<jf>Agronomy (Madison); Plant and nematode interactions</jf>
<yr>1998</yr>
<sp>251</sp>
<op>287</op>
<k1>Agronomy (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>52807, Soil science - Fertility and applied studies</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>(pesticide)</k1>
<k1>integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>crop rotation, pest control method, sanitation, tillage, physical-chemical methods</k1>
<no>PT: S; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199800520046&lt;br&gt;ME: print</no>
<a2>Barker, K. R. Pederson, G. A. Windham,G.L.</a2>
<t2>Agronomy (Madison) : 36</t2>
<pb>Soil Science Society of America, Inc., American Society of Agronomy, Inc., Crop Science Society of America, Inc. {a}</pb>
<pp>677 South Segoe Road, Madison, Wisconsin 53711, USA</pp>
<sn>0065-4663; 0-89118-136-9</sn>
<ad>Univ. Florida, Lake Alfred, FL, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Book; Book Chapter; LT: Literature Review</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2802</id>
<a1>Dunn,Robert A.</a1>
<t1>Characteristics of principal nematicides </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Multi-purpose soil fumigants -- Equipment -- Soil preparation -- Fumigant nematicides -- Application -- Overall vs. row fumigation -- Aeration -- No residual effect -- Non-fumigant nematicides -- Environmental problems and user safety.</ab>
<no>Robert A. Dunn and Joseph W. Noling. : Robert A. Dunn and Joseph W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG009; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG009, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Guide of the Department of Entomology and Nematology Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on October 19, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG009; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG009pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3131</id>
<a1>Esmel,Camille</a1>
<a1>Santos,Bielinski</a1>
<a1>Simonne,Eric</a1>
<a1>Recheigl,Jack E.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<t1>Effects of S Fertilization Rates and Irrigation Programs on Tomato Growth and Yields</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUL 2009</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1045</sp>
<k1>Agrichemicals</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10064, Biochemistry studies - Proteins, peptides and amino acids</k1>
<k1>16504, Reproductive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>51512, Plant physiology - Reproduction</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>52807, Soil science - Fertility and applied studies</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tomato</k1>
<k1>(vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>chlorophyll/nitrogen</k1>
<k1>7727-37-9</k1>
<k1>(agrichemical, fertilizer)/sulfur</k1>
<k1>7704-34-9</k1>
<k1>(agrichemical, fertilizer)</k1>
<k1>fruit</k1>
<k1>reproductive system</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900460165; CT: 106th Annual Conference of the American-Society-for-Horticultural-Science; CL: St Louis, MO, USA; CY: July 25 -28, 2009; SP: Amer Soc Hort Sci; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>Esmel, Camille ; GCREC Balm, Wimauma, FL USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3390</id>
<a1>Ferris,H.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Analysis and prediction as a basis for management decisions.</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<sp>85</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) PP710 Biological Resources (Animal)</k1>
<k1>assessment</k1>
<k1>crops</k1>
<k1>Ecology</k1>
<k1>losses</k1>
<k1>Mathematical models</k1>
<k1>models</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>Pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>reviews</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<ab>The various biological models used to assess the many factors influencing nematode damage to crops are discussed. Models used to explain the damage function, the environment and nematode community structure, host status effects, economic threshold concepts, seasonal nematode multiplication rates, overwinter survival rates and life tables are among those described.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; NR: 97 ref.</no>
<a2>Brown,R. H. Kerry,B.R.</a2>
<pb>Academic Press Australia</pb>
<pp>Marrickville, NSW Australia</pp>
<sn>0-12-137640-0</sn>
<ad>Div. Nematol., Univ. California, Davis, CA 95616, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19891129732</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2759</id>
<a1>Gilreath,JP</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Locascio,SJ</a1>
<a1>Chellemi,DO</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of methyl bromide alternatives in tomato and double-cropped cucumber</t1>
<jf>1999 Annual Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions</jf>
<fd>1-4 Nov 1999</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 994 5035); Availability: Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach (MBAO), 144 W. Peace River Drive, Fresno, CA 93711-6953, USA; phone: 559-447-2127; email: gobenauf@agrc.cnchost.com, Full papers available. Contact MBAO for price.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>San Diego, CA (USA)</ed>
<ad>IFAS, Univ. Florida, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA; Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach, Crop Protection Coalition, EPA, Department of Agriculture</ad>
<an>3511978</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 4300 Environmental Science</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2755</id>
<a1>Gilreath,JP</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Santos,BM</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide alternatives for bell pepper (Capsicum annuum) and cucumber (Cucumis sativus) rotations</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>347</sp>
<op>351</op>
<k1>Soil fumigant</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>Chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>Metam sodium</k1>
<k1>Napropamide</k1>
<k1>Metolachlor</k1>
<k1>Pebulate</k1>
<k1>Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>Cucumis sativus</k1>
<k1>Eleusine indica</k1>
<k1>Digitaria ciliaris</k1>
<k1>Amaranthus hybridus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<ab>Two field trials were conducted to determine the effect of soil fumigant and herbicide combinations as potential alternatives for methyl bromide (MBr) in bell pepper-cucumber rotations. For the first bell pepper-cucumber trial, fumigant levels were a non-treated control, MBr+chloropicrin (Pic) (67/33%, respectively) at a rate of 400kg/ha, Pic at 400kg/ha, metam sodium (MNa) at 945l /ha, 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D)+Pic (83/17%, respectively) at 330l/ha, and anhydrous ammonia (ANH4) at 300l/ha. For the second bell pepper-cucumber trial, fumigants levels were the same, except that ANH 4 was substituted by 1,3-D+Pic (65/35%, respectively) at 330l a.i./ha. Fumigants were only applied during the bell pepper seasons. Herbicides used were napropamide at 4.50kg/ha, metolachlor at 2.25kg/ha, pebulate at 4.50kg/ha, in addition to an untreated check. Applied herbicides did not interact with fumigants and had excellent control of goosegrass (Eleusine indica L.), southern crabgrass (Digitaria ciliaris L.) and smooth pigweed (Amaranthus hybridus L.), but only poor to fair control of purple nutsedge (Cyperus rotundus L.). The fumigants 1,3-D+17% Pic, MNa, and Pic had reduced nematode root galling compared with the unchecked control. All fumigants tested for bell pepper, except ANH4, successfully showed significant residual effects for cucumbers in the same plots. In most cases, 1,3-D+17% Pic, and Pic were comparable to MBr. (copyright) 2003 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>CD: CRPTD; 14 refs.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pp>United Kingdom</pp>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>B.M. Santos, Gulf Coast Res. and Education Center, University of Florida, 5007 60th Street East, Bradenton, FL 34203, United States. Email: bmsantos@yahoo.com</ad>
<an>2004077734</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>92.10.4 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection; 92.10.2.4 CROP SCIENCE: Agronomy and Horticulture: Vegetables</cl>
<sf>Journal; Article; Plant Science</sf>
<db>Plant Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3356</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Motis,T. N.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Mirusso,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,P. R.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Jones,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Influence of supplementary in-bed chloropicrin application on soilborne pest control in tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum).</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>779</sp>
<op>784</op>
<k1>FF610 Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Diseases of Plants (NEW March 2000) FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>broadcasting</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>fungal diseases</k1>
<k1>fungicides</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant disease control</k1>
<k1>plant diseases</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus</k1>
<k1>fungi</k1>
<k1>Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Tylenchorhynchus</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Hyphomycetes</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Four consecutive field trials were conducted in a four-season study to determine the long-term efficacy of supplementary in-bed applications of chloropicrin (Pic) in addition to 1,3-dichloropropene plus Pic (1,3-D+Pic) on soilborne pest control and tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) yield. Treatments compared combinations of in-bed and broadcast 1,3-D and Pic with an untreated control and were repeated over several seasons. Results indicated that in-bed applications of C-35 and MBr+Pic consistently had the highest control of soilborne fungus (Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici race 3), weeds (Cyperus spp.), and nematodes (Meloidogyne spp., Belonolaimus spp., and Tylenchorhynchus spp.) and tomato fruit weights, followed by the C-35+Pic, and 1,3-D+Pic, which had excellent performance in three of the four tomato seasons.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Belonolaimidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes;&lt;br&gt;   Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; Fusarium oxysporum; Fusarium; Deuteromycotina; Eumycota; fungi;&lt;br&gt;   Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; Heteroderidae; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; NR: 13 ref.</no>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<pp>Oxford UK</pp>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 5007 60th Street East, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.; bmsantos@yahoo.com; bmsantos@ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053129856</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/02612194</lk>
<do>10.1016/j.cropro.2005.01.002</do>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3352</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Motis,T. N.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Chellemi,D. O.</a1>
<t1>Resurgence of soilborne pests in double-cropped cucumber after application of methyl bromide chemical alternatives and solarization in tomato.</t1>
<jf>HortTechnology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>797</sp>
<op>801</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) HH420 Pesticides and Drugs: Chemistry and Formulation (NEW March 2000) HH430 Pesticide and Drug Residues and Ecotoxicology (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>cucumbers</k1>
<k1>fungicides</k1>
<k1>herbicide mixtures</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>mulching</k1>
<k1>napropamide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>pebulate</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>residual effects</k1>
<k1>resurgence</k1>
<k1>soil solarization</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cucumis sativus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus esculentus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>gherkins</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Field studies were conducted during four consecutive tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum)-cucumber (Cucumis sativus) rotations during the 1998/2001 autumn and 1999/2002 spring seasons in Florida, USA, to examine the long-term residual effects of tomato methyl bromide (MBr) alternatives on the soilborne pests in double-cropped cucumber. Four treatments were established in tomato fields: (a) nontreated control; (b) MBr + chloropicrin (Pic) (67:33 by weight) at a rate of 392.31 kg/ha; (c) tank-mixed pebulate + napropamide at 4.48 and 2.24 kg/ha, respectively, followed by 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D) + Pic (83:17 by volume) at 374.16 litres/ha; and (d) napropamide at 2.24 kg/ha followed by soil solarization for 7 to 8 weeks. Each of the following seasons, cucumber was planted in the same tomato plots without removing mulch films. For purple (Cyperus rotundus) and yellow nutsedge (C. esculentus) densities, napropamide followed by solarization plots had equal control (15 plants/m2) as MBr + Pic during all four cropping seasons. However, nematode control with solarization was inconsistent. The marketable yield data proved that fumigation in tomato fields with either MBr + Pic or pebulate + napropamide followed by 1,3-D + Pic had a long-term effect on the double-cropped cucumber.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Cucumis; Cucurbitaceae; Violales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; Cyperus; Cyperaceae; Cyperales;&lt;br&gt;   monocotyledons; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA;&lt;br&gt;   North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 14 ref.</no>
<pb>American Society for Horticultural Science</pb>
<pp>Alexandria USA</pp>
<sn>1063-0198</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 14625 County Rd. 672, Wimauma, FL 33598, USA.; bmsantos@ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053189583</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>1114-71-2; 15299-99-7; 542-75-6; 76-06-2; 74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3358</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Jones,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Overman,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide alternatives in fresh tomato: first experiences.</t1>
<jf>Manejo Integrado de Plagas y Agroecologia</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<is>69</is>
<sp>73</sp>
<op>76</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF610 Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Diseases of Plants (NEW March 2000) FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>dazomet</k1>
<k1>fosthiazate</k1>
<k1>fruits</k1>
<k1>fungicides</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>pebulate</k1>
<k1>plant disease control</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>fungi</k1>
<k1>Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Hyphomycetes</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Since the beginning of the 90s, the University of Florida has conducted hundreds of trials searching for methyl bromide (MBr) alternatives in vegetables, ornamentals and fruit crops. Because the use of this soil fumigant will be restricted in 2005, preliminary studies were conducted to determine possible alternatives to replace MBr in mulched fresh tomato. The studies examined the efficacy of chloropicrin (Pic), dazomet, 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D), 1,3-D + Pic (C-17), metam sodium [metam] (MNa), C-17 + Pic, C-17 + MNa, and C-17 + pebulate for weed, nematode, and soilborne disease control in planting beds. The results indicated that the application of C-17 (250 kg/ha) combined with pebulate (4.5 kg/ha) consistently produced similar yield to that of MBr, and reduced Cyperus rotundus densities, and Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici and Meloidogyne spp. incidence.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Cyperus; Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; Fusarium oxysporum; Fusarium;&lt;br&gt;   Deuteromycotina; Eumycota; fungi; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales;&lt;br&gt;   dicotyledons; Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; NR: 7 ref.</no>
<pb>Centro Agronomico Tropical de Investigacion y Ensenanza</pb>
<pp>Turrialba Costa Rica</pp>
<sn>1016-0469</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Bradenton, Florida, USA.; bmsantos@yahoo.com</ad>
<an>CABI:20043014995</an>
<la>Spanish; English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ot>Experiencias iniciales con alternativas al bromuro de metilo en tomate.</ot>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 533-74-4; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 1114-71-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3364</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Chellemi,D. O.</a1>
<t1>Effect of methyl bromide, 1,3-dichloropropene + chloropicrin with pebulate and soil solarization on soilborne pest control in tomato followed by double-cropped cucumber.</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<is>112</is>
<sp>292</sp>
<op>297</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF610 Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Diseases of Plants (NEW March 2000) FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH200 Environmental Pest Management HH300 Integrated Pest Management HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) JJ100 Soil Biology JJ900 Soil Management FF005 Field Crops (NEW March 2000) HH100 Biological Control</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>biological control agents</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>cucumbers</k1>
<k1>fumigant insecticides</k1>
<k1>fumigants</k1>
<k1>fungal antagonists</k1>
<k1>fungal diseases</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>microbial pesticides</k1>
<k1>natural enemies</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>pathogens</k1>
<k1>pebulate</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>residual effects</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>soil solarization</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cucumis sativus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>fungi</k1>
<k1>Fusarium oxysporum</k1>
<k1>Gliocladium virens</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>biocontrol agents</k1>
<k1>biological control organisms</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>gherkins</k1>
<k1>Hyphomycetes</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>plant diseaes</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Soil fumigation with 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D) + chloropicrin (Telone C-17), or with pebulate (Tillam), and soil solarization + Gliocladium virens (SoilGard) were compared with soil fumigation with methyl bromide for the control of soilborne pests and crop response of autumn tomatoes (Lycopersicon esculentum) and double-cropped spring cucumbers (Cucumis sativus) during 1998-99 atBrandenton, Florida, USA. Soil treatments were applied prior to the autumn tomato crop and soil solarization was conducted for 8 weeks pre-plant. G. virens was applied to the tomato plants as a drench in the setting water at transplanting. Brown top millet [species not specified] was planted in one subplot per main plot on 22 March 1999. The millet was allowed to grow using only residual fertilizer from the autumn tomato crop. The combination of pebulate and 1,3-D + chloropicrin provided nutsedge (Cyperus rotundus), Fusarium wilt (incited by Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici race 3) and root knot nematode (Meloidogyne spp.) control and tomato yields similar to those obtained with methyl bromide. Plant vigour and yield were higher after soil fumigation than after soil solarization. Soil solarization, 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate and methyl bromide provided statistically similar control of nutsedge, though a widespread numerical difference occurred between methyl bromide and the other two treatments; but there was more crabgrass (Digitaria ciliaris) in solarized plots than in those which received either of the two fumigants. Root gall formation on tomato due to rootknot nematodes was worse with solarization than with any other treatment, including the nontreated control, and the incidence of Fusarium wilt was intermediate between that of the fumigant treatment and the nontreated control. Tomato fruit production with 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate was equal to that with methyl bromide, but solarization resulted in fewer fruits in each size grade, and reduced total marketable yield. Tomato production with soil solarization + G. virens drench was only slightly higher than that obtained without fumigation. When cucumbers were grown as a double crop in the spring following autumn tomatoes, yields were similar with 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate and methyl bromide. Solarization + G. virens drench reduced cucumber yield relative to methyl bromide, but was similar to that of 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate. Rootknot nematode galling of second crop cucumber was similar with soil solarization, 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate, and no fumigant. Gall formation was not significantly different between methyl bromide and 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate, whereas methyl bromide greatly reduced gall severity compared to solarization. Methyl bromide improved millet growth in the spring following autumn application compared to solarization or no treatment, but was not different with 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate. Fewer crabgrass plants were present in millet grown in soil treated with either methyl bromide or 1,3-D + chloropicrin + pebulate than with no fumigant or with soil solarization.</ab>
<no>BD: Cucumis; Cucurbitaceae; Violales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; Cyperus; Cyperaceae; Cyperales;&lt;br&gt;   monocotyledons; Fusarium; Deuteromycotina; Eumycota; fungi;&lt;br&gt;   Gliocladium; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; Heteroderidae;&lt;br&gt;   Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; NR: 9 ref.</no>
<t2>Proceedings of the Florida State Horticultural Society; Proceedings of the 112th Annual Meeting of the Florida State Horticultural Society, Stuart, Florida, USA, 31 October - 2 November, 1999.</t2>
<sn>0886-7283</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20001701577</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 74-83-9; 1114-71-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3368</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Chellemi,D. O.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of methyl bromide alternatives in tomato and double-cropped cucumber.</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<sp>2.</sp>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>cucumbers</k1>
<k1>cucurbit vegetables</k1>
<k1>fruit vegetables</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>vegetables</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>Cucumis sativus</k1>
<k1>Cucurbitaceae</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>gherkins</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<no>BD: Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; Cucumis; Cucurbitaceae; Violales; SU: Available on the internet at http://search.epa.gov/spdpublc/mbr/mbrqa.html</no>
<a2>Obenauf,G. L. Williams,A.</a2>
<t2>Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.; Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.</t2>
<pb>Environment Protection Agency (EPA)</pb>
<pp>Washington USA</pp>
<ad>IFAS, University of Florida, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20002302696</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper</sf>
<cn>74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3351</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<t1>Alternatives to methyl bromide for the management of weeds in vegetables: experiences at the University of Florida.</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<sp>32</sp>
<op>35</op>
<k1>FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>fumigants</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>strawberries</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Fragaria ananassa</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>United States of</k1>
<k1>America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>The efficacy of Telone II (83% 1,3-dichloropropene plus 17% chloropicrin) in combination with other fumigants and herbicides was compared with that of methyl bromide for the control of weeds in tomatoes, strawberries and other crops in Florida. This study demonstrated the efficacy of fumigants and herbicides for the control of weeds in vegetables. Appropriate application techniques were considered to be vital for control.</ab>
<no>GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Rosaceae; Rosales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Fragaria; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA</no>
<a2>Pedrero, G. M. Valenzuela, J. A. D. Diaz, G. M. Ruiz,R.A.O.</a2>
<t2>Memoria XVI Congreso Latinoamericano de Malezas y XXIV Congreso Nacional de la Asociacion Mexicana de la Ciencia de la Maleza, Manzanillo, Colima, Mexico, del 10 al 12 de Noviembre de 2003; Memoria XVI Congreso Latinoamericano de Malezas y XXIV Congreso Nacional de la Asociacion Mexicana de la Ciencia de la Maleza, Manzanillo, Colima, Mexico, del 10 al 12 de Noviembre de 2003.</t2>
<pb>Asociacion Latinoamericana de Malezas</pb>
<pp>Wimauma USA</pp>
<sn>968-884-988-X</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Bradenton, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20053167207</an>
<la>Spanish</la>
<sf>C; Book chapter, Conference paper</sf>
<ot>Alternativas al bromuro de metilo en el manejo de malezas en vegetales: experiencias de la Universidad de Florida.</ot>
<lk>http://gcrec.ifas.ufl.edu/Weed%20Science/ALAM/Web%20page/ALAM01.htm</lk>
<cn>74-83-9; 542-75-6</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3349</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,P. R.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Validation of 1,3-dichloropropene plus chloropicrin broadcast application in tomato grower fields.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Vegetable Science</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>133</sp>
<op>139</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>broadcasting</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cyperus</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>There is a need to test the efficacy of weed control technologies on a commercial scale. Therefore, large-plot field studies were conducted on tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum) farms during 1999 and 2000, in Florida, USA to compare the effect of 1,3-dichloropropene + chloropicrin (1,3-D + Pic) application methods on rootknot nematode (Meloidogyne spp.) and nutsedge (Cyperus spp.) populations, and tomato growth and fruit yield. Treatments were 1,3-D + Pic (65:35 v/v) applied broadcast at 250 l.ha-1; 1,3-D+Pic (65:35 v/v) applied in-bed at 330 l.ha-1; and methyl bromide (MBr) + Pic (67:33 v/v) applied in-bed at 350 kg.ha-1. Both 1,3-D+Pic treatments received a broadcast application of the herbicide pebulate at a rate of 4 kg.ha-1 before fumigant injection. The results indicated that MBr + Pic and 1,3-D + Pic applied in-bed + pebulate resulted in the lowest rootknot counts, with nearly three times less nematodes than treatment with 1,3-D + Pic applied broadcast+pebulate. However, there were no differences among the treatments for nutsedge density, tomato plant height and vigour, and marketable and non-marketable fruit weight. This finding indicated that by applying 1,3-D + Pic broadcast, it is possible to reduce fumigant rates and personnel poisoning risks and maintain the same tomato yield, and nutsedge and rootknot nematode control as with MBr + Pic.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; eukaryotes; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons;&lt;br&gt;   Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; South Atlantic States&lt;br&gt;   of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 11 ref.</no>
<pb>Food Products Press</pb>
<pp>Binghamton USA</pp>
<sn>1548-1689</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, Institute of Food and Agricultural Science, University of Florida, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20063053180</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://www.HaworthPress.com</lk>
<do>10.1300/J484v11n01_11</do>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3353</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Jones,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of mulches and methyl bromide alternatives on soilborne pests and weeds in spring tomato.</t1>
<jf>Asian Journal of Plant Sciences</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>670</sp>
<op>674</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) JJ900 Soil Management</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>fumigants</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>mulches</k1>
<k1>pebulate</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>polyethylene film</k1>
<k1>potatoes</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>mulching materials</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The effects of mulch types combined with soil fumigants on the yield of tomato cv. Sunbeam and on the soilborne pests and weeds infesting the crop were determined in a field experiment conducted in Florida, USA in 1998. The treatments comprised the (a) untreated control, (b) methyl bromide + chloropicrin (67/33%, respectively) at a rate of 400 kg/ha, (c) chloropicrin at 400 kg/ha + pebulate at 4.5 kg/ha, (d) 1,3-dichlopropene at 325 kg/ha + chloropicrin at 67 kg/ha (83/17%, respectively) + pebulate at 4.5 kg/ha and (e) metam sodium at 485 kg/ha + pebulate at 4.5 kg/ha. Mulch types were either black low-density polyethylene film (0.038 mm thick) or black paper mulch. Application of any of the fumigants with either mulch type resulted in higher tomato yield and more effective soilborne disease and purple nutsedge (Cyperus rotundus) control than the non-fumigated control. Paper mulch appeared to be a valuable alternative to control purple nutsedge without fumigants or in combination with low-volatility fumigants, such as metam sodium. Plastic mulch retained longer high-volatility fumigants, such as methyl bromide, thus increasing its efficacy.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Cyperus; Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales;&lt;br&gt;   dicotyledons; Solanum; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; USA; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries;&lt;br&gt;   Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 18 ref.</no>
<pb>ANSInet, Asian Network for Scientific Information</pb>
<pp>Faisalabad Pakistan</pp>
<sn>1682-3974</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 5007 60th St. E., Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.; bmsantos@ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053081695</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://www.ansinet.org/ajps</lk>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 74-83-9; 1114-71-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3354</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Motis,T. N.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mirusso,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide alternatives for nematode and Cyperus control in bell pepper (Capsicum annuum).</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>903</sp>
<op>908</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>napropamide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>pesticide mixtures</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>trifluralin</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus</k1>
<k1>Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>Cyperus</k1>
<k1>Heterodera</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Three field trials were conducted to determine the efficacy of fumigant and herbicide combinations on nematode and Cyperus control in bell pepper (Capsicum annuum L.). Various in-bed, broadcast and drip-applied fumigants were combined with napropamide, trifluralin, and a non-herbicide treated control. Results indicated that during all the three bell pepper seasons, metham sodium plus chloropicrin (MNa+Pic), and both the gas and emulsifiable formulations of 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D) plus Pic provided equal or better Meloidogyne control than methyl bromide (MBr) plus Pic. For Heterodera and Belonolaimus control, MNa+Pic and both formulations of 1,3-D+Pic were equally effective as MBr+Pic during the three bell pepper trials. For Cyperus control, the herbicides failed to improve weed control. For the fumigants, MBr+Pic consistently controlled the weed better than the others. However, most of the MBr alternatives reduced Cyperus populations with respect to the non-fumigant control. For bell pepper yield, the application of MNa and MNa+Pic provided similar fruit weight as for MBr+Pic in two of the three seasons.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Belonolaimidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Capsicum;&lt;br&gt;   Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; Heteroderidae; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southeastern States of USA; NR: 19 ref.</no>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<pp>Oxford UK</pp>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 5007 60th Street East, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.; bmsantos@yahoo.com; bmsantos@ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20053148299</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<lk>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/02612194</lk>
<do>10.1016/j.cropro.2005.01.016</do>
<cn>76-06-2; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 15299-99-7; 1582-09-8</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3139</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The vagaries of alternatives to methyl bromide for nutsedge control.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>SEP 2005</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>371</sp>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Monocots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cyperaceae [25280]</k1>
<k1>[Cyperus esculentus</k1>
<k1>yellow nutsedge</k1>
<k1>(pest)] [Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>purple nutsedge</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tomato</k1>
<k1>(vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>iodomethane</k1>
<k1>74-88-4/propylene oxide</k1>
<k1>75-56-9/fumigants</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, herbicide)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, herbicide)/1,3-D</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, herbicide)/pebulate</k1>
<k1>Tillam</k1>
<k1>1114-71-2</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, herbicide)</k1>
<k1>drip irrigation</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques/integrated weed management</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200600213985; CT: 44th Annual Meeting of Society-of-Nematologists; CL: Ft Lauderdale, FL, USA; CY: July 09 -13, 2005; SP: Soc Nematologists; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3348</id>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Rosskopf,E. N.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<t1>Performance of containerized and bare-root transplants with soil fumigants for Florida strawberry production.</t1>
<jf>HortTechnology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>461</sp>
<op>465</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF100 Plant Production FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>biomass</k1>
<k1>biomass production</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop production</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>fruits</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>napropamide</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>roots</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>strawberries</k1>
<k1>transplanting</k1>
<k1>vigour</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Criconema</k1>
<k1>Cyperus esculentus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Fragaria ananassa</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>vigor</k1>
<ab>Field studies were conducted in three Florida locations (Bradenton, Gainesville, and Quincy) during 1998-99 and 1999-2000 to: (1) compare the performance of two transplant systems under diverse MBr alternative programs in &amp;#39;Chandler&amp;#39; strawberry (Fragaria * ananassa), and (2) determine the efficacy of these treatments on soilborne pest control in strawberry. Fumigant treatments were: (1) nonfumigated control, (2) methyl bromide plus chloropicrin (MBr+Pic) at a rate of 350 lb/acre, (3) Pic at 300 lb/acre and napropamide at 4 lb/acre, (4) 1, 3-dichloropropene (1, 3-D) plus Pic at 35 gal/acre and napropamide at 4 lb/acre, (5) metam sodium (MNa) at 60 gal/acre and napropamide at 4 lb/acre, and (6) MNa followed by 1, 3-D at 60 and 12 gal/acre and napropamide at 4 lb/acre, respectively. Strawberry transplants were either bare-root or containerized plugs. There were no significant fumigant by transplant type interactions for strawberry plant vigor and root weight per plant, whereas ring nematode (Criconema spp.) and nutsedge (Cyperus rotundus and C. esculentus) populations, and total marketable fruit weight were only influenced by fumigant application. The nonfumigated plots had the lowest strawberry plant vigor and root weight per plant in all three locations. In most cases, plant vigor and root biomass per plant increased as a response to any fumigant application. With regard to the transplant type, bare-root transplants had similar plant vigor as plugs in two of the three locations. Fumigation improved nutsedge and ring nematode control. All fumigants had higher early and total marketable yield than the nonfumigated control, whereas transplant type had no effect on total fruit weight.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Criconematidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; Cyperus;&lt;br&gt;   Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; Rosaceae; Rosales; dicotyledons; Fragaria; South Atlantic&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America;&lt;br&gt;   Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; NR: 1121 ref.</no>
<pb>American Society for Horticultural Science</pb>
<pp>Alexandria USA</pp>
<sn>1063-0198</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Wimauma, FL 33598, USA.; bmsantos@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20063162083</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 15299-99-7</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3142</id>
<a1>Gilreath,James P.</a1>
<a1>Motis,Timothy N.</a1>
<a1>Santos,Bielinski M.</a1>
<a1>Mirusso,John M.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,Phyllis R.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<a1>Jones,John P.</a1>
<t1>Influence of supplementary in-bed chloropicrin application on soilborne pest control in tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum)</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>SEP 2005</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>779</sp>
<op>784</op>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Monocots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cyperaceae [25280]</k1>
<k1>[Cyperus</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Fungi, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Fungi, Microorganisms, Nonvascular Plants, Plants</k1>
<k1>Fungi Imperfecti or Deuteromycetes [15500]</k1>
<k1>[Fusarium oxysporum f. lycopersici</k1>
<k1>(pathogen</k1>
<k1>Race 3)]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>(pest)] [Belonolaimus</k1>
<k1>(pest)] [Tylenchorhynchus</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>tomato</k1>
<k1>(vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(pesticide)/1,3-dichloropropene plus Pic</k1>
<k1>1,3-D+plus/C-35</k1>
<k1>in-bed chloropicrin application</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<ab>Four consecutive field trials were conducted in a four-season study to determine the long-term efficacy of supplementary in-bed applications of chloropicrin (Pic) in addition to 1,3-dichloropropene plus Pic (1,3-D+ Pic) on soilborne pest control and tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) yield. Treatments compared combinations of in-bed and broadcast 1,3-D and Pic with an untreated control and were repeated over several seasons. Results indicated that in-bed applications of C-35 and MBr + Pic consistently had the highest control of soilborne fungus (Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici race 3), weeds (Cyperus spp.), and nematodes (Meloidogyne spp., Belonolaimus spp., and Tylenchorhynchus spp.) and tomato fruit weights, followed by the C-35 +Pic, and 1,3-D +Pic, which had excellent performance in three of the four tomato seasons. (c) 2005 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200510204579</no>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>Santos, Bielinski M. ; Univ Florida, Gulf Coast Res and Educ Ctr, 5007 60th St E, Bradenton, FL 34203 USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3144</id>
<a1>Gilreath,James P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<a1>Motis,Timothy N.</a1>
<a1>Rosskopf,Erin</a1>
<a1>Santos,Bielinski M.</a1>
<t1>Long term effect of fumigant and herbicide combinations in bell pepper (Capsicum annuum)</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>June 2004</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>659</sp>
<k1>Agrichemicals</k1>
<k1>Economics</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>00532, General biology - Miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>16504, Reproductive system - Physiology and biochemistry</k1>
<k1>51512, Plant physiology - Reproduction</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>bell pepper</k1>
<k1>(commercial species, vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>Inline</k1>
<k1>(dosage, soil fumigant)/Telone C-35</k1>
<k1>8069-49-6</k1>
<k1>(dosage, soil fumigant)/Vapam</k1>
<k1>137-42-8</k1>
<k1>(dosage, soil fumigant)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(dosage, soil fumigant)/methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(dosage, soil fumigant)/napropamide</k1>
<k1>15299-99-7</k1>
<k1>(dosage</k1>
<k1>herbicide, pesticide)/trifluralin</k1>
<k1>1582-09-8</k1>
<k1>herbicide, pesticide)</k1>
<k1>fruit</k1>
<k1>reproductive system</k1>
<k1>weight</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200500020497&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 64th Annual Meeting of the American Society for Horticultural Science Southern Region; CL: Tulsa, OK, USA; CY: February 14-16, 2004; SP: American Society for Horticultural Science, Southern Region</no>
<sn>0018-5345 (ISSN print)</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3146</id>
<a1>Gilreath,James P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<a1>Santos,Bielinski M.</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide alternatives for pepper (Capsicum annuum) and cucumber (Cucumis sativus) rotations.</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>October 2003</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1288</sp>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52518, Agronomy - Weed control</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Chenopodiaceae [25795]</k1>
<k1>[pigweed</k1>
<k1>(weed)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Cucurbitaceae [25890]</k1>
<k1>[Cucumis sativus</k1>
<k1>(vegetable crop)]/Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Monocots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cyperaceae [25280]</k1>
<k1>[nutsedge</k1>
<k1>(weed)]/Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Gramineae [25305]</k1>
<k1>[crabgrass</k1>
<k1>(weed)] [goosegrass</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>pepper</k1>
<k1>(vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>542-75-6</k1>
<k1>(fumigant)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(fumigant)/metam sodium</k1>
<k1>137-42-8</k1>
<k1>(fumigant)/methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(alternative chemicals</k1>
<k1>fumigant)/metolachlor</k1>
<k1>51218-45-2</k1>
<k1>(herbicide)/napropamide</k1>
<k1>15299-99-7</k1>
<k1>(herbicide)/pebulate</k1>
<k1>1114-71-2</k1>
<k1>(herbicide) ER</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200400108640&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: ASHS Southern Region 63rd Annual Meeting; CL: Mobile, Alabama, USA; CY: February 01-03, 2003</no>
<sn>0018-5345 (ISSN print)</sn>
<ad>Gilreath, James P. ; Noling, Joseph W. ; Santos, Bielinski M.; Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Bradenton, FL, 34203, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3143</id>
<a1>Gilreath,James P.</a1>
<a1>Santos,Bielinski M.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,Phyllis R.</a1>
<a1>Jones,John P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joseph W.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of 1,3-dichloropropene plus chloropicrin application methods in combination with pebulate and napropamide in tomato</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>December 2004</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1187</sp>
<op>1191</op>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52518, Agronomy - Weed control</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Monocots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cyperaceae [25280]</k1>
<k1>[Cyperus</k1>
<k1>weed</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Fungi, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Fungi, Microorganisms, Nonvascular Plants, Plants</k1>
<k1>Fungi Imperfecti or Deuteromycetes [15500]</k1>
<k1>[Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. lycopersici</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>(pest)] [Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>(pest)] [Tylenchorhynchus</k1>
<k1>nematode</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>tomato</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>542-75-6</k1>
<k1>(fumigant, pesticide)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(herbicide, pesticide)/napropamide</k1>
<k1>15299-99-7</k1>
<k1>(herbicide, pesticide)/pebulate</k1>
<k1>1114-71-2</k1>
<k1>(herbicide, pesticide) ER</k1>
<ab>Small-plot research and large-field validations were conducted to determine the effect of 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D) + chloropicrin (Pic) application methods in combination with the herbicides pebulate and napropamide on pest control in fresh market tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.). In both the small-plot trials and the large-validation fields, various treatments compared the efficacy of soil fumigants and herbicides based on methyl bromide, in-bed and broadcast applications of 1,3-D+Pic, pebulate, and napropamide. The results consistently indicated that either in-bed or broadcast applications of 1,3-D+Pic in combination with pebulate and napropamide are equally effective against the weed Cyperus spp., the nematodes Tylenchorhynchus spp., Belonolaimus longicaudatus, and Meloidogyne spp., and the soilborne disease Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. lycopersici in fresh market tomato. Therefore, broadcast 1,3-D + Pic application can reduce personnel exposure and poisoning risks, without losing pest control efficacy. Copyright 2004 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200500087335&lt;br&gt;ME: print</no>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>Santos, Bielinski M. ; Gulf Coast Res and Educ Ctr, Univ Florida, 5007 60th St E, Bradenton, FL, 34203, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3371</id>
<a1>Jones,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Overman,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Control of soil-borne diseases of mulched tomato by fumigation.</t1>
<yr>1995</yr>
<is>108</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>203</op>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>dazomet</k1>
<k1>fungicides</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant disease control</k1>
<k1>plant diseases</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic bacteria</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>vegetables</k1>
<k1>Corticium rolfsii</k1>
<k1>Fusarium oxysporum</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Ralstonia solanacearum</k1>
<k1>Sclerotium</k1>
<k1>Athelia rolfsii</k1>
<k1>Atheliaceae</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>Corticiaceae</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Hyphomycetes</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>sodium</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Stereales</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<ab>Methyl bromide/chloropicrin (MB-C 67), chloropicrin, metam-sodium, dazomet and dichloropropene/chloropicrin (C-17) soil fumigants were compared for control of soil-borne pathogens of tomato in the spring of 1995. The latter 4 fumigants were combined with pebulate for nutsedge control. Marketable yields were increased with all fumigants compared to a nonfumigated treatment. The incidence of bacterial wilt, caused by Pseudomonas solanacearum, was 92% on plants grown in non-fumigated plots. This was reduced to 48, 26, 20, 37, and 44% for MB-C 67, chloropicrin, metam-sodium, dazomet, and C-17, respectively. Forty-five percent of the surviving control plants had root knot (Meloidogyne spp.), whereas only 4% of the plants grown in MB-C 67-treated soil had galled roots. The other fumigants did not reduce root knot incidence of severity. Crown rot (Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. radicis-lycopersici) incidence was reduced by all fumigants compared to the nonfumigated control. Late season development of southern blight (Sclerotium rolfsii) was reduced by chloropicrin and dazomet.</ab>
<no>BD: Fusarium; Deuteromycotina; Eumycota; fungi; eukaryotes; Lycopersicon;&lt;br&gt;   Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; Ralstonia;&lt;br&gt;   Burkholderiaceae; Gracilicutes; bacteria; prokaryotes; Corticium;&lt;br&gt;   Aphyllophorales; Basidiomycotina; Athelia; NR: 6 ref.</no>
<t2>Proceedings of the Florida State Horticultural Society</t2>
<sn>0886-7283</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, IFAS, Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, Bradenton, FL 34203, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19981701050</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<cn>76-06-2; 533-74-4; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 542-75-6</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3157</id>
<a1>Knapp,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Timmer,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Tucker,D. P. H.</a1>
<t1>Florida citrus IPM</t1>
<yr>1996</yr>
<sp>317</sp>
<op>347</op>
<k1>Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60015, Economic entomology - Integrated control</k1>
<k1>60016, Economic entomology - Chemical control and apparatus</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>64076, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Insecta: physiology</k1>
<k1>Chelicerata, Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Chelicerates, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Acarina [75403]</k1>
<k1>[citrus red mite] [citrus rust mite] [Panonychus citri] [Phyllocoptruta oleivora]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[nematode]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]</k1>
<k1>[citrus]</k1>
<no>PT: B; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199799344901; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region/USA; North America; Nearctic region</no>
<a2>Rosen, D. Bennett, F. D. Capinera,J.L.</a2>
<pb>Intercept Ltd. {a}</pb>
<pp>P. O. Box 716, Andover SP10 1YG, England</pp>
<sn>0-946707-63-4</sn>
<ad>Citrus Res. Education Cent., Univ. Fla., IFAS, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850-2299, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Book Chapter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3377</id>
<a1>Knapp,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Timmer,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Tucker,D. P. H.</a1>
<t1>Florida citrus IPM.</t1>
<yr>1996</yr>
<sp>347</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants HH300 Integrated Pest Management</k1>
<k1>agricultural entomology</k1>
<k1>arthropod pests</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>diseases</k1>
<k1>fruit crops</k1>
<k1>integrated control</k1>
<k1>integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant diseases</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>plant pathology</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>integrated plant protection</k1>
<k1>IPM</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>phytopathology</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Integrated pest management strategies for the control of arthropod pests, plant diseases, weeds and nematodes in Citrus in Florida, are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: B; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD&lt;br&gt;   Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA;&lt;br&gt;   Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; invertebrates; animals; NR: 25 ref.</no>
<a2>Rosen, D. Bennett, F. D. Capinera,J.L.(Editors)</a2>
<pb>Intercept Limited</pb>
<pp>Andover UK</pp>
<sn>0-946707-63-4</sn>
<ad>Citrus Research and Education Center, University of Florida, IFAS, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850-2299, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19971101661</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Book chapter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3150</id>
<a1>Koenning,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Overstreet,C.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Donald,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Becker,J. O.</a1>
<a1>Fortnum,B. A.</a1>
<t1>Survey of crop losses in response to phytoparasitic nematodes in the United States for 1994</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec., 1999</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>4 Suppl.</is>
<sp>587</sp>
<op>618</op>
<k1>Agronomy (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Leguminosae [26260]</k1>
<k1>[peanut</k1>
<k1>(nut crop, parasite host)] [soybean</k1>
<k1>(grain crop, parasite host)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Malvaceae [26330]</k1>
<k1>[cotton</k1>
<k1>(fiber crop, parasite host)]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[nematodes</k1>
<k1>(agricultural pest, parasite)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tobacco</k1>
<k1>(parasite host, tobacco crop)]</k1>
<ab>Previous reports of crop losses to plant-parasitic nematodes have relied on published results of survey data based on certain commodities, including tobacco, peanuts, cotton, and soybean. Reports on crop-loss assessment by land-grant universities and many commodity groups generally are no longer available, with the exception of the University of Georgia, the Beltwide Cotton Conference, and selected groups concerned with soybean. The Society of Nematologists Extension Committee contacted extension personnel in 49 U.S. states for information on estimated crop losses caused by plant-parasitic nematodes in major crops for the year 1994. Included in this paper are survey results from 35 states on various crops including corn, cotton, soybean, peanut, wheat, rice, sugarcane, sorghum, tobacco, numerous vegetable crops, fruit and nut crops, and golf greens. The data are reported systematically by state and include the estimated loss, hectarage of production, source of information, nematode species or taxon when available, and crop value. The major genera of phytoparasitic nematodes reported to cause crop losses were Heterodera, Hoplolaimus, Meloidogyne, Pratylenchus, Rotylenchulus, and Xiphinema.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200000126834&lt;br&gt;ME: print</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Koenning, S. R. ; Department of Plant Pathology, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC, 27695-7616, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2767</id>
<a1>Locascio,SJ</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,JP</a1>
<a1>Dickson,DW</a1>
<a1>Kucharek,TA</a1>
<a1>Jones,JP</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Fumigant alternatives to methyl bromide for polyethylene-mulched tomato</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1208</sp>
<op>1211</op>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>Metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>Dazomet</k1>
<k1>Tetrathiocar bonate</k1>
<k1>Pest control</k1>
<k1>Nematodes</k1>
<k1>Fungi</k1>
<k1>Weed control</k1>
<ab>Tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) was grown to evaluate various chemicals as possible alternatives to methyl bromide soil fumigation. Due to a combination of weeds, nematodes, and soil fungi, the use of a broad-spectrum fumigant has been essential for economical tomato production in Florida. Methyl bromide (MBr) and combinations of MBr with chloropicrin (Pic) are the fumigants of choice for most growers using polyethylene mulch culture. In 1991, MBr was allegedly associated with stratospheric ozone depletion. The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has since mandated a phaseout of MBr for soil fumigation in the United States by the year 2001. At three locations in Florida, alternative soil fumigants were evaluated, including soil injected 98% MBr-2% Pic at 450 kg midline dot ha superior - superior 1, 67% MBr-33% Pic (390 kg midline dot ha superior - superior 1), Pic (390 kg midline dot ha superior - superior 1), dichloropropene + 17% Pic (1,3-D +Pic) at 327 L midline dot ha superior - superior 1, and metam-sodium (935 L midline dot ha superior - superior 1). Also, metam-sodium and tetrathiocarbonate (1870 L midline dot ha superior - superior 1) were applied by drip irrigation. Dazomet (450 kg midline dot ha superior - superior 1) was surface applied and soil incorporated. Pebulate (4.5 kg midline dot ha superior - superior 1) was soil incorporated with some treatments. Pic and 1,3-D + Pic treatments provided good to moderate control of nematodes and s oil fungi except in one of the six studies, in which nematode control with 1,3-D was moderate to poor. Nutsedge densities were suppressed by addition of pebulate. Tomato fruit yields with 1,3-D + Pic + pebulate and with Pic + pebulate at the three sites ranged from 85% to 114%, 60% to 95%, and 101% to 119%, respectively, of that obtained with MBr treatments. Pest control and crop yield were lower with treatments other than the above pebulate-containing or MBr-containing treatments. These studies indicate that no one alternative pesticide can provide the consistent broad-spectrum control provided by MBr. Chemical names used: trichloronitromethane (chloropicrin); 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D); sodium N-methyldithiocarbamate (metam-sodium); sodium tetrathiocarbonate (tetrathiocarbonate);3,5-dimethyl-(2H)-tetrahydro-1,3,5-thiadiazin e-2-thione (dazomet); S-propyl butyl(ethyl)thiocarbamate (pebulate).</ab>
<no>CD: HJHSA; 12 refs.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>S.J. Locascio, Horticultural Sciences Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, United States.</ad>
<an>1998001169</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>92.10.4.2 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection: Fungi; 92.10.4.1 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection: Weeds; 92.10.4.3 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection: Pests; 92.10.2.4 CROP SCIENCE: Agronomy and Horticulture: Vegetables</cl>
<sf>Journal; Article; Plant Science</sf>
<db>Plant Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3367</id>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Chase,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Sinclair,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Rosskopf,E. N.</a1>
<t1>Alternative treatments to methyl bromide for strawberry.</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<is>112</is>
<sp>297</sp>
<op>302</op>
<k1>FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF610 Viral, Bacterial and Fungal Diseases of Plants (NEW March 2000) FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH200 Environmental Pest Management HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000) JJ100 Soil Biology JJ900 Soil Management FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>integrated control</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>mulches</k1>
<k1>mulching</k1>
<k1>napropamide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>pesticides</k1>
<k1>plant diseases</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>plastic film</k1>
<k1>polyethylene film</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>soil solarization</k1>
<k1>strawberries</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus esculentus</k1>
<k1>Cyperus rotundus</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Fragaria ananassa</k1>
<k1>fungi</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>integrated plant</k1>
<k1>protection</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>mulching materials</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Strawberry cv. Chandler plants were grown at Gainesville, Quincy, and Bradenton, Florida, USA in the autumn of 1998 to evaluate the effects of several soil fumigants and soil solarization on fruit production. Napropamide was applied for weed control with all fumigants, except with the untreated check, methyl bromide-chloropicrin (MBr-Pic), and soil solarization treatments, in August 1998. Black polyethylene mulch was applied with all treatments, except with the solarization treatments. Solarization treatments included clear thermal infrared-absorbing film applied with no fumigant, with metam-Na [metam]  1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D), and with 1,3-D  35% Pic (C-35). Clear film was painted black after 8 weeks of solarization, and plants were transplanted in late October to the polyethylene-mulched beds. At the 3 locations, plant growth and yields were excellent with most treatments. Yields were statistically similar with MBr-Pic, C-35, Pic, metam-Na, metam-Na  1,3-D, and soil solarization  all fumigants. Weed growth was suppressed with pre-plant-incorporated napropamide and with solarization treatments. Purple and yellow nutsedges (Cyperus rotundus and C. esculentus) emerged before transplanting with all fumigants except with MBr-Pic and solarization treatments and were controlled with a contact herbicide applied before transplanting. Weed growth throughout the season was not severe except with the control. Treatment had little effect on sting nematode (Belonolaimus longicaudatus) population densities. Colonization of roots by some potential plant pathogenic fungi at the end of the season was significantly lower with MBr-Pic and C-35 than with no fumigant.</ab>
<no>BD: Belonolaimus; Belonolaimidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Cyperus; Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons;&lt;br&gt;   angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants; Fragaria; Rosaceae; Rosales;&lt;br&gt;   dicotyledons; NR: 7 ref.</no>
<t2>Proceedings of the Florida State Horticultural Society; Proceedings of the 112th Annual Meeting of the Florida State Horticultural Society, Stuart, Florida, USA, 31 October - 2 November, 1999.</t2>
<sn>0886-7283</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0690, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20002303724</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 15299-99-7</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3158</id>
<a1>Locascio,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Kucharek,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Jones,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Fumigant alternatives to methyl bromide for polyethylene-mulched tomato</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>1996</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>568</sp>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>52518, Agronomy - Weed control</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60016, Economic entomology - Chemical control and apparatus</k1>
<k1>Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Angiospermae [25200]</k1>
<k1>[vegetable]/Monocotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Monocots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cyperaceae [25280]</k1>
<k1>[nutsedge]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Fungi, Microorganisms, Nonvascular Plants, Plants</k1>
<k1>Fungi [15000]</k1>
<k1>[fungi] [fungus]/Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Invertebrata [34000]</k1>
<k1>[invertebrate]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[nematodes]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Plantae [11000]</k1>
<k1>[plant]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tomato] [Lycopersicon esculentum]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Tracheophyta [22000]</k1>
<k1>[weed]</k1>
<k1>METHYL BROMIDE</k1>
<k1>74-83-9/CHLOROPICRIN</k1>
<k1>76-06-2/1,3-DICHLOROPROPENE</k1>
<k1>542-75-6/METHAM SODIUM</k1>
<k1>137-42-8/DAZOMET</k1>
<k1>533-74-4/PEBULATE</k1>
<k1>1114-71-2</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199699276270; CT: 93rd Annual Conference of the American Society for Horticultural Science; CL: Lexington, Kentucky, USA; CY: October 6-10, 1996</no>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>Locascio, S. J. ; Hortic. Sci. Dep., Gainesville, FL 32611, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3153</id>
<a1>McGovern,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Vavrina,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Datnoff,L. A.</a1>
<a1>Yonce,H. D.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of application methods of metam sodium for management of Fusarium crown and root rot in tomato in southwest Florida</t1>
<jf>Plant Disease</jf>
<jo>Plant Dis.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Aug., 1998</fd>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>919</sp>
<op>923</op>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54502, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by fungi</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Lycopersicon-esculentum</k1>
<k1>tomato</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>Fusarium crown rot</k1>
<k1>fungal disease/Fusarium root rot</k1>
<k1>fungal disease</k1>
<k1>metam sodium</k1>
<k1>137-42-8</k1>
<k1>(application methods, fungicide)</k1>
<k1>chemigation</k1>
<k1>pest control method/fumigation</k1>
<k1>pest control method</k1>
<ab>Experiments were conducted during 1992 to 1995 to evaluate the effectiveness of application methods of metam sodium (MS; sodium N-methyldithio-carbamate) for the management of Fusarium crown and root rot (FCRR) caused by Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. radicis-lycopersici in mulched and staked tomatoes (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) grown on raised beds in commercial fields in southwest Florida. Efficacy of MS was compared with soil-injection of methyl bromide-chloropicrin (MBC), the current industry practice for production of tomatoes in Florida. The incidence of FCRR was consistently high in nontreated plots (80 to 100%), but disease severity varied by site, and yields were reduced by 10 to 57% at sites with high disease severity when compared to sites treated with MBC at 336 to 448 kg/ha. Application of MBC reduced FCRR incidence in all experiments. Chemigation with MS at 701 or 935 liters/ha into mulched beds using either one or two drip irrigation tubes placed on the soil surface, and soil injection of MS at 935 liters/ha, failed to reduce the disease. The application of MS at 935 liters/ha to the soil surface prior to bed formation produced variable results. Rotovation of MS at the same rate into preformed beds consistently produced reductions in the incidence of FCRR equivalent to those achieved by MBC.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199800368976&lt;br&gt;ME: print; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0191-2917</sn>
<ad>McGovern, R. J. ; Univ. Florida-IFAS, Gulf Coast Res. Educ. Cent., Bradenten, FL 34203-9324, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3151</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Obreza,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Conner,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Impact of organic soil amendments and fumigation on plant-parasitic nematodes in a Southwest Florida vegetable field</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec., 1997</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>189</op>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Criconemoides spp.</k1>
<k1>(parasite, pest)] [Hemicycliophora spp.</k1>
<k1>(parasite, pest)] [Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>(parasite, pest)] [Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>(parasite, pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>tomato]</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide/chloropicrin</k1>
<ab>The effects of composted amendments and soil fumigation with methyl bromide/chloropicrin soil plant-parasitic nematodes were examined in a three-year split-plot field experiment on tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum) in southwest Florida. Composted amendments included municipal solid waste, yard waste, and/or biosolids. Population densities of Meloidogyne incognita and root galling on tomato from this nematode were decreased (P&amp;lt; 0.05) by soil fumigation, but increased (Pltoreq0.10) in response to compost amendment, with maximum levels in non-fumigated, compost-amended plots. Population densities of Criconemoides spp. and Hemicycliophora spp. were reduced by fumigation. Application of compost reduced population densities of Hemicycliophora spp. but did not affect Criconemoides spp. Numbers of Paratrichodorus minor were not affected by either treatment. Amendment with municipal solid waste compost was not an effective alternative to methyl bromide fumigation for management of the root-knot nematode in this site within the time-frame of the experiment.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900040287&lt;br&gt;ME: print; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<ad>University Florida, Dep. Entomology Nematology, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2748</id>
<a1>Mertely,JC</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Peres,NA</a1>
<t1>Effect of the biofumigant Muscador on strawberry plant growth and yield</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>6; Suppl.</is>
<sp>S78</sp>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Canopies</k1>
<k1>Conferences</k1>
<k1>Fruits</k1>
<k1>Soil</k1>
<k1>Stings</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Belonolaimus</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<ab>In 2005-06, the biofumigant Muscador was compared to chloropicrin as a pre-plant soil treatment for the production of annual strawberry. The site was prepared for strawberry cultivation for the first time by installing drip irrigated, plastic-mulched raised beds in a former orange grove. The experiment was arranged in a randomized complete block design and consisted of four treatments in five blocks with 20-plant plots. Treatments included a seedbased formulation of Muscador applied at 2000 and 4000 kg/ha, chloropicrin injected at 300 kg/ha, and an untreated control. Treatments were applied two weeks before &amp;quot;Strawberry Festival&amp;quot; runner plants were transplanted. Plant canopy diameters were recorded two months after transplanting. Plants in all three treatments were significantly larger than those in the control, and plant canopy diameters in the high rate Muscador treatment were comparable to those in the chloropicrin standard. Yields of marketable fruit over 21 biweekly harvests were highest in the high rate Muscador treatment, comparable in the low rate Muscador and chloropicrin treatments, and lowest in the untreated check. The cause of the yield reduction is currently being investigated, and is thought to be the sting nematode Belonolaimus longicaudatus.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<t2>American Phytopathological Society 2006 Annual meeting, Quebec, Quebec (Canada), 29 Jul-2 Aug 2006</t2>
<pb>American Phytopathological Society</pb>
<pp>3340 Pilot Knob Road St. Paul MN 55121-2097 USA, [URL:http://www.apsnet.org/phyto/top.asp]</pp>
<sn>0031-949X</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, FL, USA</ad>
<an>6971436</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>A 01360 Plant Diseases</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Conference; Microbiology Abstracts A: Industrial &amp; Applied Microbiology</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3370</id>
<a1>Mislevy,P.</a1>
<a1>Brown,W. F.</a1>
<a1>Kalmbacher,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Dunavin,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Judd,W. S.</a1>
<a1>Kucharek,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Ruelke,O. C.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Sonoda,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Stanley,R. L.,Jr.</a1>
<t1>Registration of &amp;#39;Florakirk&amp;#39; bermudagrass.</t1>
<jf>Crop Science</jf>
<jo>Crop Sci.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>587</sp>
<k1>FF020 Plant Breeding and Genetics FF900 Environmental Tolerance of Plants</k1>
<k1>characteristics</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>drought resistance</k1>
<k1>fodder crops</k1>
<k1>fodder plants</k1>
<k1>hay</k1>
<k1>persistence</k1>
<k1>varieties</k1>
<k1>Cynodon</k1>
<k1>cultivated varieties</k1>
<k1>drought tolerance</k1>
<k1>Florakirk</k1>
<k1>United States of</k1>
<k1>America</k1>
<ab>Derived as a sterile F1 hybrid between Tifton 44 and Callie, the bermudagrass (Cynodon spp.) cv. Florakirk (PI604246) is a persistent, perennial grass well-adapted throughout Florida and north to middle Georgia. It is a high-yielding, fine-stemmed forage that was released in 1994 for hay production. Florakirk exhibits drought tolerance and is persistent on saturated soils, provided plants are not completely submerged. It has good cold tolerance, persisting to a low of -13C with excellent regrowth.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; Georgia; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Poaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD&lt;br&gt;   Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA;&lt;br&gt;   Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 10 ref.</no>
<sn>0011-183X</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Range Cattle Research &amp; Education Center (REC), 3401 Experiment Station, Ona, FL 33865, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19991607030</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3156</id>
<a1>Mueller,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Standardization of reporting procedures for nematicide efficacy testing: A research and extension perspective</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>1996</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>4 SUPPL.</is>
<sp>575</sp>
<op>585</op>
<k1>Conservation</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>00512, General biology - Conservation and resource management</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<ab>Nematicide tests reported in the Annals of Applied Nematology from 1991 to 1995 were reviewed and evaluated for 24 criteria. Most criteria such as soil type, nematode density, cultivar planted, test location, and nematicide applied were reported in more than adequate detail. Soil moisture content and temperature conditions during the test, field history of pesticide use, agronomic-horticultural production practices, and measurements of yield were reported less adequately. Many reports dealing with fumigant nematicides and application by irrigation had inadequate descriptions of rates and application methodology. Although areas for improvement exist, overall the published works in Annals of Applied Nematology are well-reported experiments. Pressure exists from several elements of nematology to &amp;quot;standardize&amp;quot; reporting procedures and test practices. Due to the diversity of crops, nematodes, nematicides, edaphic and environmental conditions that affect nematicide fate, nematode activity, plant growth, and subsequently nematicide efficacy, creation of a completely standardized format is improbable. More accurate reporting of some test criteria rather than standardization will allow better comparison between tests when results do not concur and allow future researchers to duplicate application rates and methodologies to determine the sources of discrepancies between tests, including environmental variations.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199799383574</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Clemson Univ., Dep. Plant Pathology and Physiology, Edisto Res. and Education Cent., P.O. Box 247, Blackville, SC 29817, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2760</id>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,JP</a1>
<t1>Propargyl bromide, biorationals, and other fumigants for nematode control</t1>
<jf>1999 Annual Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions</jf>
<fd>1-4 Nov 1999</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 994 5035); Availability: Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach (MBAO), 144 W. Peace River Drive, Fresno, CA 93711-6953, USA; phone: 559-447-2127; email: gobenauf@agrc.cnchost.com, Full papers available. Contact MBAO for price.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>San Diego, CA (USA)</ed>
<ad>Univ. Florida, Inst. Food &amp; Agric. Sciences, Citrus Res. &amp; Education Cent., 700 Experiment Stn. Rd, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA; Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach, Crop Protection Coalition, EPA, Department of Agriculture</ad>
<an>3511996</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 4300 Environmental Science</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3406</id>
<a1>Noling,J.</a1>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<t1>Joint action of nematicides and nitrogen fertilization on control of Pratylenchus penetrans and growth of Solanum tuberosum.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<sp>309</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH000 Pathogen, Pest and Parasite and Weed Management (General)</k1>
<k1>aldicarb</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>control methods</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>potatoes</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus penetrans</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>inorganic amendments</k1>
<k1>nematicides &amp; nitrogen</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The interaction of nitrogen fertilization and nematicide treatment on potato yield and numbers of Pratylenchus penetrans was measured in a field experiment. Yields were largest under the highest N regime for each nematicide treatment. Nitrogen fertilization did not significantly influence nematode population dynamics. Aldicarb treatment (3.3 kg a.i./ha) reduced both soil and root nematode populations.</ab>
<no>PT: J; CT: Society of Nematologists: Abstracts of papers presented at the 18th Annual Meeting, Salt Lake City, Utah, July 23-26, 1979.; GE: East North Central States of USA; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Pratylenchus; Pratylenchidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Solanum; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; North Central States of USA; USA; North America;&lt;br&gt;   America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Dep. of Entomology, Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, MI 48824, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19800868610</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>116-06-3</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3129</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Current status of chemical alternative technologies for managing soil borne diseases</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUN 2009</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>6, Suppl. S</is>
<sp>S173</sp>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52801, Soil science - General and methods</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Angiospermae [25200]</k1>
<k1>[crop]</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, herbicide)/methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/fumigants</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)</k1>
<k1>chisel applied fumigant application technology</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques/drip applied fumigant application technology</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900592077; CT: Annual Meeting of the American-Phytopathology-Society; CL: Portland, OR, USA; CY: August 01 -05, 2009; SP: Amer Phytopathol Soc</no>
<sn>0031-949X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W.; Univ Florida, IFAS, Ctr Citrus Res and Educ, Lake Alfred, FL USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3130</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Performance assessments of methyl bromide alternative fumigants in Sting nematode infested strawberry fields in Florida</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUN 2009</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>6, Suppl. S</is>
<sp>S94</sp>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>sting nematode</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rosaceae [26675]</k1>
<k1>[strawberry</k1>
<k1>(host, fruit crop)]</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/metam sodium</k1>
<k1>137-42-8</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/methyl iodide</k1>
<k1>74-88-4</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)/telone</k1>
<k1>542-75-6</k1>
<k1>field experiment</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900591616; CT: Annual Meeting of the American-Phytopathology-Society; CL: Portland, OR, USA; CY: August 01 -05, 2009; SP: Amer Phytopathol Soc; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0031-949X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W.; Univ Florida, Lake Alfred, FL USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3134</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Effects of soil physical characteristics on sting nematode impacts to Florida strawberry.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>MAR 2007</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>100</sp>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>53006, Horticulture - Small fruits</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>sting nematode</k1>
<k1>(pest)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rosaceae [26675]</k1>
<k1>[strawberry</k1>
<k1>(host, small fruit crop)]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200700361634; CT: 46th Annual Meeting of the Society-for-Nematologists; CL: San Diego, CA, USA; CY: 2007,; SP: Soc Nematol; GE: Dover; Florida, USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W.; Univ Florida, Ctr Citrus Res and Educ, Lake Alfred, FL 33850 USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2281</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The practical realities of alternatives to methyl bromide: concluding remarks</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1373</sp>
<op>1375</op>
<no>JID: 9427222; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0031-949X; 0031-949X</sn>
<an>PMID: 18943896</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<do>10.1094/PHYTO.2002.92.12.1373</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18943896</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2778</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Reducing methyl bromide field application rates with plastic mulch technology [electronic resource]</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Plastic mulch bed covers -- Emissions of methyl bromide from agricultural fields -- Mulch permeability -- Potential problems with high barrier mulches.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-046; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 Title from Web page viewed on October 15, 2002.; 50013 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS.; 50014 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-046, one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published: January 2002&amp;quot;--Footnote.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.</pp>
<lk>Html version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/IN403; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/IN403pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2779</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematodes and their management </t1>
<yr>2001</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Biology and life history -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis and sampling -- General management considerations -- Cultural practices -- Crop rotation -- Fallowing -- Biological control -- Biorational compounds -- Plant resistance -- Soil amendments -- Flooding -- Soil solarization -- Other cultural practices -- Chemical control -- Nonfumigant nematicides -- Fumigant nematicides.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY625; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY625, one of a series of the Horticultural Sciences Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Date first printed: June, 1995. Date revised: September, 2001.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Caption title from HTML version; viewed March 19, 2002.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV112; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV112pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3149</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Effects of continuous culture of a resistant tomato cultivar on Meloidogyne incognita soil population density, and pathogenicity</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>December, 2000</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>452</sp>
<k1>Agriculture</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>(parasite)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tomato</k1>
<k1>(cultivar-Agriset 761, cultivar-Florida 47, cultivar-Sanibel)]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200100510182&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 39th Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: Quebec City, Quebec, Canada; CY: June 24-28, 2000; SP: Society of Nematologists</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W.; Citrus Research and Education Center, University of Florida, IFAS, Lake Alfred, FL, 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2780</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Florida citrus pest management guide. Citrus root sprouts </t1>
<yr>2000</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Recommended chemical controls.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: Citrus root sprouts; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet ENY-607; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet ENY-607, part of the 2002 Florida Citrus Pest Management Guide, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Date printed: December 1995. Date revised: October 2001.&amp;quot;-Footnote; 50014 Title from web page viewed on October 26, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CG014; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CG014pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2782</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in beans and peas (bush beans, pole beans, lima beans, southern peas, english peas, chinese or snow peas) </t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<ab>Summary: 01 &amp;quot;In summary, nematode control measures can be conveniently divided into 2 major categories including cultural and chemical control measures. None of these measures should be relied upon exclusively for nematode management. Rather, when practical and economics permit, each management procedure should be considered for use in conjuction with all other available measures for nematode control and used in an integrated program of nematode management. In addition to nematodes, many other pests can cause crop damage and yield losses which further enforces the development of an overall, Integrated Pest Management (IPM) program, utilizing all available chemical and nonchemical means of reducing pest populations to subeconomic levels. An IPM approach further requires that growers attempt to monitor or scout fields for pest densities at critical periods of crop growth. Fumigant nematicides listed in Table 1 are most reliable for reduction of rootnematodes.&amp;quot;; Summary: 02 &amp;quot;Nonnematicides listed in Table 2 have not been as reliable against rootnematodes as fumigants, but may be effective against other nematodes under some conditions.For an explanation of the tables in this document, see the section called &amp;quot;Explanation of Rates Listed in Nematicide Tables for Vegetable Crops&amp;quot; found on p. 8 inNematode Management in Commercial Vegetable Production.&amp;quot;; Contents: 01 General IPM considerations -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis &amp;amp; sampling -- Advisory or predictive sample -- Diagnostics on established plants -- General management considerations -- Chemical control -- Nonfumigant nematicides -- Fumigant nematicides.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-20; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-20 (formerly RF NG 20), one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published, March 1999.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG020; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG020pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2785</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in carrots </t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<ab>Summary: 01 &amp;quot;In summary, nematode control measures can be conveniently divided into 2 major categories including cultural and chemical control measures. None of these measures should be relied upon exclusively for nematode management. Rather, when practical and economics permit, each management procedure should be considered for use in conjuction with all other available measures for nematode control and used in an integrated program of nematode management. In addition to nematodes, many other pests can cause crop damage and yield losses which further enforces the development of an overall, Integrated Pest Management (IPM) program, utilizing all available chemical and nonchemical means of reducing pest populations to subeconomic levels. An IPM approach further requires that growers attempt to monitor or scout fields for pest densities at critical periods of crop growth.&amp;quot;; Contents: 01 &amp;quot;General IPM considerations -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis &amp;amp; sampling -- Advisory or predictive sample -- Diagnostics on established plants -- General management considerations -- Chemical control -- Nonfumigant nematicides -- Fumigant nematicides.&amp;quot;</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-21; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-21 (formerly RF NG 21), one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published, March 1999.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG021; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG021pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2781</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in cucurbits (cucumber, melons, squash) </t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<ab>Summary: 01 &amp;quot;In summary, nematode control measures can be conveniently divided into 2 major categories including cultural and chemical control measures. None of these measures should be relied upon exclusively for nematode management. Rather, when practical and economics permit, each management procedure should be considered for use in conjuction with all other available measures for nematode control and used in an integrated program of nematode management. In addition to nematodes, many other pests can cause crop damage and yield losses which further enforces the development of an overall, Integrated Pest Management (IPM) program, utilizing all available chemical and nonchemical means of reducing pest populations to subeconomic levels. An IPM approach further requires that growers attempt to monitor or scout fields for pest densities at critical periods of crop growth.; Contents: 01 General IPM considerations -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis &amp;amp; sampling -- Advisory or predictive sample -- Diagnostics on established plants -- General management considerations -- Chemical control -- Nonfumigant nematicides -- Fumigant nematicides.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-25; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-25 (formerly RF NG 25), one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published, March 1999.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed December 20, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG025; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG025pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2784</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in strawberries </t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Symptoms -- Casual organism -- Field diagnosis &amp;amp; sampling -- Advisory or predictive sample -- Host range &amp;amp; damage -- Control -- Chemical control -- Explanation of rates listed in the nematicide table.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-31; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-31 (formerly RF NG 31), one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published, March 1999.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG031; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG031pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2783</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in tomatoes, peppers and eggplant </t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<ab>Summary: 01 &amp;quot;In summary, nematode control measures can be conveniently divided into 2 major categories including cultural and chemical control measures. None of these measures should be relied upon exclusively for nematode management. Rather, when practical and economics permit, each management procedure should be considered for use in conjuction with all other available measures for nematode control and used in an integrated program of nematode management. In addition to nematodes, many other pests can cause crop damage and yield losses which further enforces the development of an overall, Integrated Pest Management (IPM) program, utilizing all available chemical and nonchemical means of reducing pest populations to subeconomic levels.&amp;quot;; Contents: 01 Biology &amp;amp; life history -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis &amp;amp; sampling -- Advisory or predictive sample -- Diagnostics on established plants -- General management considerations -- Cultural practices -- Crop rotation -- Fallowing -- Biological control -- Plant resistance -- Soil amendments -- Flooding -- Soil solarization -- Other cultural practices -- Chemical control -- Nonfumigant nematicides -- Fumigant nematicides.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-32; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-32 (formerly RF NG 32), one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published, March 1999.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG032; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG032pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3366</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Plant resistance and soil amendments in Florida tomato and pepper.</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<sp>4.</sp>
<k1>FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH600 Host Resistance and Immunity FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>cover crops</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>physical control</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>soil amendments</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>vegetables</k1>
<k1>Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<no>GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Capsicum; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; South Atlantic States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; invertebrates; animals; Lycopersicon; SU: Chapter 34. Available on the internet at http://search.epa.gov/spdpublc/mbr/mbrqa.html</no>
<a2>Obenauf,G. L. Williams,A.</a2>
<t2>Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.; Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.</t2>
<pb>Environment Protection Agency (EPA)</pb>
<pp>Washington USA</pp>
<ad>University of Florida, Institute of Food &amp; Agricultural Sciences, Citrus Research &amp; Educ. Center, 700 Experiment Station Rd, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20001701106</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2787</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide/chloropicrin formulations registered for vegetable crop use </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG034; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG034, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG034; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG034pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2795</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in celery </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG-022; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG-022, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG022; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG022pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2789</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in commercial vegetable production </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Land and crop management practices that help manage nematodes -- Nematode management for vegetables in Florida -- Nematode pests of vegetable crops in Florida -- Multiple-pest interactions -- Types of interactions -- Quantifying nematode stress -- Distributional aspects -- Prescriptive approaches to soil pest control with methyl bromide and chloropicrin -- Weeds -- Nematodes -- Other plant pathogens -- Formulation assessment -- Chemigation -- Calibration and injection -- Explanation of rates listed in the nematicide tables for vegetable crops.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact-Sheet RF-NG004; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact-Sheet RF-NG004, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide of the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG004; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG004pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2786</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in crucifers (broccoli, brussels sprouts, cabbage, cauliflower, chinese cabbages, collards, mustards, radishes, rutabagas and turnips) </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG024; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG024, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG024; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG024pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2794</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in leaf crops []</t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG-026; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG026, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed December 20, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG026; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG026pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2792</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in okra </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Non-fumigant nematicide for okra in Florida.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG027; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG027, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG027; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG027pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2788</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in onions </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG028; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG028, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG028; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG028pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2791</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in potatoes (irish or white) </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Crop rotation -- Soil management practices -- Varietal resistance -- Nematicides.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : RF-NG029; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is RF-NG029, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG029; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG029pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2776</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in sweet potatoes (including boniatos) </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Crop rotation -- Varietal resistance -- Nematode-free transplants -- Nematicides.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG030; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG030, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG030; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG030pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2798</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in sweet-corn </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG023; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG023, part 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG023; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG023pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2793</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Non-fumigant nematicides registered for vegetable crop use </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG033; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG033, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 16, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG033; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG033pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2790</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Pepper production guide for Florida. Nematode control </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Typical symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis and sampling -- General management considerations -- Crop rotation -- Fallowing -- Resistant varieties -- Other cultural and biological methods -- Chemical control -- Fumigant nematicides -- Nonfumigant nematicides.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : SP-215; Alternate title: Nematode control; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is a chapter of SP 215, last printed in 1990 as Circular 102 E. SP 215, Pepper Production Guide for Florida, last printed in 1990 as Circular 102 E, is a publication of the Commercial Vegetable Guide Series, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Publication date, August 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 21, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV184; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV184pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3154</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Relative lethal dose, a time temperature model of thermally induced mortality of nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec., 1997</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>596</sp>
<op>597</op>
<k1>Models and Simulations (Computational Biology)</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>04500, Mathematical biology and statistical methods</k1>
<k1>10515, Biophysics - Biocybernetics</k1>
<k1>10614, External effects - Temperature as a primary variable</k1>
<k1>12510, Pathology - Necrosis</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Cucurbitaceae [25890]</k1>
<k1>[cucumber</k1>
<k1>(crop, parasite host)]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne-incognita</k1>
<k1>(egg, juvenile, pest)]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199800283095&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 36th Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: Tucson, Arizona, USA; CY: July 19-23, 1997; SP: Society of Nematologists</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W.; Univ. Fla., IFAS, CREC, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2799</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Soil fumigation with methyl bromide  : environmental quality and worker safety</t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Method of application -- Potential risks to human health -- Worker exposure during fumigation -- Worker exposure after fumigation -- Worker exposure downwind of fumigation site -- Food residues -- Risk to environment -- Conclusions -- Worker safety -- Environmental.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet RF-NG001; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet RF-NG001, part of the 1997 Florida Nematode Management Guide from the Department of Entomology and Nematology, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. March 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on October 26, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG001; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/NG001pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2797</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Tomato production guide for Florida. Nematode control </t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Typical symptoms -- Damage -- Field diagnosis and sampling -- General management considerations -- Crop rotation -- Fallowing -- Resistant varieties -- Other cultural and biological methods -- Chemical control.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling. : J.W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : SP-214; Alternate title: Nematode control; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is a chapter of SP 214, last printed in 1990 as Circular 98 C. SP 214, Tomato Production Guide for Florida, last printed in 1990 as Circular 98 C, is a publication of the Commercial Vegetable Guide Series, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Publication date, August 1997.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on November 21, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV170; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CV170pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3160</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Physical methods of nematode control</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>512</sp>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Radiology (Medical Sciences)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>06504, Radiation biology - Radiation and isotope techniques</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10504, Biophysics - Methods and techniques</k1>
<k1>10610, External effects - Electric, magnetic and gravitational phenomena</k1>
<k1>39500, Disinfection, disinfectants and sterilization -</k1>
<k1>52801, Soil science - General and methods</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Nematoda]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Spermatophyta [25000]</k1>
<k1>[Spermatophyta]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199698755060; CT: 34th Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: Little Rock, Arkansas, USA; CY: August 5-9, 1995</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Univ. Fla., Citrus Res. Education Cent., 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3161</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The role of soil fumigants in agriculture</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of Papers American Chemical Society</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>210</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>AGRO63</sp>
<k1>Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10506, Biophysics - Molecular properties and macromolecules</k1>
<k1>52805, Soil science - Physics and chemistry</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598436322; CT: 210th American Chemical Society National Meeting; CL: Chicago, Illinois, USA; CY: August 20-24, 1995</no>
<sn>0065-7727</sn>
<ad>Univ. Fla., IFAS, Citrus Res. Educ. Cent., 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3167</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Effect of reduced methyl bromide application rate and high barrier plastic mulch covers on tomato yield and nematode control</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>114</sp>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>25508, Development and Embryology - Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne incognita]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Lycopersicon esculentum]</k1>
<k1>METHYL BROMIDE</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497253145; CT: 32nd Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: Nashville, Tennessee, USA; CY: November 7-10, 1993</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Citrus Res. Educ. Center, 700 Experiment Station Rd., Univ. Florida, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3165</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Soil fumigation for citrus root sucker control</t1>
<jf>Soil and Crop Science Society of Florida Proceedings</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>0</is>
<sp>26</sp>
<op>31</op>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>01008, Methods - Field methods</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]</k1>
<k1>[Citrus jambhiri] [Citrus sinensis]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598122608; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region/USA; North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0096-4522</sn>
<ad>Univ. Fla., Citrus Res. Educ. Center, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850-2299, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3163</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Use of hot water, broad spectrum fumigants, and soil solarization for nematode control</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>562</sp>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>12512, Pathology - Therapy</k1>
<k1>52801, Soil science - General and methods</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64026, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Mollusca</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne incognita]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598151364; CT: 33rd Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: San Antonio, Texas, USA; CY: August 14-18, 1994</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Dep. Entomol. Nematol., Univ. Fla., Citrus Res. Educ. Cent., 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2801</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Citrus root growth and soil pest management practices </t1>
<yr>1993</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Citrus root growth -- Pest population growth -- Citrus root distribution -- Excluding root growth into nematode barriers -- Irrigation -- Conclusion.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet ENY-617; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet ENY-617, a series of the Entomology and Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Publication date: June 1992. Revised: November 1993.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on October 26, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CH008; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CH008pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2800</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematodes </t1>
<yr>1993</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Citrus nematode -- Life history -- Population dynamics -- Symptoms -- Damage -- Sampling -- Single tree samples -- Grove samples -- Management considerations -- Exclusion -- Resistant rootstocks -- Cultural practices -- Chemical control -- Postplant nematicides -- Burrowing nematode -- Life history -- Symptoms -- Population dynamics -- Damage -- Sampling -- Management considerations -- Exclusion -- Cultural practices -- Resistant rootstocks -- Other nematodes -- Summary.</ab>
<no>J. W. Noling. : J. W. Noling.; Alternate title: EDIS : fact sheet ENY-608; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS.; 50013 &amp;quot;This document is Fact Sheet ENY-608, a series of the Entomology and Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Publication date: January 1993. Revised: November 1993.&amp;quot;--Footnote.; 50014 Title from web page viewed on October 26, 2001.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.&gt;</pp>
<lk>HTML version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CH051; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/CH051pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3169</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Chemigational use of Metham Sodium in Florida Multiple-Cropping Systems</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>545</sp>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>07506, Ecology: environmental biology - Plant</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52805, Soil science - Physics and chemistry</k1>
<k1>53002, Horticulture - Temperate zone fruits and nuts</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>METHAM SODIUM</k1>
<k1>137-42-8</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199242035129; CT: 30TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS, BALTIMORE, MARYLAND, USA, JULY 7-11, 1991. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W; DEP ENTOMOL NEMATOL, UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUC CENT, 700 EXPERIMENT STATION RD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3384</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Metham sodium application via drip irrigation systems.</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<is>196</is>
<sp>4</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>application</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>Control</k1>
<k1>METAM</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<ab>The application of metam-sodium [metham] and the factors involved when using it for nematode control are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; NR: 13 ref.</no>
<sn>0360-7550</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, IFAS, Citrus Research and Education Center, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19922319983</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<cn>144-54-7; 137-42-8</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3170</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Methyl Bromide Soil Fumigation for Multiple Pest Control in Florida Usa Citrus Replant Sites</t1>
<jf>Nematologica</jf>
<jo>Nematologica</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>378</sp>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52518, Agronomy - Weed control</k1>
<k1>52801, Soil science - General and methods</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Plantae</k1>
<k1>Fungi, Microorganisms, Nonvascular Plants, Plants</k1>
<k1>Fungi [15000]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Spermatophyta [25000]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>METHYL BROMIDE</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199141029581; CT: SECOND INTERNATIONAL NEMATOLOGY CONGRESS, VELDHOVEN, NETHERLANDS, AUGUST 11-17, 1990. NEMATOLOGICA.</no>
<sn>0028-2596</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W; DEP ENTOMOL NEMATOL, UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUCATION CENT, 700 EXPERIMENT STATION ROAD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3385</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Multiple-pest interactions: the problem of quantifying crop losses.</t1>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>89</sp>
<op>98</op>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>assessment</k1>
<k1>crops</k1>
<k1>losses</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Reviews</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Mexican Society of Phytopathology</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Crop loss is any pest-induced reduction in quality or quantity of yield or the difference between attainable and actual yield. In assessing the loss the first priority is given to breaking down the total loss into its constituent parts and then to identify and rank the relative losses associated with each pest in order to prioritize the efforts to be taken. There are several important aspects to be considered, such as types of interactions, experimental design, types of analysis, temporal and distributional aspects, and economics. As regards the last-named factor, it is important to consider not only how the presence of concomitant pests influence the production function for a particular crop but also how management decisions with respect to multiple pests can be optimized. This paper was presented at the symposium on disease complexes at the 15th Annual Congress of the Mexican Society of Phytopathology, held at Cuidad de Jalapa, Veracruz, Mexico.</ab>
<no>GE: Mexico; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: North America; America; Developing Countries; Threshold Countries;&lt;br&gt;   Latin America; OECD Countries; Developed Countries; invertebrates;&lt;br&gt;   animals; eukaryotes; NR: 70 ref.</no>
<t2>Revista Mexicana de Fitopatologia</t2>
<sn>0185-3309</sn>
<ad>Citrus Research and Education Centre, 700 Experiment Station Rd, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19912310019</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3387</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Methyl bromide use, environmental impact and worker safety.</t1>
<yr>1989</yr>
<is>162</is>
<sp>4</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>environment</k1>
<k1>Exposure</k1>
<k1>Methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>nontarget effects</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Man</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Methods of application of methyl bromide, potential risks to human health, worker exposure during fumigation, worker exposure after fumigation, worker exposure downwind of fumigation site and the risk to the environment are discussed. Under normal conditions the available evidence indicates that worker exposure to cautious, responsible field use of methyl bromide does not produce any unreasonable human health or environmental risks.</ab>
<no>PT: B; GE: North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Homo; Hominidae; Primates; mammals; vertebrates; Chordata; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; NR: 3 ref.</no>
<sn>0360-7550</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Citrus Research and Education Center, Lake Alfred, Fl 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19912304560</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<cn>74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3392</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Multiple-pest interactions: a basis for crop loss estimation and nematode management.</t1>
<yr>1988</yr>
<is>26</is>
<sp>5</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General)</k1>
<k1>crops</k1>
<k1>Fruit crops</k1>
<k1>Fruits</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>Losses</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pathogens</k1>
<k1>pests</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Vegetables</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<ab>The identification of different types of interactions between nematodes and other pathogens, the quantification of nematode stress in such associations and the distribution of nematodes in predicting and assessing crop losses is discussed. The suitability of 9 nematicides against nematodes attacking several fruit and vegetable crops is tabulated.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes</no>
<pb>Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida</pb>
<pp>Florida USA</pp>
<ad>IFAS, Univ. Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19891124353</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3394</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Multiple pest problems and control on tomato.</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<is>139</is>
<sp>4</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH000 Pathogen, Pest and Parasite and Weed Management (General) FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF400 Mycorrhizas and Fungi of Economic Importance, Symbiotic Nitrogen Fixation (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>fruit vegetables</k1>
<k1>Fumigants</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>plant pathogens</k1>
<k1>plant pathology</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>Vegetables</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>Weeds</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>Fungi</k1>
<k1>Fusarium</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Verticillium</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Hyphomycetes</k1>
<k1>phytopathogens</k1>
<k1>phytopathology</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<ab>The interaction of Meloidogyne spp. and Belonolaimus longicaudatus with other soil borne pathogens of tomato are discussed. Methyl bromide/chloropicrin mixtures are the most frequently used fumigants in soil pathogen management programmes, protecting crops from Fusarium, Verticillium, nematodes and weeds.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: eukaryotes; invertebrates; animals; Heteroderidae; Nematoda;&lt;br&gt;   Belonolaimus; Belonolaimidae; Deuteromycotina; Eumycota; fungi;&lt;br&gt;   Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; NR: 11 ref.</no>
<ad>Univ. Florida, Citrus Res. &amp; Education Cent., Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19881106303</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<cn>74-83-9; 76-06-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3393</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Partitioning crop losses.</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<sp>74</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) PP710 Biological Resources (Animal)</k1>
<k1>crops</k1>
<k1>Ecology</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>losses</k1>
<k1>Mathematical models</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Statistics</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<ab>In the analysis of crop losses in complex agricultural systems, it is not always possible to predict potential suppressions of crop yields due to nematodes based solely on estimates of nematode population density. The ability to partition and account for the interaction of multiple pests under varying agronomic practices and conditions is necessary. All these types of interactions and the experimental designs and field studies used to study them are discussed. The use of this information for incorporation into economic, multiple pest crop management decision models is described.</ab>
<no>PT: B&lt;br&gt;BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes; NR: 70 ref.</no>
<a2>Veech,J. A. Dickson,D.W.</a2>
<pb>Society of Nematologists, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Hyattsville, Maryland USA</pp>
<ad>Dep. Entomol. &amp; Nematol., Univ. Florida, Citrus Res. &amp; Educ. Cent., Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19881109201</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3398</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>An economic and epidemiological analysis of the role of Meloidogyne hapla in alfalfa production.</t1>
<jf>Dissertation Abstracts International, B (Sciences and Engineering)</jf>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>2187</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>FODDER CROPS</k1>
<k1>Legumes</k1>
<k1>losses</k1>
<k1>lucerne</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Fabaceae</k1>
<k1>Medicago</k1>
<k1>Medicago sativa</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne hapla</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>alfalfa</k1>
<k1>economic and epidemiological considerations</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<no>PT: J&lt;br&gt;BD: Meloidogyne; Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Papilionoideae; Fabaceae; Fabales; dicotyledons;&lt;br&gt;   angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants; Medicago</no>
<ad>Univ. California, Riverside, CA, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19870840322</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Thesis, Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3186</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Partitioning Crop Losses among Pest Groups</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>594</sp>
<k1>Agronomy (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Mathematical Biology (Computational Biology)</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>01008, Methods - Field methods</k1>
<k1>04500, Mathematical biology and statistical methods</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198732041119; CT: 25TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W; UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUCATION CENT, 700 EXPERIMENT STATION RD, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2285</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Becker,J. O.</a1>
<t1>The challenge of research and extension to define and implement alternatives to methyl bromide</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4 Suppl</is>
<sp>573</sp>
<op>586</op>
<ab>Over the past 30 years, methyl bromide (MBr), a broad spectrum fumigant, has been used extensively for soilborne disease and pest control in the production of many fruit, vegetable, turf, and nursery crops. Recently, agricultural emissions of MBr were implicated as a potentially significant contributor to stratospheric ozone depletion. As a precautionary measure for global ozone protection, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has enforced federal legislation which mandates a complete phase-out of MBr use within the United States by 1 January 2001. Thus, new cost effective, environmentally compatible strategies for control of nematodes and other soilborne pests and pathogens must be developed and tested in a relatively short time to avoid significant losses in crop productivity. The extent to which certain agricultural industries that are now heavily reliant on MBr are affected will depend on the development of sustainable, integrated tactics to pest control, such as combinations of cultural, chemical, and biological tactics. New muhidisciplinary research and extension programs must be developed to address and overcome major constraints and incompatibilities that have prevented such tactics from being widely adopted.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619561; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279928</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279928</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619561</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3405</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<t1>Joint impact of Pratylenchus penetrans and Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Insecta) on the growth of Solanum tuberosum.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>12</vo>
<sp>233</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>damage</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>potatoes</k1>
<k1>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus penetrans</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<no>PT: J; CT: Society of Nematologists: Abstracts of papers presented at the 19th Annual meeting of the Society of Nematologists, New Orleans, Louisiana, August 10-13, 1980.&lt;br&gt;BD: Pratylenchus; Pratylenchidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Leptinotarsa; Chrysomelidae; Coleoptera; insects; Hexapoda;&lt;br&gt;   arthropods; Solanum; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Dep. of Entomol., Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, MI 48824, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19800878512</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2290</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<a1>Grafius,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Joint Influence of Pratylenchus penetrans (Nematoda) and Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Insecta) on Solanum tuberosum Productivity and Pest Population Dynamics</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>230</sp>
<op>234</op>
<ab>The joint action of a plant parasitic nematode, Pratylenchus penetrans (root-lesion nematode), and an insect defoliator, Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Colorado potato beetle), on growth, development, and yield of Solanum tuberosum cv. Superior was studied in the field. Three population densities of P. penetrans were superimposed on each of three population levels of L. decemlineata. The major impact of P. penetrans on final yield was through a reduction in the number of tubers formed during tuber initiation. Defoliation by L. decemlineata increased with time as larvae advanced through successive instars and densities increased. This resulted in a significant reduction in tuber weight and numbers. Total yield of S. tuberosum was decreased by 66% with increasing population densities of L. decemlineata and 27 % with increasing densities of P. penetrans. L. decemlineata feeding did not affect soil population densities of P. penetrans. Root population densities of P. penetrans, however, were significantly (P = 0.05) higher in plants maintained beetle free than in plants grown in the presence of the beetles.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618380; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19294016</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19294016</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618380</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3347</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Buchanon,S.</a1>
<a1>Schumann,A. W.</a1>
<t1>Impacts of EPA proposed buffer zone restrictions for use of soil fumigants on Florida strawberry acreage and production.</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<is>824</is>
<sp>351</sp>
<op>359</op>
<k1>DD500 Laws and Regulations EE110 Agricultural Economics EE111 Horticultural Economics (NEW March 2000) FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>acreage</k1>
<k1>crop production</k1>
<k1>economic impact</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>strawberries</k1>
<k1>Fragaria</k1>
<k1>Fragaria ananassa</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>92 EURO</k1>
<ab>The objective of studies reported herein were to characterize acreage and economic impacts from lost production for implementing fumigation buffer zone restrictions of 100, 200, 300, 400, 500, 1,000, 2,000, and 4,000 ft surrounding each Hillsborough County, Florida strawberry field. These analyses used ArcGIS mapping and buffer tool software to indicate that buffer zone requirements of 2000 ft or more will virtually eliminate 100% of strawberry production in Hillsborough County, FL. In general, and using adjusted centroid values, the results for imposing buffer zones of 100, 200, 300, 400, 500, 1,000, 2,000, and 4,000 ft will cost Hillsborough County strawberry growers approximately $17.6, $37.8, $61.8, $89.3, $115.7, $187.4, $234.7, and $239.2 million dollars, respectively, by reducing available land by 7.4, 18.8, 25.8, 37.3, 48.4, 78.4, 98.1, and 100%, respectively. These analyses show that if acceptable regulatory changes in proposed buffer zone restrictions do not occur, Florida strawberry growers will either have to move to new production sites in which buffers are not at issue, or accept significant yield penalties following use of other, less effective, pest and crop management tactics.</ab>
<no>GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North&lt;br&gt;   America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southeastern States of USA; Fragaria; Rosaceae; Rosales;&lt;br&gt;   dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; NR: 7 ref.</no>
<a2>Albrigo,L. G. Ehsani,R.</a2>
<t2>Acta Horticulturae; Proceedings of the International Symposium on Application of Precision Agriculture for Fruits and Vegetables, Orlando, Florida, USA, 6-9 January 2008.</t2>
<pb>International Society for Horticultural Science (ISHS)</pb>
<pp>Leuven Belgium</pp>
<sn>0567-7572; 978-90-6605-370-0</sn>
<ad>Citrus Research and Education Center, University of Florida/IFAS, Lake Alfred, Florida, USA.; jwn@crec.ifas.ufl.edu; schumaw@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20093281858</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Journal article, Conference paper</sf>
<lk>http://www.actahort.org</lk>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3391</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Ducan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Guidelines for managing citrus nematodes.</t1>
<yr>1988</yr>
<is>27</is>
<sp>7</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>citrus fruits</k1>
<k1>Control</k1>
<k1>fruit crops</k1>
<k1>Life history</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>Pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>pests</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>subtropical fruits</k1>
<k1>Temperate fruits</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>Tylenchulus semipenetrans</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>general account</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>The life history, symptoms of damage and control of Tylenchulus semipenetrans on citrus are discussed. The nematode infests a large proportion (53-89%) of the citrus growing area in Florida, USA, and about 8-12% of the total world citrus growing area.</ab>
<no>PT: B; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Tylenchulus; Tylenchulidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA</no>
<pb>Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida</pb>
<pp>Florida USA</pp>
<ad>IFAS, Univ. Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19891124354</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Miscellaneous</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3388</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Young citrus tree management programs for nematodes.</t1>
<jf>Citrus &amp; Vegetable Magazine</jf>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1544566264</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH000 Pathogen, Pest and Parasite and Weed Management (General)</k1>
<k1>citrus fruits</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>fruit crops</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>subtropical fruits</k1>
<k1>Tropical fruits</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<ab>Methods of controlling plant parasitic nematodes on Citrus in Florida, USA are discussed. These include exclusionary measures, using resistant rootstocks, chemical control and cultural practices.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; North America; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta; plants;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; invertebrates; animals; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA</no>
<sn>0009-7586</sn>
<ad>Citrus Research Education Center, Lake Alfred, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19901145748</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3176</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Estimation of Citrus Nematode Stress and Yield Losses in a Mature Citrus Grove</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>653</sp>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Morphology</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>07504, Ecology: environmental biology - Bioclimatology and biometeorology</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>51000, Morphology, anatomy and embryology of plants</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>PHENAMIPHOS</k1>
<k1>22224-92-6</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198936031827; CT: TWENTY-SEVENTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS, RALEIGH, NORTH CAROLINA, USA, JUNE 12-16, 1988. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W ; DEP ENTOMOL NEMATOL, IFAS, UNIV FLA, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3178</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode Degree Days a Measure of Nematode-Induced Stress</t1>
<jf>Soil and Crop Science Society of Florida Proceedings</jf>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>47</vo>
<sp>249</sp>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Reproduction</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>51512, Plant physiology - Reproduction</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198936030719; CT: FORTY-SEVENTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOIL AND CROP SCIENCE SOCIETY OF FLORIDA, SARASOTA, FLORIDA, USA, OCTOBER 20-22, 1987. SOIL CROP SCI SOC FLA PROC.</no>
<sn>0096-4522</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W ; UNIV FLORIDA, IFAS, CITRUS RES AND EDUC CENT, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3137</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Grower conducted root-gall surveys for field diagnosis and sampling for root-knot nematode.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>SEP 2005</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>386</sp>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>12504, Pathology - Diagnostic</k1>
<k1>52801, Soil science - General and methods</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>(parasite, pathogen)]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Plantae [11000]</k1>
<k1>[plant</k1>
<k1>(host)]</k1>
<k1>root-gall</k1>
<k1>parasitic disease</k1>
<k1>etiology, prevention and control, diagnosis/root-knot</k1>
<k1>etiology, prevention and control, diagnosis</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(pesticide, fumigant)</k1>
<k1>soil sampling</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques ER</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200600214035; CT: 44th Annual Meeting of Society-of-Nematologists; CL: Ft Lauderdale, FL, USA; CY: July 09 -13, 2005; SP: Soc Nematologists</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2287</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Ferris,H.</a1>
<t1>Nematode-degree days, a density-time model for relating epidemiology and crop losses in perennials</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>108</sp>
<op>118</op>
<ab>The impact of Meloidogyne hapla on alfalfa (Medicago sativa) yield was described by a multiple point damage model as a function of current plant status, cumulative pest stress, and crop history. Nematode-degree days (NDD(female symbol)), calculated on a physiologic time scale as total area under the adult female population density curve, were used to express M. hapla parasitism as cumulative nematode dosage. NDD(female symbol) increased exponentially over physiological time at rates relative to M. hapla initial population density of eggs and second-stage juveniles (Pi). Dosage accumulation rates, varying from 213 to 272 NDD(female symbol) per degree day, did not differ (P = 0.05) among six Pi levels. Cumulative yield reductions, increasing linearly with NDD(female symbol) over time to 50% of the M. hapla-free controls, were well correlated for the six initial Pi levels (r(2) = 0.93). Progressive reductions in alfalfa yields to 65% of the nematode-free controls, reflective of the prolonged exposure of the crop to M. hapla, were adequately described by NDD model estimates of either combined population densities of eggs and juveniles or adult females. Cumulative area under the combined eggs (e) and juvenile (J) population curve (NDD(e+J)) and NDD(female symbol) were linearly related (r(2) = 0.97).</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618601; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19290114</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19290114</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618601</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2288</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Ferris,H.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Alfalfa Plant Growth on the Multiplication Rates and Ceiling Population Density of Meloidogyne hapla</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>505</sp>
<op>511</op>
<ab>The rates of reproduction and multiplication of Meloidogyne hapla decreased as a result of self-regulatory, density-dependent processes with time and nematode population increase in the soil and roots of Medicago sativa cv. Cuf 101. Juvenile, egg, and mature female population densities increased at a maximum rate until damage to the host resulted in alfalfa yield reductions. Temporal differences in multiplication and reproduction rates of M. hapla were observed to be a function of initial population density (Pi), host damage, and root biomass, indicating increased levels of competition for a constant but limited number of feeding sites. Over time, a log linear relationship emerged between multiplication rate of M. hapla and Pi. Slopes of -0.90953 for combined eggs and juveniles and -0.71349 for mature females indicated a gradual approach to ceiling densities. Reproductive rates decreased exponentially from an initial maximal value of 200 to a relatively constant rate of 53 eggs per female.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618574; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19294220</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19294220</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618574</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2289</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Ferris,H.</a1>
<t1>Influence of Meloidogyne hapla on Alfalfa Yield and Host Population Dynamics</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>415</sp>
<op>421</op>
<ab>Self-thinning in alfalfa, a dynamic process involving the progressive elimination of the weakest plants, was enhanced by Meloidogyne hapla. Alfalfa stand densities decreased exponentially with time and were reduced 62% (P = 0.05) in the presence of M. hapla. As stand densities decreased over time, mean plant weights increased at a rate 2.59 times faster in the absence of M. hapla. In a stepwise multiple regression analysis, 65% of the total variation in yield could be explained by changes in stand density and 85% by average weight of individual stems. Alfalfa yields were suppressed (P = 0.05) by M. hapla, with suppression generally increasing with time and as the nematode population density increased. Yield suppression was attributable primarily to the decline in plant numbers and to suppression in individual plant weights.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618478; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19294119</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19294119</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618478</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3378</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Futch,S. H.</a1>
<a1>Hebb,J.</a1>
<t1>Influence of methyl bromide soil fumigation on citrus root sucker development and growth of replant trees.</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>107</vo>
<sp>76</sp>
<op>78</op>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF100 Plant Production</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>citranges</k1>
<k1>citrus fruits</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>fruit crops</k1>
<k1>growth rate</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>oranges</k1>
<k1>regeneration</k1>
<k1>replanting</k1>
<k1>responses</k1>
<k1>rootstocks</k1>
<k1>subtropical fruits</k1>
<k1>suckering</k1>
<k1>suckers</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>Citrus sinensis</k1>
<k1>citrus sinensis x poncirus trifoliata</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>Florida State Horticultural Society</k1>
<k1>Rutales</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Two experiments were conducted to evaluate deep probe injection and split application of methyl bromide+chloropicrin (MBC) on citrus root suckering and subsequent growth of replant trees following tree removal by shearing or uprooting. MBC was soil injected, without using a polyethylene cover, to a depth of 45 cm via hydraulically driven, tractor-mounted steel probes. Application rates of 0.45 and 0.91 kg MBC/site were dispensed equally through 2 or 4 injection points around a newly sheared citrus tree stump or vacant but future replant site. Valencia orange on Carrizo citrange or rough lemon rootstocks were used for replanting. Without MBC, root sucker densities were reduced by 95% using traditional uprooting methods compared with tree shearing. For sheared trees, average sucker density reductions of 94% were achieved within the MBC fumigated zone. Highest sucker densities were always observed within the fumigated zone (within 1 m of the stump) which contributed to a significant removal system * methyl bromide dose interaction. The number of injection probes and the MBC application rate had no effect on sucker density reductions. Use of MBC increased trunk diameter and tree height of replant trees only when former trees had been removed by shearing but not by uprooting. There would appear to be no distinct advantage to MBC soil fumigation for sucker control or benefit to replant tree growth when redundant trees are removed by uprooting.</ab>
<no>GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Citrus; Rutaceae; Sapindales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; eukaryotes; Citrus sinensis; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern&lt;br&gt;   States of USA; USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; NR: 4 ref.</no>
<t2>Proceedings of the Florida State Horticultural Society; 107th Annual meeting of the Florida State Horticultural Society, Orlando, Florida, USA, 30 October-1 November 1994.</t2>
<sn>0886-7283</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, IFAS, Citrus Research and Education Centre, 700 Experiment Station Road, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19960302963</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<cn>76-06-2; 74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3138</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Alternatives to methyl bromide using an integrated approach.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>SEP 2005</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>385</sp>
<op>386</op>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Methods and Techniques</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Agriculture</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>(parasite)]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Tracheophyta [22000]</k1>
<k1>[weed</k1>
<k1>(pest)]</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne infection</k1>
<k1>parasitic disease</k1>
<k1>etiology, prevention and control</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>(soil application</k1>
<k1>pesticide, fumigant, herbicide)</k1>
<k1>tillage</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques/drip irrigation</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques/integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques ER</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200600214034; CT: 44th Annual Meeting of Society-of-Nematologists; CL: Ft Lauderdale, FL, USA; CY: July 09 -13, 2005; SP: Soc Nematologists; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3147</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Role of weed hosts in population enhancement of root-knot nematode.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>September 2003</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>356</sp>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>52518, Agronomy - Weed control</k1>
<k1>54506, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by phanerogams</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne incognita] [Meloidogyne mayagensis] [Meloidogyne spp.</k1>
<k1>root-knot nematode</k1>
<k1>(parasite)]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Tracheophyta [22000]</k1>
<k1>[weed</k1>
<k1>(nematode population maintenance role)]</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques/weed control</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200400008022&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 42nd Annual Meeting of the Society of Nematologists; CL: Ithaca, NY, USA; CY: July 12-17, 2003; SP: Society of Nematologists; GE: Florida; USA, North America; Nearctic region</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Noling, J. W. ; IFAS, Citrus Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Lake Alfred, FL, 33850, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2777</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Proper calibration of soil fumigant application equipment [electronic resource]</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<ab>Contents: 01 Dosage and field application rate -- Flow meter calibration -- Tractor speed calibration -- Treatment width.</ab>
<no>J.W. Noling and J.P. Gilreath. : J.W. Noling and J.P. Gilreath.; Alternate title: EDIS : ENY-047; Technical Note: 53811 Internet access required.; 50012 Title from Web page viewed on October 15, 2002.; 50013 At head of title: University of Florida, Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS.; 50014 &amp;quot;This document is ENY-047, one of a series of the Entomology &amp;amp; Nematology Department, Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida. Published: February 2002&amp;quot;--Footnote.</no>
<pb>University of Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, EDIS</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, Fla.</pp>
<lk>Html version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/IN404; PDF version: http://purl.fcla.edu/UF/lib/IN404pdf</lk>
<cn>(ONLINE See Link to Connect)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3365</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Propargyl bromide, biorationals, and other fumigants for nematode control [on tomato].</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<sp>4.</sp>
<k1>FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General)</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>fumigants</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>vegetables</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>plant</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<no>BD: Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; eukaryotes; invertebrates; animals; Lycopersicon; SU: Chapter 33. Available on the internet at http://search.epa.gov/spdpublc/mbr/mbrqa.html</no>
<a2>Obenauf,G. L. Williams,A.</a2>
<t2>Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.; Annual International Research Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions, San Diego, California, USA, 1-4 November, 1999.</t2>
<pb>Environment Protection Agency (EPA)</pb>
<pp>Washington USA</pp>
<ad>Citrus Research &amp; Education Center, 700 Experiment Station Rd, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20001701105</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3172</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Overman,A. J.</a1>
<t1>Estimation of Crop Loss Caused by Nematodes in Florida Usa Tomato Production</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>577</sp>
<op>578</op>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>52807, Soil science - Fertility and applied studies</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>METHYL BROMIDE</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199038049466; CT: TWENTY-EIGHTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS, DAVIS, CALIFORNIA, USA, AUGUST 13-17, 1989. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W ; UNIV FLA, IFAS, CITRUS RES EDUCATION CENT, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3175</id>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Overman,A. J.</a1>
<t1>Movement Dissipation and Efficacy of Ethoprop for Citrus in a Deep Well Drained Sandy Soil</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>653</sp>
<k1>Conservation</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Pollution Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Toxicology</k1>
<k1>00512, General biology - Conservation and resource management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>12100, Movement</k1>
<k1>22506, Toxicology - Environment and industry</k1>
<k1>37015, Public health - Air, water and soil pollution</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>ETHOPROP</k1>
<k1>13194-48-4</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198936031828; CT: TWENTY-SEVENTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SOCIETY OF NEMATOLOGISTS, RALEIGH, NORTH CAROLINA, USA, JUNE 12-16, 1988. J NEMATOL.</no>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<ad>NOLING J W ; DEP ENTOMOL NEMATOL, IFAS, UNIV FLA, LAKE ALFRED, FLA 33850, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2771</id>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Citrus root growth and soil pest management practices</t1>
<jf>Citrus and Vegetable Magazine</jf>
<jo>Citrus Veg.Mag.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>12</sp>
<op>18, 36</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: disease control</k1>
<k1>growth</k1>
<k1>root rot</k1>
<k1>roots</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Citrus</k1>
<k1>Phytophthora parasitica</k1>
<ab>Similar to the seasonal bursts and temperature regulation of fibrous root growth, two population peaks of the citrus nematode, Tylenchulus sempenetrans, and of Phytopthora parasitica, causal agent of fibrous root rot, are known to seasonally occur in mature citrus. Nematode and fungal population cycling is closely associated with and commonly follows major spring and fall periods of flushing.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0009-7586</sn>
<an>3504743</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>A 01027 Fruit trees</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Microbiology Abstracts A: Industrial &amp; Applied Microbiology</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2762</id>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Effects of continuous culture of a resistant tomato cultivar on Meloidogyne incognita soil population density and pathogenicity</t1>
<jf>Society of Nematologists</jf>
<fd>24-28 Jun 2000</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 001 5110); Availability: Society of Nematologists, P.O. Box 1897, Lawrence, Kansas, 66044-8897, USA; URL: www.ianr.unl.edu/son/&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>39th Annual Meeting, Quebec (Canada)</ed>
<ad>Society of Nematologists</ad>
<an>3536369</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 2000 Biology</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2761</id>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Plant resistance and soil amendments in Florida tomato and pepper</t1>
<jf>1999 Annual Conference on Methyl Bromide Alternatives and Emissions Reductions</jf>
<fd>1-4 Nov 1999</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 994 5035); Availability: Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach (MBAO), 144 W. Peace River Drive, Fresno, CA 93711-6953, USA; phone: 559-447-2127; email: gobenauf@agrc.cnchost.com, Full papers available. Contact MBAO for price.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>San Diego, CA (USA)</ed>
<ad>Univ. Florida, Inst. Food &amp; Agric. Sciences, Citrus Res. &amp; Educ. Cent., 700 Experiment Stn. Rd, Lake Alfred, FL 33850, USA; Methyl Bromide Alternatives Outreach, Crop Protection Coalition, EPA, Department of Agriculture</ad>
<an>3511997</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 4300 Environmental Science</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3382</id>
<a1>Norris,F. A.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Jones,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Kirkland,S. D.</a1>
<a1>Overman,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Stanley,C. D.</a1>
<t1>Field studies of ethoprop [ethoprophos] movement and degradation in 2 Florida soils.</t1>
<jf>Journal of contaminant hydrology</jf>
<jo>J.Contam.Hydrol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>3-4</is>
<sp>299</sp>
<op>316</op>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) JJ400 Soil Morphology, Formation and Classification PP600 Pollution and Degradation</k1>
<k1>agricultural entomology</k1>
<k1>degradation</k1>
<k1>effects</k1>
<k1>Environment</k1>
<k1>ethoprophos</k1>
<k1>insecticides</k1>
<k1>movement</k1>
<k1>nontarget effects</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Soil</k1>
<k1>soil types</k1>
<k1>ethoprop</k1>
<k1>prophos</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: North America; America; Developed Countries; OECD Countries; South&lt;br&gt;   Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; Gulf States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; Southeastern States of USA</no>
<sn>0169-7722</sn>
<an>CABI:19921969930</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>13194-48-4</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2763</id>
<a1>Olson,SM</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of alternative fumigants for tomato production</t1>
<jf>91st Annual Meeting of the American Society for Horticultural Science</jf>
<fd>7-10 Aug 1994</fd>
<no>(World Meeting Number 943 0288); Availability: American Society for Horticultural Science, 113 S. West Street, Suite 400, Alexandria, VA 22314-2824, Abstracts available. ISSN 0018-5345. Paper No. 642&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<ed>Corvallis, OR (USA)</ed>
<ad>North Florida Res. and Education Cent., Quincy, FL, USA; American Society for Horticultural Science</ad>
<an>3150778</an>
<la>English</la>
<cl>U 1000 Animal and Plant Science</cl>
<sf>CPI, Conference Papers Index</sf>
<db>Conference Papers Index</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3166</id>
<a1>Olson,Stephen M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,Joe W.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of alternative fumigants for tomato production</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>524</sp>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Invertebrata [34000]</k1>
<k1>[invertebrate]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Nematoda]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Plantae [11000]</k1>
<k1>[plant]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[Solanaceae]</k1>
<k1>METHYLBROMIDE</k1>
<k1>74-83-9/METHAM SODIUM</k1>
<k1>137-42-8/DAZOMET</k1>
<k1>533-74-4/1,3-DICHLOROPROPENE</k1>
<k1>542-75-6/CHLOROPICRIN</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497388328; CT: 91st Annual Meeting of the American Society for Horticultural Science; CL: Corvallis, Oregon, USA; CY: August 7-10, 1994</no>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>Olson, Stephen M. ; North Fla. Res. and Educ. Cent., Quincy, FL, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract; Meeting Poster</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3360</id>
<a1>Rich,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematicides: past and present uses.</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<sp>1200</sp>
<k1>HH420 Pesticides and Drugs: Chemistry and Formulation (NEW March 2000) HH430 Pesticide and Drug Residues and Ecotoxicology (NEW March 2000) XX700 Biodegradation ZZ900 Techniques and Methodology</k1>
<k1>biodegradation</k1>
<k1>chemical structure</k1>
<k1>fumigants</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>techniques</k1>
<no>PT: B; NR: many ref.</no>
<a2>Chen, Z. X. Chen, S. Y. Dickson,D.W.</a2>
<pb>CABI Publishing</pb>
<pp>Wallingford UK</pp>
<sn>0-85199-646-9</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, 30 Research Road, Quincy, FL 32351, USA.; jrich@mail.ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>CABI:20043189775</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Book chapter</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3359</id>
<a1>Rich,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Management of root-knot nematodes and nutsedge with fumigant alternatives to methyl bromide in North Florida U.S.A. tomato production.</t1>
<jf>Nematologia Mediterranea</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>163</sp>
<op>168</op>
<k1>FF003 Horticultural Crops (NEW March 2000) FF100 Plant Production FF500 Weeds and Noxious Plants FF620 Plant Pests (NEW March 2000) FF700 Plant Disorders and Injuries (Not caused directly by Organisms) HH405 Pesticides and Drugs: Control (NEW March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>application rates</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>dazomet</k1>
<k1>fruits</k1>
<k1>galls</k1>
<k1>herbicides</k1>
<k1>metam</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>nematode juveniles</k1>
<k1>pebulate</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>plant disorders</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant pests</k1>
<k1>roots</k1>
<k1>soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>tomatoes</k1>
<k1>weed control</k1>
<k1>weeds</k1>
<k1>Cyperus</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>carbathion</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>metam-sodium</k1>
<k1>metham</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>soil sterilants</k1>
<k1>trichloronitromethane</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>weedicides</k1>
<k1>weedkillers</k1>
<ab>Four field trials were conducted between 1993 and 1996 in Florida, USA, to determine the efficacy of soil fumigant alternatives to methyl bromide for the control of root-knot nematodes (Meloidogyne spp.) and nutsedge (Cyperus spp.) in tomato. Chemical treatments, rates and combinations varied, but generally included 1,3-dichloropropene (1,3-D), methyl bromide, metam-sodium, dazomet, and chloropicrin (Pic). The herbicide pebulate was applied to all treatments except methyl bromide and the controls to provide suppression of nutsedge. Black polyethylene mulch and drip irrigation tubing were laid concurrently with or immediately after chemical application. Data collection in the tests included fruit yield, root gall indices, second-stage root-knot nematode juvenile (J2) numbers and nutsedge populations. Methyl bromide, methyl bromide+Pic, and 1,3-D+Pic produced the greatest reduction in root galling and J2 population densities in these tests while the dazomet and metam-sodium treatments provided variable reductions. Nutsedge population densities were reduced by 1,3-D+Pic+pebulate, Pic+pebulate and the methyl bromide treatments. Dazomet+pebulate and metam-sodium+pebulate provided intermediate reductions in nutsedge population densities. Average tomato yields across trials and among treatments mirrored root galling, J2 numbers and nutsedge population densities. Mean yields for methyl bromide, 1,3-D+Pic, Pic, dazomet (high rate), metam-sodium (high rate), and the control were 58.0, 54.2, 49.5, 50.8, 51.7, and 50.3 mt/ha. Data from these tests indicated that soil treatments with 1,3-D+Pic provided greatest control of root-knot nematodes and nutsedge and produced higher average tomato fruit yields compared to the other methyl bromide alternatives and rates tested.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Cyperaceae; Cyperales; monocotyledons; angiosperms; Spermatophyta;&lt;br&gt;   plants; eukaryotes; Lycopersicon; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons;&lt;br&gt;   Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals; South Atlantic States&lt;br&gt;   of USA; Southern States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of&lt;br&gt;   USA; NR: 11 ref.</no>
<pb>Istituto di Nematologia Agraria, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</pb>
<pp>Bari Italy</pp>
<sn>0391-9749</sn>
<ad>North Florida Research and Education Center, University of Florida, 155 Research Road, Quincy, FL 32351, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:20043013118</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>542-75-6; 76-06-2; 533-74-4; 144-54-7; 137-42-8; 74-83-9; 1114-71-2</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3173</id>
<a1>Roberts,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Kirkpatric,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Arnett,J. D. Jr</a1>
<a1>Ayers,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Crawford,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Mckenry,M. V.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Bibliography of Usa Extension and Extension-Related Publications on Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Annals of Applied Nematology</jf>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<sp>121</sp>
<op>136</op>
<k1>Agronomy (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>00526, General biology - Bibliography</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>52502, Agronomy - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54514, Phytopathology - Parasitism and resistance</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Plantae [11000]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198937002741</no>
<sn>0898-7939</sn>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3132</id>
<a1>Rosskopf,E. N.</a1>
<a1>Church,G. T.</a1>
<a1>Holzinger,J.</a1>
<a1>Yandoc-Ables,C. B.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of dimethyl disulfide (DMDS) for control of nematodes and fungal plant pathogens</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>JUN 2006</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>6, Suppl. S</is>
<sp>S100</sp>
<k1>Infection</k1>
<k1>Parasitology</k1>
<k1>Pesticides</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10802, Enzymes - General and comparative studies: coenzymes</k1>
<k1>36008, Medical and clinical microbiology - Mycology</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>53010, Horticulture - Flowers and ornamentals</k1>
<k1>53012, Horticulture - Miscellaneous and mixed crops</k1>
<k1>54502, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by fungi</k1>
<k1>54600, Pest control: general, pesticides and herbicides</k1>
<k1>60502, Parasitology - General</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Amaranthaceae [25555]</k1>
<k1>[Celosia argentea var. cristata</k1>
<k1>cockscomb</k1>
<k1>(host, ornamental crop)]/Fungi, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Fungi, Microorganisms, Nonvascular Plants, Plants</k1>
<k1>Fungi Imperfecti or Deuteromycetes [15500]</k1>
<k1>[Fusarium oxysporum f.sp.lycopersici</k1>
<k1>(pathogen)]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]</k1>
<k1>[Meloidogyne</k1>
<k1>(parasite)]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]</k1>
<k1>[tomato</k1>
<k1>(host, vegetable crop)]</k1>
<k1>wilt</k1>
<k1>fungal disease</k1>
<k1>cytochrome oxidase</k1>
<k1>9001-16-5</k1>
<k1>(EC 1.9.3.1)/dimethyl disulfide</k1>
<k1>624-92-0</k1>
<k1>(efficacy</k1>
<k1>pesticide, nematicide, fungicide)/methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>74-83-9</k1>
<k1>pesticide, nematicide, fungicide)/chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>76-06-2</k1>
<k1>pesticide, nematicide, fungicide)</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>applied and field techniques</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800468361; CT: Annual Meeting of the American-Phytopathological-Society Joint with the Canadian-Phytopathological-Society/Mycological-Society-of-America; CL: Quebec City, CANADA; CY: July 29 -August 02, 2006; SP: Amer Phytopathol Soc; Canadian Phytopathol Soc; Mycol Soc Amer</no>
<sn>0031-949X</sn>
<ad>Rosskopf, E. N. ; Holzinger Flowers Inc, Palm City, FL USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2750</id>
<a1>Santos,BM</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,JP</a1>
<a1>Motis,TN</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<a1>Jones,JP</a1>
<a1>Norton,JA</a1>
<t1>Comparing methyl bromide alternatives for soilborne disease, nematode and weed management in fresh market tomato</t1>
<jf>Crop Protection</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>690</sp>
<op>695</op>
<k1>Soil fumigants</k1>
<k1>Fusarium oxysporum</k1>
<k1>Ralstonia solanacearum</k1>
<k1>Cyperus</k1>
<k1>Tylenchorhynchus</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus</k1>
<k1>1,3-dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>Sodium azide</k1>
<k1>Propylene oxide</k1>
<k1>Chloropicrin</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<ab>Three field trials were conducted with alternatives to methyl bromide (MBr) fumigation programs to control soilborne diseases, nematodes, and weeds in fresh market tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.). Treatments compared combinations of promising MBr alternatives, such as 1,3-dichloropropene+chloropicrin (1,3-D+Pic) applied with various herbicides, and virtually impermeable film (VIF); Pic in combination with metam sodium (MNa) or pebulate and fosthiazate; propylene oxide; and sodium azide. There was a non-treated control in each season. In all three planting seasons, the fumigation programs composed of: (a) 1,3-D+Pic with either napropamide+halosulfuron, metolachlor, or trifloxysulfuron, (b) Pic followed by MNa, and (c) Pic, fosthiazate and pebulate were as effective as MBr+Pic. During two of the seasons, 1,3-D+Pic with VIF, sodium azide at 85 kg/ha, and propylene oxide were consistently equal to MBr+Pic. (copyright) 2005 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>CD: CRPTD; 19 refs.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pp>United Kingdom</pp>
<sn>0261-2194</sn>
<ad>B.M. Santos, Gulf Coast Research and Education Center, University of Florida, Wimauma, FL 33598, United States. Email: bmsantos@ifas.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>2006118087</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>92.10.4.1 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection: Weeds; 92.10.4.3 CROP SCIENCE: Crop Protection: Pests; 92.10.2.4 CROP SCIENCE: Agronomy and Horticulture: Vegetables</cl>
<sf>Journal; Article; Plant Science</sf>
<db>Plant Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3380</id>
<a1>Snell,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of soil fumigant nematicides for control of root-knot nematodes in tomatoes.</t1>
<jf>Fungicide and Nematicide Tests</jf>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>45</vo>
<sp>167</sp>
<k1>HH400 Pesticides and Drugs (General) FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000)</k1>
<k1>1,3-Dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>Fruit vegetables</k1>
<k1>Methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>Nematicides</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>Plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Tomatoes</k1>
<k1>vegetables</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>bromomethane</k1>
<k1>dichloropropene</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>IKI-1145</k1>
<k1>Secernentea</k1>
<k1>Tylenchida</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>vegetable crops</k1>
<ab>Telone II [1,3-dichloropropene] at 15.8 gal/acre, Terr-o-Gas 67 [methyl bromide] at 267 1b, IKI-1145 75EC at 0.25 or 0.385 gal or IKI-1145 10G at 17.8 or 26.7 1b were applied to tomatoes in Florida for control of Meloidogyne incognita. Terr-o-Gas 67 and IKI-1145 75EC at 0.375 gal/acre significantly reduced root gall index.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Florida; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Meloidogyne; Heteroderidae; Nematoda; invertebrates; animals;&lt;br&gt;   eukaryotes; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; North America; America; Developed Countries;&lt;br&gt;   OECD Countries; South Atlantic States of USA; Southern States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   USA; Gulf States of USA; Southeastern States of USA; Lycopersicon</no>
<sn>0148-9038</sn>
<ad>North Florida Research and Education Center, Quincy, FL 32351, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19932332496</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal article</sf>
<cn>542-75-6; 74-83-9</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3404</id>
<a1>Society of Nematologists</a1>
<t1>Abstracts of papers presented at the 18th Annual Meeting, Salt Lake City, Utah, July 23-26, 1979.</t1>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>293317</sp>
<k1>FF600 Pests, Pathogens and Biogenic Diseases of Plants (Discontinued March 2000) HH600 Host Resistance and Immunity ZZ900 Techniques and Methodology HH000 Pathogen, Pest and Parasite and Weed Management (General) JJ100 Soil Biology PP710 Biological Resources (Animal) FF020 Plant Breeding and Genetics FF000 Plant Science (General)</k1>
<k1>control</k1>
<k1>damage</k1>
<k1>ecology</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>nematology</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>plant nematology</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>techniques</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>eelworms</k1>
<k1>Society of Nematologists</k1>
<ab>Titles of contributions dealing with the effects of soil and soil management factors on nematodes are listed below: Distribution of plant parasitic nematodes on Adak Island, Alaska. Bernard, E.C. 295 Competitive interactions between bacteria-feeding nematodes. Cox, D.L.; Coleman,D.C. 296 Distribution of five plant-parasitic nematodes in alfalfa. Goodell, P.B.; Ferris, H. 299 Influence of Aphelenchus avenae on an endomycorrhizal fungus on cotton. Hussey, R.S.; Roncadori, R.W. 301 A gnotobiotic method for investigating the effect of ectoparasitic nematodes on rhizosphere biota and plant growth. Ingham, R.E.; Trofymow, J.A. 301-302 Reduced penetration of alfalfa roots by Pratylenchus penetrans with increased alfalfa root/soil ratio. Jaffee, B.A. 302 303 Survival of Nacobbus aberrans in adverse conditions. Jatala, P.; Kaltenbach, R. 303 Computer model for life-history strategies of free living nematodes. Kirchner, T.B.; Anderson, R.V. 305 Interaction of yield and nutritional status of tomatoes with Pratylenchus penetrans. Myers, R.F. 308-309 Joint action of nematicides and nitrogen fertilization on control of Pratylenchus penetrans and growth of Solanum tuberosum. Noling, J.; Bird, G.W. 309 Nematode-fungus associations in bananas and plantains. Pinochet, J. 311-312 The effect of clay particles on the migration of Meloidogyne incognita toward and into tomato roots. Prot, J.C.; Gundy, S.D.Van 312 Effects of subsoiling, 1,3-D before planting, and 1,3-D or carbofuran at planting on yield of field corn grown in nematode-infested soil. Rich, J.R.; Johnson, J.T. 313 Influence of different nitrogen nutrition of tomato on parasitism by the root-knot nematode. Spiegel, Y.; Cohn, E.; Kafkafi, U. 314 A bioassay method for the detection of Pratylenchus brachyurus (Nematoda: Tylenchoidea) in soil from peanut fields. Thames, W.H.; Boswell, T.E. 315 The influence of nematodes on cellulose decomposition in gnotobiotic systems. Trifymow, J.A.; Coleman, D.C. 315-316 Anhydrobiosis of the reniform nematode: survival and coiling. Tsai, B.Y.; Apt, W.J. 316.</ab>
<no>BD: invertebrates; animals; eukaryotes</no>
<t2>Journal of Nematology; Abstracts of papers presented at the 18th Annual Meeting, Salt Lake City, Utah, July 23-26, 1979.</t2>
<sn>0022-300X</sn>
<an>CABI:19801955953</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>C; Conference paper, Journal article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2766</id>
<a1>Thomas,MB</a1>
<a1>Crane,JH</a1>
<a1>Ferguson,JI</a1>
<a1>Beck,HW</a1>
<a1>Noling,JW</a1>
<t1>Two computer-based diagnostic systems for diseases, insect pests, and physiological disorders of citrus and selected tropical fruit crops</t1>
<jf>HortTechnology</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>293</sp>
<op>298</op>
<k1>Diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Extension</k1>
<k1>Computer programs</k1>
<k1>Tropical fruits</k1>
<ab>The TFRUIT midline dot Xpert and CIT midline dot Xpert computer-based diagnostic programs can quickly assist commercial producers, extension agents, and homeowners in the diagnosis of diseases, insect pest problems and physiological disorders. The CIT midline dot Xpert system focuses on citrus (Citrus spp.), whereas the TFRUIT midline dot Xpert system focuses on avocado (Peases americana Mill.), carambola (Averrboa carambola L.), lychee (Litchi chinensis Soma.), mango (Mangifera indica L.), papaya (Carica papaya L.), and &amp;#39;Tahiti&amp;#39; lime (Citrus latifolia Tan.). The systems were developed in cooperation with research and extension specialists with expertise in the area of diagnosing diseases, disorders, and pest problems of citrus and tropical fruit. The systems&amp;#39; methodology reproduces the diagnostic reasoning process of these experts. Reviews of extension and research literature and 35-mm color slide images were completed to obtain representative information and slide images illustrative of diseases, disorders, and pest problems specific to Florida. The diagnostic programs operate under Microsoft-Windows. Full-screen color images are linked to symptoms (87 for CIT midline dot Xpert and 167 for TFRUIT midline dot Xpert) of diseases, disorders, and insect pest problems of citrus and tropical fruit, respectively. Users can also refer to summary documents and retrieve management information from the Univ. of Florida&amp;#39;s Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences extension publications through hypertext links. The programs are available separately on CD-ROM and each contains over 150 digital color images of symptoms.</ab>
<no>CD: HORTF; 16 refs.&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1063-0198</sn>
<ad>M.B. Thomas, Horticultural Sciences Department, University of Florida, IFAS, Gainesville, FL 32611, United States.</ad>
<an>1997237512</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>92.9.1.3 BIOTECHNOLOGY: Biotechnology and Bioengineering: Diagnostics</cl>
<sf>Journal; Article; Plant Science</sf>
<db>Plant Science</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3162</id>
<a1>Thomas,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Beck,H. W.</a1>
<a1>Crane,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Ferguson,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>A computer-based diagnostic system for diseases, disorders, and pests of subtropical and tropical fruits</t1>
<jf>HortScience</jf>
<jo>HortScience</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>758</sp>
<k1>Computer Applications (Computational Biology)</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>00520, General biology - Symposia, transactions and proceedings</k1>
<k1>00530, General biology - Information, documentation, retrieval and computer applications</k1>
<k1>53004, Horticulture - Tropical, subtropical fruits and plantation crops</k1>
<k1>54518, Phytopathology - General and miscellaneous</k1>
<k1>60006, Economic entomology - Fruits and nuts</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Anacardiaceae [25565]</k1>
<k1>[mango]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Caricaceae [25755]</k1>
<k1>[papaya]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Lauraceae [26245]</k1>
<k1>[avocado]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Oxalidaceae [26500]</k1>
<k1>[carambola]/Plantae</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Plantae [11000]</k1>
<k1>[plant]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Rutaceae [26685]</k1>
<k1>[citrus]/Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Sapindaceae [26710]</k1>
<k1>[lychee]</k1>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598391918; CT: 92nd Annual Meeting of the American Society for Horticultural Science and the 40th Annual Congress of the Canadian Society for Horticultural Science; CL: Montreal, Quebec, Canada; CY: July 30-August 3, 1995</no>
<sn>0018-5345</sn>
<ad>Thomas, M. B. ; Ferguson, J. J. ; Horticultural Sci. Dep., Univ. Cent., Univ. Fla., Gainesville, FL 32611-0690, USA</ad>
<la>English</la>
<sf>DT: Meeting; LT: Meeting Abstract</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3403</id>
<a1>Vitosh,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<a1>Chase,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>The interaction of nitrogen fertilizer and several pesticides on potato yield.</t1>
<jf>American Potato Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Potato J.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>483</sp>
<op>484</op>
<k1>FF100 Plant Production JJ700 Fertilizers and other Amendments FF061 Plant Nutrition FF000 Plant Science (General) FF020 Plant Breeding and Genetics</k1>
<k1>aldicarb</k1>
<k1>carbofuran</k1>
<k1>chemicals</k1>
<k1>disulfoton</k1>
<k1>effects</k1>
<k1>fertilizers</k1>
<k1>methyl isothiocyanate</k1>
<k1>nitrogen</k1>
<k1>nitrogen fertilizers</k1>
<k1>pesticides</k1>
<k1>plant nutrition</k1>
<k1>potatoes</k1>
<k1>responses</k1>
<k1>root crops</k1>
<k1>thiofanox</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>United States of America</k1>
<k1>Vorlex</k1>
<ab>In field trials in 1977-8, potato cv. (a) Onaway, (b) Superior and (c) Russet Burbank were given 84, 168 or 336 kg N/ha + DiSyston [disulfoton], Temik [aldicarb], Dacamox [thiofanox], Furadan [carbofuran] or Vorlex. In 1977, (b) gave significantly greater tuber yields with DiSyston, Temik and Vorlex; (a) gave lower tuber yields than (b); and only Vorlex at the highest N rate significantly increased the tuber yields of (c). N rates did not significantly affect the tuber yields of any of the cv. In 1978, using only (a), Temik and Vorlex gave increased tuber yields at all N rates.</ab>
<no>PT: J; GE: Michigan; USA&lt;br&gt;BD: Solanum; Solanaceae; Solanales; dicotyledons; angiosperms;&lt;br&gt;   Spermatophyta; plants; eukaryotes; East North Central States of USA;&lt;br&gt;   North Central States of USA; USA; North America; America; Developed&lt;br&gt;   Countries; OECD Countries; Lake States of USA</no>
<sn>0003-0589</sn>
<ad>Michigan State Univ., East Lansing, MI 48824, USA.</ad>
<an>CABI:19800700328</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Abstract only</sf>
<cn>7727-37-9; 298-04-4; 116-06-3; 39196-18-4; 1563-66-2; 556-61-6</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3190</id>
<a1>Vitosh,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Bird,G. W.</a1>
<a1>Chase,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The Joint Action of Nitrogen and Nematocides on Pratylenchus-Penetrans and Potato Yield</t1>
<jf>American Potato Journal</jf>
<jo>Am.Potato J.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>101</sp>
<op>111</op>
<k1>Development</k1>
<k1>Ecology (Environmental Sciences)</k1>
<k1>Economic Entomology</k1>
<k1>Horticulture (Agriculture)</k1>
<k1>Nutrition</k1>
<k1>Pathology</k1>
<k1>Pest Assessment Control and Management</k1>
<k1>Pharmacognosy (Pharmacology)</k1>
<k1>Physiology</k1>
<k1>Soil Science</k1>
<k1>07508, Ecology: environmental biology - Animal</k1>
<k1>10060, Biochemistry studies - General</k1>
<k1>10069, Biochemistry studies - Minerals</k1>
<k1>13206, Nutrition - Minerals</k1>
<k1>51000, Morphology, anatomy and embryology of plants</k1>
<k1>51504, Plant physiology - Nutrition</k1>
<k1>51510, Plant physiology - Growth, differentiation</k1>
<k1>51512, Plant physiology - Reproduction</k1>
<k1>52807, Soil science - Fertility and applied studies</k1>
<k1>53008, Horticulture - Vegetables</k1>
<k1>54000, Pharmacognosy and pharmaceutical botany</k1>
<k1>54508, Phytopathology - Diseases caused by animal parasites</k1>
<k1>54516, Phytopathology - Disease control</k1>
<k1>60004, Economic entomology - Field, flower and truck crops</k1>
<k1>60016, Economic entomology - Chemical control and apparatus</k1>
<k1>64016, Invertebrata: comparative, experimental morphology, physiology and pathology - Aschelminthes</k1>
<k1>Dicotyledones, Angiospermae, Spermatophyta, Plantae</k1>
<k1>Angiosperms, Dicots, Plants, Spermatophytes, Vascular Plants</k1>
<k1>Solanaceae [26775]/Aschelminthes, Helminthes, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Aschelminths, Helminths, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Nematoda [51300]/Arthropoda, Invertebrata, Animalia</k1>
<k1>Animals, Arthropods, Insects, Invertebrates</k1>
<k1>Insecta [75300]</k1>
<k1>NITROGEN</k1>
<k1>7727-37-9/ DISULFOTON</k1>
<k1>298-04-4/ ALDICARB</k1>
<k1>116-06-3/ METHYLISOTHIOCYANATE</k1>
<k1>556-61-6/ THIOFANOX</k1>
<k1>39196-18-4/ CARBOFURAN</k1>
<k1>1563-66-2</k1>
<ab>The joint action of N fertilizer and nematocides on P. penetrans and yield was investigated using 3 potato varieties (Superior, Onaway and Russet Burbank), 3 rates of N (84, 168 and 336 kg/ha), 5 edaphic pesticides (disulfoton, aldicarb, 1,3-D [1,3-dichloropropene] + MIC [methylisothiocyanate], carbofuran and thiofanox), and an insecticide spray to minimize the role of foliar feeding insects. In 1977, disulfoton, aldicarb and disulfoton plus 1,3-D + MIC significantly increased the yield of &amp;#39;Superior&amp;#39; at all N rates. The yield increases ranged 37-56% for &amp;#39;Superior&amp;#39;, 15-35% for &amp;#39;Onaway&amp;#39; and 13-27% for &amp;#39;Russet Burbank&amp;#39;. N had no detectable influence on yield. Population densities of P. penetrans were significantly reduced by disulfoton plus 1,3-D + MIC and by aldicarb. &amp;#39;Superior&amp;#39; was most susceptible to P. penetrans, &amp;#39;Onaway&amp;#39; was intermediate and &amp;#39;Russet Burbank&amp;#39; was moderately tolerant. Neither the potato variety or N significantly influenced the population densities of P. penetrans. In 1978 aldicarb, 1,3-D + MIC and thiofanox significantly increased yields of &amp;#39;Superior&amp;#39; at all N rates. N also significantly increased yields, but only where aldicarb and 1,3-D + MIC were applied. Total yield was increased 12-14% and 17-23% by 1,3-D + MIC and aldicarb at 168 and 336 kg N/ha, respectively. Aldicarb, 1,3-D + MIC, and thiofanox appeared to increase tuber set, while N increased tuber size. Although all of the nematocides provided some control of P. penetrans, aldicarb had the highest degree of efficacy and gave excellent season-long control.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198070019020</no>
<sn>0003-0589</sn>
<ad>VITOSH M L ; DEP CROP SOIL SCI, MICH STATE UNIV, EAST LANSING, MICH 48824, USA</ad>
<la>ENGLISH</la>
<sf>DT: Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2280</id>
<a1>Zasada,I. A.</a1>
<a1>Halbrendt,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Kokalis-Burelle,N.</a1>
<a1>Lamondia,J.</a1>
<a1>McKenry,M. V.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<t1>Managing Nematodes Without Methyl Bromide</t1>
<jf>Annual Review of Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Annu.Rev.Phytopathol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May 10</fd>
<ab>Methyl bromide is an effective pre-plant soil fumigant used to control nematodes in many high-input, high-value crops in the United States, including vegetables, nursery plants, ornamentals, tree fruits, strawberries, and grapes. Because methyl bromide has provided a reliable return on investment for nematode control, many of these commodities have standardized their production practices based on the use of this chemical and will be negatively impacted if effective and economical alternatives are not identified. Alternative control measures based on other chemicals, genetic resistance, and cultural practices require a greater knowledge of nematode biology to achieve satisfactory results. Here, we provide an overview of nematode management practices that we believe will be relied upon heavily in U.S. high-value crop production systems in a world without methyl bromide. Included are case studies of U.S. high-value crop production systems to demonstrate how nematode management practices other than methyl bromide may be incorporated. Expected final online publication date for the Annual Review of Phytopathology Volume 48 is August 04, 2010. Please see http://www.annualreviews.org/catalog/pubdates.aspx for revised estimates.</ab>
<no>JID: 0372373; aheadofprint</no>
<sn>0066-4286; 0066-4286</sn>
<ad>USDA-ARS Horticultural Crops Research, Corvallis, OR 97330; email: inga.zasada@ars.usda.gov.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20455696</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1146/annurev-phyto-073009-114425</do>
<wp>20100510</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20455696</pmid></reference></refworks>
