
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4001</id>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<t1>A Simple Method for Determining Arbovirus Transmission in Mosquitoes</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>108</sp>
<op>111</op>
<ab>We present a simplified method for the collection of mosquito saliva to determine Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus transmission of West Nile virus that can be used for experiments requiring large sample sizes.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000276230200016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4000</id>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<t1>Effects of West Nile Virus Dose and Extrinsic Incubation Temperature on Temporal Progression of Vector Competence in Culex Pipiens Quinquefasciatus</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>103</sp>
<op>107</op>
<ab>Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus were fed blood containing either 7.0 +/- 0.1 logs plaque-forming units (pfu)/ml (high dose) or 5.9 +/- 0.1 logs pfu/ml (low dose) of West Nile virus and held at extrinsic incubation temperatures (EIT) of 28 degrees C or 25 degrees C. Approximately 20 mosquitoes per dose were collected after incubation periods (EP) of 4, 6, 8, and 12 days postinfection (dpi). Infection rates were influenced by EIT and virus dose but not by IP. Body titer was significantly higher for mosquitoes fed the high dose and held at 28 C at the later IPs (6, 8, and 12 dpi). However, leg titer was significantly higher for mosquitoes at the later IPs but did not differ between EITs or doses. Because infection rates varied with EIT and dose, there is likely a midgut infection barrier influenced by these factors that is not influenced by IP. Dissemination rates were influenced by all 3 factors consistent with the presence of a midgut escape barrier. Dissemination rate, body titer, and leg titer were dependent on IP, indicating the need to investigate multiple time points in vector competence studies to elucidate critical events in infection and dissemination.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000276230200015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4003</id>
<a1>Eans,Shainnel</a1>
<a1>Frommer,Robert L.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and Spatial Expression Analysis of a Partial Esterase Gene of Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1370</sp>
<op>1375</op>
<ab>Mosquitoes play an important role as vectors for a variety of pathogens. Insecticide use for control means results in selection of tolerant/resistant mosquitoes. An esterase cDNA was isolated from Culex nigripalpus Theobald (Diptera: Culicidae), and its spatial expression was characterized. GenBank tblastx and VectorBase searches with the translation product of the longest cDNA fragment (397 bp CN Temsha est-1) of the Cx. nigripalpus esterase revealed similarity (95%) to the estalpha2 esterase gene product of Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say, suggesting it is a member of the esterase family. Transcripts encoding Cx. nigripalpus esterase were detected in midgut tissue, thoraces, and abdomens of female Cx. nigripalpus, findings that may support possible roles in feeding, digestion, or reproduction. Gene expression studies to determine the role of Cx. nigripalpus esterase in the mosquito are being conducted.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000271591800016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4004</id>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Erickson,Jennifer S.</a1>
<t1>Expression of a Novel Member of the Odorant-Binding Protein Gene Family in Culex nigripalpus (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1376</sp>
<op>1381</op>
<ab>We previously showed that gene expression in the midgut of female Culex nigripalpus Theobald (Diptera: Culicidae) was altered after ingestion of a bloodmeal and some of the expressed cDNAs showed stage-, sex-, and tissue-specific expression. One of these expressed cDNAs, CN G11B, is here shown to be similar to members of a gene family that encodes odorant-binding proteins. CN G11B.1 is a cDNA fragment of 721 bp, is incomplete at the 5&amp;#39;-end, and contains a canonical polyadenylic acid tail signal sequence in the 103-bp 3&amp;#39;-untranslated region. Translation of CN G11B.1 provides a putative protein product of 207 amino acids. CenBank tblastx, VectorBase, and Pfam database searches showed identity to hypothetical proteins from Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say (86%) and Aedes aegypti (L.) (55%). These proteins have structural motifs similar to those found in the gene family that includes odorant-binding proteins. CN G11B.1 putative protein has two of the six cysteines that are highly conserved in most invertebrate odorant-binding proteins. CN G11B.1 expression increased in thoraces (6-12 h) and in abdomens (3-48 h) of blood fed female Cx. nigripalpus but was not detected in RNA from heads, indicating a possible role in both chemoreception and blood feeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000271591800017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4008</id>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Erickson,Jennifer S.</a1>
<t1>Bloodmeal-induced differential gene expression in the disease vector Culex nigripalpus (Diptera : Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>326</sp>
<op>330</op>
<ab>We have characterized gene expression changes in the midgut tissue of Culex nigripalpus Theobold (Diptera: Culicidae) females, after they ingest a bloodmeal, by differential display of RNA isolated from pre- and postfeeding females. Seventy-two cDNA fragments exhibiting reproducible differences were observed. Of these, 22 showed an increase in gene expression and 50 showed a decrease in gene expression as a result of blood feeding. Eleven cDNA fragments exhibiting increased expression after a bloodmeal were cloned and sequenced. Seven of these were novel transcripts, and they did not match any sequences in GenBank. Three clones were similar to conserved proteins of unknown function from Aedes aegypti (L.) and Anopheles gambiae Giles. Here, we present the expression data on the first cDNA clones isolated from Cx. nigripalpus midgut tissue, including their molecular characterization, and we discuss their possible involvement in blood-feeding-associated processes and disease transmission.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000253555700018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4007</id>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Erickson,Jennifer S.</a1>
<t1>CNAct-1 gene is differentially expressed in the subtropical mosquito Culex nigripalpus (Diptera : Culicidae), the primary West Nile virus vector in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>877</sp>
<op>884</op>
<ab>Analysis of differentially expressed genes is a common molecular biological tool to investigate changes in mosquito genes after a bloodmeal or parasite exposure. We report here the characterization of a differentially expressed actin gene, CNAct-1, from the subtropical mosquito, Culex nigripalpus Theobald (Diptera: Culicidae). The CNAct-1 genomic clone is 1.525 kb, includes one 66-bp intron, and a 328-bp 3&amp;#39;-untranslated region. The 376-amino acid putative translation product shares high similarity with muscle-specific actin proteins from other insects, including Culex pipiens pipiens L., Aedes aegypti (L.), Anopheles gambiae Giles and Drosophila melanogaster (Meigen). CNAct-1 is expressed in second and third instars, late pupae, and adult females and males. Interestingly, Cx. nigripalpus actin was highly expressed in female mosquito midgut tissue isolated 6-12 h after ingestion of a bloodmeal. This expression profile indicates a unique function for CNAct-1 in midgut processes that are initiated after blood ingestion.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000259099000008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4006</id>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Erickson,Jennifer S.</a1>
<t1>West Nile Virus Infection Alters Midgut Gene Expression in Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>258</sp>
<op>263</op>
<ab>Alterations in gene expression in the midgut of female Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus exposed to blood meals containing 6.8 logs plaque-forming units/mL of West Nile virus (WNV) were Studied by fluorescent differential display. Twenty-six different cDNAs exhibited reproducible differences after feeding on infected blood. Of these, 21 cDNAs showed an increase in expression, and 5 showed a decrease in expression as a result of WNV presence in the blood meal. GenBank database searches showed that one clone with increased expression, CQ G12A2, shares 94% identify with a leucine-rich repeat-containing protein from Cx. p. quinquefasciatus and 32% identify to Toll-like receptors from Aedes aegypti. We present the first cDNA clone isolated from female Cx. p. quinquefasciatus midgut tissue whose expression changes Oil exposure to WNV This cDNA represents it mosquito gene that is an excellent candidate for interacting, with WNV in Cx. p. quinquefasciatus and may play a role in disease transmission.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>000268360400015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4002</id>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Vitek,Christopher J.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Forced Egg Retention on the Temporal Progression of West Nile Virus Infection in Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>190</sp>
<op>194</op>
<ab>Environmental factors that impact the biology of mosquito vectors can have epidemiological implications. Lack of oviposition sites facilitated by environmental factors such as temperature and drought can often force Culex spp. mosquitoes to retain their eggs. Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say were fed blood meals containing West Nile virus (WNV; family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus) and either allowed to oviposit or forced to retain their eggs through different time points postinfection (9, 13, 20, 27 d) at 28 degrees C. Oviposition status did not significantly affect rates of WNV infection (% with virus-positive bodies), dissemination (% with virus-positive legs), or transmission (% with virus-positive saliva) for any of the tested time points. As expected, WNV titers in bodies and legs were significantly (P &amp;lt; 0.05) higher at late time points compared with early time points. No significant differences were observed in WNV titers in saliva between time points. There were no significant effects of oviposition status on virus titers of bodies, legs, or saliva. However, we found that egg retention may increase vector competence at early and late time points after infection and that a single oviposition event may decrease vector competence, possibly by activating an immune response against the virus. Environmental changes that influence mosquito biology are important determinants of virus transmission, and further studies are needed to assess the effects of drought on virus transmission risk and how these interactions affect our interpretation of field data.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000274498000022</an>
<do>10.1603/EN09172</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4005</id>
<a1>Vitek,Christopher J.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Robinson,Heather L.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<t1>A Model to Assess the Accuracy of Detecting Arboviruses in Mosquito Pools</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>374</sp>
<op>378</op>
<ab>Vigilant surveillance of virus prevalence in mosquitoes is essential for risk assessment and outbreak prediction. Accurate virus detection methods are essential for arbovirus surveillance. We have developed a model to estimate the probability of accurately detecting a virus-positive mosquito from pooled Field collections using standard molecular techniques. We discuss several factors influencing the probability of virus detection, including the number of virions in the sample, the total sample volume, and the portion of the sample volume that is being tested. Our model determines the probability of obtaining at least 1 virion in the sample that is tested. The model also determines the optimal sample volume that is required in any test to ensure a desired probability of virus detection is achieved, and can be used to support the accuracy of current tests or to optimize existing techniques.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000270598300023</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
