<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>106</id>
<a1>Barmina,O.</a1>
<a1>Gonzalo,M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Kopp,A.</a1>
<t1>Sex- and segment-specific modulation of gene expression profiles in Drosophila</t1>
<jf>Developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec 15</fd>
<vo>288</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>528</sp>
<op>544</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Extremities/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Pupa</k1>
<k1>Sex Differentiation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Homeotic and sex-determining genes control a wide range of morphological traits by regulating the expression of different target genes in different tissues. The identity of most of these target genes remains unknown, and it is not even clear what fraction of the genome is regulated in a segment- and sex-specific manner. In this report, we examine segment- and sex-specific gene expression in Drosophila pupal legs. The first and second legs in Drosophila have clearly distinguishable bristle patterns. Bristle pattern in the first leg also differs between males and females, whereas the second leg has no overt sexual dimorphism. To identify the genes responsible for these differences, we compared transcriptional profiles between male and female first and second legs during early pupal development. The extent of sexually dimorphic gene expression parallels morphological differences: over 100 genes are expressed sex specifically in the first leg, whereas no sexual differences are seen in the second leg. Segmental differences are less extensive than sexual dimorphism and involve fewer than 14 genes. We have identified a novel gene, CG13857, that is expressed exclusively in the first leg in a pattern that suggests this gene may play an important role in specifying segment- and sex-specific bristle patterns.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081015; GR: 1R24GM065513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK35747/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372762; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (DSX protein, Drosophila); 0 (Drosophila Proteins); 0 (Sex combs reduced protein, Drosophila); 0 (Transcription Factors); 2005/08/04 [received]; 2005/09/28 [revised]; 2005/09/30 [accepted]; 2005/11/02 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0012-1606; 0012-1606</sn>
<ad>Section of Evolution and Ecology, Center for Genetics and Development, University of California-Davis, One Shields Ave., Davis, CA 95616, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16269142; S0012-1606(05)00689-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ydbio.2005.09.052</do>
<wp>20051102</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16269142</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>118</id>
<a1>Bepler,G.</a1>
<a1>Gautam,A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Beck,A. F.</a1>
<a1>Chervinsky,D. S.</a1>
<a1>Kim,Y. C.</a1>
<a1>Pitterle,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Hyland,A.</a1>
<t1>Prognostic significance of molecular genetic aberrations on chromosome segment 11p15.5 in non-small-cell lung cancer</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Mar 1</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1353</sp>
<op>1360</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung/genetics/mortality</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 11</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Loss of Heterozygosity</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms/genetics/mortality</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Regression Analysis</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: The assessment of prognosis and decisions on treatment for patients with non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) are determined on the basis of disease stage and performance status. NSCLC frequently manifests loss of heterozygosity (LOH) at chromosome segment 11p15.5. Whether LOH at 11p15.5 is an independent prognostic variable has yet to be determined. PATIENTS AND METHODS: We developed five novel markers, which can be assessed by polymerase chain reaction and restriction enzyme digestion. LOH at 11p15.5 was assessed in 193 patients who underwent surgical resection for pathologic stage I and II of the disease. RESULTS: LOH at 11p15.5 was associated with poor survival (P =.021). Multivariate logistic regression analysis showed that after disease stage, performance status, weight loss, sex, age at diagnosis, and smoking history were controlled for, patients with LOH were two times more likely to die than those without LOH (relative risk [RR] = 2.01, P =.021). Cox regression analysis with disease stage and LOH revealed that the survival of patients with stage I disease and LOH was similar to the survival of patients with stage II disease, and it was significantly worse than the survival of stage I patients without LOH (RR = 2.38, P =.038). CONCLUSION: LOH in a 310-kb region on chromosome segment 11p15.5 that includes the gene for the regulatory subunit of the enzyme ribonucleotide reductase is highly predictive of poor survival from NSCLC. The future utility of analysis of the allelic status of this region may involve treatment decisions, such as the use of neoadjuvant and adjuvant chemotherapy for patients with stage I disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5P01 CA 72099/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: 5R01 CA 70317/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8309333; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0732-183X; 0732-183X</sn>
<ad>Lung Cancer Program, Roswell Park Cancer Institute, Buffalo, NY, USA. beplerg@moffitt.usf.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11870179</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11870179</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>91</id>
<a1>Bosworth,H. B.</a1>
<a1>Parsey,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Butterfield,M. I.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Oddone,E. Z.</a1>
<a1>Stechuchak,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Bastian,L. A.</a1>
<t1>Racial variation in wanting and obtaining mental health services among women veterans in a primary care clinic.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the National Medical Association</jf>
<jo>J.Natl.Med.Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>231</sp>
<pb>National Medical Association</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>128</id>
<a1>Butterfield,M.</a1>
<a1>Bastian,L. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Koons,C.</a1>
<a1>Vollmer,M.</a1>
<a1>Burns,B.</a1>
<t1>Screening for mental disorder symptoms and a history of sexual trauma and battering among women using primary health services</t1>
<jf>Journal of Clinical Outcomes Management</jf>
<jo>J. Clinical Outcomes Management</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>3</vo>
<sp>55-61</sp>
<op>55-61</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>127</id>
<a1>Butterfield,M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Stechuchak,K.</a1>
<a1>Nanda,K.</a1>
<a1>Bastian,L. A.</a1>
<t1>Mental disorder symptoms in veteran women: Impact of physical and sexual assault</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Medical Women&#39;s Association</jf>
<jo>J. Am. Med. Women&#39;s Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>53</vo>
<sp>198-200</sp>
<op>198-200</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>72</id>
<a1>Coffman,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Higgins,L. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Identification of co-regulated transcripts affecting male body size in Drosophila</t1>
<jf>Genome Biol</jf>
<jo>Genome Biol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>R53</sp>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>107</id>
<a1>Coffman,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Doerge,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Simonsen,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Nichols,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Duarte,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Wolfinger,R. D.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Model selection in binary trait locus mapping</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>170</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1281</sp>
<op>1297</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping/methods</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Epistasis, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Genes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>Oncorhynchus mykiss/genetics</k1>
<ab>Quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping methodology for continuous normally distributed traits is the subject of much attention in the literature. Binary trait locus (BTL) mapping in experimental populations has received much less attention. A binary trait by definition has only two possible values, and the penetrance parameter is restricted to values between zero and one. Due to this restriction, the infinitesimal model appears to come into play even when only a few loci are involved, making selection of an appropriate genetic model in BTL mapping challenging. We present a probability model for an arbitrary number of BTL and demonstrate that, given adequate sample sizes, the power for detecting loci is high under a wide range of genetic models, including most epistatic models. A novel model selection strategy based upon the underlying genetic map is employed for choosing the genetic model. We propose selecting the &amp;quot;best&amp;quot; marker from each linkage group, regardless of significance. This reduces the model space so that an efficient search for epistatic loci can be conducted without invoking stepwise model selection. This procedure can identify unlinked epistatic BTL, demonstrated by our simulations and the reanalysis of Oncorhynchus mykiss experimental data.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 2G12RR003048/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: AG16996/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0374636; OID: NLM: PMC1451193; 2005/04/16 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0016-6731; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Institute for Clinical and Epidemiological Research Biostatistics Unit, Durham VA Medical Center (152), Durham, North Carolina 27705, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15834149; genetics.104.033910 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1534/genetics.104.033910</do>
<wp>20050416</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15834149</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1451193</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>78</id>
<a1>Coffman,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Doerge,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Intersection tests for single marker QTL analysis can be more powerful than two marker QTL analysis</t1>
<jf>BMC genetics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genet.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun 19</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<sp>10</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping/methods</k1>
<k1>Drosophila melanogaster/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Markers</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>Quantitative Trait Loci</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: It has been reported in the quantitative trait locus (QTL) literature that when testing for QTL location and effect, the statistical power supporting methodologies based on two markers and their estimated genetic map is higher than for the genetic map independent methodologies known as single marker analyses. Close examination of these reports reveals that the two marker approaches are more powerful than single marker analyses only in certain cases. Simulation studies are a commonly used tool to determine the behavior of test statistics under known conditions. We conducted a simulation study to assess the general behavior of an intersection test and a two marker test under a variety of conditions. The study was designed to reveal whether two marker tests are always more powerful than intersection tests, or whether there are cases when an intersection test may outperform the two marker approach.We present a reanalysis of a data set from a QTL study of ovariole number in Drosophila melanogaster. RESULTS: Our simulation study results show that there are situations where the single marker intersection test equals or outperforms the two marker test. The intersection test and the two marker test identify overlapping regions in the reanalysis of the Drosophila melanogaster data. The region identified is consistent with a regression based interval mapping analysis. CONCLUSION: We find that the intersection test is appropriate for analysis of QTL data. This approach has the advantage of simplicity and for certain situations supplies equivalent or more powerful results than a comparable two marker test.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AG16996/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM59884-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100966978; 0 (Genetic Markers); OID: NLM: PMC166174; 2002/11/26 [received]; 2003/06/19 [accepted]; 2003/06/19 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2156; 1471-2156</sn>
<ad>Institute for Clinical and Epidemiological Research, Biostatistics Unit, Durham VA Medical Center (152), Durham, NC 27705, USA. cynthia.coffman@duke.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12816551</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1471-2156-4-10</do>
<wp>20030619</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12816551</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC166174</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>122</id>
<a1>Denmark-Wahnefried,W.</a1>
<a1>Schildkraut,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,D.</a1>
<a1>Lesko,S. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Schwingl,P.</a1>
<a1>Paulson,D. F.</a1>
<a1>Robertson,C. N.</a1>
<a1>Anderson,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Walther,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Early onset baldness and prostate cancer risk</t1>
<jf>Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</jf>
<jo>Cancer Epidemiol.Biomarkers Prev.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>325</sp>
<op>328</op>
<k1>Adenocarcinoma/etiology</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Age of Onset</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Alopecia/classification/complications</k1>
<k1>Case-Control Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Prostatic Neoplasms/etiology</k1>
<k1>Regression Analysis</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<ab>Prostatic carcinoma is the leading cancer among American men, yet few risk factors have been established. Although increased androgen levels have long been associated with both prostatic carcinoma and baldness, to date no studies have shown an association between hair patterning and prostate cancer risk. A lack of standardized instruments to assess baldness or the assessment of hair patterning during uninformative periods of time may have precluded the ability of previous studies to detect an association. We hypothesized that baldness, specifically vertex baldness, should be assessed using standardized instruments and during early adulthood if an association with prostate cancer risk is to be found. To test this hypothesis, we included identical items related to hair patterning in surveys that were administered in two distinct prostate cancer case-control studies (Duke-based study, n = 149; 78 cases; 71 controls and community-based study, n = 130; 56 cases; 74 controls). In each, participants were provided with an illustration of the Hamilton Scale of Baldness and asked to select the diagrams that best represented their hair patterning at age 30 and again at age 40. From these data, the following five categories were created and compared: not bald (referent group); vertex bald early onset (by age 30); vertex bald later onset (by age 40); frontal bald early onset (by age 30); frontal bald later onset (by age 40); and frontal (at age 30) to vertex bald (at age 40). Separate analyses of the two studies are consistent and suggest an association between vertex baldness and prostate cancer [vertex bald early onset odds ratios, 2.44 [confidence interval (CI), 0.57-10.46)] and 2.11 (CI, 0.66-6.73), respectively; vertex bald later onset odds ratios, 2.10 (CI, 0.63-7.00) and 1.37 (CI, 0.47-4.06), respectively]. Although statistical significance was not achieved in either one of these studies, the concordance between the data suggests a need for future studies to determine whether early onset vertex baldness serves as a novel biomarker for prostate cancer and whether androgen production, metabolism, or receptor status differs among these men when compared to those who exhibit other types of hair patterning.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: K07-CA62215/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R03-CA59263/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R21-CA69773/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9200608; CIN: Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2001 Apr;10(4):415-6. PMID: 11319187; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1055-9965; 1055-9965</sn>
<ad>Division of Urology/Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina 27710, USA. demar001@mc.duke.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10750672</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10750672</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>65</id>
<a1>Engelkes,T.</a1>
<a1>Morriën,E.</a1>
<a1>Verhoeven,K. J. F.</a1>
<a1>Bezemer,T. M.</a1>
<a1>Biere,A.</a1>
<a1>Harvey,J. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Tamis,W. L. M.</a1>
<a1>Van der Putten,W. H.</a1>
<t1>Successful range-expanding plants experience less above-ground and below-ground enemy impact</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>456</vo>
<is>7224</is>
<sp>946</sp>
<op>948</op>
<pb>Nature Publishing Group</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>88</id>
<a1>Fowler Jr,V. G.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Yeaman,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Peterson,G. E.</a1>
<a1>Reller,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Corey,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Wray,D.</a1>
<a1>Bayer,A. S.</a1>
<t1>In vitro resistance to thrombin‐induced platelet microbicidal protein in isolates of Staphylococcus aureus from endocarditis patients correlates with an intravascular device source</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>182</vo>
<sp>1251</sp>
<op>1254</op>
<pb>UChicago Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>74</id>
<a1>Fowler Jr,V. G.</a1>
<a1>Sakoulas,G.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Meka,V. G.</a1>
<a1>Arbeit,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Cabell,C. H.</a1>
<a1>Stryjewski,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Eliopoulos,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Reller,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Corey,G. R.</a1>
<t1>Persistent bacteremia due to methicillin‐resistant Staphylococcus aureus infection is associated with agr dysfunction and low‐level in vitro resistance to thrombin‐induced platelet microbicidal protein</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>190</vo>
<sp>1140</sp>
<op>1149</op>
<pb>UChicago Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>67</id>
<a1>Fowler,V. G.</a1>
<a1>Nelson,C. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Kreiswirth,B. N.</a1>
<a1>Monk,A.</a1>
<a1>Archer,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Federspiel,J.</a1>
<a1>Naidich,S.</a1>
<a1>Remortel,B.</a1>
<a1>Rude,T.</a1>
<t1>Potential associations between hematogenous complications and bacterial genotype in Staphylococcus aureus infection</t1>
<jf>The Journal of infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>J.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>196</vo>
<sp>738</sp>
<op>747</op>
<pb>UChicago Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>101</id>
<a1>Fung,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Gonzalo,M.</a1>
<a1>Fekete,C.</a1>
<a1>Kovacs,L. G.</a1>
<a1>He,Y.</a1>
<a1>Marsh,E.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Schachtman,D. P.</a1>
<a1>Qiu,W.</a1>
<t1>Powdery mildew induces defense-oriented reprogramming of the transcriptome in a susceptible but not in a resistant grapevine</t1>
<jf>Plant Physiology</jf>
<jo>Plant Physiol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>146</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>236</sp>
<op>249</op>
<k1>Ascomycota/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Plant</k1>
<k1>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Host-Pathogen Interactions</k1>
<k1>Plant Diseases/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Vitis/genetics/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Grapevines exhibit a wide spectrum of resistance to the powdery mildew fungus (PM), Erysiphe necator (Schw.) Burr., but little is known about the transcriptional basis of the defense to PM. Our microscopic observations showed that PM produced less hyphal growth and induced more brown-colored epidermal cells on leaves of PM-resistant Vitis aestivalis &amp;#39;Norton&amp;#39; than on leaves of PM-susceptible Vitis vinifera &amp;#39;Cabernet sauvignon&amp;#39;. We found that endogenous salicylic acid levels were higher in V. aestivalis than in V. vinifera in the absence of the fungus and that salicylic acid levels increased in V. vinifera at 120 h postinoculation with PM. To test the hypothesis that gene expression differences would be apparent when V. aestivalis and V. vinifera were mounting a response to PM, we conducted a comprehensive Vitis GeneChip analysis. We examined the transcriptome at 0, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 h postinoculation with PM. We found only three PM-responsive transcripts in V. aestivalis and 625 in V. vinifera. There was a significant increase in the abundance of transcripts encoding ENHANCED DISEASE SUSCEPTIBILITY1, mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase, WRKY, PATHOGENESIS-RELATED1, PATHOGENESIS-RELATED10, and stilbene synthase in PM-infected V. vinifera, suggesting an induction of the basal defense response. The overall changes in the PM-responsive V. vinifera transcriptome also indicated a possible reprogramming of metabolism toward the increased synthesis of the secondary metabolites. These results suggested that resistance to PM in V. aestivalis was not associated with overall reprogramming of the transcriptome. However, PM induced defense-oriented transcriptional changes in V. vinifera.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GEO/GSE6404; JID: 0401224; OID: NLM: PMC2230561; 2007/11/09 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0032-0889; 0032-0889</sn>
<ad>Department of Agriculture, Missouri State University, Mountain Grove, MO 65711, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17993546; pp.107.108712 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1104/pp.107.108712</do>
<wp>20071109</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17993546</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2230561</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1105</id>
<a1>Genissel,A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<t1>Cis and trans regulatory effects contribute to natural variation in transcriptome of Drosophila melanogaster</t1>
<jf>Molecular biology and evolution</jf>
<jo>Mol.Biol.Evol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>101</sp>
<pb>SMBE</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>99</id>
<a1>Gonzalo,M.</a1>
<a1>Holland,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Vyn,T. J.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Direct mapping of density response in a population of B73 x Mo17 recombinant inbred lines of maize (Zea Mays L.)</t1>
<jf>Heredity</jf>
<jo>Heredity</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov 4</fd>
<ab>Maize yield per unit area has dramatically increased over time as have plant population densities, but the genetic basis for plant response to density is unknown as is its stability over environments. To elucidate the genetic basis of plant response to density in maize, we mapped QTL for plant density-related traits in a population of 186 recombinant inbred lines (RILs) derived from the cross of inbred lines B73 and Mo17. All RILs were evaluated for growth, development, and yield traits at moderate (50 000 plants per hectare) and high (100 000 plants per hectare) plant densities. The results show that genetic control of the traits evaluated is multigenic in their response to density. Five of the seven loci significant for final height showed statistical evidence for epistatic interactions. Other traits such as days to anthesis, anthesis-to-silking interval, barrenness, ears per plant, and yield per plant all showed statistical evidence for an epistatic interaction. Locus by density interactions are of critical importance for anthesis-to-silking interval, barrenness, and ears per plant. A second independent experiment to examine the stability of QTL for barrenness in a new environment clearly showed that the multilocus QTL were stable across environments in their differential response to density. In this verification experiment, the four-locus QTL was used to choose lines with the four unfavorable alleles and compare them with the lines with four favorable alleles and the effect was confirmed.Heredity advance online publication, 4 November 2009; doi:10.1038/hdy.2009.140.</ab>
<no>JID: 0373007; 2009/11/04 [aheadofprint]; aheadofprint</no>
<sn>1365-2540; 0018-067X</sn>
<ad>[1] Nidera SA, Buenos Aires, Argentina [2] Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19888291; hdy2009140 [pii]</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1038/hdy.2009.140</do>
<wp>20091104</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19888291</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>102</id>
<a1>Gonzalo,M.</a1>
<a1>Vyn,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Holland,J. B.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Mapping reciprocal effects and interactions with plant density stress in Zea mays L</t1>
<jf>Heredity</jf>
<jo>Heredity</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>14</sp>
<op>30</op>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Inbreeding</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/genetics</k1>
<ab>Reciprocal effects are due to genetic effects of the parents (i.e. maternal and paternal effects), cytoplasmic effects and parent-of-origin effects. However, in Zea mays L. the extent to which reciprocal effects exist, or can be attributed to specific underlying components, remains an area of interest and study. Reciprocal effects have been reported by several investigators for various agronomic characters in different types of maize materials for grain and silage usage. Maize geneticists and breeders have recognized reciprocal effects as one source of genetic variability, but the lack of consistency in the observation of these effects, particularly due to stress conditions, has prevented a systematic exploitation of these effects in practical breeding programs. There is mounting molecular evidence for underlying mechanisms in maize, which could be responsible for both the existence, and the instability of reciprocal effects. In this study, we developed population of reciprocal backcrosses based on an initial set of recombinant inbred lines. This population was used for dissecting reciprocal effects into the underlying components (maternal, cytoplasmic and parent-of-origin) effects. We also developed statistical framework to identify and map contributions of specific nuclear chromosomal regions to reciprocal effects. We showed that differences in maternal parents, endosperm DNA and maternally transmitted factors collectively influence reciprocal effects early during the season, and that their influence diluted at later stages. We also found evidence that parent-of-origin effects in the sporophyte DNA existed at all stages and played an important role in establishing differences between reciprocal backcrosses at later developmental stages.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: 1R24GM65513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0373007; 2007/05/02 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0018-067X; 0018-067X</sn>
<ad>Nidera SA, Buenos Aires, Argentina.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17473872; 6800955 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/sj.hdy.6800955</do>
<wp>20070502</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17473872</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>104</id>
<a1>Gonzalo,M.</a1>
<a1>Vyn,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Holland,J. B.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Mapping density response in maize: a direct approach for testing genotype and treatment interactions</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>173</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>331</sp>
<op>348</op>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping/methods</k1>
<k1>Genetics, Population</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Hybridization, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Likelihood Functions</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/genetics</k1>
<ab>Maize yield improvement has been strongly linked to improvements in stress tolerance, particularly to increased interplant competition. As a result, modern hybrids are able to produce kernels at high plant population densities. Identification of the genetic factors responsible for density response in maize requires direct testing of interactions between genetic effects and density and evaluation of that response in multiple traits. In this article we take a broad view of the problem and use a general approach based upon mixed models to analyze data from eight segmental inbred lines in a B73 background and their crosses to the unrelated parent Mo17 (hybrids). We directly test for the interaction between treatment effects and genetic effects instead of the commonly used overlaying of results on a common map. Additionally, we demonstrate one way to handle heteroscedasticity of variances common in stress responses. We find that some SILs are consistently different from the recurrent parent regardless of the density, while others differ from the recurrent parent in one density level but not in the other. Thus, we find positive evidence for both main effects and interaction between genetic loci and density in cases where the approach of overlapping results fails to find significant results. Furthermore, our study clearly identifies segments that respond differently to density depending upon the inbreeding level (inbred/hybrid).</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AG16996/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0374636; OID: NLM: PMC1461438; 2006/02/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0016-6731; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana 47907, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16489238; genetics.105.045757 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1534/genetics.105.045757</do>
<wp>20060219</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16489238</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1461438</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>100</id>
<a1>Graze,R. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Main,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<t1>Regulatory divergence in Drosophila melanogaster and D. simulans, a genomewide analysis of allele-specific expression</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>183</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>547</sp>
<op>61, 1SI-21SI</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Brain/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Crosses, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Drosophila melanogaster/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genes, Insect/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Genome, Insect/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genome-Wide Association Study/methods</k1>
<k1>Hybridization, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Species-specific regulation of gene expression contributes to the development and maintenance of reproductive isolation and to species differences in ecologically important traits. A better understanding of the evolutionary forces that shape regulatory variation and divergence can be developed by comparing expression differences among species and interspecific hybrids. Once expression differences are identified, the underlying genetics of regulatory variation or divergence can be explored. With the goal of associating cis and/or trans components of regulatory divergence with differences in gene expression, overall and allele-specific expression levels were assayed genomewide in female adult heads of Drosophila melanogaster, D. simulans, and their F1 hybrids. A greater proportion of cis differences than trans differences were identified for genes expressed in heads and, in accordance with previous studies, cis differences also explained a larger number of species differences in overall expression level. Regulatory divergence was found to be prevalent among genes associated with defense, olfaction, and among genes downstream of the Drosophila sex determination hierarchy. In addition, two genes, with critical roles in sex determination and micro RNA processing, Sxl and loqs, were identified as misexpressed in hybrid female heads, potentially contributing to hybrid incompatibility.</ab>
<no>GEO/GSE17453; GR: 1R01GM077618/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0374636; OID: NLM: PMC2766316; 2009/08/10 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1943-2631; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Genetics Institute, Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 3261--3610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19667135; genetics.109.105957 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1534/genetics.109.105957</do>
<wp>20090810</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19667135</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2766316</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>108</id>
<a1>Hammes,U. Z.</a1>
<a1>Schachtman,D. P.</a1>
<a1>Berg,R. H.</a1>
<a1>Nielsen,E.</a1>
<a1>Koch,W.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Taylor,C. G.</a1>
<t1>Nematode-induced changes of transporter gene expression in Arabidopsis roots</t1>
<jf>Molecular plant-microbe interactions : MPMI</jf>
<jo>Mol.Plant Microbe Interact.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1247</sp>
<op>1257</op>
<k1>Amino Acids/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Arabidopsis/cytology/genetics/parasitology</k1>
<k1>Biological Transport, Active</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Plant</k1>
<k1>Membrane Transport Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Organ Specificity</k1>
<k1>Plant Diseases/genetics/parasitology</k1>
<k1>Plant Roots/cytology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Tylenchoidea/physiology</k1>
<ab>Root-knot plant-parasitic nematodes (Meloidogyne spp.) account for much of the damage inflicted to plants by nematodes. The feeding sites of these nematodes consist of &amp;quot;giant&amp;quot; cells, which have characteristics of transfer cells found in other parts of plants. Increased transport activity across the plasma membrane is a hallmark of transfer cells, and giant cells provide nutrition for nematodes; therefore, we initiated a study to identify the transport processes that contribute to the development and function of nematode-induced feeding sites. The study was conducted over a 4-week period, during which time the large changes in the development of giant cells were documented. The Arabidopsis ATH1 GeneChip was used to identify the many transporter genes that were regulated by nematode infestation. Expression of 50 transporter genes from 18 different gene families was significantly changed upon nematode infestation. Sixteen transporter genes were studied in more detail using real-time reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction to determine transcript abundance in nematode-induced galls that contain giant cells and uninfested regions of the root. Certain genes were expressed primarily in galls whereas others were expressed primarily in the uninfested regions of the root, and a third group was expressed evenly throughout the root. Multiple transport processes are regulated and these may play important roles in nematode feeding-site establishment and maintenance.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9107902; 0 (Amino Acids); 0 (Membrane Transport Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0894-0282; 0894-0282</sn>
<ad>Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, 975 N. Warson Rd., St. Louis, MO 63132, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16478044</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1094/MPMI-18-1247</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16478044</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1347</id>
<a1>Handa,A. K.</a1>
<a1>Srivastava,A.</a1>
<a1>Datsenka,T.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Transcriptional Regulation during Tomato Fruit Development: Identification of Novel Genes Involved in Fruit Ripening</t1>
<yr>2006</yr>
<sp>437</sp>
<op>448</op>
<t2>VI International Solanaceae Conference: Genomics Meets Biodiversity 745</t2>
<pb>ISHS</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>84</id>
<a1>Hoenig,H.</a1>
<a1>Hoff,J.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Branch,L. G.</a1>
<t1>The self-reported functional measure: Predictive validity for health care utilization in multiple sclerosis and spinal cord injury* 1</t1>
<jf>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</jf>
<jo>Arch.Phys.Med.Rehabil.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>613</sp>
<op>618</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>92</id>
<a1>Hoenig,H.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Hoff,J.</a1>
<a1>Samsa,G.</a1>
<a1>Branch,L. G.</a1>
<t1>Disability fingerprints: patterns of disability in spinal cord injury and multiple sclerosis differ</t1>
<jf>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</jf>
<jo>J.Gerontol.A Biol.Sci.Med.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<vo>54</vo>
<sp>M613</sp>
<op>20</op>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>124</id>
<a1>Hoenig,H.</a1>
<a1>Branch,L. G.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Hoff,J.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<t1>The validity in persons with spinal cord injury of a self-reported functional measure derived from the functional independence measure</t1>
<jf>Spine</jf>
<jo>Spine (Phila Pa.1976)</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar 15</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>539</sp>
<op>43; discussion 543-4</op>
<k1>Activities of Daily Living</k1>
<k1>Chi-Square Distribution</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Cross-Sectional Studies</k1>
<k1>Disability Evaluation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Questionnaires</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord Injuries/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Veterans</k1>
<ab>STUDY DESIGN: A cross-sectional, mailed survey on impairment and function using 6361 respondents to the Spinal Cord Dysfunction National Veterans Survey who reported spinal cord injury as the sole cause of their spinal cord dysfunction. OBJECTIVES: To establish the concurrent and construct validities of a Self-Reported Functional Measure appropriate for use in patients with spinal cord injuries. SUMMARY OF BACKGROUND DATA: Functional assessment is of increasing importance in clinical care, quality assurance, and national health-care planning. There is a conspicuous need for validated functional assessment measures that are rapid, reliable, and appropriate for use in the disabled population. METHODS: The correlation was examined of hours of personal assistance, number of affected limbs, amount of motor impairment, and amount of combined limb-motor impairment to Self-Reported Functional Measure response tertile (scores, 13-32, 33-45, 46-52; lower scores indicated worse function). RESULTS: There were statistically significant correlations between Self-Reported Functional Measure score and hours of personal assistance (P &amp;lt; 0.001), the number of affected limbs (P &amp;lt; 0.001), the amount of motor impairment (P &amp;lt; 0.001), and the amount of combined limbmotor impairment (P &amp;lt; 0.001). For example, 87% of people with the most limb-motor impairment (four affected limbs and no useful movement) were in the lowest Self-Reported Functional Measure tertile, compared with 3% of people in the least-affected category of limb-motor impairment. Furthermore, visual, sensory, or memory impairment did not influence the correlation between limbmotor impairment and Self-Reported Functional Measure score. CONCLUSION: The Self-Reported Functional Measure shows good concurrent and construct validities.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090709; JID: 7610646; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0362-2436; 0362-2436</sn>
<ad>Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Service, Durham Veterans Administration Medical Center, North Carolina, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10101817</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10101817</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>97</id>
<a1>Hoenig,H.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Sloane,R.</a1>
<a1>Branch,L. G.</a1>
<a1>Truncali,A.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<t1>The reliability of a self-reported measure of disease, impairment, and function in persons with spinal cord dysfunction</t1>
<jf>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</jf>
<jo>Arch.Phys.Med.Rehabil.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>378</sp>
<op>387</op>
<k1>Activities of Daily Living</k1>
<k1>Health Status Indicators</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Questionnaires</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord Diseases/rehabilitation</k1>
<k1>Spinal Cord Injuries/rehabilitation</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To develop a self-report instrument that would provide information about the different levels of the disablement process, and that (1) was suitable for persons with spinal cord disease (SCD), (2) could be completed quickly, (3) could be mailed, (4) had acceptable reliability, and (5) would be clinically useful. STUDY DESIGN: Test-retest using a convenience sample. METHODS: Review of the literature and an expert panel were used to develop the instrument. It was mailed to 49,458 individuals in June 1995 and a second mailing was done in August 1995. A subset of 725 individuals who responded to both mailings was used to examine the instrument&amp;#39;s test-retest reliability. RESULTS: The instrument has a 4th grade reading level and has questions on causal disease, disease severity, impairment, activities of daily living (including a self-reported version of the Functional Independence Measure, the SRFM), and resource utilization. Individual item test-retest reliability was high for a mailed questionnaire; all kappa coefficients were near or above .60 and most were over .70. Intraclass correlation coefficient for the SRFM was .90 and internal consistency (Chronbach&amp;#39;s alpha) was .96. CONCLUSION: This instrument provides a new, rapid way to obtain information relative to the differing levels of the disablement process.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5 P60 AG 11268/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985158R; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-9993; 0003-9993</sn>
<ad>Durham Veterans Administration Medical Center and Duke University Medical Center, NC 27705, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9552102; S0003-9993(98)90137-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9552102</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>96</id>
<a1>Hulette,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Welsh-Bohmer,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Murray,M. G.</a1>
<a1>Saunders,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Mash,D. C.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Neuropathological and neuropsychological changes in &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; aging: evidence for preclinical Alzheimer disease in cognitively normal individuals</t1>
<jf>Journal of neuropathology and experimental neurology</jf>
<jo>J.Neuropathol.Exp.Neurol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1168</sp>
<op>1174</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Aging/pathology/psychology</k1>
<k1>Alzheimer Disease/pathology/psychology</k1>
<k1>Case-Control Studies</k1>
<k1>Cognition/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neuropsychological Tests</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Registries</k1>
<ab>The presence of diffuse or primitive senile plaques in the neocortex of cognitively normal elderly at autopsy has been presumed to represent normal aging. Alternatively, these patients may have developed dementia and clinical Alzheimer disease (AD) if they had survived. In this setting, these patients could be subjects for cognitive or pharmacologic intervention to delay disease onset. We have thus followed a cohort of cognitively normal elderly subjects with a Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) of 0 at autopsy. Thirty-one brains were examined at postmortem according to Consortium to Establish a Registry for Alzheimer Disease (CERAD) criteria and staged according to Braak. Ten patients were pathologically normal according to CERAD criteria (1a). Two of these patients were Braak Stage II. Seven very elderly subjects exhibited a few primitive neuritic plaques in the cortex and thus represented CERAD 1b. These individuals ranged in age from 85 to 105 years and were thus older than the CERAD la group that ranged in age from 72 to 93. Fourteen patients displayed Possible AD according to CERAD with ages ranging from 66 to 95. Three of these were Braak Stage I, 4 were Braak Stage II, and 7 were Braak Stage III. The Apolipoprotein E4 allele was over-represented in this possible AD group. Neuropsychological data were available on 12 individuals. In these 12 individuals, Possible AD at autopsy could be predicted by cognitive deficits in 1 or more areas including savings scores on memory testing and overall performance on some measures of frontal executive function.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AG05128/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; GR: AG09997/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985192R; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-3069; 0022-3069</sn>
<ad>Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC 27710, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9862640</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9862640</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1343</id>
<a1>Jansen,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Tesson,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Fu,J.</a1>
<a1>Yang,Y.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Defining Gene and QTL networks</t1>
<jo>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>12</vo>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>6</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>76</id>
<a1>Jin,T.</a1>
<a1>Bokarewa,M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Tarkowski,A.</a1>
<a1>Corey,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Reller,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Fowler Jr,V. G.</a1>
<t1>Fatal outcome of bacteraemic patients caused by infection with staphylokinase-deficient Staphylococcus aureus strains</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>919</sp>
<pb>Soc General Microbiol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>93</id>
<a1>Johnston,E. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Hoff,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Bepler,G.</a1>
<t1>The effect of orchiectomy on lung cancer survival</t1>
<jf>Anticancer Research</jf>
<jo>Anticancer Res.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Nov-Dec</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>6C</is>
<sp>5567</sp>
<op>5570</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Androgens/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Orchiectomy</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<ab>Gender is an independent prognostic factor for survival from lung cancer with the relative risk of lung cancer death for men compared to women being 1.3. This observation remains unexplained but in vitro data suggests a stimulatory effect of androgens on lung cancer growth. We hypothesized that androgen deprivation improves survival in men with lung cancer compared to hormonally intact men with lung cancer. On the basis of age, race and region, we matched 44 men with lung cancer and bilateral orchiectomy with 88 men who had lung cancer and no history of orchiectomy and compared their survival. Since hazards were non-proportional we chose the generalized gamma model to describe the survival function. The survival was significantly different between the two groups (p = 0.0048) with the orchiectomy group having a better two year overall survival. This retrospective study suggests that androgen depletion may significantly improve the short term survival of men with lung cancer but further, prospective investigation is required for confirmation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5P01 CA 72099-02/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: 5RO1 CA 70317-02/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8102988; 0 (Androgens); ppublish</no>
<pp>GREECE</pp>
<sn>0250-7005; 0250-7005</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina, USA. gerold.bepler@roswellpark.org</ad>
<an>PMID: 10697618</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10697618</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>103</id>
<a1>Kopp,A.</a1>
<a1>Barmina,O.</a1>
<a1>Hamilton,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Higgins,L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Jones,C. D.</a1>
<t1>Evolution of gene expression in the Drosophila olfactory system</t1>
<jf>Molecular biology and evolution</jf>
<jo>Mol.Biol.Evol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1081</sp>
<op>1092</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Insect</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Multigene Family</k1>
<k1>Olfactory Pathways/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Smell/genetics</k1>
<ab>Host plant shifts by phytophagous insects play a key role in insect evolution and plant ecology. Such shifts often involve major behavioral changes as the insects must acquire an attraction and/or lose the repulsion to the new host plant&amp;#39;s odor and taste. The evolution of chemotactic behavior may be due, in part, to gene expression changes in the peripheral sensory system. To test this hypothesis, we compared gene expression in the olfactory organs of Drosophila sechellia, a narrow ecological specialist that feeds on the fruit of Morinda citrifolia, with its close relatives Drosophila simulans and Drosophila melanogaster, which feed on a wide variety of decaying plant matter. Using whole-genome microarrays and quantitative polymerase chain reaction, we surveyed the entire repertoire of Drosophila odorant receptors (ORs) and odorant-binding proteins (OBPs) expressed in the antennae. We found that the evolution of OR and OBP expression was accelerated in D. sechellia compared both with the genome average in that species and with the rate of OR and OBP evolution in the other species. However, some of the gene expression changes that correlate with D. sechellia&amp;#39;s increased sensitivity to Morinda odorants may predate its divergence from D. simulans. Interspecific divergence of olfactory gene expression cannot be fully explained by changes in the relative abundance of different sensilla as some ORs and OBPs have evolved independently of other genes expressed in the same sensilla. A number of OR and OBP genes are upregulated in D. sechellia compared with its generalist relatives. These genes include Or22a, which likely responds to a key odorant of M. citrifolia, and several genes that are yet to be characterized in detail. Increased expression of these genes in D. sechellia may have contributed to the evolution of its unique chemotactic behavior.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: 1R01GM077618-01A1/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: 1R24GM065513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK35747/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8501455; 0 (Drosophila Proteins); 2008/02/23 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-1719; 0737-4038</sn>
<ad>Section of Evolution and Ecology, University of California, Davis, USA. akopp@ucdavis.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18296696; msn055 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/molbev/msn055</do>
<wp>20080223</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18296696</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>77</id>
<a1>Lahner,B.</a1>
<a1>Gong,J.</a1>
<a1>Mahmoudian,M.</a1>
<a1>Smith,E. L.</a1>
<a1>Abid,K. B.</a1>
<a1>Rogers,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Guerinot,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Harper,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Ward,J. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<t1>Genomic scale profiling of nutrient and trace elements in Arabidopsis thaliana</t1>
<jf>Nature biotechnology</jf>
<jo>Nat.Biotechnol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1215</sp>
<op>1221</op>
<pb>Nature Publishing Group</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>113</id>
<a1>Li,H.</a1>
<a1>Singh,A. K.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Sherman,L. A.</a1>
<t1>Differential gene expression in response to hydrogen peroxide and the putative PerR regulon of Synechocystis sp. strain PCC 6803</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>186</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3331</sp>
<op>3345</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cyanobacteria/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen Peroxide/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Chaperones/genetics</k1>
<k1>Photosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Regulon/physiology</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Thioredoxins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics</k1>
<ab>We utilized a full genome cDNA microarray to identify the genes that comprise the peroxide stimulon in the cyanobacterium Synechocystis sp. strain PCC 6803. We determined that a gene (slr1738) encoding a protein similar to PerR in Bacillus subtilis was induced by peroxide. We constructed a PerR knockout strain and used it to help identify components of the PerR regulon, and we found that the regulatory properties were consistent with the hypothesis that PerR functions as a repressor. This effort was guided by finding putative PerR boxes in positions upstream of specific genes and by careful statistical analysis. PerR and sll1621 (ahpC), which codes for a peroxiredoxin, share a divergent promoter that is regulated by PerR. We found that isiA, encoding a Chl protein that is induced under low-iron conditions, was strongly induced by a short-term peroxide stress. Other genes that were strongly induced by peroxide included sigD, sigB, and genes encoding peroxiredoxins and Dsb-like proteins that have not been studied yet in this strain. A gene (slr1894) that encoded a protein similar to MrgA in B. subtilis was upregulated by peroxide, and a strain containing an mrgA knockout mutation was highly sensitive to peroxide. A number of genes were downregulated, including key genes in the chlorophyll biosynthesis pathway and numerous regulatory genes, including those encoding histidine kinases. We used PerR mutants and a thioredoxin mutant (TrxA1) to study differential expression in response to peroxide and determined that neither PerR nor TrxA1 is essential for the peroxide protective response.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Molecular Chaperones); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Transcription Factors); 0 (peroxide repressor proteins); 52500-60-4 (Thioredoxins); 7722-84-1 (Hydrogen Peroxide); OID: NLM: PMC415769; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Biological Sciences, Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana 47907, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15150218; 186/11/3331 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.186.11.3331-3345.2004</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15150218</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC415769</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>62</id>
<a1>Main,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Bickel,R. D.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Graze,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Calabrese,P. P.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<t1>Allele-specific expression assays using Solexa</t1>
<jf>BMC genomics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genomics</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep 9</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<sp>422</sp>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling/methods</k1>
<k1>Genes, Insect</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis/methods</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Allele-specific expression (ASE) assays can be used to identify cis, trans, and cis-by-trans regulatory variation. Understanding the source of expression variation has important implications for disease susceptibility, phenotypic diversity, and adaptation. While ASE is commonly measured via relative fluorescence at a SNP, next generation sequencing provides an opportunity to measure ASE in an accurate and high-throughput manner using read counts. RESULTS: We introduce a Solexa-based method to perform large numbers of ASE assays using only a single lane of a Solexa flowcell. In brief, transcripts of interest, which contain a known SNP, are PCR enriched and barcoded to enable multiplexing. Then high-throughput sequencing is used to estimate allele-specific expression using sequencing counts. To validate this method, we measured the allelic bias in a dilution series and found high correlations between measured and expected values (r&amp;gt;0.9, p &amp;lt; 0.001). We applied this method to a set of 5 genes in a Drosophila simulans parental mix, F1 and introgression and found that for these genes the majority of expression divergence can be explained by cis-regulatory variation. CONCLUSION: We present a new method with the capacity to measure ASE for large numbers of assays using as little as one lane of a Solexa flowcell. This will be a valuable technique for molecular and population genetic studies, as well as for verification of genome-wide data sets.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 1R01GM077618/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: RGM076643/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 100965258; OID: NLM: PMC2749874; 2009/04/21 [received]; 2009/09/09 [accepted]; 2009/09/09 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2164; 1471-2164</sn>
<ad>Section of Molecular and Computational Biology, Department of Biological Sciences, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California 90089, USA. bmain@usc.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19740431; 1471-2164-10-422 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1471-2164-10-422</do>
<wp>20090909</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19740431</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2749874</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>120</id>
<a1>McBride,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Halabi,S.</a1>
<a1>Bepler,G.</a1>
<a1>Lyna,P.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Lipkus,I.</a1>
<a1>Albright,J.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Briant,K.</a1>
<t1>Maximizing the motivational impact of feedback of lung cancer susceptibility on smokers&amp;#39; desire to quit</t1>
<jf>Journal of health communication</jf>
<jo>J.Health Commun.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jul-Sep</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>229</sp>
<op>241</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Biological Markers</k1>
<k1>Communication</k1>
<k1>Disease Susceptibility</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Logistic Models</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Motivation</k1>
<k1>Odds Ratio</k1>
<k1>Smoking Cessation/methods/psychology</k1>
<ab>This two-by-two factorially designed study evaluate approaches for communicating feedback of lung cancer susceptibility to smokers as a method for motivating smoking cessation. The study factors were: method of communicating feedback (by mail with telephone follow-up or in-person) and carbon monoxide feedback (yes or no). One-hundred-forty-four smokers were stratified on race and randomized to one of four conditions. Participants were surveyed at baseline and 2-month follow-up. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) testing for the absence of the glutathione S transferase mu (GSTM1) gene was the susceptibility marker. Regardless of counseling method or carbon monoxide (CO) feedback, the majority (90%) of smokers accurately recalled the test result and 66% accurately interpreted the meaning of the test result. Smokers who received their result in person were significantly less likely to have read the result booklet than those in the telephone counseling group (OR = .28, 95%; CI .12-.62; p &amp;lt; .05). Neither counseling method nor CO feedback increased smokers&amp;#39; perceived risks for lung cancer. However, at the counseling session those who received in-person counseling were significantly less frightened by the test result than those who received telephone counseling (OR = .42, 95%; CI .20-86; p &amp;lt; .05) and at the 2-month follow-up those who received a CO test were significantly less frightened by their susceptibility result (OR = .40, 95%; CI .17-.92; p &amp;lt; .05) than those who did not have a CO test. Evaluation of further refinements in communicating the meaning of susceptibility results to motivate smoking cessation is warranted.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01-CA-70317/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9604100; 0 (Biological Markers); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1081-0730; 1081-0730</sn>
<ad>Duke Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11185023</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Randomized Controlled Trial; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; T</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11185023</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>70</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Bono,L.</a1>
<a1>Genissel,A.</a1>
<a1>Westerman,R.</a1>
<a1>Junk,D.</a1>
<a1>Telonis-Scott,M.</a1>
<a1>Harshman,L.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M.</a1>
<a1>Kopp,A.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S.</a1>
<t1>Sex-specific expression of alternative transcripts in Drosophila</t1>
<jf>Genome biology</jf>
<jo>Genome Biol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>R79</sp>
<pb>BioMed Central Ltd</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>129</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Using cigarette data for an introduction to multiple regression</t1>
<jf>Journal of Statistics Education</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>83</id>
<a1>McINTYRE,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Coffman,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Doerge,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Detection and localization of a single binary trait locus in experimental populations</t1>
<jf>Genetics Research</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>01</is>
<sp>79</sp>
<op>92</op>
<pb>Cambridge Univ Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>90</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Martin,E. R.</a1>
<a1>Simonsen,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,N. L.</a1>
<t1>Circumventing multiple testing: a multilocus Monte Carlo approach to testing for association</t1>
<jf>Genetic epidemiology</jf>
<jo>Genet.Epidemiol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>18</sp>
<op>29</op>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>59</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Data: the foundation of science</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>184</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biological Specimen Banks</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Internet</k1>
<k1>Periodicals as Topic</k1>
<k1>Publishing</k1>
<no>LR: 20100402; JID: 0374636; OID: NLM: PMC2815909; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1943-2631; 0016-6731</sn>
<an>PMID: 20061563; 184/1/1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Editorial; IM</sf>
<do>10.1534/genetics.109.108498</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20061563</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2815909</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>125</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Butterfield,M. I.</a1>
<a1>Nanda,K.</a1>
<a1>Parsey,K.</a1>
<a1>Stechuchak,K. M.</a1>
<a1>McChesney,A. W.</a1>
<a1>Koons,C.</a1>
<a1>Bastian,L. A.</a1>
<t1>Validation of a Trauma Questionnaire in veteran women</t1>
<jf>Journal of general internal medicine</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Intern.Med.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>186</sp>
<op>189</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Domestic Violence</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Questionnaires</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Sexual Harassment</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Veterans</k1>
<ab>The Trauma Questionnaire (TQ) assesses a woman&amp;#39;s history of childhood and adult sexual trauma, sexual harassment, and domestic violence. The TQ is used widely at Veterans Affairs Medical Centers, but its validity has not been thoroughly examined. In a prospective study of 127 women, we found the TQ to have good to excellent agreement with a semistructured clinician interview and good sensitivity and specificity. The TQ can be used as a valid alternative to the clinician interview in the initial elicitation of trauma history among women veterans in the primary care setting. KEY WORDS: trauma; questionnaire; women; veterans.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090224; JID: 8605834; OID: NLM: PMC1496546; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0884-8734; 0884-8734</sn>
<ad>Center for Health Services Research in Primary Care, Durham VAMC, Durham, NC 27705, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10203625</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10203625</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1496546</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>85</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Briant,K. C.</a1>
<a1>McBride,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Bepler,G.</a1>
<t1>Rater agreement and utility of the mutagen-induced chromosome damage assay</t1>
<jf>Anticancer Research</jf>
<jo>Anticancer Res.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>1B</is>
<sp>605</sp>
<op>609</op>
<k1>Bleomycin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Chromatids/drug effects/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Breakage</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Human/drug effects/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance</k1>
<k1>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/drug effects/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mutagenicity Tests/economics/standards</k1>
<k1>Observer Variation</k1>
<k1>Odds Ratio</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Translocation, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Chromosomal damage in peripheral blood lymphocytes induced by short-term in vitro exposure to the cytotoxic antibiotic bleomycin was first described in 1983 and proposed as a phenotypic assay for chromosome instability. This assay was subsequently described as potentially useful in assessing an individual&amp;#39;s risk to environmental carcinogens in 1989. Since 1995 numerous published studies have used this assay to assess risk for cancer in the aerodigestive tract, particularly lung cancer, in various ethnic populations. Odds ratios up to 8.5 have been reported for individuals deemed &amp;quot;mutagen sensitive&amp;quot; (defined as &amp;gt; or = 1 chromatid break per metaphase averaged in 50 metaphases analyzed). While this phenotypic assay is appealing for lung cancer risk assessment it has not been reproduced by other investigators. Because of our interest in lung cancer biology, epidemiology, and genetics, we sought to independently assess the rater agreement of this assay. We found that 1) the assay is laborious to conduct (8 hours of labor) and relatively expensive (&amp;gt; $100), yet reducing the number of metaphases from 50 to 20 produced a reliable, less expensive, and less laborious test; and 2) the rater agreement of individual metaphase readings is poor, but agreement for a summary measure is high.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5P01-CA72099/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: 5RO1-CA70317/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8102988; 11056-06-7 (Bleomycin); ppublish</no>
<pp>Greece</pp>
<sn>0250-7005; 0250-7005</sn>
<ad>Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11299813</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11299813</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>126</id>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Weir,B. S.</a1>
<t1>Hardy-Weinberg testing for continuous data</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>147</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1965</sp>
<op>1975</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Databases as Topic</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Minisatellite Repeats</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>Numerical Analysis, Computer-Assisted</k1>
<ab>Estimation of allelic and genotypic distributions for continuous data using kernel density estimation is discussed and illustrated for some variable number of tandem repeat data. These kernel density estimates provide a useful representation of data when only some of the many variants at a locus are present in a sample. Two Hardy-Weinberg test procedures are introduced for continuous data: a continuous chi-square test with test statistic T(CCS) and a test based on Hellinger&amp;#39;s distance with test statistic T(HD). Simulations are used to compare the powers of these tests to each other and to the powers of a test of intraclass correlation T(IC), as well as to the power of Fisher&amp;#39;s exact test T(FET) applied to discretized data. Results indicate that the power of T(CCS) is better than that of T(HD), but neither is as powerful as T(FET). The intraclass correlation test does not perform as well as the other tests examined in this article.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM-45344/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0374636; OID: NLM: PMC1208361; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0016-6731; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Department of Statistics, North Carolina State University, Raleigh 27695-8203, USA. mcintyre@acpub.duke.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 9409851</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9409851</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1208361</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>81</id>
<a1>Moody,D.</a1>
<a1>Fadlia,B.</a1>
<a1>Singh,A.</a1>
<a1>Shah,S.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Quantitative comparison of image analysis software</t1>
<jf>DNA Array Image Analysis: Nuts &amp; Bolts</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<sp>155</sp>
<t2>DNA Array Image Analysis: Nuts &amp;amp; Bolts</t2>
<pb>DNA Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>80</id>
<a1>Moody,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Zou,Z.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<t1>Cross-species hybridisation of pig RNA to human nylon microarrays</t1>
<jf>BMC genomics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genomics</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Sep 27</fd>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>27</sp>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The objective of this research was to investigate the reproducibility of cross-species microarray hybridisation. Comparisons between same- and cross-species hybridisations were also made. Nine hybridisations between a single pig skeletal muscle RNA sample and three human cDNA nylon microarrays were completed. Three replicate hybridisations of two different amounts of pig RNA, and of human skeletal muscle RNA were completed on three additional microarrays. RESULTS: Reproducibility of microarray hybridisations of pig cDNA to human microarrays was high, as determined by Spearman and Pearson correlation coefficients and a Kappa statistic. Variability among replicate hybridisations was similar for human and pig data, indicating the reproducibility of results were not compromised in cross-species hybridisations. The concordance between data generated from hybridisations using pig and human skeletal muscle RNA was high, further supporting the use of human microarrays for the analysis of gene expression in the pig. No systematic effect of stripping and re-using nylon microarrays was found, and variability across microarrays was minimal. CONCLUSION: The majority of genes generated highly reproducible data in cross-species microarray hybridisations, although approximately 6% were identified as highly variable. Experimental designs that include at least three replicate hybridisations for each experimental treatment will enable the variability of individual genes to be considered appropriately. The use of cross-species microarray analysis looks promising. However, additional validation is needed to determine the specificity of cross-species hybridisations, and the validity of results.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 100965258; OID: NLM: PMC130049; 2002/06/02 [received]; 2002/09/27 [accepted]; 2002/09/27 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2164; 1471-2164</sn>
<ad>Department of Animal Science, 1151 Lilly Hall, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907, USA. moodyd@purdue.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12354330</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<wp>20020927</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12354330</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC130049</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>64</id>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Brisson,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Pickering,A.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Harshman,L. G.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Natural genetic variation in transcriptome reflects network structure inferred with major effect mutations: insulin/TOR and associated phenotypes in Drosophila melanogaster</t1>
<jf>BMC genomics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genomics</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar 24</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<sp>124</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Drosophila Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Drosophila melanogaster/genetics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Forkhead Transcription Factors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Gene Regulatory Networks</k1>
<k1>Genes, Insect</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Genome, Insect</k1>
<k1>Insulin/genetics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases/genetics</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: A molecular process based genotype-to-phenotype map will ultimately enable us to predict how genetic variation among individuals results in phenotypic alterations. Building such a map is, however, far from straightforward. It requires understanding how molecular variation re-shapes developmental and metabolic networks, and how the functional state of these networks modifies phenotypes in genotype specific way. We focus on the latter problem by describing genetic variation in transcript levels of genes in the InR/TOR pathway among 72 Drosophila melanogaster genotypes. RESULTS: We observe tight co-variance in transcript levels of genes not known to influence each other through direct transcriptional control. We summarize transcriptome variation with factor analyses, and observe strong co-variance of gene expression within the dFOXO-branch and within the TOR-branch of the pathway. Finally, we investigate whether major axes of transcriptome variation shape phenotypes expected to be influenced through the InR/TOR pathway. We find limited evidence that transcript levels of individual upstream genes in the InR/TOR pathway predict fly phenotypes in expected ways. However, there is no evidence that these effects are mediated through the major axes of downstream transcriptome variation. CONCLUSION: In summary, our results question the assertion of the &amp;#39;sparse&amp;#39; nature of genetic networks, while validating and extending candidate gene approaches in the analyses of complex traits.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: 1R24GM065513/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: 5R01GM077618/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: K99ES017367/ES/NIEHS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 GM076643-01A1/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: RGM076643/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 100965258; 0 (Drosophila Proteins); 0 (FOXO protein, Drosophila); 0 (Forkhead Transcription Factors); 11061-68-0 (Insulin); EC 2.7.1.- (torso protein, Drosophila); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases); OID: NLM: PMC2674066; 2008/12/19 [received]; 2009/03/24 [accepted]; 2009/03/24 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2164; 1471-2164</sn>
<ad>Molecular and Computational Biology, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA 90089, USA. snuzhdin@usc.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19317915; 1471-2164-10-124 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1471-2164-10-124</do>
<wp>20090324</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19317915</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2674066</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>111</id>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Harmon,K. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Common pattern of evolution of gene expression level and protein sequence in Drosophila</t1>
<jf>Molecular biology and evolution</jf>
<jo>Mol.Biol.Evol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1308</sp>
<op>1317</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Silencing</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, Protein</k1>
<ab>Sequence divergence scaled by variation within species has been used to infer the action of selection upon individual genes. Applying this approach to expression, we compared whole-genome whole-body RNA levels in 10 heterozygous Drosophila simulans genotypes and a pooled sample of 10 D. melanogaster lines using Affymetrix Genechip. For 972 genes expressed in D. melanogaster, the transcript level was below detection threshold in D. simulans, which may be explained either by sequence divergence between the primers on the chip and the mRNA transcripts or by down-regulation of these genes. Out of 6,707 genes that were expressed in both species, transcript level was significantly different between species for 534 genes (at P &amp;lt; 0.001). Genes whose expression is under stabilizing selection should exhibit reduced genetic variation within species and reduced divergence between species. Expression of genes under directional selection in D. simulans should be highly divergent from D. melanogaster, while showing low genetic variation in D. simulans. Finally, the genes with large variation within species but modest divergence between species are candidates for balancing selection. Rapidly diverging, low-polymorphism genes included those involved in reproduction (e.g., Mst 3Ba, 98Cb; Acps 26Aa, 63F; and sperm-specific dynein). Genes with high variation in transcript abundance within species included metallothionein and hairless, both hypothesized to be segregating in nature because of gene-by-environment interactions. Further, we compared expression divergence and DNA substitution rate in 195 genes. Synonymous substitution rate and expression divergences were uncorrelated, whereas there was a significant positive correlation between nonsynonymous substitution rate and expression divergence. We hypothesize that as a substantial fraction of nonsynonymous divergence has been shown to be adaptive, much of the observed expression divergence is likewise adaptive.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: 1R01GM61773-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: 1R24GM65513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 GM59884-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8501455; 0 (Drosophila Proteins); 2004/03/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0737-4038; 0737-4038</sn>
<ad>Evolution and Ecology, University of California at Davis, CA, USA. svnuzhdin@ucdavis.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15034135; msh128 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/molbev/msh128</do>
<wp>20040319</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15034135</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>89</id>
<a1>Oberg,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Ferguson,J. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<t1>Incidence of stroke and season of the year: evidence of an association</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Epidemiology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Epidemiol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>152</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>558</sp>
<pb>Oxford Univ Press</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>98</id>
<a1>Oddone,E. Z.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Diers,T.</a1>
<a1>Lipscomb,J.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Cauffman,C.</a1>
<a1>Whittle,J.</a1>
<a1>Passman,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Kroupa,L.</a1>
<a1>Heaney,R.</a1>
<t1>Understanding racial variation in the use of carotid endarterectomy: the role of aversion to surgery.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the National Medical Association</jf>
<jo>J.Natl.Med.Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>25</sp>
<pb>National Medical Association</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>79</id>
<a1>Oddone,E. Z.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Johnston,D. C. C.</a1>
<a1>Stechuchak,K.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Ward,A.</a1>
<a1>Alley,L. G.</a1>
<a1>Whittle,J.</a1>
<a1>Kroupa,L.</a1>
<a1>Taylor,J.</a1>
<t1>Carotid endarterectomy and race: do clinical indications and patient preferences account for differences?</t1>
<jf>Stroke</jf>
<jo>Stroke</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2936</sp>
<pb>Am Heart Assoc</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>94</id>
<a1>Oddone,E. Z.</a1>
<a1>Horner,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Sloane,R.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L.</a1>
<a1>Ward,A.</a1>
<a1>Whittle,J.</a1>
<a1>Passman,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Kroupa,L.</a1>
<a1>Heaney,R.</a1>
<a1>Diem,S.</a1>
<t1>Race, presenting signs and symptoms, use of carotid artery imaging, and appropriateness of carotid endarterectomy</t1>
<jf>Stroke</jf>
<jo>Stroke</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1350</sp>
<pb>Am Heart Assoc</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>87</id>
<a1>Peck,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Asch,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Goold,S. D.</a1>
<a1>Roter,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Ubel,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Abbott,K. H.</a1>
<a1>Hoff,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Koropchak,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Tulsky,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Measuring patient expectations: does the instrument affect satisfaction or expectations?</t1>
<jf>Medical care</jf>
<jo>Med.Care</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>100</sp>
<op>108</op>
<k1>Ambulatory Care Facilities</k1>
<k1>Attitude to Health</k1>
<k1>Health Services Research/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interviews as Topic/methods</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Outcome Assessment (Health Care)/methods</k1>
<k1>Patient Satisfaction</k1>
<k1>Physician&#39;s Practice Patterns</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Statistics, Nonparametric</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Veterans</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Fulfillment of patients&amp;#39; expectations may influence health care utilization, affect patient satisfaction, and be used to indicate quality of care. Several different instruments have been used to measure expectations, yet little is known about how different assessment methods affect outcomes. OBJECTIVE: The object of the study was to determine whether different measurement instruments elicit different numbers and types of expectations and different levels of patient satisfaction. DESIGN: Patients waiting to see their physician were randomly assigned to receive 1 of 2 commonly used instruments assessing expectations or were assigned to a third (control) group that was not asked about expectations. After the visit, patients in all 3 groups were asked about their satisfaction and services they received. SUBJECTS: The study subjects were 290 male, primary care outpatients in a VA general medicine clinic. MEASURES: A &amp;quot;short&amp;quot; instrument asked about 3 general expectations for tests, referrals, and new medications, while a &amp;quot;long&amp;quot; instrument nested similar questions within a more detailed list. Wording also differed between the 2 instruments. The short instrument asked patients what they wanted; the long instrument asked patients what they thought was necessary for the physician to do. Satisfaction was measured with a visit-specific questionnaire and a more general assessment of physician interpersonal skills. RESULTS: Patients receiving the long instrument were more likely to express expectations for tests (83% vs. 28%, P &amp;lt;0.001), referrals (40% vs. 18%, P &amp;lt;0.001), and new medications (45% vs. 28%, P &amp;lt;0.001). The groups differed in the number of unmet expectations: 40% of the long instrument group reported at least 1 unmet expectation compared with 19% of the short instrument group (P &amp;lt;0.001). Satisfaction was similar among the 3 groups. CONCLUSIONS: These different instruments elicit different numbers of expectations but do not affect patient satisfaction.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0230027; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0025-7079; 0025-7079</sn>
<ad>Center for Health Services Research in Primary Care, Durham VA Medical Center, North Carolina 27705, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11176547</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Comparative Study; Journal Article; Randomized Controlled Trial; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Validation Studies; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11176547</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>114</id>
<a1>Pedra,J. H.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Scharf,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Pittendrigh,B. R.</a1>
<t1>Genome-wide transcription profile of field- and laboratory-selected dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT)-resistant Drosophila</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>May 4</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<is>18</is>
<sp>7034</sp>
<op>7039</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DDT/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance/genetics</k1>
<k1>Enzymes/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Lipid Metabolism</k1>
<ab>Genome-wide microarray analysis (Affymetrix array) was used (i) to determine whether only one gene, the cytochrome P450 enzyme Cyp6g1, is differentially transcribed in dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT)-resistant vs. -susceptible Drosophila; and (ii) to profile common genes differentially transcribed across a DDT-resistant field isolate [Rst(2)DDT(Wisconsin)] and a laboratory DDT-selected population [Rst(2)DDT(91-R)]. Statistical analysis (ANOVA model) identified 158 probe sets that were differentially transcribed among Rst(2)DDT(91-R), Rst(2)DDT(Wisconsin), and the DDT-susceptible genotype Canton-S (P &amp;lt; 0.01). The cytochrome P450 Cyp6a2 and the diazepam-binding inhibitor gene (Dbi) were over transcribed in the two DDT-resistant genotypes when compared to the wild-type Drosophila, and this difference was significant at the most stringent statistical level, a Bonferroni correction. The list of potential candidates differentially transcribed also includes 63 probe sets for which molecular function ontology annotation of the probe sets did not exist. A total of four genes (Cyp6a2, Dbi, Uhg1, and CG11176) were significantly different (P &amp;lt; 5.6 e(-06)) between Rst(2)DDT(91-R) and Canton-S. Additionally, two probe sets encoding Cyp12d1 and Dbi were significantly different between Rst(2)DDT(Wisconsin) and Canton-S after a Bonferroni correction. Fifty-two probe sets, including those associated with pesticide detoxification, ion transport, signal transduction, RNA transcription, and lipid metabolism, were commonly expressed in both resistant lines but were differentially transcribed in Canton-S. Our results suggest that more than Cyp6g1 is overtranscribed in field and laboratory DDT-resistant genotypes, and the number of commonalities suggests that similar resistance mechanisms may exist between laboratory- and field-selected DDT-resistant fly lines.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 1R01 AI51513-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Enzymes); 50-29-3 (DDT); OID: NLM: PMC406461; 2004/04/26 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907-1158, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15118106; 0400580101 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0400580101</do>
<wp>20040426</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15118106</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC406461</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>112</id>
<a1>Pirttila,A. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Payne,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Woloshuk,C. P.</a1>
<t1>Expression profile analysis of wild-type and fcc1 mutant strains of Fusarium verticillioides during fumonisin biosynthesis</t1>
<jf>Fungal genetics and biology : FG &amp; B</jf>
<jo>Fungal Genet.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>41</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>647</sp>
<op>656</op>
<k1>Expressed Sequence Tags</k1>
<k1>Fumonisins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fungal Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Fusarium/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Fungal</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis/methods</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Fusarium verticillioides produces a group of mycotoxins known as fumonisins that are associated with a variety of mycotoxicoses in humans and animals. In this study, DNA microarrays were constructed with expressed sequence tags (ESTs) from F. verticillioides. To identify genes with patterns of expression similar to the fumonisin biosynthetic (FUM) genes, the microarray was probed with labeled cDNAs originating from a wild-type strain and a fcc1 mutant grown on maize and in a defined medium adjusted to either pH 3 or pH 8. The comparative analyses revealed differential expression of genes corresponding to 116 ESTs when the fungal strains were grown on maize. Under different pH conditions, 166 ESTs were differentially expressed, and 19 ESTs were identified that displayed expression patterns similar to the FUM ESTs. These results provide candidate genes with potential roles in fumonisin biosynthesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9607601; 0 (Fumonisins); 0 (Fungal Proteins); 2003/10/09 [received]; 2004/02/06 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1087-1845; 1087-1845</sn>
<ad>Department of Botany and Plant Pathology, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15121086; S1087184504000337 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.fgb.2004.02.001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15121086</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>119</id>
<a1>Rosenberg,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Cummings,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Saunders,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Widico,C.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Hulette,C. M.</a1>
<t1>Dementia with Lewy bodies and Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease</t1>
<jf>Acta Neuropathologica</jf>
<jo>Acta Neuropathol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>621</sp>
<op>626</op>
<k1>Age Factors</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Alzheimer Disease/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Apolipoproteins E/genetics</k1>
<k1>Brain/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Testing</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lewy Body Disease/genetics/pathology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neurons/pathology</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Sex Factors</k1>
<ab>To investigate similarities and differences between Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease (AD) and dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB), we undertook a demographic analysis of 277 patients from the Kathleen Price Bryan Brain Bank with an antemortem diagnosis of probable AD. Patients with additional, possibly confounding clinical and pathologic diagnoses such as infarcts, hematomas, neoplasms, and other neurodegenerative disorders, were excluded from the analysis. Neuropathologically, AD alone was present in 192 subjects (69%), and DLB was found in 85 subjects (31%). All of the DLB cases had neuropathologic evidence of AD sufficient to meet CERAD criteria for a diagnosis of definite AD plus nigral Lewy bodies. Gender, apolipoprotein E (APOE) genotype, brain weight, age at death, duration of disease and Braak stage were compared between the two groups. Statistical analyses were performed using Fisher&amp;#39;s exact test for comparisons of categorical data and Student&amp;#39;s t-test for comparison of means for continuous outcomes. The proportion of males and females was balanced in the combined AD and DLB populations. There was a highly statistically significant increased frequency of APOE 3/4 in males with DLB (P = 0.007). We found higher brain weights in males with DLB versus males with AD (P = 0.012). AD was more frequent in females and DLB was more frequent in males (P = 0.019). Our findings with respect to age at death, duration of disease and Braak stage within diagnostic groups confirm previously reported findings. These data suggest that Lewy bodies are more common in males affected with dementia, especially those with the APOE 3/4 genotype.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: P50 AG05128/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; GR: P50, NS 39764/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0412041; 0 (Apolipoproteins E); ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0001-6322; 0001-6322</sn>
<ad>Bryan Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Research Center, Department of Medicine, Division of Neurology, Box 2900, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC 27710, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11761723</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11761723</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>75</id>
<a1>Simonsen,K. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Using alpha wisely: Improving power to detect multiple QTL</t1>
<jf>Statistical applications in genetics and molecular biology</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1023</sp>
<pb>Berkeley Electronic Press, 805 Camelia St, Second Floor, Berkeley, CA, 94710, USA,</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>115</id>
<a1>Singh,A. K.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Sherman,L. A.</a1>
<t1>Microarray analysis of the genome-wide response to iron deficiency and iron reconstitution in the cyanobacterium Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803</t1>
<jf>Plant Physiology</jf>
<jo>Plant Physiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1825</sp>
<op>1839</op>
<k1>Cyanobacteria/cytology/drug effects/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Energy Metabolism/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genome, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Iron/deficiency/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Photosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Phycobilisomes</k1>
<k1>Pigments, Biological/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>A full-genome microarray of the (oxy)photosynthetic cyanobacterium Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803 was used to identify genes that were transcriptionally regulated by growth in iron (Fe)-deficient versus Fe-sufficient media. Transcript accumulation for 3,165 genes in the genome was analyzed using an analysis of variance model that accounted for slide and replicate (random) effects and dye (a fixed) effect in testing for differences in the four time periods. We determined that 85 genes showed statistically significant changes in the level of transcription (P 1.25 x). The genes identified included those known previously to be Fe regulated, such as isiA that encodes a novel chlorophyll-binding protein responsible for the pigment characteristics of low-Fe (LoFe) cells. ATP synthetase and phycobilisome genes were down-regulated in LoFe, and there were interesting changes in the transcription of genes involved in chlorophyll biosynthesis, in photosystem I and II assembly, and in energy metabolism. Hierarchical clustering demonstrated that photosynthesis genes, as a class, were repressed in LoFe and induced upon the re-addition of Fe. Specific regulatory genes were transcriptionally active in LoFe, including two genes that show homology to plant phytochromes (cph1 and cph2). These observations established the existence of a complex network of regulatory interactions and coordination in response to Fe availability.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0401224; 0 (Phycobilisomes); 0 (Pigments, Biological); 7439-89-6 (Iron); OID: NLM: PMC181269; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0032-0889; 0032-0889</sn>
<ad>Department of Biological Sciences, Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana 47907, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12913140</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12913140</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC181269</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>68</id>
<a1>Slotte,T.</a1>
<a1>Holm,K.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Lagercrantz,U.</a1>
<a1>Lascoux,M.</a1>
<t1>Differential expression of genes important for adaptation in Capsella bursa-pastoris (Brassicaceae)</t1>
<jf>Plant Physiology</jf>
<jo>Plant Physiol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>145</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>160</sp>
<pb>Am Soc Plant Biol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>71</id>
<a1>Spurlock,D. M.</a1>
<a1>McDaneld,T. G.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Changes in skeletal muscle gene expression following clenbuterol administration</t1>
<jf>BMC genomics</jf>
<jo>BMC Genomics</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Dec 20</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<sp>320</sp>
<k1>Adrenergic beta-Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blood Urea Nitrogen</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Clenbuterol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cyclin-Dependent Kinase Inhibitor p21/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Hypertrophy/chemically induced</k1>
<k1>Lipocalins</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Muscle, Skeletal/drug effects/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Somatotropin/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Beta-adrenergic receptor agonists (BA) induce skeletal muscle hypertrophy, yet specific mechanisms that lead to this effect are not well understood. The objective of this research was to identify novel genes and physiological pathways that potentially facilitate BA induced skeletal muscle growth. The Affymetrix platform was utilized to identify gene expression changes in mouse skeletal muscle 24 hours and 10 days after administration of the BA clenbuterol. RESULTS: Administration of clenbuterol stimulated anabolic activity, as indicated by decreased blood urea nitrogen (BUN; P &amp;lt; 0.01) and increased body weight gain (P &amp;lt; 0.05) 24 hours or 10 days, respectively, after initiation of clenbuterol treatment. A total of 22,605 probesets were evaluated with 52 probesets defined as differentially expressed based on a false discovery rate of 10%. Differential mRNA abundance of four of these genes was validated in an independent experiment by quantitative PCR. Functional characterization of differentially expressed genes revealed several categories that participate in biological processes important to skeletal muscle growth, including regulators of transcription and translation, mediators of cell-signalling pathways, and genes involved in polyamine metabolism. CONCLUSION: Global evaluation of gene expression after administration of clenbuterol identified changes in gene expression and overrepresented functional categories of genes that may regulate BA-induced muscle hypertrophy. Changes in mRNA abundance of multiple genes associated with myogenic differentiation may indicate an important effect of BA on proliferation, differentiation, and/or recruitment of satellite cells into muscle fibers to promote muscle hypertrophy. Increased mRNA abundance of genes involved in the initiation of translation suggests that increased levels of protein synthesis often associated with BA administration may result from a general up-regulation of translational initiators. Additionally, numerous other genes and physiological pathways were identified that will be important targets for further investigations of the hypertrophic effect of BA on skeletal muscle.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 100965258; 0 (Adrenergic beta-Agonists); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Cdkn1a protein, mouse); 0 (Cyclin-Dependent Kinase Inhibitor p21); 0 (Lipocalins); 0 (Neoplasm Proteins); 0 (Receptors, Somatotropin); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Tgfb1i4 protein, mouse); 0 (Tinagl protein, mouse); 37148-27-9 (Clenbuterol); OID: NLM: PMC1766935; 2006/05/19 [received]; 2006/12/20 [accepted]; 2006/12/20 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2164; 1471-2164</sn>
<ad>Department of Animal Sciences, Iowa State University, Ames, IA, USA. moodyd@iastate.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17181869; 1471-2164-7-320 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Validation Studies; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1471-2164-7-320</do>
<wp>20061220</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17181869</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1766935</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>121</id>
<a1>Steinhauser,K. E.</a1>
<a1>Clipp,E. C.</a1>
<a1>McNeilly,M.</a1>
<a1>Christakis,N. A.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Tulsky,J. A.</a1>
<t1>In search of a good death: observations of patients, families, and providers</t1>
<jf>Annals of Internal Medicine</jf>
<jo>Ann.Intern.Med.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>May 16</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>825</sp>
<op>832</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Advance Care Planning</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Attitude to Death</k1>
<k1>Decision Making</k1>
<k1>Family/psychology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Focus Groups</k1>
<k1>Health Personnel/psychology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interviews as Topic</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Pain/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Patients/psychology</k1>
<k1>Qualitative Research</k1>
<k1>Research</k1>
<k1>Terminal Care</k1>
<k1>Death and Euthanasia</k1>
<k1>Empirical Approach</k1>
<k1>Professional Patient Relationship</k1>
<ab>Despite a recent increase in the attention given to improving end-of-life care, our understanding of what constitutes a good death is surprisingly lacking. The purpose of this study was to gather descriptions of the components of a good death from patients, families, and providers through focus group discussions and in-depth interviews. Seventy-five participants-including physicians, nurses, social workers, chaplains, hospice volunteers, patients, and recently bereaved family members-were recruited from a university medical center, a Veterans Affairs medical center, and a community hospice. Participants identified six major components of a good death: pain and symptom management, clear decision making, preparation for death, completion, contributing to others, and affirmation of the whole person. The six themes are process-oriented attributes of a good death, and each has biomedical, psychological, social, and spiritual components. Physicians&amp;#39; discussions of a good death differed greatly from those of other groups. Physicians offered the most biomedical perspective, and patients, families, and other health care professionals defined a broad range of attributes integral to the quality of dying. Although there is no &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; way to die, these six themes may be used as a framework for understanding what participants tend to value at the end of life. Biomedical care is critical, but it is only a point of departure toward total end-of-life care. For patients and families, psychosocial and spiritual issues are as important as physiologic concerns.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0372351; OID: KIE: 64954; OTO: KIE; GN: KIE: KIE BoB Subject Heading: terminal care; GN: KIE: Full author name: Steinhauser, Karen E; GN: KIE: Full author name: Clipp, Elizabeth C; GN: KIE: Full author name: McNeilly, Maya; GN: KIE: Full author name: Christakis, Nicholas A; GN: KIE: Full author name: McIntyre, Lauren M; GN: KIE: Full author name: Tulsky, James A; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-4819; 0003-4819</sn>
<ad>Durham Veterans Affairs Medical Center, North Carolina 27705, USA. karensteinhauser@mindspring.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 10819707; 200005160-00011 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; AIM; E; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10819707</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>66</id>
<a1>Telonis-Scott,M.</a1>
<a1>Kopp,A.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Sex-specific splicing in Drosophila: widespread occurrence, tissue specificity and evolutionary conservation</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>181</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>421</sp>
<pb>Genetics Soc America</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>109</id>
<a1>Telonis-Scott,M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<t1>Genetic architecture of two fitness-related traits in Drosophila melanogaster: ovariole number and thorax length</t1>
<jf>Genetica</jf>
<jo>Genetica</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>125</vo>
<is>2-3</is>
<sp>211</sp>
<op>222</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Crosses, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Drosophila melanogaster/anatomy &amp; histology/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Ovary/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Reproduction/genetics</k1>
<k1>Selection, Genetic</k1>
<ab>In Drosophila melanogaster, ovariole number and thorax length are morphological characters thought to be associated with fitness. Maximum daily egg production in females is positively correlated with ovariole number, while thorax length is correlated with male reproductive success and female fecundity. Though both traits are related to fitness, ovariole number is likely to be under stabilizing selection, while thorax length appears to be under directional selection. Current research has focused on examining the sources of variation for ovariole number in relation to fitness, with a view towards elucidating how segregating variation is maintained in natural populations. Here, we utilize a diallel design to explore the genetic architecture of ovariole number and thorax length in nine isogenic lines derived from a natural population. The full diallel design allows the estimation of general combining ability (GCA), specific combining ability (SCA), and also describes variation due to reciprocal effects (RGCA and RSCA). Ovariole number and thorax length differed with respect to their genetic architecture, reflective of the independent selective forces acting on the traits. For ovariole number, GCA accounted for the majority (67.3%) of variation segregating between the lines, with no evidence of reciprocal effects or inbreeding depression; SCA accounted for a small percentage (3.9%) of the variance, suggesting dominance variation; no reciprocal effects were observed. In contrast, for thorax length, the majority of the non-error variance was accounted for by SCA (17.9%), with only one third as much variance (6.2%) due to GCA. Interestingly, RSCA (nuclear-extranuclear interactions) accounted for slightly more variation (7.5%) than GCA in these data. Thus, genetic variation for thorax length is largely in accord with predictions for a fitness trait under directional selection: little additive genetic variation and substantial dominance variation (including a suggestion of inbreeding depression); while the mechanisms underlying the maintenance of variation for ovariole number are more complex.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: GM59884-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM65513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0370740; 2005/02/15 [received]; 2005/06/08 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0016-6707; 0016-6707</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA. mtelonis@zoo.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16247693</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s10709-005-8549-4</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16247693</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>73</id>
<a1>Verhoeven,K. J. F.</a1>
<a1>Simonsen,K. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Implementing false discovery rate control: increasing your power</t1>
<jf>Oikos</jf>
<jo>Oikos</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>108</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>643</sp>
<op>647</op>
<pb>Citeseer</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>105</id>
<a1>Verhoeven,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Jannink,J. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Using mating designs to uncover QTL and the genetic architecture of complex traits</t1>
<jf>Heredity</jf>
<jo>Heredity</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>139</sp>
<op>149</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Breeding</k1>
<k1>Computer Simulation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Inbreeding</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Pedigree</k1>
<k1>Quantitative Trait Loci</k1>
<k1>Quantitative Trait, Heritable</k1>
<ab>Analysis of quantitative trait loci (QTL) affecting complex traits is often pursued in single-cross experiments. For most purposes, including breeding, some assessment is desired of the generalizability of the QTL findings and of the overall genetic architecture of the trait. Single-cross experiments provide a poor basis for these purposes, as comparison across experiments is hampered by segregation of different allelic combinations among different parents and by context-dependent effects of QTL. To overcome this problem, we combined the benefits of QTL analysis (to identify genomic regions affecting trait variation) and classic diallel analysis (to obtain insight into the general inheritance of the trait) by analyzing multiple mapping families that are connected via shared parents. We first provide a theoretical derivation of main (general combining ability (GCA)) and interaction (specific combining ability (SCA)) effects on F(2) family means relative to variance components in a randomly mating reference population. Then, using computer simulations to generate F(2) families derived from 10 inbred parents in different partial-diallel designs, we show that QTL can be detected and that the residual among-family variance can be analyzed. Standard diallel analysis methods are applied in order to reveal the presence and mode of action (in terms of GCA and SCA) of undetected polygenes. Given a fixed experiment size (total number of individuals), we demonstrate that QTL detection and estimation of the genetic architecture of polygenic effects are competing goals, which should be explicitly accounted for in the experimental design. Our approach provides a general strategy for exploring the genetic architecture, as well as the QTL underlying variation in quantitative traits.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0373007; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0018-067X; 0018-067X</sn>
<ad>Computational Genomics and Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, Lilly Hall of Life Sciences, 915 W State Street, West Lafayette, IN 47907-2054, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16304603; 6800763 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/sj.hdy.6800763</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16304603</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1106</id>
<a1>Vermerris,W.</a1>
<a1>Sherman,D. M.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Phenotypic plasticity in cell walls of maize brown midrib mutants is limited by lignin composition</t1>
<jf>Journal of experimental botany</jf>
<jo>J.Exp.Bot.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<pb>Soc Experiment Biol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>123</id>
<a1>Vermerris,W.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Time to flowering in brown midrib mutants of maize: an alternative approach to the analysis of developmental traits</t1>
<jf>Heredity</jf>
<jo>Heredity</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>83 ( Pt 2)</vo>
<is>Pt 2</is>
<sp>171</sp>
<op>178</op>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plant Structures</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>The brown midrib (bm) mutations of maize affect the biosynthesis of lignin, resulting in reddish-brown vascular tissue in the stem, the leaf blade and sheath. Investigating the effects of the change in lignin content and composition on other phenotypic traits in bm mutants is important in increasing the understanding of how secondary metabolism affects plant development. We examined the time to flowering of inbred A619 and near-isogenic lines of bm2, bm1-bm2 and a segregating population with wild-type and bm1 heterozygotes in a controlled experimental design (Latin square) in two locations. Survival analysis was used to describe the distribution of the time to flowering and compare differences between genotypic classes. Survival analysis is a readily accessible technique that can improve inferences in cases where distributions are skewed, or where data are missing or incomplete. The basic approach to survival analysis as well as its specific application to these data is described. After controlling for the effects of the locations, the time to flowering of the bm2 and segregating populations was found to be significantly different from the wild-type and bm1-bm2 populations.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: 1P01CA7/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0373007; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0018-067X; 0018-067X</sn>
<ad>Department of Genetics, Box 7614, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27695, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10469205; her569 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10469205</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>117</id>
<a1>Vermerris,W.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,K. J.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>The maize Brown midrib1 locus affects cell wall composition and plant development in a dose-dependent manner</t1>
<jf>Heredity</jf>
<jo>Heredity</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>450</sp>
<op>457</op>
<k1>Cell Wall/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Gene Dosage</k1>
<k1>Genes, Plant</k1>
<k1>Heterozygote</k1>
<k1>Homozygote</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/chemistry/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>The four brown midrib (bm) mutants of maize have a reduced content and altered subunit composition of the cell wall polymer lignin. The bm mutations have traditionally been considered completely recessive, because the brown midrib phenotype is only apparent in plants homozygous for the mutation. In addition to an effect on cell wall composition, some bm mutations have been shown to affect flowering time. We had preliminary evidence for a dosage effect of the Bm1 locus on flowering time, which prompted this detailed study on the Bm1 locus. In this study, near-isogenic lines (in an A619 background) with zero, one or two bm1 mutant alleles were compared. The bm1 heterozygotes flowered significantly earlier than both the wild-type plants and bm1 mutants. This difference can at least be partly attributed to an accelerated growth rate in the later stages of plant development. Furthermore, Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy revealed that the cell wall composition of the bm1 heterozygous plants is distinct from both the bm1 and wild-type homozygotes. The combination of the data on flowering time and the data on cell wall composition provide evidence for a dosage effect at the Bm1 locus.</ab>
<no>JID: 0373007; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0018-067X; 0018-067X</sn>
<ad>Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907, USA. vermerris@purdue.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12180087</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12180087</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>82</id>
<a1>Vermerris,W.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,K. J.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Axtell,J. D.</a1>
<t1>Evidence for an evolutionarily conserved interaction between cell wall biosynthesis and flowering in maize and sorghum</t1>
<jf>BMC evolutionary biology</jf>
<jo>BMC Evol.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<sp>2</sp>
<k1>Body Height</k1>
<k1>Cell Wall/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Flowers/genetics/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Linear Models</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sorghum/cytology/genetics/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Zea mays/cytology/genetics/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Factors that affect flowering vary among different plant species, and in the grasses in particular the exact mechanism behind this transition is not fully understood. The brown midrib (bm) mutants of maize (Zea mays L.), which have altered cell wall composition, have different flowering dynamics compared to their wild-type counterparts. This is indicative of a link between cell wall biogenesis and flowering. In order to test whether this relationship also exists in other grasses, the flowering dynamics in sorghum (Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench) were investigated. Sorghum is evolutionarily closely related to maize, and a set of brown midrib (bmr) mutants similar to the maize bm mutants is available, making sorghum a suitable choice for study in this context. RESULTS: We compared the flowering time (time to half-bloom) of several different bmr sorghum lines and their wild-type counterparts. This revealed that the relationship between cell wall composition and flowering was conserved in sorghum. Specifically, the mutant bmr7 flowered significantly earlier than the corresponding wild-type control, whereas the mutants bmr2, bmr4, bmr6, bmr12, and bmr19 flowered later than their wild-type controls. CONCLUSION: The change in flowering dynamics in several of the brown midrib sorghum lines provides evidence for an evolutionarily conserved mechanism that links cell wall biosynthesis to flowering dynamics. The availability of the sorghum bmr mutants expands the germplasm available to investigate this relationship in further detail.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 100966975; OID: NLM: PMC65529; 2001/07/10 [received]; 2002/01/07 [accepted]; 2002/01/07 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1471-2148; 1471-2148</sn>
<ad>Department of Agronomy, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907-1150, USA. vermerris@purdue.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11835688</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<wp>20020107</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11835688</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC65529</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>69</id>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Telonis-Scott,M.</a1>
<a1>Bono,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Harshman,L.</a1>
<a1>Kopp,A.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Simpler mode of inheritance of transcriptional variation in male Drosophila melanogaster</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>104</vo>
<is>47</is>
<sp>18577</sp>
<pb>National Acad Sciences</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>116</id>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Combining mapping and arraying: An approach to candidate gene identification</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Nov 12</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>14903</sp>
<op>14906</op>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping/methods</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Insects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis/methods</k1>
<k1>Quantitative Trait Loci</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<ab>A combination of quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping and microarray analysis was developed and used to identify 34 candidate genes for ovariole number, a quantitative trait, in Drosophila melanogaster. Ovariole number is related to evolutionary fitness, which has been extensively studied, but for which few a priori candidate genes exist. A set of recombinant inbred lines were assayed for ovariole number, and QTL analyses for this trait identified 5,286 positional candidate loci. Forty deletions spanning the QTL were employed to further refine the map position of genes contributing to variation in this trait between parental lines, with six deficiencies showing significant effects and reducing the number of positional candidates to 548. Parental lines were then assayed for expression differences by using Affymetrix microarray technology, and ANOVA was used to identify differentially expressed genes in these deletions. Thirty-four genes were identified that showed evidence for differential expression between the parental lines, one of which was significant even after a conservative Bonferroni correction. The list of potential candidates includes 5 genes for which previous annotations did not exist, and therefore would have been unlikely choices for follow-up from mapping studies alone. The use of microarray technology in this context allows an efficient, objective, quantitative evaluation of genes in the QTL and has the potential to reduce the overall effort needed in identifying genes causally associated with quantitative traits of interest.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: GM59884-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC137517; 2002/11/01 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, P.O. Box 118525, University of Florida, Gainesville 32611-8525, USA. mlwayne@zoo.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12415114; 222549199 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.222549199</do>
<wp>20021101</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12415114</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC137517</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>110</id>
<a1>Wayne,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Pan,Y. J.</a1>
<a1>Nuzhdin,S. V.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<t1>Additivity and trans-acting effects on gene expression in male Drosophila simulans</t1>
<jf>Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genetics</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>168</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1413</sp>
<op>1420</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chi-Square Distribution</k1>
<k1>Drosophila/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/physiology</k1>
<k1>X Chromosome</k1>
<ab>Understanding how genetic variation is maintained begins with a comprehensive description of what types of genetic variation exist, the extent and magnitude of the variation, and patterns discernable in that variation. However, such studies have focused primarily on DNA sequence data and have ignored genetic variation at other hierarchical levels of genetic information. Microarray technology permits an examination of genetic variation at the level of mRNA abundance. Utilizing a round-robin design, we present a quantitative description of variation in mRNA abundance in terms of GCA (general combining ability or additive variance). We test whether genes significant for GCA are randomly distributed across chromosomes and use a nonparametric approach to demonstrate that the magnitude of the variation is not random for GCA. We find that there is a paucity of genes significant for GCA on the X relative to the autosomes. The overall magnitude of the effects for GCA on the X tends to be lower than that on the autosomes and is contributed by rare alleles of larger effect. Due to male hemizygosity, GCA for X-linked phenotypes must be due to trans-acting factors, while GCA for autosomal phenotypes may be due to cis- or trans-acting factors. The contrast in the amount of variation between the X and the autosomes suggests that both cis and trans factors contribute to variation for expression in D. simulans with the preponderance of effects being trans. This nonrandom patterning of genetic variation in gene expression data with respect to chromosomal context may be due to hemizygosity in the male.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 GM59884-02/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 GM61773/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R24 GM65513-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0374636; 0 (Trans-Activators); OID: NLM: PMC1448806; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0016-6731; 0016-6731</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA. mlwayne@zoo.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15579694; 168/3/1413 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1534/genetics.104.030973</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15579694</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1448806</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>58</id>
<a1>Xu,P.</a1>
<a1>McIntyre,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Scardina,J.</a1>
<a1>Wheeler,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Thorgaard,G. H.</a1>
<a1>Nichols,K. M.</a1>
<t1>Transcriptome Profiling of Embryonic Development Rate in Rainbow Trout Advanced Backcross Introgression Lines</t1>
<jf>Marine Biotechnology</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>17</op>
<pb>Springer</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
