
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>51</id>
<a1>Fillingim,R. B.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,L.</a1>
<a1>Staud,R.</a1>
<a1>Ness,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Glover,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Campbell,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Mogil,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>The A118G single nucleotide polymorphism of the mu-opioid receptor gene (OPRM1) is associated with pressure pain sensitivity in humans</t1>
<jf>The journal of pain : official journal of the American Pain Society</jf>
<jo>J.Pain</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>159</sp>
<op>167</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Ischemia/genetics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Pain/genetics</k1>
<k1>Pain Threshold/physiology</k1>
<k1>Perception</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</k1>
<k1>Pressure</k1>
<k1>Questionnaires</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Opioid, mu/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sex Characteristics</k1>
<ab>Responses to painful stimuli are characterized by tremendous interindividual variability, and genetic factors likely account for some proportion of this variability. However, few studies have identified genetic contributions to experimental pain perception in humans. This experiment investigated whether the A118G single nucleotide polymorphism of the mu-opioid receptor gene ( OPRM1 ) was associated with responses to three different experimental pain modalities in a sample of 167 healthy volunteers (96 female, 71 male). Responses to thermal, mechanical, and ischemic pain were assessed in all subjects, and genotyping of OPRM1 was performed, which revealed that the rare A118G allele occurred in 24 females (25%) and 12 males (17%). Statistical analyses indicated that subjects with a rare allele had significantly higher pressure pain thresholds than those homozygous for the common allele. Also, a sex by genotype interaction emerged for heat pain ratings at 49 degrees C, such that the rare allele was associated with lower pain ratings among men but higher pain ratings among women. These data indicate an association of a common single nucleotide polymorphism of OPRM1 with mechanical pain responses and that this genotype may be associated with heat pain perception in a sex-dependent manner. This study examines the association of the A118G SNP of OPRM1 to experimental pain sensitivity. The results indicate that the rare allele is associated with higher pressure pain thresholds. These results support previous contentions that OPRM1 may be a pain-relevant gene; however, replication of these findings is needed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: NS41670/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: RR00082/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 100898657; 0 (OPRM1 protein, human); 0 (Receptors, Opioid, mu); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1526-5900; 1526-5900</sn>
<ad>University of Florida College of Dentistry, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. rfillingi@dental.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15772909; S1526590004011174 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.jpain.2004.11.008</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15772909</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>50</id>
<a1>Fishbein,L.</a1>
<a1>Eady,B.</a1>
<a1>Sanek,N.</a1>
<a1>Muir,D.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of somatic NF1 promoter methylation in plexiform neurofibromas and Schwann cells</t1>
<jf>Cancer genetics and cytogenetics</jf>
<jo>Cancer Genet.Cytogenet.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>157</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>186</op>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>CpG Islands</k1>
<k1>Cytosine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Methylation</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Neurofibromatosis 1</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neurofibroma, Plexiform/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Schwann Cells/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Neurofibromatosis 1 (NF1) is an autosomal dominant disorder with the characteristic feature being the neurofibroma. It is believed that both NF1 alleles must be inactivated as the first step in tumorigenesis. However, often the somatic mutations are not identified, suggesting that epigenetic changes such as methylation could account for the &amp;quot;second hit&amp;quot; in some tumors. The literature reports that the region of the NF1 promoter surrounding the transcription start site is completely unmethylated in several normal tissues and some NF1-related dermal and plexiform neurofibromas. We analyzed the methylation state of the NF1 promoter in normal Schwann cells (the cell type clonally expanded in neurofibromas) and in NF1-related plexiform tumor samples with unidentified somatic mutations. In a region of 451 bp surrounding the transcription start site, a low level of methylation was found at several specific cytosines in 12 of 18 tumor samples. Overall, epigenetic silencing through methylation does not appear to be a major mechanism for the second hit. However, this study, which analyzed the largest number of NF1-related plexiform tumors and is the first to include Schwann cell-enriched tumor cultures, detected greater methylation than in any previous reports. This suggests that methylation, especially at potential transcription factor binding sites, is moderately perturbed in some plexiform neurofibromas and should be investigated further.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; GR: 1R01 NS34780/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: 1R29 NS31550/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-CA01926-22/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7909240; 71-30-7 (Cytosine); 2004/05/10 [received]; 2004/07/26 [revised]; 2004/07/28 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0165-4608; 0165-4608</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, ARB R2-220, P.O. Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15721644; S0165-4608(04)00320-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.cancergencyto.2004.08.016</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15721644</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>47</id>
<a1>Fishbein,L.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,X.</a1>
<a1>Fisher,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Li,H.</a1>
<a1>Campbell-Thompson,M.</a1>
<a1>Yachnis,A.</a1>
<a1>Rubenstein,A.</a1>
<a1>Muir,D.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>In vitro studies of steroid hormones in neurofibromatosis 1 tumors and Schwann cells</t1>
<jf>Molecular carcinogenesis</jf>
<jo>Mol.Carcinog.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>512</sp>
<op>523</op>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoenzyme Techniques</k1>
<k1>In Situ Nick-End Labeling</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromatosis 1/genetics/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptor, erbB-2/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Androgen/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Estrogen/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Progesterone/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Steroid/agonists/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Schwann Cells/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<ab>The most common NF1 feature is the benign neurofibroma, which consists predominantly of Schwann cells. Dermal neurofibromas usually arise during puberty and increase in number throughout adulthood. Plexiform neurofibromas, associated with larger nerves, are often congenital and can be life threatening. Malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumors (MPNST) in NF1 are believed to arise from plexiforms in 5%-10% of patients. There are reports of increased potential for malignant transformation of plexiform tumors and increase in dermal neurofibromas, during pregnancy. These observations suggest that steroid hormones influence neurofibroma growth, and our work is the first to examine steroid hormone receptor expression and ligand-mediated cell growth and survival in normal human Schwann cells and neurofibroma-derived Schwann cell cultures. Immunohistochemistry and real-time PCR showed that estrogen receptors (ERs), progesterone receptor (PR), and androgen receptor are differentially expressed in primary neurofibromas and in NF1 tumor-derived Schwann cell cultures compared to normal Schwann cells. However, there is substantial heterogeneity, with no clear divisions based on tumor type or gender. The in vitro effects of steroid hormone receptor ligands on proliferation and apoptosis of early passage NF1 tumor-derived Schwann cell cultures were compared to normal Schwann cell cultures. Some statistically significant changes in proliferation and apoptosis were found, also showing heterogeneity across groups and ligands. Overall, the changes are consistent with increased cell accumulation. Our data suggest that steroid hormones can directly influence neurofibroma initiation or progression by acting through their cognate receptor, but that these effects may only apply to a subset of tumors, in either gender.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; CI: (c) 2007; GR: 1F30 NS 43951/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8811105; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Receptors, Androgen); 0 (Receptors, Estrogen); 0 (Receptors, Progesterone); 0 (Receptors, Steroid); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor, erbB-2); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptors, Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor); ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley-Liss, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0899-1987; 0899-1987</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, UF College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17393410</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/mc.20236</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17393410</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>45</id>
<a1>George,S. Z.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Wright,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Moser,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Greenfield,W. H.,3rd</a1>
<a1>Sack,B. K.</a1>
<a1>Herbstman,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Fillingim,R. B.</a1>
<t1>Evidence for a biopsychosocial influence on shoulder pain: pain catastrophizing and catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) diplotype predict clinical pain ratings</t1>
<jf>Pain</jf>
<jo>Pain</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>53</sp>
<op>61</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Catechol O-Methyltransferase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Pain Measurement/methods/psychology</k1>
<k1>Pain, Postoperative/enzymology/genetics/psychology</k1>
<k1>Predictive Value of Tests</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Shoulder Pain/enzymology/genetics/psychology</k1>
<ab>The experience of pain is believed to be influenced by social, cultural, environmental, psychological, and genetic factors. Despite this assertion, few studies have included clinically relevant pain phenotypes when investigating interactions among these variables. This study investigated whether psychological variables specific to fear-avoidance models and catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) genotype influenced pain ratings for a cohort of patients receiving operative treatment of shoulder pain. Patients (n=58) completed questionnaires and had COMT genotype determined pre-operatively. Then, shoulder pain ratings were collected 3-5 months post-operatively. This cohort consisted of 24 females and 34 males, with mean age of 50.3 (SD=15.0) and pre-operative pain rating of 4.5/10 (SD=1.8). The frequency of COMT diplotypes was 34 with &amp;quot;high COMT activity&amp;quot; (LPS group) and 24 with &amp;quot;low COMT activity&amp;quot; (APS/HPS group). Preliminary analysis indicated that of all the fear-avoidance variables considered (fear of pain, kinesiophobia, pain catastrophizing, and anxiety), only pain catastrophizing was a unique contributor to clinical pain ratings. A hierarchical regression model indicated that an interaction between pain catastrophizing and COMT diplotype contributed additional variance in pre-operative pain ratings. The pain catastrophizingxCOMT diplotype interaction demonstrated predictive validity as patients with high pain catastrophizing and low COMT activity (APS/HPS group) were more likely (RR=6.8, 95% CI=2.8-16.7) to have post-operative pain ratings of 4.0/10 or higher. Our findings suggest that an interaction between pain catastrophizing and COMT diplotype has the potential to influence pain ratings in patients seeking operative treatment of their shoulder pain.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 NS041670-08/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7508686; EC 2.1.1.6 (Catechol O-Methyltransferase); NIHMS98631; OID: NLM: NIHMS98631; OID: NLM: PMC2669670; 2007/03/02 [received]; 2007/05/11 [revised]; 2007/06/15 [accepted]; 2007/08/07 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>1872-6623; 0304-3959</sn>
<ad>Department of Physical Therapy, Brooks Center for Rehabilitation Studies, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA. szgeorge@phhp.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17686583; S0304-3959(07)00346-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.pain.2007.06.019</do>
<wp>20070807</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17686583</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2669670</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>54</id>
<a1>Humma,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Puckett,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Richardson,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Terra,S. G.</a1>
<a1>Andrisin,T. E.</a1>
<a1>Lejeune,B. L.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lewis,J. F.</a1>
<a1>McNamara,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Picoult-Newberg,L.</a1>
<a1>Pepine,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of beta1-adrenoceptor genetic polymorphisms on resting hemodynamics in patients undergoing diagnostic testing for ischemia</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Cardiology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Cardiol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Nov 1</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>1034</sp>
<op>1037</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Arginine/genetics</k1>
<k1>Codon</k1>
<k1>Echocardiography, Stress</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Glycine/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Myocardial Ischemia/genetics/physiopathology/ultrasonography</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Adrenergic, beta-1/genetics</k1>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: M01-RR00425/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68161/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68162/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68163/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68164/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-HL64691/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0207277; 0 (Codon); 0 (Receptors, Adrenergic, beta-1); 56-40-6 (Glycine); 74-79-3 (Arginine); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0002-9149; 0002-9149</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacy, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11704005; S0002-9149(01)01986-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11704005</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>42</id>
<a1>Jin,Y.</a1>
<a1>Birlea,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Fain,P. R.</a1>
<a1>Gowan,K.</a1>
<a1>Riccardi,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Holland,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Mailloux,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Sufit,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Hutton,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Amadi-Myers,A.</a1>
<a1>Bennett,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>McCormack,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Kemp,E. H.</a1>
<a1>Gawkrodger,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Weetman,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Picardo,M.</a1>
<a1>Leone,G.</a1>
<a1>Taieb,A.</a1>
<a1>Jouary,T.</a1>
<a1>Ezzedine,K.</a1>
<a1>van Geel,N.</a1>
<a1>Lambert,J.</a1>
<a1>Overbeck,A.</a1>
<a1>Spritz,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Variant of TYR and autoimmunity susceptibility loci in generalized vitiligo</t1>
<jf>The New England journal of medicine</jf>
<jo>N.Engl.J.Med.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May 6</fd>
<vo>362</vo>
<is>18</is>
<sp>1686</sp>
<op>1697</op>
<k1>Autoimmune Diseases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Markers</k1>
<k1>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</k1>
<k1>Genome-Wide Association Study</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Major Histocompatibility Complex/genetics</k1>
<k1>Melanoma/genetics</k1>
<k1>Monophenol Monooxygenase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</k1>
<k1>Vitiligo/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Generalized vitiligo is an autoimmune disease characterized by melanocyte loss, which results in patchy depigmentation of skin and hair, and is associated with an elevated risk of other autoimmune diseases. METHODS: To identify generalized vitiligo susceptibility loci, we conducted a genomewide association study. We genotyped 579,146 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 1514 patients with generalized vitiligo who were of European-derived white (CEU) ancestry and compared the genotypes with publicly available control genotypes from 2813 CEU persons. We then tested 50 SNPs in two replication sets, one comprising 677 independent CEU patients and 1106 CEU controls and the other comprising 183 CEU simplex trios with generalized vitiligo and 332 CEU multiplex families. RESULTS: We detected significant associations between generalized vitiligo and SNPs at several loci previously associated with other autoimmune diseases. These included genes encoding major-histocompatibility-complex class I molecules (P=9.05x10(-23)) and class II molecules (P=4.50x10(-34)), PTPN22 (P=1.31x10(-7)), LPP (P=1.01x10(-11)), IL2RA (P=2.78x10(-9)), UBASH3A (P=1.26x10(-9)), and C1QTNF6 (P=2.21x10(-16)). We also detected associations between generalized vitiligo and SNPs in two additional immune-related loci, RERE (P=7.07x10(-15)) and GZMB (P=3.44x10(-8)), and in a locus containing TYR (P=1.60x10(-18)), encoding tyrosinase. CONCLUSIONS: We observed associations between generalized vitiligo and markers implicating multiple genes, some associated with other autoimmune diseases and one (TYR) that may mediate target-cell specificity and indicate a mutually exclusive relationship between susceptibility to vitiligo and susceptibility to melanoma.</ab>
<no>CI: 2010; GR: AR056292/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: AR45584/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0255562; 0 (Genetic Markers); EC 1.14.18.1 (Monophenol Monooxygenase); 2010/04/21 [aheadofprint]; 2010/04/27 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pb>Massachusetts Medical Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1533-4406; 0028-4793</sn>
<ad>Human Medical Genetics Program, School of Medicine, University of Colorado, P.O. Box 6511, Mailstop 8300, Aurora, CO 80045, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20410501; NEJMoa0908547 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1056/NEJMoa0908547</do>
<wp>20100421</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20410501</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>56</id>
<a1>Messiaen,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Callens,T.</a1>
<a1>Roux,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Mortier,G. R.</a1>
<a1>De Paepe,A.</a1>
<a1>Abramowicz,M.</a1>
<a1>Pericak-Vance,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Vance,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Exon 10b of the NF1 gene represents a mutational hotspot and harbors a recurrent missense mutation Y489C associated with aberrant splicing</t1>
<jf>Genetics in medicine : official journal of the American College of Medical Genetics</jf>
<jo>Genet.Med.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sep-Oct</fd>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>248</sp>
<op>253</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Complementary/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation, Missense</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromin 1</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To analyze the spectrum and frequency of NF1 mutations in exon 10b. METHODS: Mutation and sequence analysis was performed at the DNA and cDNA level. RESULTS: We identified nine exon 10b mutations in 232 unrelated patients. Some mutations were recurrent (Y489C and L508P), others were unique (1465-1466insC and IVS10b+2delTAAG). Surprisingly, at the RNA level, Y489C causes skipping of the last 62 nucleotides of exon 10b. Another recurrent mutation, L508P, is undetectable by the Protein Truncation Test. CONCLUSION: As exon 10b shows the highest mutation rate yet found in any of the 60 NF1 exons, it should be implemented with priority in mutation analysis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/AC004222; GENBANK/AF064564; GENBANK/D45201; GENBANK/L10370; GENBANK/L26501; GR: N53155/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 9815831; 0 (DNA, Complementary); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Neurofibromin 1); CIN: Genet Med. 1999 Sep-Oct;1(6):245-7. PMID: 11258624; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-3600; 1098-3600</sn>
<ad>Department of Medical Genetics, University Hospital, Gent, Belgium.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11258625</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11258625</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>43</id>
<a1>Miller,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Jessen,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Mehta,T.</a1>
<a1>Hardiman,A.</a1>
<a1>Sites,E.</a1>
<a1>Kaiser,S.</a1>
<a1>Jegga,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Li,H.</a1>
<a1>Upadhyaya,M.</a1>
<a1>Giovannini,M.</a1>
<a1>Muir,D.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,E.</a1>
<a1>Serra,E.</a1>
<a1>Nielsen,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Lazaro,C.</a1>
<a1>Stemmer-Rachamimov,A.</a1>
<a1>Page,G.</a1>
<a1>Aronow,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Ratner,N.</a1>
<t1>Integrative genomic analyses of neurofibromatosis tumours identify SOX9 as a biomarker and survival gene</t1>
<jf>EMBO molecular medicine</jf>
<jo>EMBO Mol.Med.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>236</sp>
<op>248</op>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromatosis 1/diagnosis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Peripheral Nervous System Neoplasms/diagnosis/genetics</k1>
<k1>SOX9 Transcription Factor/diagnostic use/genetics</k1>
<k1>Schwann Cells/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Tumor Markers, Biological/genetics</k1>
<ab>Understanding the biological pathways critical for common neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) peripheral nerve tumours is essential, as there is a lack of tumour biomarkers, prognostic factors and therapeutics. We used gene expression profiling to define transcriptional changes between primary normal Schwann cells (n = 10), NF1-derived primary benign neurofibroma Schwann cells (NFSCs) (n = 22), malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumour (MPNST) cell lines (n = 13), benign neurofibromas (NF) (n = 26) and MPNST (n = 6). Dermal and plexiform NFs were indistinguishable. A prominent theme in the analysis was aberrant differentiation. NFs repressed gene programs normally active in Schwann cell precursors and immature Schwann cells. MPNST signatures strongly differed; genes up-regulated in sarcomas were significantly enriched for genes activated in neural crest cells. We validated the differential expression of 82 genes including the neural crest transcription factor SOX9 and SOX9 predicted targets. SOX9 immunoreactivity was robust in NF and MPSNT tissue sections and targeting SOX9 - strongly expressed in NF1-related tumours - caused MPNST cell death. SOX9 is a biomarker of NF and MPNST, and possibly a therapeutic target in NF1.</ab>
<no>GR: K01-NS049191/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 CA 59268/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101487380; 0 (SOX9 Transcription Factor); 0 (SOX9 protein, human); 0 (Tumor Markers, Biological); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1757-4684; 1757-4676</sn>
<ad>Division of Experimental Hematology, Cincinnati Children&#39;s Hospital, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20049725</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/emmm.200900027</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20049725</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>52</id>
<a1>Mogil,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Wilson,S. G.</a1>
<a1>Chesler,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Rankin,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Nemmani,K. V.</a1>
<a1>Lariviere,W. R.</a1>
<a1>Groce,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,L.</a1>
<a1>Staud,R.</a1>
<a1>Ness,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Glover,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Stankova,M.</a1>
<a1>Mayorov,A.</a1>
<a1>Hruby,V. J.</a1>
<a1>Grisel,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Fillingim,R. B.</a1>
<t1>The melanocortin-1 receptor gene mediates female-specific mechanisms of analgesia in mice and humans</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Apr 15</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>4867</sp>
<op>4872</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Analgesia</k1>
<k1>Analgesics, Opioid/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred DBA</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Pain/genetics/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Pentazocine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Corticotropin/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Melanocortin</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Opioid, kappa/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Sex Characteristics</k1>
<ab>Sex specificity of neural mechanisms modulating nociceptive information has been demonstrated in rodents, and these qualitative sex differences appear to be relevant to analgesia from kappa-opioid receptor agonists, a drug class reported to be clinically effective only in women. Via quantitative trait locus mapping followed by a candidate gene strategy using both mutant mice and pharmacological tools, we now demonstrate that the melanocortin-1 receptor (Mc1r) gene mediates kappa-opioid analgesia in female mice only. This finding suggested that individuals with variants of the human MC1R gene, associated in our species with red hair and fair skin, might also display altered kappa-opioid analgesia. We found that women with two variant MC1R alleles displayed significantly greater analgesia from the kappa-opioid, pentazocine, than all other groups. This study demonstrates an unexpected role for the MC1R gene, verifies that pain modulation in the two sexes involves neurochemically distinct substrates, and represents an example of a direct translation of a pharmacogenetic finding from mouse to human.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: DA15191/DA/NIDA NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE12735/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK17420/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: NS41670/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7505876; 0 (Analgesics, Opioid); 0 (Receptors, Corticotropin); 0 (Receptors, Melanocortin); 0 (Receptors, Opioid, kappa); 359-83-1 (Pentazocine); OID: NLM: PMC153647; 2003/03/27 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Psychology, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada H3A 1B1. jeffrey.mogil@mcgill.ca</ad>
<an>PMID: 12663858; 0730053100 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0730053100</do>
<wp>20030327</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12663858</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC153647</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>44</id>
<a1>Shabalina,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Zaykin,D. V.</a1>
<a1>Gris,P.</a1>
<a1>Ogurtsov,A. Y.</a1>
<a1>Gauthier,J.</a1>
<a1>Shibata,K.</a1>
<a1>Tchivileva,I. E.</a1>
<a1>Belfer,I.</a1>
<a1>Mishra,B.</a1>
<a1>Kiselycznyk,C.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Staud,R.</a1>
<a1>Spiridonov,N. A.</a1>
<a1>Max,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Goldman,D.</a1>
<a1>Fillingim,R. B.</a1>
<a1>Maixner,W.</a1>
<a1>Diatchenko,L.</a1>
<t1>Expansion of the human mu-opioid receptor gene architecture: novel functional variants</t1>
<jf>Human molecular genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Mol.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar 15</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1037</sp>
<op>1051</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>Exons/genetics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</k1>
<k1>Haplotypes</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Introns/genetics</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Conformation</k1>
<k1>Pain/genetics</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Isoforms/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA Splicing/genetics</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Opioid, mu/genetics</k1>
<ab>The mu-opioid receptor (OPRM1) is the principal receptor target for both endogenous and exogenous opioid analgesics. There are substantial individual differences in human responses to painful stimuli and to opiate drugs that are attributed to genetic variations in OPRM1. In searching for new functional variants, we employed comparative genome analysis and obtained evidence for the existence of an expanded human OPRM1 gene locus with new promoters, alternative exons and regulatory elements. Examination of polymorphisms within the human OPRM1 gene locus identified strong association between single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) rs563649 and individual variations in pain perception. SNP rs563649 is located within a structurally conserved internal ribosome entry site (IRES) in the 5&amp;#39;-UTR of a novel exon 13-containing OPRM1 isoforms (MOR-1K) and affects both mRNA levels and translation efficiency of these variants. Furthermore, rs563649 exhibits very strong linkage disequilibrium throughout the entire OPRM1 gene locus and thus affects the functional contribution of the corresponding haplotype that includes other functional OPRM1 SNPs. Our results provide evidence for an essential role for MOR-1K isoforms in nociceptive signaling and suggest that genetic variations in alternative OPRM1 isoforms may contribute to individual differences in opiate responses.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: NS41670/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: P01 NS045685/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE016558-05/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-DE16558/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: U01-DE017018/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9208958; 0 (OPRM1 protein, human); 0 (Protein Isoforms); 0 (Receptors, Opioid, mu); OID: NLM: PMC2649019; 2008/12/22 [aheadofprint]; 2009/01/07 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1460-2083; 0964-6906</sn>
<ad>National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Library of Medicine, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD 20894, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19103668; ddn439 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, N.I.H., Intramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1093/hmg/ddn439</do>
<wp>20081222</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19103668</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2649019</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>49</id>
<a1>Terra,S. G.</a1>
<a1>McGorray,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Wu,R.</a1>
<a1>McNamara,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Cavallari,L. H.</a1>
<a1>Walker,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,B. D.</a1>
<a1>Bairey Merz,C. N.</a1>
<a1>Sopko,G.</a1>
<a1>Pepine,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Association between beta-adrenergic receptor polymorphisms and their G-protein-coupled receptors with body mass index and obesity in women: a report from the NHLBI-sponsored WISE study</t1>
<jf>International journal of obesity (2005)</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Obes.(Lond)</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>746</sp>
<op>754</op>
<k1>Adipose Tissue/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>African Continental Ancestry Group</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Body Mass Index</k1>
<k1>Cohort Studies</k1>
<k1>European Continental Ancestry Group</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Frequency</k1>
<k1>Haplotypes</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Linkage Disequilibrium</k1>
<k1>Logistic Models</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Obesity/ethnology/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Adrenergic, beta/genetics</k1>
<k1>Receptors, G-Protein-Coupled/metabolism</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: The beta-adrenergic receptor (betaAR) genes are candidate genes for obesity because of their roles in energy homeostasis and promotion of lipolysis in human adipose tissue. Objective is to determine the association between obesity and polymorphisms in genes of the beta(1)AR (ADRB1), beta(2)AR (ADRB2), beta(3)AR (ADRB3), Gs protein alpha (GNAS1), to which all three beta-receptors couple and the G protein beta3 subunit (GNB3), to which beta(3)ARs couple. DESIGN: A case-control genetic association study. SUBJECTS: A total of 643 black or white women enrolled in Women&amp;#39;s Ischemia Syndrome Evaluation (WISE) study. MEASUREMENTS: Genotypes were determined by PCR with single primer extension. Associations between genotype and body mass index (BMI), waist-to-hip ratio (WHR), waist circumference, and obesity were made. RESULTS: Polymorphisms in the three betaAR genes, GNAS1, and GNB3 were not associated with BMI, WHR, waist circumference, or obesity. Linear and logistic regression analyses found no contribution of either genotype or haplotype with anthropometric measurements or obesity. CONCLUSIONS: Our study suggests that among American women with suspected coronary heart disease, polymorphisms in the betaARs and their G-protein-coupled receptors do not contribute to increased BMI, WHR, waist circumference, or obesity. Given that 50% of all women die from coronary heart disease, and a higher percentage have heart disease during their lifetime, our results are likely generalizable to many American women.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090915; GR: M01-RR00425/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68161/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68162/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68163/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-HV68164/HV/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: R03HL65729/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: U01-HL64924-01/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101256108; 0 (Receptors, Adrenergic, beta); 0 (Receptors, G-Protein-Coupled); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0307-0565</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmacy Practice, University of Florida College of Pharmacy, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15917856; 0802978 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/sj.ijo.0802978</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15917856</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>53</id>
<a1>Thomson,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>RT-PCR splicing analysis of the NF1 open reading frame</t1>
<jf>Human genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>110</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>495</sp>
<op>502</op>
<k1>Alternative Splicing/genetics</k1>
<k1>Exons/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromin 1/genetics</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames/genetics</k1>
<k1>Organ Specificity</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single-Stranded Conformational</k1>
<k1>Protein Isoforms/genetics</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Schwann Cells/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Neurofibromatosis 1 (NF1) is an autosomal dominant condition whose molecular diagnosis is challenging because of the large size of the gene and the vast number of unique NF1 gene mutations. Some splicing and nonsense mutations have been shown to cause exon skipping. Recently, temperature-induced abnormal splicing has been found in NF1 in ex-vivo tissues. This prompted us to investigate the entire NF1 transcript for such aberrant splicing. We found several novel exon skips that appeared de novo or were present initially and increased in aged/cooled blood: exon 20, exons 20 and 21 combined, exon 33, exon 34, exon 37, exon 40, exon 45, exons 43 and 45 combined, part of exon 43, and the first codon of exon 12b. Some aberrant splice forms were undetectable when blood was drawn into Qiagen PAXgene tubes, rather than EDTA vacutainers, and we demonstrate how these aberrant splicing events are a potential pitfall for RNA-based NF1 mutation characterization. The same reverse transcription/polymerase chain reaction strategy was used to screen for novel NF1 alternative splicing in Schwann cells and seven other tissues. Even though no Schwann-specific alternative exons were identified, we found minor novel splicing isoforms differentially expressed such as skips of exon 37 and exon 40. Skipping of exon 43, part of exon 43, and the first codon of exon 12b were found in all tissues analyzed. These forms suggest greater tissue-based variability in the NF1 message than was previously thought and may indicate minor amounts of heterogeneity at the protein level.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: NS 31550/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 CA 01926/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7613873; 0 (Neurofibromin 1); 0 (Protein Isoforms); 2001/11/01 [received]; 2002/02/25 [accepted]; 2002/04/04 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0340-6717; 0340-6717</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics (Division of Genetics), University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12073021</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00439-002-0714-6</do>
<wp>20020404</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12073021</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>55</id>
<a1>Urban,Z.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,J.</a1>
<a1>Davis,E. C.</a1>
<a1>Maeda,G. K.</a1>
<a1>Kumar,A.</a1>
<a1>Stalker,H.</a1>
<a1>Belmont,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Boyd,C. D.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Supravalvular aortic stenosis: genetic and molecular dissection of a complex mutation in the elastin gene</t1>
<jf>Human genetics</jf>
<jo>Hum.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>109</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>512</sp>
<op>520</op>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Aortic Stenosis, Supravalvular/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>Elastin/genetics</k1>
<k1>Exons</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Frequency</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation, Missense</k1>
<k1>Pedigree</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<ab>We have identified two elastin gene (ELN) mutations located in cis in two related families with supravalvular aortic stenosis (SVAS). These mutations included an in-frame duplication in exon 18 (1034-1057dup) and a single base substitution in exon 26 (1829G--&amp;gt;A) predicted to result in the amino acid substitution R610Q. Haplotype analysis in one of the families identified an individual with a recombination between exon 18 and 26 of the elastin gene. This individual was unaffected and carried the exon 18 insertion mutation but not 1829G--&amp;gt;A. Skin fibroblasts were established from this recombinant normal individual and from an affected individual carrying both of the mutations. Reverse transcription/polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis indicated that the expression of the mutant allele was reduced to 12%-27% of the normal allele in the affected but not in the unaffected individual. RNA-blot hybridization and immunoprecipitation experiments revealed reduced steady-state elastin mRNA levels and tropoelastin synthesis in the affected individual. RT-PCR analysis of the mRNA rescued by cycloheximide treatment indicated that mutation 1829G--&amp;gt;A created a cryptic donor splice site within exon 26, resulting in the deletion of four nucleotides at the 3&amp;#39;-end of exon 26 and a frameshift in the mRNA. This frameshift mutation generated a premature termination codon in the domain encoded by exon 28, clearly resulting in nonsense-mediated decay (NMD) of this frameshift RNA product. Despite considerable variability in the molecular nature of mutations responsible for SVAS, the unifying mechanism appears to be the generation of null alleles by NMD leading to elastin haploinsufficiency.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AR467379/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: HL60394/HL/NHLBI NIH HHS/United States; GR: RR03061/RR/NCRR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7613873; 0 (DNA Primers); 9007-49-2 (DNA); 9007-58-3 (Elastin); 2001/07/16 [received]; 2001/09/05 [accepted]; 2001/10/13 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0340-6717; 0340-6717</sn>
<ad>Pacific Biomedical Research Center, University of Hawaii, 1960 East-West Road, BIOMED T-309, Honolulu, HI 96822-2321, USA. zsolt@pbrc.hawaii.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11735026</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00439-001-0608-z</do>
<wp>20011013</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11735026</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>57</id>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Marchuk,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Andersen,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Letcher,R.</a1>
<a1>Odeh,H. M.</a1>
<a1>Saulino,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Fountain,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Brereton,A.</a1>
<a1>Nicholson,J.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,A. L.</a1>
<t1>Type 1 neurofibromatosis gene: identification of a large transcript disrupted in three NF1 patients</t1>
<jf>Science (New York, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jul 13</fd>
<vo>249</vo>
<is>4965</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>186</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Neoplasm/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hybrid Cells</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromatosis 1/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Neoplasm/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Translocation, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Von Recklinghausen neurofibromatosis (NF1) is a common autosomal dominant disorder characterized by abnormalities in multiple tissues derived from the neural crest. No reliable cellular phenotypic marker has been identified, which has hampered direct efforts to identify the gene. The chromosome location of the NF1 gene has been previously mapped genetically to 17q11.2, and data from two NF1 patients with balanced translocations in this region have further narrowed the candidate interval. The use of chromosome jumping and yeast artificial chromosome technology has now led to the identification of a large (approximately 13 kilobases) ubiquitously expressed transcript (denoted NF1LT) from this region that is definitely interrupted by one and most likely by both translocations. Previously identified candidate genes, which failed to show abnormalities in NF1 patients, are apparently located within introns of NF1LT, on the antisense strand. A new mutation patient with NF1 has been identified with a de novo 0.5-kilobase insertion in the NF1LT gene. These observations, together with the high spontaneous mutation rate of NF1 (which is consistent with a large locus), suggest that NF1LT represents the elusive NF1 gene.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/M60496; GR: NS23410/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0404511; 0 (DNA, Neoplasm); 0 (RNA, Neoplasm); EIN: Science 1990 Dec 21;250(4988):1749; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0036-8075; 0036-8075</sn>
<ad>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Ann Arbor, MI.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2134734</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2134734</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>46</id>
<a1>Wang,C.</a1>
<a1>Cheng,Y.</a1>
<a1>Liu,T.</a1>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Fillingim,R. B.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Staud,R.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,L.</a1>
<a1>Wu,R.</a1>
<t1>A computational model for sex-specific genetic architecture of complex traits in humans: implications for mapping pain sensitivity</t1>
<jf>Molecular pain</jf>
<jo>Mol.Pain</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Apr 16</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<sp>13</sp>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>Pain Threshold</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</k1>
<k1>Quantitative Trait, Heritable</k1>
<k1>Sex Characteristics</k1>
<ab>Understanding differences in the genetic architecture of complex traits between the two sexes has significant implications for evolutionary studies and clinical diagnosis. However, our knowledge about sex-specific genetic architecture is limited largely because of a lack of analytical models that can detect and quantify the effects of sex on the complexity of quantitative genetic variation. Here, we derived a statistical model for mapping DNA sequence variants that contribute to sex-specific differences in allele frequencies, linkage disequilibria, and additive and dominance genetic effects due to haplotype diversity. This model allows a genome-wide search for functional haplotypes and the estimation and test of haplotype by sex interactions and sex-specific heritability. The model, validated by simulation studies, was used to detect sex-specific functional haplotypes that encode a pain sensitivity trait in humans. The model could have important implications for mapping complex trait genes and studying the detailed genetic architecture of sex-specific differences.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 0540745/PHS HHS/United States; GR: R01 NS041670-05A1/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101242662; OID: NLM: PMC2422840; 2007/11/29 [received]; 2008/04/16 [accepted]; 2008/04/16 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1744-8069</sn>
<ad>Department of Statistics, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611 USA. cgwang@cog.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18416828; 1744-8069-4-13 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1744-8069-4-13</do>
<wp>20080416</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18416828</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2422840</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>48</id>
<a1>Zhang,J.</a1>
<a1>Kumar,A.</a1>
<a1>Kaplan,L.</a1>
<a1>Fricker,F. J.</a1>
<a1>Wallace,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Genetic linkage of a novel autosomal dominant restrictive cardiomyopathy locus</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical genetics</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>663</sp>
<op>665</op>
<k1>Cardiomyopathy, Restrictive/genetics</k1>
<k1>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 10</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Markers</k1>
<k1>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</k1>
<k1>Genetic Testing</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lod Score</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Microsatellite Repeats</k1>
<k1>Pedigree</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: In recent years, non-syndromic idiopathic cardiomyopathies have increasingly been characterised as autosomal dominant conditions caused by single gene mutations. Loci have been identified for hypertrophic and dilated cardiomyopathy, and in some cases the same loci are associated with restrictive cardiomyopathy (RCM). In a kindred with RCM that we previously reported, we ruled out the known cardiomyopathy loci and other candidate genes by linkage analysis and mutation screening. METHODS AND RESULTS: Here we report a genome-wide analysis in this family that has resulted in linkage to a region on chromosome 10. CONCLUSIONS: There are no genes in the interval that are known to cause idiopathic cardiomyopathy, and thus this linkage represents localisation of a new RCM locus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 2985087R; 0 (Genetic Markers); OID: NLM: PMC1736124; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1468-6244; 0022-2593</sn>
<an>PMID: 16061566; 42/8/663 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Letter; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1136/jmg.2004.030189</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16061566</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1736124</pmcid></reference></refworks>
