<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1929</id>
<a1>Abud,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Skinner,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Heath,J. K.</a1>
<t1>Multiple functions of fibroblast growth factors in vertebrate development</t1>
<jf>Biochemical Society symposium</jf>
<jo>Biochem.Soc.Symp.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>62</vo>
<sp>39</sp>
<op>50</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Chimera</k1>
<k1>Extremities/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 4</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins/physiology</k1>
<ab>The biological consequences of ectopic FGF-4 expression were examined in chimaeric mouse embryos prepared with ES cells constitutively expressing FGF-4. The embryos exhibit abnormalities of the limbs and the anterior central nervous system. The limb phenotype consisted of the induction of early phases of limb development along the lateral ridge between the definitive fore and hind limb buds, where normally no limb outgrowth takes place. This phenotype was examined further by the implantation of beads soaked in FGF into the flank of developing chick embryos. This resulted in the induction of complete supernumerary limbs containing skeletal structures. These results indicated that FGFs have the ability to induce the outgrowth of limbs in an ectopic site and implicate FGFs in the initiation of normal limb development.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051117; JID: 7506896; 0 (Fgf4 protein, mouse); 0 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 4); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins); 62031-54-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factors); RF: 57; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0067-8694; 0067-8694</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, U.K.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8971338</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8971338</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1931</id>
<a1>Bradley,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Pennycook,S. J.</a1>
<t1>Z-contrast imaging of supported Pt and Pd clusters</t1>
<jf>Microscopy research and technique</jf>
<jo>Microsc.Res.Tech.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Aug 1</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>427</sp>
<op>429</op>
<k1>Catalysis</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning Transmission/methods</k1>
<k1>Palladium/analysis</k1>
<k1>Platinum/analysis</k1>
<ab>High-angle annular dark-field or Z-contrast microscopy was used to demonstrate that well dispersed metal supported catalysts consist of nanometer sized clusters. Depending upon the impregnated metal, different cluster sizes were observed. Grouping of Pd clusters could also be confirmed by analytical electron microscopy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9203012; 7440-05-3 (Palladium); 7440-06-4 (Platinum); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1059-910X; 1059-910X</sn>
<ad>UOP Research Center, Des Plaines, Illinois 60017.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7919530</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/jemt.1070280509</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7919530</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1901</id>
<a1>Choi,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Harfe,B. D.</a1>
<t1>Identification of nucleus pulposus precursor cells and notochordal remnants in the mouse: implications for disk degeneration and chordoma formation</t1>
<jf>Developmental dynamics : an official publication of the American Association of Anatomists</jf>
<jo>Dev.Dyn.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>237</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>3953</sp>
<op>3958</op>
<k1>Aging/physiology</k1>
<k1>Alleles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Chordoma/genetics/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Intervertebral Disk/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Notochord/cytology/drug effects/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Stem Cells/cytology</k1>
<k1>Tamoxifen/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>A classically identified &amp;quot;notochordal&amp;quot; cell population in the nucleus pulposus is thought to regulate disk homeostasis. However, the embryonic origin of these cells has been under dispute for &amp;gt;60 years. Here we provide the first direct evidence that all cell types in the adult mouse nucleus pulposus are derived from the embryonic notochord. Additionally, rare isolated embryonic notochord cells remained in the vertebral column and resembled &amp;quot;notochordal remnants,&amp;quot; which in humans have been proposed to give rise to a rare type of late-onset cancer called chordoma. Previously, this cell type had not been identified in the mouse model system. The development and characterization of a mouse model that can be used to fate map nucleus pulposus precursor cells in any mutant background will be useful for uncovering the cellular and molecular mechanisms of disk degeneration. In addition, the identification of notochordal remnants in mice is the first step towards generating an in vivo model of chordoma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091230; CI: (c) 2008; GR: AG029353/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; GR: AR055568/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: HD054554/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AG029353-02/AG/NIA NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AR055568-01A1/AR/NIAMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 HD054554-02/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9201927; 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Shh protein, mouse); 10540-29-1 (Tamoxifen); NIHMS89727; OID: NLM: NIHMS89727; OID: NLM: PMC2646501; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley-Liss, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1058-8388; 1058-8388</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19035356</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/dvdy.21805</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19035356</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2646501</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1915</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Developmental genetics of the external genitalia</t1>
<jf>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</jf>
<jo>Adv.Exp.Med.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>545</vo>
<sp>149</sp>
<op>157</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genitalia/embryology/growth &amp; development/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Urethra/embryology</k1>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0121103; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0065-2598; 0065-2598</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, 223 Bartram Hall, Box 11858, Gainesville, FL 32611-8525, USA. cohn@zoo.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15086025</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15086025</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1919</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Evolutionary biology: lamprey Hox genes and the origin of jaws</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Mar 28</fd>
<vo>416</vo>
<is>6879</is>
<sp>386</sp>
<op>387</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox</k1>
<k1>Jaw/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology</k1>
<k1>Lampreys/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology/genetics</k1>
<ab>The development of jaws was a critical event in vertebrate evolution because it ushered in a transition to a predatory lifestyle, but how this innovation came about has been a mystery. In the embryos of jawed vertebrates (gnathostomes), the jaw cartilage develops from the mandibular arch, where none of the Hox genes is expressed; if these are expressed ectopically, however, jaw development is inhibited. Here I show that in the lamprey, a primitively jawless (agnathan) fish that is a sister group to the gnathostomes, a Hox gene is expressed in the mandibular arch of developing embryos. This finding, together with outgroup comparisons, suggests that loss of Hox expression from the mandibular arch of gnathostomes may have facilitated the evolution of jaws.</ab>
<no>LR: 20040528; JID: 0410462; CIN: Nature. 2004 May 20;429(6989):1 p following 262. PMID: 15154395; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, School of Animal and Microbial Sciences, University of Reading, Whiteknights, Reading RG6 6AJ, UK. m.j.cohn@reading.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 11919618; 416386a [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/416386a</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11919618</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1920</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Developmental mechanisms of vertebrate limb evolution</t1>
<jf>Novartis Foundation symposium</jf>
<jo>Novartis Found.Symp.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>232</vo>
<sp>47</sp>
<op>57; discussion 57-62</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Development/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Extremities</k1>
<k1>Fossils</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox</k1>
<k1>Mammals</k1>
<k1>Vertebrates/genetics</k1>
<ab>Over the past few years, our understanding of the evolution of limbs has been improved by important new discoveries in the fossil record. Additionally, rapid progress has been made in identifying the molecular basis of vertebrate limb development. It is now possible to integrate these two areas of research in order to identify the molecular developmental mechanisms underlying the evolution of paired appendages in vertebrates. After the origin of paired appendages, several vertebrate lineages reduced or eliminated fins and limbs and returned to the limbless condition. Examples include eels, caecilians, snakes, slow worms and several marine mammals. Analyses of fossil and extant vertebrates show that evolution of limblessness frequently occurred together with elongation of the trunk and loss of clear morphological boundaries in the vertebral column. This may be suggestive of a common developmental mechanism linking these two processes. We have addressed this question by analysing python embryonic development at tissue, cellular and molecular levels, and we have identified a developmental mechanism which may account for evolution of limb loss in these animals.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9807767; RF: 29; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1528-2511; 1528-2511</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, School of Animal and Microbial Sciences, University of Reading, Whiteknights, Reading RG6 6AJ, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11277086</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11277086</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1921</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Developmental biology. Giving limbs a hand</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Aug 31</fd>
<vo>406</vo>
<is>6799</is>
<sp>953</sp>
<op>954</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Basic Helix-Loop-Helix Transcription Factors</k1>
<k1>Cell Polarity</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Feedback</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Zebrafish Proteins</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0410462; 0 (Basic Helix-Loop-Helix Transcription Factors); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Hand2 protein, mouse); 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Transcription Factors); 0 (Zebrafish Proteins); 0 (hand2 protein, zebrafish); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<an>PMID: 10984039</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>News; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/35023216</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10984039</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1926</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Bright,P. E.</a1>
<t1>Molecular control of vertebrate limb development, evolution and congenital malformations</t1>
<jf>Cell and tissue research</jf>
<jo>Cell Tissue Res.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>296</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>3</sp>
<op>17</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Bone Development</k1>
<k1>Congenital Abnormalities</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Osteogenesis</k1>
<k1>Vertebrates/embryology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>The vertebrate limb is a powerful model system for studying the cellular and molecular interactions that determine morphological pattern during embryonic development. Recent advances in our understanding of these interactions have shed new light on the molecular mechanisms of vertebrate limb development, evolution and congenital malformations. The transfer of information has, until recently, been largely one way, with developmental studies informing our understanding of the fossil record and clinical limb anomalies; however, evolutionary and clinical studies are now beginning to shed light onto one another and onto basic developmental processes. In this review, we discuss recent advances in these fields and how they are interacting to improve our understanding of vertebrate limb biology.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0417625; RF: 170; ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0302-766X; 0302-766X</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, School of Animal and Microbial Sciences, University of Reading, Whiteknights, Reading RG6 6AJ, UK. m.j.cohn@reading.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 10199960</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10199960</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1932</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Cohen,A. J.</a1>
<t1>RADCOM: a computerized translation device for use during fluoroscopic examination of non-English-speaking patients</t1>
<jf>AJR.American journal of roentgenology</jf>
<jo>AJR Am.J.Roentgenol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>162</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>455</sp>
<op>457</op>
<k1>Communication Barriers</k1>
<k1>Fluoroscopy/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Language</k1>
<k1>Medical Informatics Applications</k1>
<k1>Microcomputers</k1>
<k1>Software</k1>
<k1>Translating</k1>
<k1>Voice</k1>
<ab>We developed and have implemented RADCOM (RADiology COMmunicator), a computerized speech-based language translator for use during fluoroscopic examination of non-English-speaking patients. It is controlled completely by voice commands issued into a headset microphone. The system output is digital audio via a small speaker, in the native language of the patient. RADCOM currently supports more than 40 commands in more than a dozen languages. The language data base is easily expandable. We have performed more than 20 fluoroscopic examinations with the RADCOM system. The non-English-speaking patients respond well, following the selected instructions appropriately.</ab>
<no>LR: 20080215; JID: 7708173; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0361-803X; 0361-803X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiological Sciences, University of California, Irvine Medical Center, Orange 92668-3298.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8310947</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8310947</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1930</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Izpisua-Belmonte,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Abud,H.</a1>
<a1>Heath,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>Fibroblast growth factors induce additional limb development from the flank of chick embryos</t1>
<jf>Cell</jf>
<jo>Cell</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Mar 10</fd>
<vo>80</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>739</sp>
<op>746</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Embryonic Induction/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins</k1>
<k1>Mesoderm/cytology/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Microspheres</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors</k1>
<ab>Fibroblast growth factors (FGFs) act as signals in the developing limb and can maintain proliferation of limb bud mesenchyme cells. Remarkably, beads soaked in FGF-1, FGF-2, or FGF-4 and placed in the presumptive flank of chick embryos induce formation of ectopic limb buds, which can develop into complete limbs. The entire flank can produce additional limbs, but generally wings are formed anteriorly and legs posteriorly. FGF application activates Sonic hedgehog in cells with polarizing potential to make a discrete polarizing region. Hoxd-13 is also expressed in the ectopic bud, and an apical ectodermal ridge forms. A limb bud is thus established that can generate the appropriate signals to develop into a complete limb. The additional limbs have reversed polarity. This can be explained by the distribution of cells in the flank with potential polarizing activity. The results suggest that local production of an FGF may initiate limb development.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090929; GR: Wellcome Trust/United Kingdom; JID: 0413066; 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Trans-Activators); 0 (Transcription Factors); 62031-54-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0092-8674; 0092-8674</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, University College and Middlesex School of Medicine, London, England.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7889567; 0092-8674(95)90352-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7889567</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1933</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Kurtz,D.</a1>
<t1>Frequency of certain urgent eye problems in an emergency room in Massachusetts</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Optometric Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Optom.Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>63</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>628</sp>
<op>633</op>
<k1>Cost-Benefit Analysis</k1>
<k1>Emergencies/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Emergency Service, Hospital/economics/statistics &amp; numerical data/utilization</k1>
<k1>Eye Diseases/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Insurance, Health, Reimbursement</k1>
<k1>Massachusetts</k1>
<k1>Optometry/economics</k1>
<ab>The frequency and cost of emergency room care for certain ocular problems was surveyed. Superficial eye problems accounted for 2.67 percent of patients reporting to the emergency room, while 0.23 percent reported for penetrating injuries. Of the conditions surveyed, conjunctivitis was the most commonly presenting diagnosis. Abrasions and superficial foreign bodies were the next most common presentations. Together these three diagnoses accounted for nearly 75 percent of all superficial eye problems seen in the emergency room. The cost of each emergency room visit averaged $132. This study has implications for health care managers and for legislatures contemplating expanding the scope of optometric practice.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7505575; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-0244; 0003-0244</sn>
<ad>New England College of Optometry, Boston, MA 02115.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1430752</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1430752</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1918</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Lovejoy,C. O.</a1>
<a1>Wolpert,L.</a1>
<a1>Coates,M. I.</a1>
<t1>Branching, segmentation and the metapterygial axis: pattern versus process in the vertebrate limb</t1>
<jf>BioEssays : news and reviews in molecular, cellular and developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Bioessays</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>460</sp>
<op>465</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Cartilage/physiology</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Fishes</k1>
<k1>Wing/embryology</k1>
<ab>Explanations of the patterns of vertebrate fin and limb evolution are improving as specific hypotheses based on molecular and developmental data are proposed and tested. Comparative analyses of gene expression patterns and functions in developing limbs, and morphological patterns in embryonic, adult and fossil limbs point to digit specification as a key developmental innovation associated with the origin of tetrapods. Digit development during the fin-to-limb transition involved sustained proximodistal outgrowth and a new phase of Hox gene expression in the distal fin bud. These patterning changes in the distal limb have been explained by the linked concepts of the metapterygial axis and the digital arch. These have been proposed to account for the generation of limb pattern by sequential branching and segmentation of precartilagenous elements along the proximodistal axis of the limb. While these ideas have been very fruitful, they have become increasingly difficult to reconcile with experimental and comparative studies of fin and limb development. Here we argue that limb development does not involve a branching mechanism, and reassess the concept of a metapterygial axis in limb development and evolution.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 2002; JID: 8510851; CIN: Bioessays. 2002 Nov;24(11):1077-8. PMID: 12386940; RF: 42; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc</pb>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0265-9247; 0265-9247</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, University of Reading, UK. m.j.cohn@reading.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 12001269</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/bies.10088</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12001269</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1927</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Patel,K.</a1>
<a1>Krumlauf,R.</a1>
<a1>Wilkinson,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Clarke,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>Hox9 genes and vertebrate limb specification</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>May 1</fd>
<vo>387</vo>
<is>6628</is>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>101</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Lineage</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Embryonic Induction/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 2/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox</k1>
<k1>Leg/embryology</k1>
<k1>Mesoderm/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Wing/embryology</k1>
<ab>Development of paired appendages at appropriate levels along the primary body axis is a hallmark of the body plan of jawed vertebrates. Hox genes are good candidates for encoding position in lateral plate mesoderm along the body axis and thus for determining where limbs are formed. Local application of fibroblast growth factors (FGFs) to the anterior prospective flank of a chick embryo induces development of an ectopic wing, and FGF applied to posterior flank induces an ectopic leg. If particular combinations of Hox gene expression determine where wings and legs develop, then formation of additional limbs from flank should involve changes in Hox gene expression that reflect the type of limb induced. Here we show that the same population of flank cells can be induced to form either a wing or a leg, and that induction of these ectopic limbs is accompanied by specific changes in expression of three Hox genes in lateral plate mesoderm. This then reproduces, in the flank, expression patterns found at normal limb levels. Hox gene expression is reprogrammed in lateral plate mesoderm, but is unaffected in paraxial mesoderm. Independent regulation of Hox gene expression in lateral plate mesoderm may have been a key step in the evolution of paired appendages.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090929; GR: Wellcome Trust/United Kingdom; JID: 0410462; 103107-01-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 2); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, University College London Medical School, UK. m.cohn@ucl.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 9139829</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/387097a0</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9139829</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1925</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>Developmental basis of limblessness and axial patterning in snakes</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jun 3</fd>
<vo>399</vo>
<is>6735</is>
<sp>474</sp>
<op>479</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning/physiology</k1>
<k1>Boidae/embryology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Ectoderm</k1>
<k1>Embryonic Development</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/embryology</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<ab>The evolution of snakes involved major changes in vertebrate body plan organization, but the developmental basis of those changes is unknown. The python axial skeleton consists of hundreds of similar vertebrae, forelimbs are absent and hindlimbs are severely reduced. Combined limb loss and trunk elongation is found in many vertebrate taxa, suggesting that these changes may be linked by a common developmental mechanism. Here we show that Hox gene expression domains are expanded along the body axis in python embryos, and that this can account for both the absence of forelimbs and the expansion of thoracic identity in the axial skeleton. Hindlimb buds are initiated, but apical-ridge and polarizing-region signalling pathways that are normally required for limb development are not activated. Leg bud outgrowth and signalling by Sonic hedgehog in pythons can be rescued by application of fibroblast growth factor or by recombination with chick apical ridge. The failure to activate these signalling pathways during normal python development may also stem from changes in Hox gene expression that occurred early in snake evolution.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0410462; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0028-0836; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, School of Animal and Microbial Sciences, University of Reading, UK. M.J.Cohn@reading.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 10365960</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/20944</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10365960</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1928</id>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>Limbs: a model for pattern formation within the vertebrate body plan</t1>
<jf>Trends in genetics : TIG</jf>
<jo>Trends Genet.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>257</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Drosophila</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development/genetics</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/embryology</k1>
<k1>Mesoderm/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Wing/embryology</k1>
<ab>Giant strides have been made in identifying the molecular basis of limb development. The four main phases are initiation of the limb bud, specification of limb pattern, differentiation of tissues and shaping of the limb, and growth of the miniature limb to the adult size. We will focus on the exciting advances that have been made in initiation and specification of limb pattern. The limb is a model system and the same sets of molecules are used at different times and places in vertebrate embryos. There is also remarkable conservation of the molecular mechanisms of limb development in insects and vertebrates.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8507085; RF: 56; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0168-9525; 0168-9525</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, University College and Middlesex School of Medicine, London, UK. ucgamcc@uclac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 8763496; 0168-9525(96)10030-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8763496</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1912</id>
<a1>Freitas,R.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Genomic regulation of Hox collinearity</t1>
<jf>Developmental cell</jf>
<jo>Dev.Cell.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>8</sp>
<op>9</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning/physiology</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genomics</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<ab>During vertebrate limb development, Hoxd genes are transcribed in two temporal phases; an early wave controls growth and polarity up to the forearm and a late wave patterns the digits. In this issue of Developmental Cell, Tarchini and Duboule (2006) report that two opposite regulatory modules direct early collinear expression of Hoxd genes.</ab>
<no>JID: 101120028; 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); CON: Dev Cell. 2006 Jan;10(1):93-103. PMID: 16399081; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1534-5807; 1534-5807</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, P.O. Box 118525, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16399073; S1534-5807(05)00484-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comment; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.devcel.2005.12.008</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16399073</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1914</id>
<a1>Freitas,R.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of EphA4 in the lesser spotted catshark identifies a primitive gnathostome expression pattern and reveals co-option during evolution of shark-specific morphology</t1>
<jf>Development genes and evolution</jf>
<jo>Dev.Genes Evol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>214</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>466</sp>
<op>472</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Embryo, Nonmammalian</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Gnathostoma/genetics</k1>
<k1>Likelihood Functions</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Receptor, EphA4/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, Protein</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Sharks/embryology/genetics</k1>
<ab>The Eph family is the largest known group of structurally related receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs). Each Eph receptor has a specific Ephrin ligand, and these function to define spatial boundaries during development. Analyses of EphA4 in mouse, chick, frog and zebrafish embryos have implicated this gene in a number of developmental processes, including maintenance of segmental boundaries, axon guidance, limb development, neural crest migration and patterning of the ear. In order to determine which components of EphA4 function may be primitive for gnathostomes, we cloned EphA4 from the lesser spotted catshark ( Scyliorhinus canicula) and examined its expression pattern during shark embryonic development. Consistent with the patterns reported for bony fish and tetrapods, we observed segmental expression of EphA4 in the developing hindbrain and later in the pharyngeal arches of shark embryos. EphA4 was also detected during sensory organogenesis, in the developing ear, eye, nasal pits and lateral line. A dynamic pattern of EphA4expression occurs during shark fin development, suggesting an early role in outgrowth and patterning of the fin buds and a later role in tissue differentiation. We also observed several novel domains of EphA4expression that have not been reported in other vertebrates, including external gill buds, dermal denticles, median fins and claspers. While some of these domains may reflect co-option of EphA4expression to novel sites for development of shark-specific characters, others are more likely to be ancestral patterns of expression that were lost in other vertebrate lineages.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 9613264; EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor, EphA4); 2004/05/14 [received]; 2004/06/30 [accepted]; 2004/08/06 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0949-944X; 0949-944X</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, P.O. Box 118525, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15300436</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00427-004-0426-0</do>
<wp>20040806</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15300436</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1911</id>
<a1>Freitas,R.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Albert,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Evans,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Developmental origin of shark electrosensory organs</t1>
<jf>Evolution &amp; development</jf>
<jo>Evol.Dev.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>74</sp>
<op>80</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Ephrin-B2/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Mechanoreceptors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Neural Crest/cytology</k1>
<k1>Receptor, EphA4/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sense Organs/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Sharks/embryology/genetics</k1>
<ab>Vertebrates have evolved electrosensory receptors that detect electrical stimuli on the surface of the skin and transmit them somatotopically to the brain. In chondrichthyans, the electrosensory system is composed of a cephalic network of ampullary organs, known as the ampullae of Lorenzini, that can detect extremely weak electric fields during hunting and navigation. Each ampullary organ consists of a gel-filled epidermal pit containing sensory hair cells, and synaptic connections with primary afferent neurons at the base of the pit that facilitate detection of voltage gradients over large regions of the body. The developmental origin of electroreceptors and the mechanisms that determine their spatial arrangement in the vertebrate head are not well understood. We have analyzed electroreceptor development in the lesser spotted catshark (Scyliorhinus canicula) and show that Sox8 and HNK1, two markers of the neural crest lineage, selectively mark sensory cells in ampullary organs. This represents the first evidence that the neural crest gives rise to electrosensory cells. We also show that pathfinding by cephalic mechanosensory and electrosensory axons follows the expression pattern of EphA4, a well-known guidance cue for axons and neural crest cells in osteichthyans. Expression of EphrinB2, which encodes a ligand for EphA4, marks the positions at which ampullary placodes are initiated in the epidermis, and EphA4 is expressed in surrounding mesenchyme. These results suggest that Eph-Ephrin signaling may establish an early molecular map for neural crest migration, axon guidance and placodal morphogenesis during development of the shark electrosensory system.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 100883432; 0 (Ephrin-B2); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor, EphA4); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1520-541X; 1520-541X</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, PO Box 118525, Gainesville, FL 32611-8525, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16409384; EDE05076 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1525-142X.2006.05076.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16409384</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1905</id>
<a1>Freitas,R.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Biphasic Hoxd gene expression in shark paired fins reveals an ancient origin of the distal limb domain</t1>
<jf>PloS one</jf>
<jo>PLoS One</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Aug 15</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>e754</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Extremities</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/anatomy &amp; histology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Multigene Family</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Sharks/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology/genetics</k1>
<ab>The evolutionary transition of fins to limbs involved development of a new suite of distal skeletal structures, the digits. During tetrapod limb development, genes at the 5&amp;#39; end of the HoxD cluster are expressed in two spatiotemporally distinct phases. In the first phase, Hoxd9-13 are activated sequentially and form nested domains along the anteroposterior axis of the limb. This initial phase patterns the limb from its proximal limit to the middle of the forearm. Later in development, a second wave of transcription results in 5&amp;#39; HoxD gene expression along the distal end of the limb bud, which regulates formation of digits. Studies of zebrafish fins showed that the second phase of Hox expression does not occur, leading to the idea that the origin of digits was driven by addition of the distal Hox expression domain in the earliest tetrapods. Here we test this hypothesis by investigating Hoxd gene expression during paired fin development in the shark Scyliorhinus canicula, a member of the most basal lineage of jawed vertebrates. We report that at early stages, 5&amp;#39;Hoxd genes are expressed in anteroposteriorly nested patterns, consistent with the initial wave of Hoxd transcription in teleost and tetrapod paired appendages. Unexpectedly, a second phase of expression occurs at later stages of shark fin development, in which Hoxd12 and Hoxd13 are re-expressed along the distal margin of the fin buds. This second phase is similar to that observed in tetrapod limbs. The results indicate that a second, distal phase of Hoxd gene expression is not uniquely associated with tetrapod digit development, but is more likely a plesiomorphic condition present the common ancestor of chondrichthyans and osteichthyans. We propose that a temporal extension, rather than de novo activation, of Hoxd expression in the distal part of the fin may have led to the evolution of digits.</ab>
<no>GR: HD054554/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101285081; 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC1937022; GN: NLM: Original DateCompleted: 20070822; 2007/05/26 [received]; 2007/07/24 [accepted]; epublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1932-6203; 1932-6203</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, Cancer/Genetics Research Complex, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United Sates of America.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17710153</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1371/journal.pone.0000754</do>
<wp>20070815</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17710153</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1937022</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1908</id>
<a1>Freitas,R.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Evidence that mechanisms of fin development evolved in the midline of early vertebrates</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Aug 31</fd>
<vo>442</vo>
<is>7106</is>
<sp>1033</sp>
<op>1037</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genes, Homeobox/genetics</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Lampreys/embryology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Sharks/embryology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Somites/cytology/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The origin of paired appendages was a major evolutionary innovation for vertebrates, marking the first step towards fin- (and later limb-) driven locomotion. The earliest vertebrate fossils lack paired fins but have well-developed median fins, suggesting that the mechanisms of fin development were assembled first in the midline. Here we show that shark median fin development involves the same genetic programs that operate in paired appendages. Using molecular markers for different cell types, we show that median fins arise predominantly from somitic (paraxial) mesoderm, whereas paired appendages develop from lateral plate mesoderm. Expression of Hoxd and Tbx18 genes, which specify paired limb positions, also delineates the positions of median fins. Proximodistal development of median fins occurs beneath an apical ectodermal ridge, the structure that controls outgrowth of paired appendages. Each median fin bud then acquires an anteroposteriorly-nested pattern of Hoxd expression similar to that which establishes skeletal polarity in limbs. Thus, despite their different embryonic origins, paired and median fins utilize a common suite of developmental mechanisms. We extended our analysis to lampreys, which diverged from the lineage leading to gnathostomes before the origin of paired appendages, and show that their median fins also develop from somites and express orthologous Hox and Tbx genes. Together these results suggest that the molecular mechanisms for fin development originated in somitic mesoderm of early vertebrates, and that the origin of paired appendages was associated with re-deployment of these mechanisms to lateral plate mesoderm.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; GENBANK/DQ659101; GENBANK/DQ659102; GENBANK/DQ659103; GENBANK/DQ659104; GENBANK/DQ659105; GENBANK/DQ659106; GENBANK/DQ659107; GENBANK/DQ659108; GENBANK/DQ659109; GENBANK/DQ659110; GENBANK/DQ659111; JID: 0410462; 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); 2005/07/26 [received]; 2006/06/19 [accepted]; 2006/07/26 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1476-4687; 0028-0836</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, PO Box 118525, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16878142; nature04984 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/nature04984</do>
<wp>20060726</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16878142</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1923</id>
<a1>Isaac,A.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Ashby,P.</a1>
<a1>Ataliotis,P.</a1>
<a1>Spicer,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cooke,J.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>FGF and genes encoding transcription factors in early limb specification</t1>
<jf>Mechanisms of development</jf>
<jo>Mech.Dev.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>41</sp>
<op>48</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Avian Proteins</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>DNA, Complementary</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 10</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 2/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 8</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factors/genetics/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>T-Box Domain Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Twist Transcription Factor</k1>
<ab>SnR, twist and Fgf10 are expressed in presumptive limb territories of early chick embryos. When FGF-2/FGF-8 beads are implanted in chick flank, an ectopic limb develops and SnR is irreversibly activated as early as 1 h. Ectopic Fgf10 and twist expression are activated much later at 17 and 20 h, respectively. FGF-10 can also induce SnR, but much later, and in this case activation occurs simultaneously with that of twist and Fgf10 via the Fgf8- expressing ridge. Tbx-4 and Tbx-5 are expressed in leg and wing forming regions, respectively, in a similar pattern to SnR and twist. FGF-2 leads to ectopic expression of Tbx-4 and Tbx-5 as rapidly as ectopic expression of SnR, but the patterns of ectopic transcripts suggest that induction of SnR and Tbx gene expression occur via different pathways.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; GENBANK/AF094816; JID: 9101218; 0 (Avian Proteins); 0 (DNA, Complementary); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 10); 0 (T-Box Domain Proteins); 0 (T-box transcription factor 5); 0 (TBX4 protein, Gallus gallus); 0 (Transcription Factors); 0 (Twist Transcription Factor); 0 (Twist protein, Gallus gallus); 0 (snail-related protein, Gallus gallus); 103107-01-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 2); 148997-75-5 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 8); 62031-54-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>IRELAND</pp>
<sn>0925-4773; 0925-4773</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, University College London, UK. a.j.isaac@dundee.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 10781938; S0925477300002616 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10781938</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1924</id>
<a1>Lovejoy,C. O.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>White,T. D.</a1>
<t1>Morphological analysis of the mammalian postcranium: a developmental perspective</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Nov 9</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>13247</sp>
<op>13252</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Development</k1>
<k1>Cartilage/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Knee/anatomy &amp; histology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Mammals</k1>
<k1>Pelvis/anatomy &amp; histology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<ab>The past two decades have greatly improved our knowledge of vertebrate skeletal morphogenesis. It is now clear that bony morphology lacks individual descriptive specification and instead results from an interplay between positional information assigned during early limb bud deployment and its &amp;quot;execution&amp;quot; by highly conserved cellular response programs of derived connective tissue cells (e.g., chondroblasts and osteoblasts). Selection must therefore act on positional information and its apportionment, rather than on more individuated aspects of presumptive adult morphology. We suggest a trait classification system that can help integrate these findings in both functional and phylogenetic examinations of fossil mammals and provide examples from the human fossil record.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC23933; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Anthropology, Biological Anthropology Program, Division of Biomedical Sciences, Kent State University, Kent, Ohio 44242, USA. olivejoy@aol.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 10557306</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10557306</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC23933</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1917</id>
<a1>Perriton,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Powles,N.</a1>
<a1>Chiang,C.</a1>
<a1>Maconochie,M. K.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Sonic hedgehog signaling from the urethral epithelium controls external genital development</t1>
<jf>Developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jul 1</fd>
<vo>247</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>26</sp>
<op>46</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Polarity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Embryonic Induction</k1>
<k1>Epithelial Cells/cytology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genitalia/cytology/embryology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/physiology</k1>
<k1>Urethra/embryology/physiology</k1>
<ab>External genital development begins with formation of paired genital swellings, which develop into the genital tubercle. Proximodistal outgrowth and axial patterning of the genital tubercle are coordinated to give rise to the penis or clitoris. The genital tubercle consists of lateral plate mesoderm, surface ectoderm, and endodermal urethral epithelium derived from the urogenital sinus. We have investigated the molecular control of external genital development in the mouse embryo. Previous work has shown that the genital tubercle has polarizing activity, but the precise location of this activity within the tubercle is unknown. We reasoned that if the tubercle itself is patterned by a specialized signaling region, then polarizing activity may be restricted to a subset of cells. Transplantation of urethral epithelium, but not genital mesenchyme, to chick limbs results in mirror-image duplication of the digits. Moreover, when grafted to chick limbs, the urethral plate orchestrates morphogenetic movements normally associated with external genital development. Signaling activity is therefore restricted to urethral plate cells. Before and during normal genital tubercle outgrowth, urethral plate epithelium expresses Sonic hedgehog (Shh). In mice with a targeted deletion of Shh, external genitalia are absent. Genital swellings are initiated, but outgrowth is not maintained. In the absence of Shh signaling, Fgf8, Bmp2, Bmp4, Fgf10, and Wnt5a are downregulated, and apoptosis is enhanced in the genitalia. These results identify the urethral epithelium as a signaling center of the genital tubercle, and demonstrate that Shh from the urethral epithelium is required for outgrowth, patterning, and cell survival in the developing external genitalia.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: (c) 2002; JID: 0372762; 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); ppublish</no>
<pb>Elsevier Science (USA)</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0012-1606; 0012-1606</sn>
<ad>Division of Zoology, University of Reading, Whiteknights, United Kingdom.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12074550; S0012160602906688 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/dbio.2002.0668</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12074550</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1913</id>
<a1>Petiot,A.</a1>
<a1>Perriton,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,C.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Development of the mammalian urethra is controlled by Fgfr2-IIIb</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>2441</sp>
<op>2450</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins</k1>
<k1>Histological Techniques</k1>
<k1>Hypospadias/genetics</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>Protein Isoforms/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Fibroblast Growth Factor, Type 2</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Androgen/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Fibroblast Growth Factor/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Urethra/embryology</k1>
<ab>Development of external genitalia in mammalian embryos requires tight coordination of a complex series of morphogenetic events involving outgrowth, proximodistal and dorsoventral patterning, and epithelial tubulogenesis. Hypospadias is a congenital defect of the external genitalia that results from failure of urethral tube closure. Although this is the second most common birth defect in humans, affecting one in every 250 children, the molecular mechanisms that regulate morphogenesis of the mammalian urethra are poorly understood. We report that mice lacking the IIIb isoform of fibroblast growth factor receptor 2 (Fgfr2) exhibit severe hypospadias. Urethral signaling regions, as indicated by Shh and Fgf8 expression, are established in Fgfr2-IIIb null mice; however, cell proliferation arrests prematurely and maturation of the urethral epithelium is disrupted. Fgfr2-IIIb-/- mutants fail to maintain the progenitor cell population required for uroepithelial renewal during tubular morphogenesis. In addition, we show that antagonism of the androgen receptor (AR) leads to loss of Fgfr2-IIIb and Fgf10 expression in the urethra, and an associated hypospadias phenotype, suggesting that these genes are downstream targets of AR during external genital development. Genitourinary defects resulting from disruption of AR activity, by either genetic or environmental factors, may therefore involve negative regulation of the Fgfr2 pathway. This represents the first example of how the developing genitourinary system integrates cues from systemically circulating steroid hormones with a locally expressed growth factor pathway.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: HD047885/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8701744; 0 (Protein Isoforms); 0 (Receptors, Androgen); 0 (Receptors, Fibroblast Growth Factor); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); EC 2.7.1.112 (Fgfr2 protein, mouse); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases); EC 2.7.10.1 (Receptor, Fibroblast Growth Factor, Type 2); 2005/04/20 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-1991; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>Cancer Research UK, Lincoln&#39;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PX, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15843416; dev.01778 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1242/dev.01778</do>
<wp>20050420</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15843416</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1904</id>
<a1>Reno,P. L.</a1>
<a1>McCollum,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Meindl,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Hamrick,M.</a1>
<a1>Lovejoy,C. O.</a1>
<t1>Patterns of correlation and covariation of anthropoid distal forelimb segments correspond to Hoxd expression territories</t1>
<jf>Journal of experimental zoology.Part B, Molecular and developmental evolution</jf>
<jo>J.Exp.Zool.B.Mol.Dev.Evol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May 15</fd>
<vo>310</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>240</sp>
<op>258</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecidae/classification/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Forelimb/anatomy &amp; histology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Hand/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>Haplorhini/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Platyrrhini/classification/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>Anthropoids in general and hominoids in particular exhibit differential adaptations in forearm and digital skeletal proportions to a diverse array of locomotor modes. Hox genes act as selector genes with spatially regulated expression patterns during development. Their expression in the forelimb appears to define modules that specify differential skeletal growth. Here we explore forelimb skeletal proportions in a large sample of anthropoids from a background provided by Hoxd expression patterns in late-stage murine embryonic forelimbs. Interspecific correlation and principal components analyses of primate forelimb data indicate that morphological variation in anthropoids reflects well-defined developmental modules downstream of Hoxd expression. The phalanges of digit one appear to represent a single growth module, whereas the metacarpals and manual phalanges of the posterior digits correspond to a second, independent, expression territory that extends proximally into the distal zeugopod. In particular, hominoids show very high correlations among the posterior digits and the independence of digit one. In addition, the distal radius is generally highly correlated with the posterior digits and not digit one. Relying on established functional differences among Hox paralogs, we present a model that parsimoniously explains hominoid forearm and digital proportions as a consequence of downstream effects of Hox. We, therefore, suggest that Hox-defined developmental modules have served as evolutionary modules during manual evolution in anthropoids.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091005; CI: (c) 2007; JID: 101168228; 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley-Liss, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1552-5015; 1552-5007</sn>
<ad>Department of Anthropology, School of Biomedical Science, Kent State University, Kent, Ohio 44242, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18080316</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/jez.b.21207</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18080316</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1898</id>
<a1>Seifert,A. W.</a1>
<a1>Bouldin,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Choi,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Harfe,B. D.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Multiphasic and tissue-specific roles of sonic hedgehog in cloacal septation and external genitalia development</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>3949</sp>
<op>3957</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation</k1>
<k1>Cloaca/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ectoderm/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Embryo, Mammalian</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Genitalia/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Organogenesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Pregnancy</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Urethra/embryology/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<ab>Malformations of the external genitalia are among the most common congenital anomalies in humans. The urogenital and anorectal sinuses develop from the embryonic cloaca, and the penis and clitoris develop from the genital tubercle. Within the genital tubercle, the endodermally derived urethral epithelium functions as an organizer and expresses sonic hedgehog (Shh). Shh knockout mice lack external genitalia and have a persistent cloaca. This identified an early requirement for Shh, but precluded analysis of its later role in the genital tubercle. We conducted temporally controlled deletions of Shh and report that Shh is required continuously through the onset of sexual differentiation. Shh function is divisible into two temporal phases; an anogenital phase, during which Shh regulates outgrowth and patterning of the genital tubercle and septation of the cloaca, and a later external genital phase, during which Shh regulates urethral tube closure. Disruption of Shh function during the anogenital phase causes coordinated anorectal and genitourinary malformations, whereas inactivation during the external genital phase causes hypospadias. Shh directs cloacal septation by promoting cell proliferation in adjacent urorectal septum mesenchyme. Additionally, conditional inactivation of smoothened in the genital ectoderm and cloacal/urethral endoderm shows that the ectoderm is a direct target of Shh and is required for urethral tube closure, highlighting a novel role for genital ectoderm in urethragenesis. Identification of the stages during which disruption of Shh results in either isolated or coordinated malformations of anorectal and external genital organs provides a new tool for investigating the etiology of anogenital malformations in humans.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100602; GR: 5R01HD054554/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; GR: Howard Hughes Medical Institute/United States; JID: 8701744; 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Shh protein, mouse); OID: NLM: PMC2778742; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1477-9129; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>Department of Biology, University of Florida, Cancer/Genetics Research Complex, PO Box 103610, Gainesville, FL 32610-3610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19906862; 136/23/3949 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1242/dev.042291</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19906862</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2778742</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1903</id>
<a1>Seifert,A. W.</a1>
<a1>Harfe,B. D.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Cell lineage analysis demonstrates an endodermal origin of the distal urethra and perineum</t1>
<jf>Developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>318</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>143</sp>
<op>152</op>
<k1>Androgen Antagonists/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation</k1>
<k1>Cell Lineage</k1>
<k1>Cloaca/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology</k1>
<k1>Endoderm/cytology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Flutamide/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Transgenic</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>Perineum/abnormalities/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology</k1>
<k1>Pregnancy</k1>
<k1>Sex Differentiation/physiology</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Urethra/abnormalities/anatomy &amp; histology/embryology</k1>
<ab>Congenital malformations of anorectal and genitourinary (collectively, anogenital) organs occur at a high frequency in humans, however the lineage of cells that gives rise to anogenital organs remains poorly understood. The penile urethra has been reported to develop from two cell populations, with the proximal urethra developing from endoderm and the distal urethra forming from an apical ectodermal invagination, however this has never been tested by direct analysis of cell lineage. During gut development, endodermal cells express Sonic hedgehog (Shh), which is required for normal patterning of digestive and genitourinary organs. We have taken advantage of the properties of Shh expression to genetically label and follow the fate of posterior gut endoderm during anogenital development. We report that the entire urethra, including the distal (glandar) region, is derived from endoderm. Cloacal endoderm also gives rise to the epithelial linings of the bladder, rectum and anterior region of the anus. Surprisingly, the lineage map also revealed an endodermal origin of the perineum, which is the first demonstration that endoderm differentiates into skin. In addition, we fate mapped genital tubercle ectoderm and show that it makes no detectable contribution to the urethra. In males, formation of the urethral tube involves septation of the urethral plate by continued growth of the urorectal septum. Analysis of cell lineage following disruption of androgen signaling revealed that the urethral plate of flutamide-treated males does not undergo this septation event. Instead, urethral plate cells persist to the ventral margin of the tubercle, mimicking the pattern seen in females. Based on these spatial and temporal fate maps, we present a new model for anogenital development and suggest that disruptions at specific developmental time points can account for the association between anorectal and genitourinary defects.</ab>
<no>GR: 1R01 HD054554-01/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0372762; 0 (Androgen Antagonists); 13311-84-7 (Flutamide); 2007/05/30 [received]; 2008/03/06 [revised]; 2008/03/10 [accepted]; 2008/03/21 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1095-564X; 0012-1606</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, Cancer/Genetics Research Complex, PO Box 103610, Gainesville, FL 32610-3610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18439576; S0012-1606(08)00221-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ydbio.2008.03.017</do>
<wp>20080321</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18439576</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1899</id>
<a1>Seifert,A. W.</a1>
<a1>Yamaguchi,T.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Functional and phylogenetic analysis shows that Fgf8 is a marker of genital induction in mammals but is not required for external genital development</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>15</is>
<sp>2643</sp>
<op>2651</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biological Markers/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Bone Morphogenetic Protein 4/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival</k1>
<k1>Cloaca/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Ectoderm/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Endoderm/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 8/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Genitalia/cytology/embryology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mammals/embryology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Penis/embryology</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Reptiles/embryology</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Wnt Proteins/deficiency/metabolism</k1>
<ab>In mammalian embryos, male and female external genitalia develop from the genital tubercle. Outgrowth of the genital tubercle is maintained by the urethral epithelium, and it has been reported that Fgf8 mediates this activity. To test directly whether Fgf8 is required for external genital development, we conditionally removed Fgf8 from the cloacal/urethral epithelium. Surprisingly, Fgf8 is not necessary for initiation, outgrowth or normal patterning of the external genitalia. In early genital tubercles, we found no redundant Fgf expression in the urethral epithelium, which contrasts with the situation in the apical ectodermal ridge (AER) of the limb. Analysis of Fgf8 pathway activity showed that four putative targets are either absent from early genital tubercles or are not regulated by Fgf8. We therefore examined the distribution of Fgf8 protein and report that, although it is present in the AER, Fgf8 is undetectable in the genital tubercle. Thus, Fgf8 is transcribed, but the signaling pathway is not activated during normal genital development. A phylogenetic survey of amniotes revealed Fgf8 expression in genital tubercles of eutherian and metatherian mammals, but not turtles or alligators, indicating that Fgf8 expression is neither a required nor a conserved feature of amniote external genital development. The results indicate that Fgf8 expression is an early readout of the genital initiation signal rather than the signal itself. We propose that induction of external genitalia involves an epithelial-epithelial interaction at the cloacal membrane, and suggest that the cloacal ectoderm may be the source of the genital initiation signal.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091223; GR: 5R01HD054554/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8701744; 0 (Biological Markers); 0 (Bone Morphogenetic Protein 4); 0 (Fgf8 protein, mouse); 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); 0 (Hoxd13 protein, mouse); 0 (Shh protein, mouse); 0 (Transcription Factors); 0 (Wnt Proteins); 148997-75-5 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 8); OID: NLM: PMC2709070 [Available on 08/01/10]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-1991; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, UF Genetics Institute, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19592577; 136/15/2643 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1242/dev.036830</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19592577</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2709070</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1916</id>
<a1>Takahashi,T.</a1>
<a1>Holland,P. W.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Shimizu,K.</a1>
<a1>Kurokawa,M.</a1>
<a1>Hirai,H.</a1>
<t1>An orphan PRD class homeobox gene expressed in mouse brain and limb development</t1>
<jf>Development genes and evolution</jf>
<jo>Dev.Genes Evol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>212</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>293</sp>
<op>297</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Brain/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Homeodomain Proteins/chemistry/classification/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/chemistry/classification/genetics</k1>
<k1>Otx Transcription Factors</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<ab>We report the cDNA sequence and expression of a mouse homeobox gene, Dmbx1, from the PRD class and comparison to its human orthologue. The gene defines a new homeobox gene family, Dmbx, phylogenetically distinct from the Ptx, Alx, Prx Otx, Gsc, Otp and Pax gene families. The Dmbx1 gene is expressed in the developing mouse diencephalon, midbrain and hindbrain, and has dynamic expression during forelimb and hindlimb development. Unusually for homeobox genes, there is no orthologue in the Drosophila or Caenorhabditis genomes; we argue this reflects secondary loss.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; GENBANK/AF499446; JID: 9613264; 0 (Homeodomain Proteins); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Otx Transcription Factors); 0 (Otx3 protein, mouse); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 2001/12/18 [received]; 2002/03/21 [accepted]; 2002/05/24 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0949-944X; 0949-944X</sn>
<ad>School of Animal and Microbial Science, The University of Reading, Whiteknights, Reading, RG6 6AJ, UK.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12111214</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1007/s00427-002-0244-1</do>
<wp>20020524</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12111214</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1922</id>
<a1>Tanaka,M.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Ashby,P.</a1>
<a1>Davey,M.</a1>
<a1>Martin,P.</a1>
<a1>Tickle,C.</a1>
<t1>Distribution of polarizing activity and potential for limb formation in mouse and chick embryos and possible relationships to polydactyly</t1>
<jf>Development (Cambridge, England)</jf>
<jo>Development</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>127</vo>
<is>18</is>
<sp>4011</sp>
<op>4021</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Cell Differentiation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Ectoderm/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Embryo, Nonmammalian/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Extremities/embryology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factor 4</k1>
<k1>Fibroblast Growth Factors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Hedgehog Proteins</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/metabolism/transplantation</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred Strains</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Neck/embryology</k1>
<k1>Polydactyly/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Tail/embryology</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators</k1>
<k1>Wing/embryology</k1>
<ab>A central feature of the tetrapod body plan is that two pairs of limbs develop at specific positions along the head-to-tail axis. However, the potential to form limbs in chick embryos is more widespread. This could have implications for understanding the basis of limb abnormalities. Here we extend the analysis to mouse embryos and examine systematically the potential of tissues in different regions outside the limbs to contribute to limb structures. We show that the ability of ectoderm to form an apical ridge in response to FGF4 in both mouse and chick embryos exists throughout the flank as does ability of mesenchyme to provide a polarizing region signal. In addition, neck tissue has weak polarizing activity. We show, in chick embryos, that polarizing activity of tissues correlates with the ability either to express Shh or to induce Shh expression. We also show that cells from chick tail can give rise to limb structures. Taken together these observations suggest that naturally occurring polydactyly could involve recruitment of cells from regions adjacent to the limb buds. We show that cells from neck, flank and tail can migrate into limb buds in response to FGF4, which mimics extension of the apical ectodermal ridge. Furthermore, when we apply simultaneously a polarizing signal and a limb induction signal to early chick flank, this leads to limb duplications.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8701744; 0 (Fgf4 protein, mouse); 0 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 4); 0 (Hedgehog Proteins); 0 (Proteins); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins); 0 (Trans-Activators); 62031-54-3 (Fibroblast Growth Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-1991; 0950-1991</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Physiology, Wellcome Trust Biocentre, University of Dundee, Dow Street, Dundee DD1 5EH, UK. m.tanaka@dundee.ac.uk.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10952899</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10952899</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1909</id>
<a1>Thewissen,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Bajpai,S.</a1>
<a1>Heyning,J.</a1>
<a1>Horton,W. E.,Jr</a1>
<t1>Developmental basis for hind-limb loss in dolphins and origin of the cetacean bodyplan</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>May 30</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>8414</sp>
<op>8418</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Patterning</k1>
<k1>Cell Polarity</k1>
<k1>Dolphins/embryology/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Hindlimb/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Limb Buds/cytology/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<ab>Among mammals, modern cetaceans (whales, dolphins, and porpoises) are unusual in the absence of hind limbs. However, cetacean embryos do initiate hind-limb bud development. In dolphins, the bud arrests and degenerates around the fifth gestational week. Initial limb outgrowth in amniotes is maintained by two signaling centers, the apical ectodermal ridge (AER) and the zone of polarizing activity (ZPA). Our data indicate that the cetacean hind-limb bud forms an AER and that this structure expresses Fgf8 initially, but that neither the AER nor Fgf8 expression is maintained. Moreover, Sonic hedgehog (Shh), which mediates the signaling activity of the ZPA, is absent from the dolphin hind-limb bud. We find that failure to establish a ZPA is associated with the absence of Hand2, an upstream regulator of Shh. Interpreting our results in the context of both the cetacean fossil record and the known functions of Shh suggests that reduction of Shh expression may have occurred approximately 41 million years ago and led to the loss of distal limb elements. The total loss of Shh expression may account for the further loss of hind-limb elements that occurred near the origin of the modern suborders of cetaceans approximately 34 million years ago. Integration of paleontological and developmental data suggests that hind-limb size was reduced by gradually operating microevolutionary changes. Long after locomotor function was totally lost, modulation of developmental control genes eliminated most of the hind-limb skeleton. Hence, macroevolutionary changes in gene expression did not drive the initial reduction in hind-limb size.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; OID: NLM: PMC1482506; 2006/05/22 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy, Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine, Rootstown, OH 44272, USA. thewisse@neoucom.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16717186; 0602920103 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0602920103</do>
<wp>20060522</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16717186</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1482506</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1906</id>
<a1>Yong,W.</a1>
<a1>Yang,Z.</a1>
<a1>Periyasamy,S.</a1>
<a1>Chen,H.</a1>
<a1>Yucel,S.</a1>
<a1>Li,W.</a1>
<a1>Lin,L. Y.</a1>
<a1>Wolf,I. M.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Baskin,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Sanchez,E. R.</a1>
<a1>Shou,W.</a1>
<t1>Essential role for Co-chaperone Fkbp52 but not Fkbp51 in androgen receptor-mediated signaling and physiology</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Feb 16</fd>
<vo>282</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>5026</sp>
<op>5036</op>
<k1>Active Transport, Cell Nucleus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Androgens/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genital Diseases, Male/genetics/metabolism/pathology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Molecular Chaperones/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Penis/embryology</k1>
<k1>Prostate/embryology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Androgen/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Tacrolimus Binding Proteins/deficiency/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Fkbp52 and Fkbp51 are tetratricopeptide repeat proteins found in steroid receptor complexes, and Fkbp51 is an androgen receptor (AR) target gene. Although in vitro studies suggest that Fkbp52 and Fkbp51 regulate hormone binding and/or subcellular trafficking of receptors, the roles of Fkbp52 and Fkbp51 in vivo have not been extensively investigated. Here, we evaluate their physiological roles in Fkbp52-deficient and Fkbp51-deficient mice. Fkbp52-deficient males developed defects in select reproductive organs (e.g. penile hypospadias and prostate dysgenesis but normal testis), pointing to a role for Fkbp52 in AR-mediated signaling and function. Surprisingly, ablation of Fkbp52 did not affect AR hormone binding or nuclear translocation in vivo and in vitro. Molecular studies in mouse embryonic fibroblast cells uncovered that Fkbp52 is critical to AR transcriptional activity. Interestingly, Fkbp51 expression was down-regulated in Fkbp52-deficient males but only in affected tissues, providing further evidence of tissue-specific loss of AR activity and suggesting that Fkbp51 is an AR target gene essential to penile and prostate development. However, Fkbp51-deficient mice were normal, showing no defects in AR-mediated reproductive function. Our work demonstrates that Fkbp52 but not Fkbp51 is essential to AR-mediated signaling and provides evidence for an unprecedented Fkbp52 function, direct control of steroid receptor transcriptional activity.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: DK43867/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK70127/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: DK73402/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DK073402-02/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Androgens); 0 (Molecular Chaperones); 0 (Receptors, Androgen); EC 5.2.1.- (Tacrolimus Binding Proteins); EC 5.2.1.- (tacrolimus binding protein 4); EC 5.2.1.8 (tacrolimus binding protein 5); NIHMS52803; OID: NLM: NIHMS52803; OID: NLM: PMC2577319; 2006/12/01 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Herman B. Wells Center for Pediatric Research, Section of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana 46202, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17142810; M609360200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1074/jbc.M609360200</do>
<wp>20061201</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17142810</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2577319</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1902</id>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Genome duplication and the origin of the vertebrate skeleton</t1>
<jf>Current opinion in genetics &amp; development</jf>
<jo>Curr.Opin.Genet.Dev.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>387</sp>
<op>393</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Development/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bone and Bones/embryology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Duplication</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>Genome/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<ab>During vertebrate embryonic development, tissue patterning and differentiation are regulated by members of multigene families. Evolutionary expansion of these families is thought to have played a role in the evolution of anatomical complexity, including the origins of new cell and tissue types. A defining feature of vertebrates is an endoskeleton, the primary components of which are cartilage and bone. The molecular control of skeletal patterning has been the subject of intensive investigation for over two decades. More recently, comparative studies of organisms at key phylogenetic positions have highlighted the importance of gene duplication in the evolutionary diversification of connective tissues. Understanding the natural histories of gene families involved in skeletogenesis is therefore central to the issue of vertebrate skeletal evolution.</ab>
<no>JID: 9111375; RF: 48; 2008/05/14 [received]; 2008/06/26 [revised]; 2008/07/21 [accepted]; 2008/09/18 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0959-437X; 0959-437X</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, Cancer/Genetics Research Complex, P.O. Box 103610, Gainesville, FL 32610, United States.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18721879; S0959-437X(08)00088-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.gde.2008.07.009</do>
<wp>20080918</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18721879</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1907</id>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Hagfish and lancelet fibrillar collagens reveal that type II collagen-based cartilage evolved in stem vertebrates</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Nov 7</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>45</is>
<sp>16829</sp>
<op>16833</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Chordata, Nonvertebrate/genetics</k1>
<k1>Collagen Type II/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Complementary/genetics</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Duplication</k1>
<k1>Hagfishes/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<ab>The origin of vertebrates was defined by evolution of a skeleton; however, little is known about the developmental mechanisms responsible for this landmark evolutionary innovation. In jawed vertebrates, cartilage matrix consists predominantly of type II collagen (Col2alpha1), whereas that of jawless fishes has long been thought to be noncollagenous. We recently showed that Col2alpha1 is present in lamprey cartilage, indicating that type II collagen-based cartilage evolved earlier than previously recognized. Here, we investigate the origin of vertebrate cartilage, and we report that hagfishes, the sister group to lampreys, also have Col2alpha1-based cartilage, suggesting its presence in the common ancestor of crown-group vertebrates. We go on to show that lancelets, a sister group to vertebrates, possess an ancestral clade A fibrillar collagen (ColA) gene that is expressed in the notochord. Together, these results suggest that duplication and diversification of ColA genes at the chordate-vertebrate transition may underlie the evolutionary origin of vertebrate skeletal tissues.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/DQ647925; GENBANK/DQ647926; JID: 7505876; 0 (Collagen Type II); 0 (DNA, Complementary); OID: NLM: PMC1636540; 2006/10/31 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, P.O. Box 118525, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17077149; 0605630103 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0605630103</do>
<wp>20061031</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17077149</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1636540</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1900</id>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Eames,B. F.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Chapter 2. Evolution of vertebrate cartilage development</t1>
<jf>Current topics in developmental biology</jf>
<jo>Curr.Top.Dev.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>86</vo>
<sp>15</sp>
<op>42</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Development/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cartilage/embryology</k1>
<k1>Cell Lineage/genetics</k1>
<k1>Chondrogenesis/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Evolution</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>Gene Regulatory Networks/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Vertebrates/embryology</k1>
<ab>Major advances in the molecular genetics, paleobiology, and the evolutionary developmental biology of vertebrate skeletogenesis have improved our understanding of the early evolution and development of the vertebrate skeleton. These studies have involved genetic analysis of model organisms, human genetics, comparative developmental studies of basal vertebrates and nonvertebrate chordates, and both cladistic and histological analyses of fossil vertebrates. Integration of these studies has led to renaissance in the area of skeletal development and evolution. Among the major findings that have emerged is the discovery of an unexpectedly deep origin of the gene network that regulates chondrogenesis. In this chapter, we discuss recent progress in each these areas and identify a number of questions that need to be addressed in order to fill key gaps in our knowledge of early skeletal evolution.</ab>
<no>JID: 0163114; RF: 191; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0070-2153; 0070-2153</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, Cancer/Genetics Research Complex, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19361688; S0070-2153(09)01002-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/S0070-2153(09)01002-3</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19361688</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1910</id>
<a1>Zhang,G.</a1>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Cohn,M. J.</a1>
<t1>Lamprey type II collagen and Sox9 reveal an ancient origin of the vertebrate collagenous skeleton</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb 28</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>3180</sp>
<op>3185</op>
<k1>Aging/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chondrogenesis</k1>
<k1>Collagen Type II/classification/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Developmental</k1>
<k1>High Mobility Group Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lampreys/embryology/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>SOX9 Transcription Factor</k1>
<k1>Skeleton</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Type II collagen is the major cartilage matrix protein in the jawed vertebrate skeleton. Lampreys and hagfishes, by contrast, are thought to have noncollagenous cartilage. This difference in skeletal structure has led to the hypothesis that the vertebrate common ancestor had a noncollagenous skeleton, with type II collagen becoming the predominant cartilage matrix protein after the divergence of jawless fish from the jawed vertebrates approximately 500 million years ago. Here we report that lampreys have two type II collagen (Col2alpha1) genes that are expressed during development of the cartilaginous skeleton. We also demonstrate that the adult lamprey skeleton is rich in Col2alpha1 protein. Furthermore, we have isolated a lamprey orthologue of Sox9, a direct transcriptional regulator of Col2alpha1 in jawed vertebrates, and show that it is coexpressed with both Col2alpha1 genes during skeletal development. These results reveal that the genetic pathway for chondrogenesis in lampreys and gnathostomes is conserved through the activation of cartilage matrix molecules and suggest that a collagenous skeleton evolved surprisingly early in vertebrate evolution.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/DQ136023; GENBANK/DQ136024; GENBANK/DQ136025; JID: 7505876; 0 (Collagen Type II); 0 (High Mobility Group Proteins); 0 (SOX9 Transcription Factor); 0 (SOX9 protein, human); 0 (Transcription Factors); OID: NLM: PMC1413883; 2006/02/21 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Zoology, University of Florida, 223 Bartram Hall, Gainesville, 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16492784; 0508313103 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1073/pnas.0508313103</do>
<wp>20060221</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16492784</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1413883</pmcid></reference></refworks>
