
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4009</id>
<a1>Allard,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Jarecki,L.</a1>
<a1>Kraus,F.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>DNA systematics and evolution of the artiodactyl family Bovidae.</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</jf>
<jo>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>3972</sp>
<ab>Nine additional sequences from representatives of different tribes of the family Bovidae were combined with six published artiodactyl sequences to provide orthologous mtDNA for investigation of bovid phylogeny and evolution. Each species was represented by a homologous 2.7-kilobase-pair stretch of mtDNA for the complete 12S and 16S rRNA genes and three adjacent tRNA genes. These data, when compared to other results, provided evidence for a monophyletic Bovidae and for two clades within the family: one including the tribes Boselaphini, Bovini, and Tragelaphini and another for an Antilopini/Neotragini grouping. All other intrafamilial relationships were only weakly supported. These sequence comparisons suggest that most bovid tribes originated early in the Miocene with all extant lineages present by approximately 16-17 million years ago. Thus, bovid tribes provide an example of rapid cladogenesis, following the origin of families in the infraorder Pecora.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1570322</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC525613</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4012</id>
<a1>Botero,C.</a1>
<a1>Carrico,S.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Using comparative online journal usage studies to assess the big deal&lt;B&gt;.&lt;/B&gt;</t1>
<jf>Library Research and Technical Services Abstracts</jf>
<jo>Libr Res &amp; Tech Serv Abstr</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>61</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4011</id>
<a1>Buhler,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Ferree,N.</a1>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>External reporting lines of academic special libraries: a health sciences case study.</t1>
<jf>College and Research Libraries</jf>
<jo>Coll Res Libs</jo>
<yr>In press</yr>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3964</id>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Sherwill-Navarro,P.</a1>
<a1>Jesano,R.</a1>
<t1>Subject specialization in a liaison librarian program.</t1>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>446</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17082839</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1629419</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1235</id>
<a1>Davis,V.</a1>
<a1>Devare,M.</a1>
<a1>Gonzalez,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Implementation of a new research discovery tool by the university libraries at Cornell University and the University of Florida</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>15 June 2009</fd>
<t2>&lt;B&gt;Proceedings of the Contributed Paper Session, Biomedical and Life Sciences Division, Special Libraries Association, 100&lt;/B&gt;&lt;B&gt;&lt;SUP&gt;th&lt;/SUP&gt;&lt;/B&gt;&lt;B&gt; Annual Conference&lt;/B&gt;</t2>
<ed>Washington, D.C.</ed>
<ul>http://units.sla.org/division/dbio/events/conf_past/WashingtonDC/Davispaper.pdf</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3945</id>
<a1>Ferree,N.</a1>
<a1>Schaefer,N.</a1>
<a1>Butson,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Liaison librarian tiers: levels of service.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Medical Library Association</jf>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>97</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>145</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19404509</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2670215</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3991</id>
<a1>Kuntz,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Case,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Meakin,F. A.</a1>
<t1>Staff-driven strategic planning: learning from the past, embracing the future.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Medical Library Association</jf>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>79</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12568161</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC141191</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3998</id>
<a1>Liu,F. G.</a1>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Freire,N. P.</a1>
<a1>Ong,P. Q.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Young,T. S.</a1>
<a1>Gugel,K. F.</a1>
<t1>Molecular and morphological supertrees for eutherian (placental) mammals.</t1>
<jf>Science (New York, N.Y.)</jf>
<jo>Science.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>291</vo>
<is>5509</is>
<sp>1709</sp>
<ab>A large body of diverse comparative data now exists for a major phylogenetic synthesis of the higher-level relationships among eutherian (placental) mammals. We present such a phylogenetic synthesis using the composite trees or supertrees from the combined and separate analyses of their published molecular and morphological source phylogenies. Our combined and separate supertrees largely support the same suprafamilial taxa and orders, but different interordinal clades. These similarities and differences reinforce the continuing contributions of morphological studies, while highlighting the growing influence of molecular information on the field. As current summaries of past research, our supertrees emphasize opportunities for future work, while providing a step toward the eventual integration of the data and characters themselves.</ab>
<pb>American Association for the Advancement of Science</pb>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11230694</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4014</id>
<a1>Lyon,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Danielson,B.</a1>
<t1>Introducing Protein Data Bank, Molecular Modeling Database, and Cn3D.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Electronic Resources in Medical Libraries</jf>
<jo>J Electron Res Med Libs</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3990</id>
<a1>Lyon,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Messner,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Osterbur,D. L.</a1>
<t1>Carving a niche: establishing bioinformatics collaborations.</t1>
<jo>Journal of the Medical Library Association</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>330</sp>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: The paper describes collaborations and partnerships developed between library bioinformatics programs and other bioinformatics-related units at four academic institutions. METHODS: A call for information on bioinformatics partnerships was made via email to librarians who have participated in the National Center for Biotechnology Information&amp;#39;s Advanced Workshop for Bioinformatics Information Specialists. Librarians from Harvard University, the University of Florida, the University of Minnesota, and Vanderbilt University responded and expressed willingness to contribute information on their institutions, programs, services, and collaborating partners. Similarities and differences in programs and collaborations were identified. RESULTS: The four librarians have developed partnerships with other units on their campuses that can be categorized into the following areas: knowledge management, instruction, and electronic resource support. All primarily support freely accessible electronic resources, while other campus units deal with fee-based ones. These demarcations are apparent in resource provision as well as in subsequent support and instruction. CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS: Through environmental scanning and networking with colleagues, librarians who provide bioinformatics support can develop fruitful collaborations. Visibility is key to building collaborations, as is broad-based thinking in terms of potential partners.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16888668 </pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1525329</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4010</id>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Koop,B. F.</a1>
<a1>Slightom,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Goodman,M.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>Molecular systematics of higher Primates: genealogical relations and classification.</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</jf>
<jo>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>20</is>
<sp>7627</sp>
<ab>We obtained 5&amp;#39; and 3&amp;#39; flanking sequences (5.4 kilobase pairs) from the psi eta-globin gene region of the rhesus macaque (Macaca mulatta) and combined them with available nucleotide data. The completed sequence, representing 10.8 kilobase pairs of contiguous noncoding DNA, was compared to the same orthologous regions available for human (Homo sapiens, as represented by five different alleles), common chimpanzee (Pan troglodytes), gorilla (Gorilla gorilla), and orangutan (Pongo pygmaeus). The nucleotide sequence for Macaca mulatta provided the outgroup perspective needed to evaluate better the relationships of humans and great apes. Pairwise comparisons and parsimony analysis of these orthologues clearly demonstrated (i) that humans and great apes share a high degree of genetic similarity and (ii) that humans, chimpanzees, and gorillas form a natural monophyletic group. These conclusions strongly favor a genealogical classification for higher primates consisting of a single family (Hominidae) with two subfamilies (Homininae for Homo, Pan, and Gorilla and Ponginae for Pongo).</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3174657 </pmid>
<pmcid>PMC282245</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1240</id>
<a1>Niu,X.</a1>
<a1>Hemminger,B. M.</a1>
<a1>Lown,C.</a1>
<a1>Adams,S.</a1>
<a1>Brown,C.</a1>
<a1>Level,A.</a1>
<a1>McLure,M.</a1>
<a1>Powers,A.</a1>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<t1>National study of information seeking behavior of academic researchers in the United States.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>869</sp>
<op>890</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1236</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>The Institutional Review Board and library research: memoirs of a multi-site project</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>16 June 2008</fd>
<t2>&lt;B&gt;Proceedings of the Contributed Paper Session, Biomedical and Life Sciences Division, Special Libraries Association, 99&lt;/B&gt;&lt;B&gt;&lt;SUP&gt;th&lt;/SUP&gt;&lt;/B&gt;&lt;B&gt; Annual Conference&lt;/B&gt;</t2>
<ed>Seattle, WA</ed>
<ul>http://units.sla.org/division/dbio/events/conf_past/Seattle08/tennant08.pdf</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4015</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>&lt;B&gt;Bioinformatics librarian: meeting the information needs of genetics and bioinformatics researchers.&lt;/B&gt;</t1>
<jf>Reference Services Review</jf>
<jo>Ref Serv Rev</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>12</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1239</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<t1>The Internet in the library/classroom:  genetics at the University of Florida</t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>11 June 1997</fd>
<sp>57</sp>
<t2>From Reactive to Proactive:  Substantive Approaches to Incorporating the Internet into Biological, Medical, and Life Sciences Libraries:  Proceedings of the Contributed Paper Session, Biological Sciences Division, Special Libraries Association, 88&lt;SUP&gt;th&lt;/SUP&gt; Annual Conference</t2>
<ed>Seattle, WA</ed>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1237</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Buhler,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Ferree,N.</a1>
<a1>Francis,B. W.</a1>
<a1>Hsu,P. P.</a1>
<a1>Jesano,R.</a1>
<a1>Layton,B.</a1>
<a1>Schaefer,N.</a1>
<a1>Sherwill,P.</a1>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<a1>Hack,G. O.</a1>
<t1>Partnerships in instruction: teaching dogs old and new, local and distant.</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>8 June 2004</fd>
<t2>Beyond Bibliographic Instruction: Teaching Old Dogs New Tricks: Proceedings of the Contributed Paper Session, Biomedical and Life Sciences Division, Special Libraries Association, 95&lt;SUP&gt;th&lt;/SUP&gt; Annual Conference</t2>
<ed>Nashville, TN</ed>
<ul>http://www.sla.org/division/dbio/nashville/Tennant.htm</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3999</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Butson,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Rezeau,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Tucker,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Boyle,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Clayton,G.</a1>
<t1>Customizing for clients: developing a library liaison program from need to plan.</t1>
<jf>Bulletin of the Medical Library Association</jf>
<jo>Bull Med Libr Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>8</sp>
<ab>Building on the experiences of librarian representatives to curriculum committees in the colleges of dentistry, medicine, and nursing, the Health Science Center Libraries (HSCL) Strategic Plan recommended the formation of a Library Liaison Work Group to create a formal Library Liaison Program to serve the six Health Science Center (HSC) colleges and several affiliated centers and institutes. The work group&amp;#39;s charge was to define the purpose and scope of the program, identify models of best practice, and recommend activities for liaisons. The work group gathered background information, performed an environmental scan, and developed a philosophy statement, a program of liaison activities focusing on seven primary areas, and a forum for liaison communication. Hallmarks of the plan included intensive subject specialization (beyond collection development), extensive communication with users, and personal information services. Specialization was expected to promote competence, communication, confidence, comfort, and customization. Development of the program required close coordination with other strategic plan implementation teams, including teams for collection development, education, and marketing. This paper discusses the HSCL&amp;#39;s planning process and the resulting Library Liaison Program. Although focusing on an academic health center, the planning process and liaison model may be applied to any library serving diverse, subject-specific user populations.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11209807</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC31699</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3996</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<t1>Development and assessment of specialized liaison librarian services: clinical vs. basic science in a veterinary medicine setting.</t1>
<jf>Medical Reference Services Quarterly</jf>
<jo>Med Ref Serv Q.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>21</sp>
<ab>In 1998, the University of Florida Health Science Center Libraries (HSCL) developed and implemented a Liaison Librarian Program, dedicated to providing customized, subject-specific services to the faculty, students, clinicians, researchers, staff, and administrators of the six Health Science Center Colleges (Dentistry, Health Professions, Medicine, Nursing, Pharmacy, and Veterinary Medicine). Subject- and role-specific (clinical vs. basic sciences) liaisons were assigned. This paper describes the HSCL liaison program, exemplified by the liaisons&amp;#39; work with the College of Veterinary Medicine. Preliminary program evaluation, a pilot project developed to discern the needs of the veterinary medicine clientele and facilitate awareness of liaison services, and subsequent re-evaluation of patron awareness and satisfaction are also discussed.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12568161</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3989</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Cataldo ,T. T.</a1>
<a1>Sherwill-Navarro,P.</a1>
<a1>Jesano,R.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of a liaison librarian program: client and liaison perspectives.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Medical Library Association</jf>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>402</sp>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: This paper describes a survey-based evaluation of the five-year old Liaison Librarian Program at the University of Florida. METHODS: Liaison librarians, faculty, students, staff, residents, and post-doctoral associates were queried via Web-based surveys. Questions addressed client and liaison perspectives on a variety of issues, including program and service awareness and usage, client-library relations and communication, client support for the program, and liaison workload. RESULTS: Approximately 43% of the 323 client respondents were aware of liaison services; 72% (n = 163) of these clients had had contact with their liaison. Ninety-five percent (n = 101) of faculty and students who reported contact with their liaison supported the continuation of the program. Liaison services were used by a greater percentage of faculty than students, although they had similar patterns of usage and reported the same &amp;quot;traditional&amp;quot; services to be most important. Liaisons indicated that communications with clients had increased, the reputation of the library was enhanced, and their workloads had increased as a result of the Liaison Librarian Program. CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS: Survey results suggest that the Liaison Librarian Program has a core set of clients who use and highly value the services provided by liaisons. Recommendations addressing workload, training, marketing, and administrative support are provided.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17082831 </pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1629425</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1238</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Francis,B. W.</a1>
<t1>Course-integrated instruction in an academic health science library:  a comparison of basic science and clinical strategies</t1>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>9 June 1999</fd>
<sp>45</sp>
<t2>Getting the Message Across: Innovation in Library Instruction and Training in Biomedical and Life Sciences Libraries:  Proceedings of the Contributed Paper Session, Biomedical and Life Sciences Division, Special Libraries Association, 90&lt;SUP&gt;th&lt;/SUP&gt; Annual Conference</t2>
<ed>Minneapolis, MN</ed>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4013</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lyon,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Entrez Gene:  a gene-centered “Information Hub”. </t1>
<jo>J Electron Res Med Libs</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>53</sp>
<rd>Journal of Electronic Resources in Medical Libraries</rd>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>4016</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Lyon,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Online resources for genetics researchers, clinicians, and the public: Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man and GeneTests.</t1>
<jf>Journal of Electronic Resources in Medical Libraries</jf>
<jo>J Electron Res Med Libs</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>3</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3946</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<t1>The role of the medical librarian in the basic biological sciences: a case study in virology and evolution.</t1>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>96</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>290</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18974807</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2568840</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3997</id>
<a1>Tennant,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Miyamoto,M. M.</a1>
<t1>The role of medical libraries in undergraduate education: a case study in genetics.</t1>
<jf>Journal of the Medical Library Association</jf>
<jo>J Med Libr Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<ab>Between 1996 and 2001, the Health Science Center Libraries and Department of Zoology at the University of Florida partnered to provide a cohesive and comprehensive learning experience to undergraduate students in PCB3063, &amp;quot;Genetics.&amp;quot; During one semester each year, a librarian worked with up to 120 undergraduates, providing bibliographic and database instruction in the tools that practicing geneticists use (MEDLINE, GenBank, BLAST, etc.). Students learned to evaluate and synthesize the information that they retrieved, coupling it with information provided in classroom lectures, thus resulting in well-researched short papers on an assigned genetics topic. Exit surveys of students indicated that the majority found the library sessions and librarian&amp;#39;s instruction to be useful. Responses also indicated that the project facilitated increased understanding of genetics concepts and appreciation for the scientific research process and the relevance of genetics to the real world. The library benefited from this partnership on a variety of fronts, including the development of skilled library users, pretrained future clientele, and increased visibility among campus research laboratories. The course and associated information instruction and assigned projects can be considered models for course-integrated instruction and the role of medical libraries in undergraduate education.</ab>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11999176</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC100763</pmcid></reference></refworks>
