
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1687</id>
<a1>Chheda,N.</a1>
<a1>Katz,A. E.</a1>
<a1>Gynizio,L.</a1>
<a1>Singer,A. J.</a1>
<t1>The pain of nasal tampon removal after nasal surgery: a randomized control trial</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>140</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>215</sp>
<op>217</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Device Removal/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hemostasis, Surgical/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nasal Septum/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pain, Postoperative/diagnosis/etiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Patient Satisfaction</k1>
<k1>Rhinoplasty/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Tampons, Surgical/adverse effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The purpose of this study was to compare the pain and discomfort associated with the removal of two commercially available nasal tampons after nasal surgery. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, paired, randomized clinical trial. SUBJECTS: Consecutive, consenting, adult patients undergoing nasal surgery. INTERVENTIONS: The nose was packed with a Rapid Rhino tampon (Applied Therapeutics, Tampa, FL) on one side and a Rhino Rocket tampon (Shippert Medical Technologies Corporation, Centennial, CO) on the other. OUTCOMES: The pain of packing removal was assessed with a validated 100-mm visual analog scale. Patient satisfaction was measured on a Likert scale from 1 to 5. RESULTS: In all 13 patients, the pain of removal was greater with the Rhino Rocket Tampon (82.7 +/- 20.9 mm) than with the Rapid Rhino tampon (12.0 +/- 11.9 mm); the mean difference was 70.7 mm (95% confidence interval [CI], 47.1-78.2 mm; P &amp;lt; 0.0001). Patient satisfaction was significantly higher with the Rapid Rhino nasal tampon (4.6 +/- 1.1 vs 1.5 +/- 0.7; mean difference 3.1 [95% CI, 2.6-3.6]; P &amp;lt; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS: Removal of the Rapid Rhino nasal tampon was significantly less painful and was associated with higher patient satisfaction than the removal of the Rhino Rocket nasal tampon.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 2008/08/12 [received]; 2008/09/09 [revised]; 2008/09/09 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Surgery, State University of New York at Stony Brook, Stony Brook, NY, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19201291; S0194-5998(08)01407-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Randomized Controlled Trial; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2008.09.012</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19201291</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1694</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<t1>Transnasal esophagoscopy</t1>
<yr>2010</yr>
<no>ID: 635795976</no>
<a2>Flint,Paul W.</a2><a2> Cummings,C. W.</a2>
<t2>Cummings otolaryngology : head &amp;amp; neck surgery</t2>
<ed>5</ed>
<pb>Mosby Elsevier</pb>
<pp>Philadelpha, PA</pp>
<sn>9780323052832 : 0323052835</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1693</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Balloon dilation of an acquired nasopharyngeal stenosis</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>140</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>939</sp>
<op>941</op>
<k1>Balloon Dilatation/methods</k1>
<k1>Constriction, Pathologic/therapy</k1>
<k1>Endoscopy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Nasopharyngeal Diseases/etiology/therapy</k1>
<no>JID: 8508176; 2008/12/02 [received]; 2009/02/09 [revised]; 2009/02/23 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Division of Laryngology, Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. neil.chheda@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19467420; S0194-5998(09)00176-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2009.02.030</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19467420</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1691</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Patient compliance with proton pump inhibitor therapy in an otolaryngology practice</t1>
<jf>The Annals of Otology, Rhinology, and Laryngology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Otol.Rhinol.Laryngol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>117</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>670</sp>
<op>672</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Interviews as Topic</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otorhinolaryngologic Diseases/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Patient Compliance</k1>
<k1>Proton Pump Inhibitors/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are used for the treatment of numerous otolaryngological disorders. It has been demonstrated that administration of the medication 15 to 45 minutes before a meal optimizes acid suppression. The rate of compliance with optimal PPI dosage patterns in an otolaryngology practice is not known. We sought to determine the rate of PPI compliance in patients seen in an otolaryngology practice. METHODS: We conducted an interview at a tertiary voice and swallowing center of 200 consecutive patients who were taking PPIs. RESULTS: Overall, 54% of patients took their PPI in an optimal manner. The rate of compliance was significantly higher for patients who had their PPI prescribed by an otolaryngologist (62%) than for patients whose PPI was prescribed by a non-otolaryngologist (40%). CONCLUSIONS: Nearly half of all patients seen at a voice and swallowing center were not compliant with optimal PPI usage. This percentage is similar to that found for other long-term medications. Patient education can lead to higher rates of compliance, improved acid control, and possibly improved treatment outcomes.</ab>
<no>JID: 0407300; 0 (Proton Pump Inhibitors); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-4894; 0003-4894</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Medical College of Georgia, Augusta, Georgia 30912, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18834069</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18834069</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1686</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Rosen,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Belafsky,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Simpson,C. B.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Revision laryngeal surgery for the suboptimal injection of calcium hydroxylapatite</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2260</sp>
<op>2263</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Ambulatory Surgical Procedures</k1>
<k1>Durapatite/administration &amp; dosage/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Granuloma, Foreign-Body/etiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Injections</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Muscles/surgery</k1>
<k1>Laryngoscopy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Microspheres</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/etiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants</k1>
<k1>Reoperation</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Stroboscopy</k1>
<k1>Vocal Cord Paralysis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Vocal Cords/surgery</k1>
<k1>Voice Disorders/etiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The objective of this study was to describe the management of suboptimal injection of calcium hydroxylapatite during augmentation laryngoplasty. STUDY DESIGN: A retrospective review was conducted at four Voice and Swallowing centers to identify patients who had a suboptimal injection of calcium hydroxylapatite during augmentation laryngoplasty. RESULTS: Five patients (ages 19-75) were identified with an impaired voice secondary to a superficial injection of calcium hydroxylapatite or over-medialization of the true vocal fold. All patients underwent revision surgery with all experiencing subjective and objective improvement. CONCLUSION: Microflap excision can lead to successful return of vibratory function after a suboptimal injection of calcium hydroxylapatite. Complete control of the initial injection is paramount to avoiding this complication.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; 1306-06-5 (Durapatite); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Medical College of Georgia, Augusta, GA 30912, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19029857</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/MLG.0b013e318184e6ee</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19029857</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1692</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Seybt,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Schade,R. R.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Normal values for pharyngeal pH monitoring</t1>
<jf>The Annals of Otology, Rhinology, and Laryngology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Otol.Rhinol.Laryngol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>166</sp>
<op>171</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Esophageal pH Monitoring/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gastric Acidity Determination/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen-Ion Concentration</k1>
<k1>Ion-Selective Electrodes</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Pharynx/physiology</k1>
<k1>Postprandial Period</k1>
<k1>Posture</k1>
<k1>Predictive Value of Tests</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: We performed a prospective study of asymptomatic adult volunteers to establish normative values of pharyngeal pH using a novel pH probe. METHODS: The Dx-pH probe is a novel pH device capable of measuring liquid and aerosolized acid levels. Twenty asymptomatic patients (Reflux Symptom Index less than 10 and Reflux Finding Score less than 6) underwent simultaneous investigation with this probe placed in the oropharynx and a dual antimony probe placed in the hypopharynx and esophagus. The reflux parameters measured from the oropharyngeal probe included the percentage of time and the number of events in which the pH was less than 5.5,5.0,4.5, and 4.0. RESULTS: The upper limits of normal (95th percentile) for the number of events below pH of 5.5, 5.0, 4.5, and 4.0 per 24-hour period were 16.6, 10.7, 7.4, and 0.2, respectively. The upper limits of normal (95th percentile) for an acid exposure time below pH of 5.5, 5.0, 4.5, and 4.0 per 24-hour period were 820 seconds, 385 seconds, 75 seconds, and 3 seconds, respectively. CONCLUSIONS: Normative pharyngeal pH values are presented. Further studies are required to determine clinical relevance.</ab>
<no>JID: 0407300; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-4894; 0003-4894</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19374146</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19374146</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Web Page</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1695</id>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Werning,J.</a1>
<t1>Functional voice disorders</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>May 11, 2009</fd>
<vo>2010</vo>
<is>June 23, 2010</is>
<ed>http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/865191-overview</ed>
<pb>Emedicine.com</pb>
<rd>June 23, 2010</rd>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1688</id>
<a1>Hachiya,A.</a1>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Large mixed hiatal hernia and stricture as a cause of dysphagia</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>826</sp>
<k1>Deglutition Disorders/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Esophageal Stenosis/complications/etiology</k1>
<k1>Esophagoscopy</k1>
<k1>Gastroesophageal Reflux/complications</k1>
<k1>Hernia, Hiatal/complications/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<no>JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1942-7522; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Center for Voice and Swallowing Disorders, Department of Otolaryngology, Medical College of Georgia, Augusta, GA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19291629</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19291629</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1689</id>
<a1>Hachiya,A.</a1>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>&amp;quot;Gastric pull-up&amp;quot; and dysphagia</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>325</sp>
<k1>Anastomosis, Surgical/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Balloon Dilatation/methods</k1>
<k1>Deglutition Disorders/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Esophageal Neoplasms/diagnosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Esophagectomy/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Esophagoscopy</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Quality of Life</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Stomach/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<no>LR: 20090520; JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1942-7522; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Center for Voice and Swallowing Disorders, Department of Otolaryngology, Medical College of Georgia, Augusta, GA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18561114</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18561114</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1690</id>
<a1>Hachiya,A.</a1>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<a1>Postma,G. N.</a1>
<t1>Acquired vascular compression of the esophagus</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>677</sp>
<k1>Barium Radioisotopes/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Cardiomegaly/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Esophageal Diseases/diagnosis/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Esophagoscopy/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hypertension, Pulmonary/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Pressure</k1>
<no>LR: 20090520; JID: 7701817; 0 (Barium Radioisotopes); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1942-7522; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Center for Voice and Swallowing Disorders, Department of Otolaryngology, Medical College of Georgia, Augusta, GA, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19105140</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19105140</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1685</id>
<a1>Shindo,M.</a1>
<a1>Chheda,N. N.</a1>
<t1>Incidence of vocal cord paralysis with and without recurrent laryngeal nerve monitoring during thyroidectomy</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>133</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>481</sp>
<op>485</op>
<k1>Electromyography/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Monitoring, Intraoperative/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Recurrent Laryngeal Nerve/physiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Thyroidectomy/methods/statistics &amp; numerical data</k1>
<k1>Vocal Cord Paralysis/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To compare the incidence of postoperative vocal cord paresis or paralysis in a cohort of patients who underwent thyroidectomy with and without continuous recurrent laryngeal nerve (RLN) monitoring by a single senior surgeon. We hypothesize that continuous RLN monitoring reduces the rate of nerve injury during thyroidectomy DESIGN: Retrospective medical chart review. SETTING: Academic tertiary care medical center. PATIENTS: A total of 684 patients (1043 nerves at risk) who underwent thyroid surgery under general anesthesia. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURE: Incidence of vocal cord paresis or paralysis in patients who underwent thyroid surgery with continuous RLN monitoring vs those undergoing surgery without continuous RLN monitoring. RESULTS: The incidence of unexpected unilateral vocal cord paresis based on RLNs at risk was 2.09% (n = 14) in the monitored group and 2.96% (n = 11) in the unmonitored group. This difference was not statistically significant. The incidence of unexpected complete unilateral vocal cord paralysis was 1.6% in each group. Two of the 5 paralyses in the unmonitored group and 7 of the 11 paralyses in the monitored group had complete resolution. CONCLUSIONS: Monitoring of the RLN does not appear to reduce the incidence of postoperative temporary or permanent complete vocal cord paralysis. There appeared to be a slightly lower rate of postoperative paresis with RLN monitoring, but this difference was not statistically significant.</ab>
<no>JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Division of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, School of Medicine, State University of New York at Stony Brook, NY 11794-8191, USA. mshindo@notes.cc.stonybrook.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17520762</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17520762</pmid></reference></refworks>
