<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1781</id>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Organ preservation with radiotherapy for T1-T2 carcinoma of the pyriform sinus</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>353</sp>
<op>362</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Neoplasms/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Larynx/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<k1>Time</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To report long-term results using radiotherapy with or without a planned neck dissection for T1-T2 carcinoma of the pyriform sinus. METHODS: An analysis of 101 patients treated at the University of Florida with RT with or without a planned neck dissection for organ preservation. RESULTS: The 5-year local control rates after RT were 90% for T1 cancers and 80% for T2 lesions. The only parameter that significantly influenced local control in univariate analyses was apex involvement for T1 tumors. Multivariate analysis revealed no parameter that significantly affected local control. Cause-specific survival rates at 5 years were as follows: stage I-II, 96%; stage III, 62%; stage IVA, 49%; and stage IVB, 33%. The absolute survival rates were as follows: stage I, 57%; stage II, 61%; stage III, 41%; stage IVA, 29%; and stage IVB, 25%. Moderate to severe long-term complications developed in 12% of patients. CONCLUSIONS: RT alone or combined with a planned neck dissection resulted in local control with larynx preservation in a high proportion of patients. The chance of cure is comparable to that observed after conservation surgery, and the risk of major complications is lower. The addition of adjuvant chemotherapy is unlikely to improve the probability of organ preservation, but might improve locoregional control for patients with advanced nodal disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2001; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida Health Science Center, PO Box 100385, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. amdurrj@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11295808; 10.1002/hed.1044 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11295808</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1791</id>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Is it worth the risk?</t1>
<jo>NCAA Sports Sciences Education Newsletter</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>April 2000</fd>
<sp>1</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1784</id>
<a1>Gomez,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Tannehill,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiation therapy in inverted papillomas of the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>May-Jun</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>174</sp>
<op>178</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nasal Cavity/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Nose Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Papilloma, Inverted/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiation Dosage</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Between December 1969 and September 1989, a total of 10 patients with advanced and/or recurrent inverted or cylindrical cell papillomas were treated with irradiation at the University of Florida in Gainesville. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Nine of 10 patients had 1 or more recurrences before they received radiation therapy. Three patients were treated with irradiation alone, and 7 patients received surgery and irradiation (preoperatively in 1 patient and postoperatively in 6 patients). Eight patients had inverted papillomas (3 with concomitant squamous cell carcinoma), and 2 patients had cylindrical cell papillomas. Results: Local recurrence developed in 4 patients at 1.5, 6.5, 12, and 13 years after treatment. No evidence of recurrence was observed in 6 patients at 7, 8.5, 8.5, 9, 9, and 20.5 years after treatment. Four patients died of intercurrent disease. No patient developed a malignant transformation. Significant complications of treatment included, in 1 patient, an area of bone exposure in the orbit that necessitated debridement. CONCLUSION: Surgery is the primary treatment of this entity. Radiation therapy should be considered in patients with incompletely resectable lesions, multiply recurrent tumors, and tumors associated with malignancy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10834551</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10834551</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1785</id>
<a1>McCord,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Parsons,J. T.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Million,R. R.</a1>
<t1>Skin cancer of the head and neck with clinical perineural invasion</t1>
<jf>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Radiat.Oncol.Biol.Phys.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Apr 1</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>89</sp>
<op>93</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Basal Cell/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Cranial Nerves/pathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Multivariate Analysis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Invasiveness</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/pathology</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To review treatment and outcomes in 62 patients with clinical and/or gross evidence of perineural invasion from skin cancer of the head and neck. METHODS AND MATERIALS: Sixty-two patients received radiotherapy at the University of Florida as part or all of their treatment between January 1965 and April 1995. All patients had clinical signs and symptoms of perineural involvement and/or documentation of tumor extending to grossly involve nerve(s). Twenty-one patients underwent therapy for previously untreated lesions, including 12 who received radiotherapy alone and nine who had surgery with postoperative radiotherapy. Forty-one patients underwent therapy for recurrent lesions, including 18 treated with radiotherapy alone and 23 who received preoperative or postoperative radiotherapy. RESULTS: Factors on multivariate analysis that predicted local control included patient age, previously untreated vs. recurrent lesions, presence of clinical symptoms, and extent of radiotherapy fields. Recurrence patterns were predominantly local; 26 of 31 patients (84%) who developed local recurrence after treatment had recurrent cancer limited to the primary site. CONCLUSIONS: Many patients with skin cancer and symptomatic perineural invasion have disease that is incompletely resectable. Approximately half these patients will be cured with aggressive irradiation alone or combined with surgery. Age, prior treatment, and clinical symptoms influence the likelihood of cure.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7603616; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0360-3016; 0360-3016</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10758309; S0360-3016(99)00533-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10758309</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Web Page</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1789</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<t1>Radiation therapy, management of neck metastases</t1>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Feb 2, 2010</fd>
<ed>http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/853346-overview</ed>
<pb>EMedicine.com</pb>
<rd>June 25, 2010</rd>
<ul>http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/853346-overview , http://www.emedicine.com/ent/topic712.htm</ul>
<wp>Auugst 15, 2003</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Electronic(1)</sr>
<id>1790</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiation therapy in the management of the neck</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>February 2002</fd>
<a2>Meyers,A. D.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology &amp;amp; Facial Plastic Surgery</t2>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1787</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Tannehill,S. P.</a1>
<t1>Therapeutic principles in the management of head and neck tumours</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<sp>1322</sp>
<op>1322-1344</op>
<no>ID: 427566850</no>
<a2>Souhami,Robert L.</a2>
<t2>Oxford textbook of oncology</t2>
<pb>Oxford University</pb>
<pp>Oxford</pp>
<sn>0192629263 9780192629265</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1788</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Riggs,C. E.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Treatment of head and neck cancers</t1>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>January 2005</fd>
<sp>642</sp>
<op>642-743</op>
<k1>Cancer</k1>
<k1>Oncology</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms</k1>
<no>edited by Vincent T. Devita Jr., Samuel Hellman, Steven A. Rosenberg ; with 355 contributing authors. : edited by Vincent T. Devita Jr., Samuel Hellman, Steven A. Rosenberg ; with 355 contributing authors.; Alternate title: Cancer, principles and practice of oncology; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>DeVita,Vincent T.</a2><a2> Hellman,Samuel</a2><a2>Rosenberg,Steven A.</a2>
<t2>Cancer, principles &amp;amp; practice of oncology</t2>
<ed>7</ed>
<pb>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia, PA</pp>
<sn>0781744504; 0781748658</sn>
<cn>QZ200.C21537 2005 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY Reference); QZ200.C21537 2005 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY Shelved on CD shelf)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1783</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiation therapy for squamous cell carcinoma of the tonsillar region: a preferred alternative to surgery?</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>2219</sp>
<op>2225</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Multivariate Analysis</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Tonsillar Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: There are no definitive randomized studies that compare radiotherapy (RT) with surgery for tonsillar cancer. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the results of RT alone and RT combined with a planned neck dissection for carcinoma of the tonsillar area and to compare these data with the results of treatment with primary surgery. PATIENTS AND METHODS: Four hundred patients were treated between October 1964 and December 1997 and observed for at least 2 years. One hundred forty-one patients underwent planned neck dissection, and 18 patients received induction (17 patients) or concomitant (one patient) chemotherapy. RESULTS: Five-year local control rates, by tumor stage, were as follows: T1, 83%; T2, 81%; T3, 74%; and T4, 60%. Multivariate analysis revealed that local control was significantly influenced by tumor stage (P =.0001), fractionation schedule (P =.0038), and external beam dose (P =.0227). Local control after RT for early-stage cancers was higher for tonsillar fossa/posterior pillar cancers than for those arising from the anterior tonsillar pillar. Five-year cause-specific survival rates, by disease stage, were as follows: I, 100%; II, 86%; III, 82%; IVa, 63%; and IVb, 22%. Multivariate analysis revealed that cause-specific survival was significantly influenced by overall stage (P =.0001), planned neck dissection (P =.0074), and histologic differentiation (P =.0307). The incidence of severe late complications after treatment was 5%. CONCLUSION: RT alone or combined with a planned neck dissection provides cure rates that are as good as those after surgery and is associated with a lower rate of severe complications.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8309333; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0732-183X; 0732-183X</sn>
<ad>Departments of Radiation Oncology and Otolaryngology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10829041</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10829041</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1782</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Stratification of stage IV SCC of the oropharynx</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>626</sp>
<op>628</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/classification/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Oropharynx</k1>
<k1>Pharyngeal Neoplasms/classification/pathology</k1>
<no>LR: 20061005; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<an>PMID: 10941166; 10.1002/1097-0347(200009)22:6&lt;626::AID-HED13&gt;3.0.CO;2-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Letter; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10941166</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1777</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Singleton,G. T.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Treatment of paragangliomas with radiation therapy</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1007</sp>
<op>20, vii-viii</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/diagnosis/mortality/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Paraganglioma/diagnosis/mortality/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiation Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>Paragangliomas of the head and neck may be treated successfully with surgery, radiation therapy, or stereotactic radiosurgery. The choice of treatment depends on the location and extent of the tumor, the presence of multiple tumors, the age and health of the patient, and the preference of the patient and attending physician. This article reviews the role of radiation therapy in the treatment of patients with paragangliomas of the head and neck.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 0144042; RF: 37; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11557452</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11557452</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1778</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Squamous cell carcinoma metastatic to the neck from an unknown head and neck primary site</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jul-Aug</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>261</sp>
<op>267</op>
<k1>Biopsy, Needle</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/diagnosis/radiotherapy/secondary</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/diagnosis/radiotherapy/secondary</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/pathology</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary/diagnosis/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Tomography, Emission-Computed</k1>
<k1>Tomography, Emission-Computed, Single-Photon</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>Squamous cell carcinoma metastatic to the neck from an unknown head and neck primary site is relatively uncommon and presents a challenging diagnostic and therapeutic dilemma. Diagnostic evaluation includes fine-needle aspiration of the neck mass, chest roentgenography, computed tomography, and/or magnetic resonance imaging of the head and neck, followed by panendoscopy and biopsies. The primary tumor will be detected in approximately 40% of patients; approximately 80% of cancers are located in the base of the tongue or tonsillar fossa. Management options include treatment of the neck alone or both sides of the neck and the potential head and neck primary sites. The latter approach is associated with better long-term control above the clavicles. The 5-year survival rate is approximately 50% after treatment and is influenced by the extent of neck disease. In this article, we review the pertinent literature.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11464323; S0196-0709(01)67792-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1053/ajot.2001.24820</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11464323</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1786</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Moore-Higgs,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Is radiation therapy a preferred alternative to surgery for squamous cell carcinoma of the base of tongue?</t1>
<jf>Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</jf>
<jo>J.Clin.Oncol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>35</sp>
<op>42</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Logistic Models</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Multivariate Analysis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/mortality/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To evaluate irradiation alone for treatment of base-of-tongue cancer. PATIENTS AND METHODS: Two hundred seventeen patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the base of tongue were treated with radiation alone and had follow-up for &amp;gt;/= 2 years. RESULTS: Local control rates at 5 years were as follows: T1, 96%; T2, 91%; T3, 81%; and T4, 38%. Multivariate analysis revealed that T stage (P =.0001) and overall treatment time (P =.0006) significantly influenced local control. The 5-year rates of local-regional control were as follows: I, 100%; II, 100%; III, 83%; IVA, 64%; and IVB, 65%. Multivariate analysis revealed that the following parameters significantly affect the probability of this end point: T stage (P =.0001), overall treatment time (P =.0001), overall stage (P =.0131), and addition of a neck dissection (P =.0021). The rates of absolute and cause-specific survival at 5 years were as follows: I, 50% and 100%; II, 81% and 100%; III, 65% and 76%; IVA, 42% and 56%; and IVB, 44% and 52%. Severe radiation complications developed in eight patients (4%). CONCLUSION: The likelihood of cure after external-beam irradiation was related to stage, overall treatment time, and addition of a planned neck dissection. The local-regional control rates and survival rates after radiation therapy were comparable to those after surgery, and the morbidity associated with irradiation was less.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8309333; CIN: J Clin Oncol. 2000 Oct 1;18(19):3452-3. PMID: 11013290; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0732-183X; 0732-183X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10623691</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10623691</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1776</id>
<a1>Parsons,J. T.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Moore-Higgs,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Greene,B. D.</a1>
<a1>Speer,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Million,R. R.</a1>
<t1>Squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx: surgery, radiation therapy, or both</t1>
<jf>Cancer</jf>
<jo>Cancer</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jun 1</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>2967</sp>
<op>2980</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Neck Dissection</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Metastasis</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Tonsillar Neoplasms/pathology/radiotherapy/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The treatment of patients with squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) of the oropharynx remains controversial. No randomized trial has addressed adequately the question of whether surgery (S), radiation therapy (RT), or combined treatment is most effective. METHODS: Treatment results from North American academic institutions that used S with or without adjuvant RT (S +/- RT) or used RT alone or followed by neck dissection (RT +/- ND) for patients with SCC of the tonsillar region or the base of tongue were compiled through a MEDLINE search (from 1970 to August, 2000) and from the references cited in each report. Studies were eligible for inclusion if they contained direct, actuarial (life-table), or Kaplan-Meier calculations for the following end points: local control, local-regional control, 5-year absolute survival, 5-year cause specific survival, or severe or fatal treatment complications. Weighted average results, which took into account series size, were calculated for each end point for the purposes of treatment comparison. Results and conclusions were based on data from 51 reported series, representing the treatment of approximately 6400 patients from the United States and Canada. RESULTS: The results for patients with SCC of the base of tongue who underwent S +/- RT versus RT +/- ND, respectively, were as follows: local control, 79% versus 76% (P = 0.087); local-regional control, 60% versus 69% (P = 0.009); 5-year survival, 49% versus 52% (P = 0.2); 5-year cause specific survival, 62% versus 63% (P = 0.4); severe complications, 32% versus 3.8% (P &amp;lt; 0.001); and fatal complications, 3.5% versus 0.4% (P &amp;lt; 0.001). The results for patients with SCC in the tonsillar region who underwent S +/- RT versus RT +/- ND, respectively, were as follows: local control, 70% versus 68% (P = 0.2); local-regional control, 65% versus 69% (P = 0.1); 5-year survival, 47% versus 43% (P = 0.2); 5-year cause specific survival, 57% versus 59% (P = 0.3); severe complications, 23% versus 6% (P &amp;lt; 0.001); and fatal complications, 3.2% versus 0.8% (P &amp;lt; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS: The information in this article provides a useful benchmark for evidence-based counseling of patients with SCC of the oropharynx. The rates of local control, local-regional control, 5-year survival, and 5-year cause specific survival were similar for patients who underwent S +/- RT or RT +/- ND, whereas the rates of severe or fatal complications were significantly greater for the S +/- RT group. Furthermore, available data on the functional consequences of treatment suggest the superiority of RT +/- ND. The authors conclude that RT +/- ND is preferable for the majority of patients with SCC of the oropharynx.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 2002; JID: 0374236; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Cancer Society</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0008-543X; 0008-543X</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, Bethesda Memorial Hospital, Boynton Beach, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12115386</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/cncr.10567</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12115386</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1779</id>
<a1>Reddy,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Long-term results of radiation therapy for juvenile nasopharyngeal angiofibroma</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>May-Jun</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>172</sp>
<op>175</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Angiofibroma/diagnosis/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Disease Progression</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nasopharyngeal Neoplasms/diagnosis/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Staging</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To analyze 15 patients treated with radiation therapy for juvenile nasopharyngeal angiofibroma (JNA) between June 1975 and March 1996. MATERIALS AND METHODS: All patients had a 2.5-year minimum follow-up. All patients had advanced disease (Chandler stage III or stage IV); two thirds of the patients had intracranial extension. RESULTS: Local control after radiotherapy was obtained in 13 of 15 patients (85%). Two patients had local recurrences, and both were salvaged with surgery for an ultimate local control rate of 100%. Late complications included cataracts in 3 patients, delayed transient central nervous system (CNS) syndrome in 1 patient, and a basal cell carcinoma of the skin in 1 patient. Of 15 patients, 13 (85%) had a complete response (CR) on physical examination following radiation therapy. The median time to CR was 13 months (range, 1 to 39 months). Of 6 patients with residual disease in more than 24 months, 2 (33%) had a recurrence, whereas no patient achieving CR in less than 24 months experienced a recurrence. CONCLUSIONS: Radiotherapy is an effective treatment for advanced JNA. Tumor regression usually occurs slowly over several months. JNAs that are slow to regress (greater than 2 years) may have an increased risk of recurrence.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11351285; S0196-0709(01)65399-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1053/ajot.2001.23458</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11351285</pmid></reference></refworks>
