<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>40</id>
<a1>Azevedo,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Ferreira,V. F.</a1>
<a1>Mello,H.</a1>
<a1>Leao-Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Jabor,A. V.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Bernardino,A. M. R.</a1>
<t1>Synthesis and Biological Evaluation of  1H-Pyrazolo[3,4-b]Pyridine-5-Carboxylic acids against vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Heterocyclic communications</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<sp>427</sp>
<op>432</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>11</id>
<a1>Black,E. P.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of the Interactions among Vaccinia Virus Transcription Factors G2R, A18R, and H5R</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>245</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>313</sp>
<op>322</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>28</id>
<a1>Borges,M. B. J.</a1>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>da Silva Freire,M.</a1>
<a1>Lambert Passos,S. R.</a1>
<a1>do Nascimento,J. P.</a1>
<t1>Accuracy and repeatability of a micro plaque reduction neutralization test for vaccinia antibodies</t1>
<jf>Biologicals</jf>
<jo>Biologicals</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>105</sp>
<op>110</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>34</id>
<a1>Boyd,O.</a1>
<a1>Strahl,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Rodeffer,C.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Temperature-sensitive mutant in the vaccinia virus E6 protein produce virions that are transcriptionally inactive</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<vo>399</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>221</sp>
<op>230</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>39</id>
<a1>Boyd,O.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>The E6 protein from vaccinia virus is required for the formation of immature virions</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Apr 10</fd>
<vo>399</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>211</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Isopropyl Thiogalactoside</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Core Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>An IPTG-inducible mutant in the E6R gene of vaccinia virus was used to study the role of the E6 virion core protein in viral replication. In the absence of the inducer, the mutant exhibited a normal pattern DNA replication, concatemer resolution and late gene expression, but it showed an inhibition of virion structural protein processing it failed to produce infectious particles. Electron microscopic analysis showed that in the absence of IPTG viral morphogenesis was arrested before IV formation: crescents, aberrant or empty IV-like structures, and large aggregated virosomes were observed throughout the cytoplasm. The addition of IPTG to release a 12-h block showed that virus infectious particles could be formed in the absence of de novo DNA synthesis. Our observations show that in the absence of E6 the association of viroplasm with viral membrane crescents is impaired.</ab>
<no>CI: Published by Elsevier Inc.; GR: R01 AI055560/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Core Proteins); 367-93-1 (Isopropyl Thiogalactoside); NIHMS171036; OID: NLM: NIHMS171036 [Available on 04/10/11]; OID: NLM: PMC2830302 [Available on 04/10/11]; 2009/10/02 [received]; 2010/01/04 [revised]; 2010/01/07 [accepted]; 2010/02/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1096-0341; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20116821; S0042-6822(10)00029-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2010.01.012</do>
<wp>20100208</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20116821</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2830302</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>20</id>
<a1>Castro,A. P. V.</a1>
<a1>Carvalho,T. M. U.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<t1>Redistribution of cyclophilin A to viral factories during vaccinia virus infection and its incorporation into mature particles</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>16</is>
<sp>9052</sp>
<pb>Am Soc Microbiol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>25</id>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Traktman,P.</a1>
<t1>In a nutshell: structure and assembly of the vaccinia virion</t1>
<jf>Advances in Virus Research</jf>
<jo>Adv.Virus Res.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<sp>31</sp>
<op>124</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>12</id>
<a1>da Matta,A. D.</a1>
<a1>dos Santos,C. V. B.</a1>
<a1>Pereira,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I. C. P. P.</a1>
<a1>de Oliveira,M. R. P.</a1>
<a1>de Souza,M. C. B. V.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Ferreira,V. F.</a1>
<t1>Synthesis of novel nucleosides of 4-oxoquinoline-3-carboxylic acid analogues</t1>
<jf>Heteroatom Chemistry</jf>
<yr>1999</yr>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>197</sp>
<op>202</op>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>10</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Inhibition of vaccinia virus replication by cyclosporin A analogues correlates with their affinity for cellular cyclophilins</t1>
<jf>Journal of General Virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>339</sp>
<pb>Soc General Microbiol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>15</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<a1>Oliveira,M. F.</a1>
<a1>Massarani,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>Azathioprine inhibits vaccinia virus replication in both BSC-40 and RAG cell lines acting on different stages of virus cycle</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>300</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>79</sp>
<op>91</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>26</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<a1>Reis,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Jesus,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Lima,P. S. F.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>A PCR-based assay for detection of emerging vaccinia-like viruses isolated in Brazil</t1>
<jf>Diagnostic microbiology and infectious disease</jf>
<jo>Diagn.Microbiol.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>39</sp>
<op>46</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>13</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Esposito,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>An emergent poxvirus from humans and cattle in Rio de Janeiro State: Cantagalo virus may derive from Brazilian smallpox vaccine</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Nov 25</fd>
<vo>277</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>439</sp>
<op>449</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Brazil/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cattle Diseases/epidemiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Disease Outbreaks/veterinary</k1>
<k1>Exanthema/epidemiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/classification/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/veterinary/virology</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Smallpox Vaccine</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<ab>The biological properties of poxvirus isolates from skin lesions on dairy cows and milkers during recent exanthem episodes in Cantagalo County, Rio de Janeiro State, Brazil, were more like vaccinia virus (VV) than cowpox virus. PCR amplification of the hemagglutinin (HA) gene substantiated the isolate classification as an Old World orthopoxvirus, and alignment of the HA sequences with those of other orthopoxviruses indicated that all the isolates represented a single strain of VV, which we have designated Cantagalo virus (CTGV). HA sequences of the Brazilian smallpox vaccine strain (VV-IOC), used over 20 years ago, and CTGV showed 98.2% identity; phylogeny inference of CTGV, VV-IOC, and 12 VV strains placed VV-IOC and CTGV together in a distinct clade. Viral DNA restriction patterns and protein profiles showed a few differences between VV-IOC and CTGV. Together, the data suggested that CTGV may have derived from VV-IOC by persisting in an indigenous animal(s), accumulating polymorphisms, and now emerging in cattle and milkers as CTGV. CTGV may represent the first case of long-term persistence of vaccinia in the New World.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; CI: Copyright 2000; GENBANK/AF229247; GENBANK/AF229248; GR: R01 AI 18094/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); 0 (Smallpox Vaccine); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Biologia Molecular de Virus, Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, CCS, Rio de Janeiro, RJ 21941-900, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11080491; S0042-6822(00)90603-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.2000.0603</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11080491</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>7</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Detection of RNA-protein complex in vaccinia virus core in vitro transcription system</t1>
<jf>The Journal of general virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>73 ( Pt 5)</vo>
<is>Pt 5</is>
<sp>1243</sp>
<op>1249</op>
<k1>Micrococcal Nuclease/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Core Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The incubation of vaccinia virus cores in appropriate conditions promotes the release of core proteins into a supernatant fraction. Under transcription assay conditions core mRNAs are extruded in association with viral core proteins, however the presence of these proteins within the core particle is not essential for RNA synthesis and extrusion. The RNA-protein complex is resistant to micrococcal nuclease. Five proteins of 60K, 43K, 28K, 18K and 14.5K with RNA-binding abilities have been identified by [32P]RNA overlay protein blot assays. These proteins are likely to be a component of the viral ribonucleoprotein complex since core basic proteins with similar MrS have been identified and at least one RNA-binding protein is predicted in the vaccinia virus genome.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0077340; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Viral Core Proteins); EC 3.1.31.1 (Micrococcal Nuclease); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-1317; 0022-1317</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Biologia Molecular de Virus, Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, CCS-UFRJ, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1588325</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1588325</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>6</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Protein synthesis in vaccinia virus-infected cells. I. Effect of hypertonic shock recovery</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>123</vo>
<is>3-4</is>
<sp>295</sp>
<op>308</op>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hypertonic Solutions/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Polyribosomes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Human Hep-2 cells were submitted to hypertonic shock (210 mM NaCl) to block host protein synthesis before infection with vaccinia virus. With the start of infection, the medium isotonicity (116 mM NaCl) was restored, and the effect of viral infection on the recovery of host polyribosomes and protein synthesis was studied. Although host translation blockage was released together with infection, vaccinia virus did not affect immediately host protein synthesis. During the first hour of recovery, infected cells could perfectly rebuild the polyribosome profile and recuperate the rate of protein synthesis. Also, during recovery, formation of the initiation complex for protein synthesis was not affected by viral infection. In this period, viral mRNA and proteins were detected by slot blot and SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. The inhibitory effect of vaccinia virus on host translation was observed after the second hour of infection. These findings suggest that vaccinia virus-mediated shutoff occurs in a later period during infection, in parallel with viral mRNA accumulation in the polyribosomes and after the on-set of viral DNA replication.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7506870; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Hypertonic Solutions); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>AUSTRIA</pp>
<sn>0304-8608; 0304-8608</sn>
<ad>Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1562234</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1562234</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>36</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Proteins released from vaccinia cores are probably not involved in protein synthesis inhibition in vitro</t1>
<jf>Brazilian journal of medical and biological research = Revista brasileira de pesquisas medicas e biologicas / Sociedade Brasileira de Biofisica ...[et al.]</jf>
<jo>Braz.J.Med.Biol.Res.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>124</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Guanosine Triphosphate/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Protein Synthesis Inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleotides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Core Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>1. It is known that vaccinia core proteins are released into the supernatant fraction when cores are incubated under appropriate conditions. When prepared in the absence of viral transcription this fraction inhibits in vitro protein synthesis. 2. We show here that after incubation, the cores loose the capability to inhibit protein synthesis. Furthermore, we show that no inhibition of translation is observed with supernatant fractions prepared from transcribing cores. 3. SDS-PAGE analysis of the supernatant fraction of cores obtained in the presence and absence of viral transcription indicated that their protein composition is similar and that approximately 17 peptides are released from the cores and that 4 are phosphorylated. 4. We conclude that the proteins associated with vaccinia cores and released in the presence of ribonucleotides are not involved in protein synthesis inhibition.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8112917; 0 (Protein Synthesis Inhibitors); 0 (Ribonucleotides); 0 (Viral Core Proteins); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); 86-01-1 (Guanosine Triphosphate); ppublish</no>
<pp>BRAZIL</pp>
<sn>0100-879X; 0100-879X</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Biologia Molecular de Virus, Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1339506</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1339506</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>5</id>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Vaccinia core transcription prevents in vitro depolymerization of polyribosomes in rabbit reticulocyte lysate</t1>
<jf>Brazilian journal of medical and biological research = Revista brasileira de pesquisas medicas e biologicas / Sociedade Brasileira de Biofisica ...[et al.]</jf>
<jo>Braz.J.Med.Biol.Res.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>763</sp>
<op>766</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Polyribosomes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Protein Synthesis Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Reticulocytes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<ab>When a rabbit reticulocyte lysate is incubated in the presence of vaccinia cores, protein synthesis is impaired at the level of the initiation step and the polyribosomes are depolymerized. However, when the same system is coupled with virus transcription: a) protein synthesis is restored, b) the initiation step is not inhibited, and c) the polyribosomes are not disaggregated. A viral factor activated in the absence of virus transcription and not activated when RNA synthesis occurs may be involved in the early mechanism of protein synthesis inhibition by vaccinia virus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8112917; 0 (Protein Synthesis Inhibitors); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>BRAZIL</pp>
<sn>0100-879X; 0100-879X</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Virologia Molecular, Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 3455255</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3455255</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1</id>
<a1>de Castro,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Carvalho,J. F. O.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>de Castro,F. T.</a1>
<t1>Nalidixic Acid and Macromolecular Metabolism in Tetrahymena pyriformis: Effects on Protein Synthesis</t1>
<jf>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</jf>
<jo>Antimicrob.Agents Chemother.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>487</sp>
<pb>Am Soc Microbiol</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>23</id>
<a1>de Oliveira,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Alves,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Pinto,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Pereira Hde,S.</a1>
<a1>Leao-Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>de Frugulhetti,I. C.</a1>
<a1>Ferreira,V. F.</a1>
<a1>de Souza,M. C.</a1>
<t1>Synthesis and antiviral activities of new pyrazolo[4,3-c]quinolin-3-ones and their ribonucleoside derivatives</t1>
<jf>Nucleosides, nucleotides &amp; nucleic acids</jf>
<jo>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>735</sp>
<op>748</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/chemical synthesis/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 1, Human/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Pyrazoles/chemistry/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Quinolines/chemistry/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleosides/chemical synthesis/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>Several new pyrazolo[4,3-c]quinolin-3-one ribonucleosides (5a-g) and their corresponding heterocycle moieties (3a-g) were synthesized and evaluated against vaccinia virus (VV) and herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1). The derivatives 3c and 3d showed modest inhibitory activity against vaccinia virus reaching 70% at a concentration of 100 microM. All heterocyclic compounds (3a-f) showed a modest inhibition against HSV-1, reaching the maximal inhibitory effect around 20-30%. The antiviral effects of most of the pyrazolo[4,3-c]quinolin-3-one ribonucleosides (5a-f) on VV and HSV were not impressive.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100892832; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (Pyrazoles); 0 (Quinolines); 0 (Ribonucleosides); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1525-7770; 1525-7770</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Quimica Organica, Instituto de Quimica, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. gqocica@vm.uff.br</ad>
<an>PMID: 15281362</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15281362</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>37</id>
<a1>de Souza Pereira,H.</a1>
<a1>Leao-Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Teixeira,V. L.</a1>
<a1>Cavalcanti,D. N.</a1>
<a1>da Costa,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Diaz,R.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I. C.</a1>
<t1>Effects of diterpenes isolated from the Brazilian marine alga Dictyota menstrualis on HIV-1 reverse transcriptase</t1>
<jf>Planta Medica</jf>
<jo>Planta Med.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1019</sp>
<op>1024</op>
<k1>Algae, Brown/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Anti-HIV Agents/chemistry/isolation &amp; purification/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Avian myeloblastosis virus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Diterpenes/chemistry/isolation &amp; purification/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>HIV Reverse Transcriptase/drug effects/genetics</k1>
<k1>Moloney murine leukemia virus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>RNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors/chemistry/isolation &amp; purification/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/drug effects</k1>
<ab>It has been recently demonstrated that HIV-1 reverse transcriptase is the target of two diterpenes, (6 R)-6-hydroxydichotoma-3,14-diene-1,17-dial (compound 1) and (6 R)-6-acetoxydichotoma-3,14-diene-1,17-dial (compound 2), that inhibit HIV-1 replication in vitro. In this work, the effects of both diterpenes on the kinetic properties of the recombinant HIV-1 reverse transcriptase (RT) enzyme were evaluated. RNA-dependent DNA-polymerase (RDDP) activity assays demonstrated that both diterpenes behave as non-competitive inhibitors with respect to dTTP and uncompetitive inhibitors with respect to poly(rA).oligo(dT) template primers. The K(i) values obtained for compounds 1 and 2 were 10 and 35 microM, respectively. Neither of these diterpenes affected the DNA-dependent DNA-polymerase (DDDP) activity of the HIV-1 RT. The RDDP activities of AMV-RT and MMLV-RT enzymes were also inhibited by compounds 1 and 2. In contrast to the HIV-1 enzyme, the DDDP activities of AMV-RT and MMLV-RT enzymes were significantly reduced by compound 1. Taken together, our results demonstrate that compound 1 is a more effective inhibitor of the viral reverse transcriptases from HIV-1, AMV and MMLV than compound 2. The kinetic behavior analyses of the HIV-1 RT demonstrate that both diterpenes have similar mechanisms of inhibition of RDDP activity.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0066751; 0 ((6 R)-6-acetoxydichotoma-3,14-diene-1,17-dial); 0 ((6 R)-6-hydroxydichotoma-3,14-diene-1,17-dial); 0 (Anti-HIV Agents); 0 (Diterpenes); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 2.7.7.49 (HIV Reverse Transcriptase); EC 2.7.7.49 (RNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); EC 2.7.7.7 (DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); ppublish</no>
<pp>Germany</pp>
<sn>0032-0943; 0032-0943</sn>
<ad>Departamento de Biologia Celular e Molecular/Programa de Neuroimunologia, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niteroi - RJ, Brasil. helena@biologia.ufrj.br</ad>
<an>PMID: 16320202</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1055/s-2005-873113</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16320202</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>16</id>
<a1>deOliveira,M. R. P.</a1>
<a1>Torres,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Garden,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Santos,C. V. B.</a1>
<a1>Alves,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Pinto,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Pereira,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Ferreira,L. R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I. C. P. P.</a1>
<t1>Synthesis and antiviral evaluation of isatin ribonucleosides</t1>
<jf>Nucleosides, Nucleotides and Nucleic Acids</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>825</sp>
<op>835</op>
<pb>Taylor &amp; Francis</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>32</id>
<a1>Jesus,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<t1>In vitro activity of cidofovir against the emerging Cantagalo virus and the smallpox vaccine strain IOC</t1>
<jf>International journal of antimicrobial agents</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Antimicrob.Agents</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>75</sp>
<op>79</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>33</id>
<a1>Jesus,D. M.</a1>
<a1>Costa,L. T.</a1>
<a1>Goncalves,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Achete,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Attias,M.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<t1>Cidofovir inhibits genome encapsidation and affects morphogenesis during the replication of vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>11477</sp>
<op>11490</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cytosine/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Phosphonic Acids/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Assembly/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>Cidofovir (CDV) is one of the most effective antiorthopoxvirus drugs, and it is widely accepted that viral DNA replication is the main target of its activity. In the present study, we report a detailed analysis of CDV effects on the replicative cycles of distinct vaccinia virus (VACV) strains: Cantagalo virus, VACV-IOC, and VACV-WR. We show that despite the approximately 90% inhibition of production of virus progeny, virus DNA accumulation was reduced only 30%, and late gene expression and genome resolution were unaltered. The level of proteolytic cleavage of the major core proteins was diminished in CDV-treated cells. Electron microscopic analysis of virus-infected cells in the presence of CDV revealed reductions as great as 3.5-fold in the number of mature forms of virus particles, along with a 3.2-fold increase in the number of spherical immature particles. A detailed analysis of purified virions recovered from CDV-treated cells demonstrated the accumulation of unprocessed p4a and p4b and nearly 67% inhibition of DNA encapsidation. However, these effects of CDV on virus morphogenesis resulted from a primary effect on virus DNA synthesis, which led to later defects in genome encapsidation and virus assembly. Analysis of virus DNA by atomic force microscopy revealed that viral cytoplasmic DNA synthesized in the presence of CDV had an altered structure, forming aggregates with increased strand overlapping not observed in the absence of the drug. These aberrant DNA aggregations were not encapsidated into virus particles.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100504; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Phosphonic Acids); 0 (Viral Proteins); 113852-37-2 (cidofovir); 71-30-7 (Cytosine); OID: NLM: PMC2772695; 2009/09/02 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5514; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Biologia Molecular de Virus, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19726515; JVI.01061-09 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.01061-09</do>
<wp>20090902</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19726515</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2772695</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>27</id>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>The vaccinia virus E8R gene product is required for formation of transcriptionally active virions</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>367</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>398</sp>
<op>412</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>24</id>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Greco,F. A. B.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>An alternative genetic method to test essential vaccinia virus early genes</t1>
<jf>Journal of virological methods</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.Methods</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>115</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>31</sp>
<op>40</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>29</id>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>D&#39;Costa,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Bainbridge,T. W.</a1>
<a1>Prins,C.</a1>
<a1>Strahl,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Shatzer,A. N.</a1>
<a1>Brinker,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Kay,N. E.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Marker rescue mapping of the combined Condit/Dales collection of temperature-sensitive vaccinia virus mutants</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>375</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>213</sp>
<op>222</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>21</id>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Strahl,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Temperature-sensitive mutants in the vaccinia virus 4b virion structural protein assemble malformed, transcriptionally inactive intracellular mature virions</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>330</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>127</sp>
<op>146</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>8</id>
<a1>Leão Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Moura Neto,V.</a1>
<t1>Rearrangement of intermediate filament network of BHK-21 cells infected with vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>138</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>273</sp>
<op>285</op>
<pb>Springer</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>14</id>
<a1>Leão Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Paes-De-Carvalho,R.</a1>
<a1>De Mello,F. G.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>Inhibition of vaccinia virus replication by adenosine in BSC-40 cells: involvement of A 2 receptor-mediated PKA activation</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>147</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1407</sp>
<op>1423</op>
<pb>Springer</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3</id>
<a1>Lobo,D. S.</a1>
<a1>Rebello,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>Core transcription restores in vitro inhibition of protein synthesis induced by vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Gene Structure and Expression</jf>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>868</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>183</sp>
<op>189</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>30</id>
<a1>Morales,I.</a1>
<a1>Carbajal,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Bohn,S.</a1>
<a1>Holzer,D.</a1>
<a1>Kato,S. E. M.</a1>
<a1>Greco,F. A. B.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Locker,J. K.</a1>
<t1>The Vaccinia Virus F11L Gene Product Facilitates Cell Detachment and Promotes Migration</t1>
<jf>Traffic</jf>
<jo>Traffic</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1283</sp>
<op>1298</op>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>41</id>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>Poxviridae</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<a2>Oliveira,L. H. S.</a2>
<t2>Virologia Humana</t2>
<pb>Cultura Medica</pb>
<pp>Rio de Janeiro, Brasil</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2</id>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>Polyamines stimulate DNA-dependent RNA synthesis catalyzed by vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Gene Structure and Expression</jf>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>826</vo>
<is>2-3</is>
<sp>113</sp>
<op>120</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>31</id>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<t1>When good vaccines go wild: Feral Orthopoxvirus in developing countries and beyond</t1>
<jf>The Journal of Infection in Developing Countries</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>03</is>
<sp>156</sp>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>35</id>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Keller,S. J.</a1>
<t1>Phosphorylation of vaccinia virus core proteins during transcription in vitro</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>2555</sp>
<op>2561</op>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen-Ion Concentration</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Phosphorylation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Core Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The phosphorylation of vaccinia virus core proteins has been studied in vitro during viral transcription. The incorporation of [gamma-32P]ATP into protein is linear for the first 2 min of the reaction, whereas incorporation of [3H]UTP into RNA lags for 1 to 2 min before linear synthesis. At least 12 different proteins are phosphorylated on autoradiograms of acrylamide gels, and the majority of label is associated with low-molecular-weight proteins. If the transcription reaction is reduced by dropping the pH to 7 from its optimal of 8.5, two proteins (70 and 80 kDa) are no longer phosphorylated. RNA isolated from the pH 7 transcription reaction hybridized primarily to the vaccinia virus HindIII DNA fragments D to F, whereas the transcripts synthesized at pH 8.5 hybridized to almost all of the HindIII-digested vaccinia virus DNA fragments. The differences between the pH 7.0 and 8.5 transcription reactions in phosphorylation and transcription could be eliminated by preincubating the viral cores with 2 mM ATP. In sum, the results suggest that the phosphorylation of the 70- and 80-kDa peptides may contribute to the regulation of early transcription.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Core Proteins); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); OID: NLM: PMC240612; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2016772</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2016772</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC240612</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>18</id>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Tuyama,M.</a1>
<a1>Kato,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Castro,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Njaine,B.</a1>
<a1>Peralta,R. H.</a1>
<a1>Peralta,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Barroso,P. F.</a1>
<t1>Accidental infection of laboratory worker with vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Emerging infectious diseases</jf>
<jo>Emerg.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>724</sp>
<op>726</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Viral/blood</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin G/analysis</k1>
<k1>Laboratory Infection/diagnosis/etiology/virology</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Polymorphism, Restriction Fragment Length</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<ab>We report the accidental needlestick inoculation of a laboratory worker with vaccinia virus. Although the patient had previously been vaccinated against smallpox, severe lesions appeared on the fingers. Western blot and polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism were used to analyze the virus recovered from the lesions. The vaccinia virus-specific immunoglobulin G levels were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Our study supports the need for vaccination for laboratory workers that routinely handle orthopoxvirus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9508155; 0 (Antibodies, Viral); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Immunoglobulin G); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1080-6040; 1080-6040</sn>
<ad>Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro Brazil. nissin@biof.ufrj.br</ad>
<an>PMID: 12781015</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12781015</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>9</id>
<a1>Pereira,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Bernardino,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Nogueira,C.</a1>
<a1>Gomes,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Romeiro,G.</a1>
<a1>Chaves,A.</a1>
<a1>Ferreira,V. F.</a1>
<a1>Caetano,M. V.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I. C. P.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<t1>Inibiçäo seletiva das atividades das enzimas transcriptase reversa do vírus HIV-1 e DNA polimerases humanas por derivados dipirazolo-piridina; Selective inhibition of reverse transcriptase enzyme activity of HIV-1 virus and human polymerases DNA by dipirazolo-pyridines derivatives</t1>
<jo>J. Bras. Doenças Sex Trans</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>14</sp>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>22</id>
<a1>Pereira,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Leao-Ferreira,L. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Teixeira,V. L.</a1>
<a1>Cavalcanti,D. N.</a1>
<a1>Costa,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Diaz,R.</a1>
<a1>Frugulhetti,I.</a1>
<t1>Antiviral activity of diterpenes isolated from the Brazilian marine alga Dictyota menstrualis against human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1)</t1>
<jf>Antiviral Research</jf>
<jo>Antiviral Res.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>69</sp>
<op>76</op>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>19</id>
<a1>Reis,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Costa,L. V.</a1>
<a1>Cavalcanti,E. D. C.</a1>
<a1>Giambiagi-deMarval,M.</a1>
<a1>Semêdo,L.</a1>
<a1>Coelho,R. R. R.</a1>
<a1>Moussatché,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R. A.</a1>
<t1>Protein synthesis inhibitory activity in culture filtrates from new strains of Streptomyces isolated from Brazilian tropical soils</t1>
<jf>Letters in applied microbiology</jf>
<jo>Lett.Appl.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>138</sp>
<op>143</op>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons</pb>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>38</id>
<a1>Reis,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<a1>Damaso,C. R.</a1>
<t1>FK506, a secondary metabolite produced by Streptomyces, presents a novel antiviral activity against Orthopoxvirus infection in cell culture</t1>
<jf>Journal of applied microbiology</jf>
<jo>J.Appl.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1373</sp>
<op>1380</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibiosis</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western/methods</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Orthopoxvirus/drug effects/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Streptomyces/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tacrolimus/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>AIMS: To investigate the antiviral potential of the macrolide FK506, produced by Streptomyces tsukubaensis, against Orthopoxvirus infection in cell culture, and determine the replicative stage of viral cycle affected by the treatment. METHODS AND RESULTS: Cell lines were infected with different Orthopoxviruses and treated with FK506. The macrolide inhibited the replication of the prototypic Orthopoxvirus, vaccinia virus strain WR, with an IC50 of 12.05 micromol l(-1). Progeny production of other Orthopoxviruses was also inhibited by FK506 at noncytotoxic concentrations, as evaluated by the neutral-red uptake assay and metabolic labelling of cellular proteins. By Western blot assay, we detected a severe inhibition (approximately 87.6% +/- 2.78%) of VV strain WR post-replicative protein synthesis. A similar reduction of virus DNA accumulation, as observed by slot-blot assay, probably accounts for the subsequent inhibition of virus late proteins. CONCLUSIONS: The macrolide FK506, isolated from S. tsukubaensis, presents a novel anti-poxvirus activity, probably targeting the stage of DNA replication during Orthopoxvirus infection. SIGNIFICANCE AND IMPACT OF THE STUDY: The secondary metabolite FK506, isolated from the culture filtrate of S. tsukubaensis, shows a pleiotropic range of activities, and might be a valuable tool as a lead structure in the generation of non-immunosuppressant analogues with strong anti-poxvirus activity.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9706280; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA, Viral); 109581-93-3 (Tacrolimus); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1364-5072; 1364-5072</sn>
<ad>Laboratorio de Biologia Molecular de Virus, Instituto de Biofisica Carlos Chagas Filho, CCS, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16696686; JAM2855 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.02855.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16696686</pmid></reference></refworks>
