
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1581</id>
<a1>Abrams,R.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P.</a1>
<t1>Fetal hearing</t1>
<jf>Developmental psychobiology</jf>
<jo>Dev.Psychobiol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>3</op>
<k1>Autoradiography/methods</k1>
<k1>Brain/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/physiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Glucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hearing/physiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inferior Colliculi/metabolism</k1>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0164074; 50-99-7 (Glucose); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0012-1630; 0012-1630</sn>
<an>PMID: 9664167; 10.1002/(SICI)1098-2302(199807)33:1&lt;1::AID-DEV1&gt;3.0.CO;2-P [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Letter; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9664167</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1580</id>
<a1>Abrams,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Schwab,M.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Bauer,R.</a1>
<a1>Bludau,T.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Vestibular caloric responses and behavioral state in the fetal sheep</t1>
<jf>International journal of pediatric otorhinolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Pediatr.Otorhinolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Sep 15</fd>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>59</sp>
<op>68</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal/physiology</k1>
<k1>Caloric Tests/methods</k1>
<k1>Electroencephalography</k1>
<k1>Electrooculography</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Nystagmus, Physiologic/physiology</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Reflex, Vestibulo-Ocular/physiology</k1>
<k1>Saccades/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<k1>Sheep/embryology</k1>
<k1>Sleep, REM/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vestibule, Labyrinth/embryology/physiology</k1>
<ab>Functional activity of the vestibular system in relation to behavioral state of fetal sheep in utero was studied by cooling and heating of the fetal middle ear and skin (control) with implanted copper-tube heat exchangers. Eye movements and fetal cortical activity were assessed before, during, and after 2 min irrigations with water at 6, 46, or 39.5 degrees C (isothermic). Cold water induced slow-phase eye movements toward the irrigated ear followed by saccades toward the opposite ear after a delay of several seconds. The direction of the response reversed with warm water, and saccades were absent during irrigation with body-temperature water. Cold-water irrigations of the skin over the jaw did not result in nystagmus. Arousal-like responses were elicited with thermal stimulation of the ear or facial skin while the fetus was in either rapid eye movement (REM) or non-REM states. Circulation of 39.5 degrees C water through the ear also produced arousal-like responses, possibly due to turbulence-induced noises in the heat exchanger or slight deviations between the irrigation temperature and the actual fetal inner ear temperature. These results suggest that mechanisms responsible for saccade suppression during depressed levels of consciousness (i.e. sleep) are inactive in utero. Fetal behavioral state responsiveness to vestibular and somatosensory thermal stimulation may be of great significance, especially in the premature neonate.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8003603; ppublish</no>
<pp>IRELAND</pp>
<sn>0165-5876; 0165-5876</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA. abramsrm@obgyn.med.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 9804021; S0165587698000883 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM; S</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9804021</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1562</id>
<a1>Adamczyk,M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Selective vestibular ablation by KTP laser in endolymphatic hydrops</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>111</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1057</sp>
<op>1062</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Endolymphatic Hydrops/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Epithelium/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory/pathology</k1>
<k1>Laser Therapy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Meniere Disease/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES AND HYPOTHESIS: Vertigo, the cause of disability in many patients with Meniere&amp;#39;s disease, may be the result of the effects of endolymphatic hydrops on the semicircular canals. We hypothesize that intractable vertigo may be controlled by destruction of the semicircular canal neuroepithelium using visible light lasers without the need for extensive fenestration of the bony labyrinth. This study was designed to assess the cochlear effects of potassium titanyl phosphate (KTP) laser-assisted triple semicircular canal ablation (TSCA) in endolymphatic hydrops. STUDY DESIGN: Randomized, prospective, and controlled. METHODS: Forty-one adult guinea pigs underwent either a unilateral endolymphatic duct occlusion to induce hydrops or a sham procedure. Ten weeks after induction of the hydrops, a KTP laser-assisted TSCA or a sham surgery was performed. RESULTS: Electrocochleographic thresholds to clicks and tone-bursts (2-20 kHz) did not change significantly up to 4 weeks after TSCA in hydropic ears. Cross-sectional histology confirmed the presence of hydrops and the ablation of the semicircular canals. Cochlear whole-mounts for hair cell counts showed no significant loss of outer or inner hair cells in hydropic ears treated with TSCA. CONCLUSION: KTP laser-assisted TSCA can be performed in the guinea pig model of endolymphatic hydrops without significant loss of hearing. Evaluation of this technique may be warranted in patients with intractable Meniere&amp;#39;s disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11404621</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200106000-00023</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11404621</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1571</id>
<a1>Adamczyk,M.</a1>
<a1>Appleton,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Parell,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Stapedectomy in the guinea pig</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>581</sp>
<op>584</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/pathology</k1>
<k1>Feasibility Studies</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Laser Therapy</k1>
<k1>Stapes/pathology</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery/methods</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>Stapedectomy has traditionally been studied in the feline model. Ethical considerations and costs have made this model less feasible for ongoing research. The purpose of this study was to examine the guinea pig as a model for research on stapedectomy. Technical difficulties included limited exposure and small dimensions of the ossicles. The surgical technique with and without the use of a CO(2) laser and the relevant anatomy of the guinea pig middle ear are described.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10547474; S0194599899005033 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10547474</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1608</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P.</a1>
<a1>Jorge,J.</a1>
<a1>Feniman,M.</a1>
<a1>Piazentin-Penna,S.</a1>
<a1>Dutka-Souza,J.</a1>
<a1>Seagle,B.</a1>
<a1>Williams,W.</a1>
<a1>Nackashi,J.</a1>
<a1>Boggs,S.</a1>
<a1>Graciano,M.</a1>
<a1>Souza,T.</a1>
<a1>Neto,J.</a1>
<a1>Garla,L.</a1>
<a1>Silva,M.</a1>
<a1>Marques,I.</a1>
<a1>Borgo,H.</a1>
<a1>Martinelli,A.</a1>
<a1>Shuster,J.</a1>
<a1>Pimentel,M.</a1>
<a1>Zimmerman,M.</a1>
<a1>Bento-Goncalves,C.</a1>
<a1>Kemker,J.</a1>
<a1>McGorray,S.</a1>
<a1>Pegoraro-Krook,M. I.</a1>
<t1>Otologic and Audiologic Outcomes with the Furlow and Von Langenbeck with Intravelar Veloplasty Palatoplasties in Unilateral Cleft Lip and Palate</t1>
<jf>The Cleft palate-craniofacial journal : official publication of the American Cleft Palate-Craniofacial Association</jf>
<jo>Cleft Palate.Craniofac.J.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jun 10</fd>
<ab>Abstract Objective: Cleft palate increases the risk of chronic middle ear disease and hearing loss. The goal of this report was to determine which of two palate surgeries and timing of palate surgery were associated with better otologic and audiologic outcomes in children with unilateral cleft lip and palate (UCLP) at 5 to 6 years of age. Design: Subjects were randomly assigned to the von Langenbeck with intravelar veloplasty or Furlow palate repair, to palate surgery at 9 - 12 months or 15 - 18 months of age, and to the Spina or Millard lip repair. Setting: Centralized, tertiary care craniofacial treatment center Patients: 673 infants with UCLP Interventions: Palate and lip were repaired using established techniques. Serial otoscopic and audiometric evaluations were performed. Main Outcome Measures: Hearing and otoscopic findings at 5 to 6 years old. Results: 370 children were available for analysis. Hearing and need for tympanostomy tube placement did not differ by palatoplasty, age at palatoplasty, cheiloplasty, or surgeon. Risk of developing cholesteatoma or perforation was higher with Millard cheiloplasty (odds ratio 5.1, 95% CI=1.44 - 18.11, p = 0.012). Type and age at palatoplasty were not significantly associated with either the rate of developing these sequelae or the rate of achieving bilaterally normal hearing and ear examinations. Conclusions: Type of palatoplasty did not influence otologic and audiologic outcomes in 5 to 6 year old children with UCLP. The potential influence of lip repair on otologic outcomes warrants further investigation. Key Words: cleft palate, ear, hearing, clinical trial.</ab>
<no>JID: 9102566; aheadofprint</no>
<sn>1545-1569; 1055-6656</sn>
<ad>1 University of Florida.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20536371</an>
<la>ENG</la>
<sf>JOURNAL ARTICLE</sf>
<do>10.1597/10-009</do>
<wp>20100610</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20536371</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1616</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Auditory and vestibular systems</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<is>10</is>
<sp>455</sp>
<op>455-492</op>
<k1>Neurophysiology</k1>
<k1>Nervous System Physiology</k1>
<k1>Neurosciences</k1>
<no>Stephen E. Nadeau ... [et al.]. : Stephen E. Nadeau ... [et al.].; 50011 Includes index.</no>
<a2>Nadeau,Stephen E.</a2>
<t2>Medical neuroscience</t2>
<pb>Saunders</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia</pp>
<sn>0721602495; 0721602495; 9780721602493</sn>
<cn>WL102M489 2004 (HSC LIBRARY, Reserves General Collection)</cn>
<db>UF Library Catalog</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1615</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation and treatment of recurrent post-tympanostomy otorrhea</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>2004</fd>
<is>53</is>
<sp>266</sp>
<op>266-270</op>
<k1>Otitis media</k1>
<k1>Otitis media -- Treatment</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media -- therapy</k1>
<no>Cuneyt M. Alper, Charles D. Bluestone. : Cuneyt M. Alper, Charles D. Bluestone.; Alternate title: Otitis media.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Alper,Cuneyt M.</a2><a2> Bluestone,Charles D.</a2>
<t2>Advanced therapy in otitis media</t2>
<pb>B C Decker</pb>
<pp>Hamilton, Ont. ; London</pp>
<sn>1550092014</sn>
<cn>WV232.A456a 2004 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY General Collection); WV232.A456a 2004 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY Shelved on CD shelf)</cn>
<db>UF Library Catalog</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1614</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Otolaryngologic treatment for individuals with oral clefts</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<is>30</is>
<sp>397</sp>
<op>397-407</op>
<k1>Cleft lip</k1>
<k1>Cleft palate</k1>
<no>edited by Diego F. Wyszynski. : edited by Diego F. Wyszynski.; Alternate title: Cleft lip &amp;amp; palate; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Wyszynski,Diego F.</a2>
<t2>Cleft lip and palate : from origin to treatment</t2>
<pb>Oxford University Press</pb>
<pp>Oxford ; New York</pp>
<sn>0195139062 (alk. paper)</sn>
<cn>WV440.C62152 2002 (HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<db>UF Library catalog</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1622</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Quality of life affects for facial paralysis</t1>
<yr>2001</yr>
<k1>Cherry Blossom Conference</k1>
<no>ID: 47838959</no>
<a2>Shelton,Clough</a2>
<t2>Update on facial nerve disorders : 1999 Cherry Blossom Conference</t2>
<pb>American Academy of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</pb>
<pp>Alexandria, VA</pp>
<sn>1567720382 9781567720389</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1578</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Update on vertigo management</t1>
<jf>Comprehensive therapy</jf>
<jo>Compr.Ther.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>5</sp>
<op>12</op>
<k1>Clinical Protocols</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Medical History Taking</k1>
<k1>Physical Examination</k1>
<k1>Vertigo/diagnosis/etiology/physiopathology/therapy</k1>
<ab>Over the past decade, the treatment of vertigo has shifted from medical and surgical modalities in favor of physical therapy. When more aggressive treatment is necessary, patients may be treated with less invasive surgical modalities. This article provides an overview of recent advances.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 7605837; RF: 25; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0098-8243; 0098-8243</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9987587</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9987587</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1587</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Abrams,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Schwab,M.</a1>
<a1>Bauer,R.</a1>
<t1>Vestibular function in the fetal sheep</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>571</sp>
<op>575</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Temperature</k1>
<k1>Brain/embryology</k1>
<k1>Caloric Tests/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Cold Temperature/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Copper</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Electrodes, Implanted</k1>
<k1>Electrooculography/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Embryonic and Fetal Development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Eye Movements/physiology</k1>
<k1>Face/innervation</k1>
<k1>Fetal Organ Maturity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Gestational Age</k1>
<k1>Hot Temperature/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Irrigation</k1>
<k1>Nystagmus, Physiologic/physiology</k1>
<k1>Saccades/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<k1>Skin/innervation</k1>
<k1>Vestibule, Labyrinth/embryology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Water/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<ab>Little is known about the functional development of the vestibular system before birth. The purpose of this study was to determine whether vestibular response to caloric stimulation could be elicited in the fetal sheep in utero. Late gestational fetal sheep (n = 6) were instrumented through a midline hysterotomy. Copper caloric probes were inserted into the right bulla and beneath the left facial skin. Electrodes were placed in the skull for monitoring of electro-ocular activity. At least 3 days after surgery the probes were irrigated with water (100 ml/minute) at body temperature, 46 degrees C, and 6 degrees C. Cold water infusion of the bulla consistently produced well-recognized, slow-phase deviations followed by saccades directed contralaterally, findings consistent with vestibular nystagmus. The direction of the response reversed with warm water irrigation. The response was absent with irrigation at fetal body temperature. Only random eye movements were observed in response to caloric stimulation of the facial skin, regardless of water temperature. These results demonstrate that the sheep vestibular system is functioning prenatally. The importance of vestibular function for normal fetal brain maturation may be revealed in future studies using this animal model.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 8508176; 7440-50-8 (Copper); 7732-18-5 (Water); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9591852; S0194599898001429 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9591852</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1569</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Adamczyk,M.</a1>
<a1>Appleton,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Parell,G. J.</a1>
<t1>Inner ear barotrauma after stapedectomy in the guinea pig</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>109</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>1991</sp>
<op>1995</op>
<k1>Acoustic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold/physiology</k1>
<k1>Barotrauma/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Diving/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/injuries/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The safety of scuba diving after stapedectomy is controversial. Stapedectomy is thought to predispose to inner ear barotrauma (e.g., perilymph fistula); however, many individuals continue to scuba dive following stapedectomy without ill effects. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the cochlear effects of barotrauma, similar to that experienced with scuba diving, on inner ears previously treated with stapedectomy. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, controlled. METHODS: Sixteen Hartley albino guinea pigs underwent unilateral total stapedectomy followed by hyperbaric dives on 5 consecutive days, beginning 3 weeks after stapedectomy. Cochlear effects were determined using click and tone-pip evoked electrocochleographic thresholds and cochlear hair cell counts. RESULTS: Mean auditory thresholds increased by 29 dB after stapedectomy (P &amp;lt; .001), then remained stable thereafter. Mean thresholds in both the operated and control ears did not change with hyperbaric dives. Evidence of middle ear barotrauma (e.g., hemorrhage or tympanic membrane perforation) was observed in eight poststapedectomy ears and five control ears, but none demonstrated significant threshold elevation greater than or equal to 10 dB. Hair cell counts were not different between operated and control ears. CONCLUSIONS: Stapedectomy does not appear to predispose to cochlear sequelae in the guinea pig model of diving-related barotrauma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10591361</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM; S</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-199912000-00018</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10591361</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1566</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Ahmadi,A.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal activity of common reagents for insect foreign bodies of the ear</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>111</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>15</sp>
<op>20</op>
<k1>Acetic Acid/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Anesthetics, Local/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Infective Agents, Local/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Bees</k1>
<k1>Beetles</k1>
<k1>Chlorhexidine/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Cocaine/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Cockroaches</k1>
<k1>Detergents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal</k1>
<k1>Ethanol/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Foreign Bodies/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen Peroxide/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Insects</k1>
<k1>Lidocaine/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Linear Models</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Saline Solution, Hypertonic/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Single-Blind Method</k1>
<k1>Solvents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Statistics, Nonparametric</k1>
<k1>Tetracaine/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Ticks</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Videotape Recording</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Insects commonly present as painful and distressing foreign bodies of the external ear canal. Removing live insects can be challenging, especially for primary care physicians who have limited equipment. The purpose of this study is to compare the insecticidal activity of commonly available preparations for insects that are most frequently recovered from ear canals: cockroaches (German and American), ticks, beetles, and honeybees. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, blinded. METHODS: One hundred seventy insects of each species were placed in test tubes and submerged in 17 test preparations (10 tubes per preparation, 1 insect per test tube). Insect activity was stimulated by agitation of the test tube. Responses were monitored, and the time until death was measured. RESULTS: Most test preparations exhibited some insecticidal activity against most insect species. Ticks were completely resistant to all of the test reagents. Ethanol killed the American cockroaches (mean time, 32.6 s), German cockroaches (mean time, 29.6 s), and honeybees (mean time, 19.6 s) the most rapidly. Conclusion: Many commonly available reagents may be used to kill or immobilize insect foreign bodies of the ear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; 0 (Anesthetics, Local); 0 (Anti-Infective Agents, Local); 0 (Detergents); 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Saline Solution, Hypertonic); 0 (Solvents); 137-58-6 (Lidocaine); 50-36-2 (Cocaine); 55-56-1 (Chlorhexidine); 64-17-5 (Ethanol); 64-19-7 (Acetic Acid); 7722-84-1 (Hydrogen Peroxide); 94-24-6 (Tetracaine); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11192884</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200101000-00003</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11192884</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1520</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Baratelli,R.</a1>
<t1>Cochlear implant integrity after adenoidectomy with Coblation and monopolar electrosurgery</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>9</sp>
<op>12</op>
<k1>Adenoidectomy/methods</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Catheter Ablation/methods</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Electrosurgery/methods</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Conventional electrosurgical adenoidectomy has been deemed contraindicated in subjects with cochlear implants (CIs) because of risk to the CI and the auditory neurons. No published studies have evaluated the safety of electrosurgical adenoidectomy techniques with CIs. The goal of this study was to compare the impact of monopolar electrosurgery and Coblation radiofrequency bipolar electrosurgery on CI integrity. METHODS: Twelve fresh, cadaveric pigs received unilateral CIs, then the nasopharynx was treated for 15 to 30 minutes with continuous monopolar electrosurgery or Coblation. CIs were tested by the manufacturer for device integrity before and after treatment. RESULTS: Integrity was maintained in all CIs treated with either monopolar or Coblation electrosurgery. CONCLUSIONS: Although the safety of electrosurgical adenoidectomy after CI placement remains unproven, these observations suggest that judicious use of conventional monopolar and Coblation electrosurgery in adenoidectomy does not convey a serious risk to CI integrity. Theoretical considerations favor the use of Coblation over monopolar electrosurgery in CI recipients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; 2006/04/16 [received]; 2006/05/02 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu &lt;antonpj@ent.ufl.edu&gt;</ad>
<an>PMID: 17162123; S0196-0709(06)00094-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.amjoto.2006.05.001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17162123</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1597</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Bouchard,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Kartush,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Carbon dioxide laser occlusion of the guinea pig posterior semicircular canal</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>113</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>453</sp>
<op>458</op>
<k1>Acoustic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Action Potentials</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Carbon Dioxide</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/physiology</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/surgery</k1>
<k1>Evoked Potentials, Auditory</k1>
<k1>Feasibility Studies</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fibrosis</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing</k1>
<k1>Laser Coagulation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/pathology</k1>
<k1>Petrous Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Tampons, Surgical</k1>
<k1>Vestibule, Labyrinth/surgery</k1>
<k1>Waxes</k1>
<ab>Preservation of hearing is possible with selective ablation of the vestibular system and mechanical occlusion of the semicircular canals. Complete ablation of all three canals would improve exposure of the internal auditory canal fundus (e.g., for acoustic tumor exposure), but mechanical packing of the vestibule would disrupt normal sound transduction. This study was designed to assess the feasibility of preserving hearing with CO2 laser occlusion, without mechanical packing of the posterior semicircular canal membranous labyrinth. Twenty adult Hartley guinea pigs underwent occlusion of the right posterior semicircular canal with one of three techniques: mechanical packing, laser coagulation, or laser coagulation with mechanical packing. Electrocochleographic thresholds to clicks and 1-kHz and 8-kHz tone bursts did not change significantly 6 weeks after posterior semicircular canal occlusion with any of these techniques. Histopathologic examination revealed complete canal occlusion with all methods. These findings suggest that mechanical occlusion and CO2 laser occlusion of the posterior semicircular canal do not significantly affect cochlear function in the guinea pig. CO2 laser occlusion of the membranous labyrinth may prove useful for more extensive selective vestibular ablation by obviating the need for mechanical packing of the labyrinth.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Waxes); 124-38-9 (Carbon Dioxide); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7567020</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7567020</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1589</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Bouchard,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Kartush,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Triple semicircular canal occlusion in the guinea pig</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>117</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>515</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold/physiology</k1>
<k1>Carbon Dioxide</k1>
<k1>Drug Combinations</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Fascia/transplantation</k1>
<k1>Feasibility Studies</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fenestration, Labyrinth</k1>
<k1>Gelatin Sponge, Absorbable/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing/physiology</k1>
<k1>Hemostatics/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Laser Coagulation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Palmitates/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Single-Blind Method</k1>
<k1>Tampons, Surgical</k1>
<k1>Vestibule, Labyrinth/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Waxes/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>Hearing preservation is possible with translabyrinthine procedures, but the optimal means of sealing the remaining labyrinth has not been determined. The purpose of this study was to compare the effects of mechanical and nonmechanical (CO2 laser-assisted) triple semicircular canal occlusion on hearing in the guinea pig. All three semicircular canals of 19 guinea pigs were treated with one of four techniques: fenestration without packing (control), fenestration with packing, CO2 laser coagulation of the membranous canal without packing, or laser coagulation with packing. Six weeks postoperatively, electrocochleographic thresholds were significantly elevated in one of five ears treated with packing alone, in one of five ears treated with laser and packing, in two of five ears treated with the laser alone, and in all four control ears. Thresholds were significantly elevated in control versus occluded ears (p &amp;lt; 0.05). There were no significant differences between the ears treated with laser or packing. These findings suggest that hearing can be preserved in triple canal occlusion by means of sealing the membranous labyrinth with either CO2 laser coagulation or mechanical packing. Further study on the feasibility of hearing preservation with complete labyrinthectomy is warranted.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Drug Combinations); 0 (Hemostatics); 0 (Palmitates); 0 (Waxes); 124-38-9 (Carbon Dioxide); 8021-48-5 (bone wax); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9374176; S0194599897002763 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9374176</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1568</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Briggs,R. D.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing preservation with labyrinthine ablation in otitis media</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>110</vo>
<is>5 Pt 1</is>
<sp>779</sp>
<op>786</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus Infections/pathology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Conductive/pathology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/pathology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pneumococcal Infections/pathology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/pathology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Iatrogenic fenestration of the inner ear in the presence of otitis media is commonly associated with permanent hearing loss. Hearing can generally be preserved when the vestibular labyrinth is ablated in a controlled manner in noninflamed ears. The purpose of this study was to examine the feasibility of hearing preservation with violation of the inner ear in the presence of middle ear inflammation. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective and controlled animal model. METHODS: Otitis media was induced bilaterally in pigmented guinea pigs with transtympanic injection of Streptococcus pneumoniae, nontypeable Haemophilus influenzae, or formalin-killed nontypeable H influenzae. Two to 4 days after injection, the horizontal canal of one ear was transected and sealed. Hearing was tested before and after labyrinthine ablation. RESULTS: Otitis media was induced in all ears. Bacterial cultures were positive in 19 of 20 S pneumoniae-injected ears, and in 10 of 16 nontypeable H influenzae-injected ears. One week after surgery, elevation of click thresholds (&amp;gt; 15 dB) was encountered in none of the fenestrated or unfenestrated S pneumoniae-infected ears, in two of six unfenestrated and three of six fenestrated nontypeable H influenzae-infected ears, and in one of five killed-nontypeable H influenzae-injected ears both with and without fenestration. CONCLUSIONS: These data suggest that ablation of a semicircular canal in the presence of middle ear inflammation or infection does not necessarily lead to profound sensorineural hearing loss. Hearing loss associated with iatrogenic violation of the semicircular canals may be more dependent on factors other than the presence of nonspecific middle ear inflammation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20031114; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10807357</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200005000-00008</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10807357</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1598</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Daly,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Veum,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Adams,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Giebink,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Tobacco smoke and otitis media in the chinchilla model</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>111</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>513</sp>
<op>518</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Plants, Toxic</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Smoke/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pneumoniae</k1>
<k1>Tobacco</k1>
<ab>To determine whether tobacco smoke contributes to the pathogenesis of acute otitis media, chinchillas were exposed to mainstream tobacco smoke or sham conditions (cigarettes not lit) in a Walton smoke exposure machine for 20-minute cycles two or three times daily. After 6 to 8 weeks of daily exposure, 12 chinchillas were nasally injected with Streptococcus pneumoniae, and 18 chinchillas were injected into both middle ears with nontypable Haemophilus influenzae. Smoke or sham exposures were continued for 2 to 4 weeks after injection. Otitis media developed in none of the 12 nasally injected chinchillas and in all 18 chinchillas whose middle ears were injected with nontypable Haemophilus influenzae. Persistence of middle ear effusion and persistence of nontypable Haemophilus influenzae in the middle ear effusion were not different between the smoke- and sham-exposed groups. This suggests that mainstream smoke exposure does not change the natural course of otitis media in the chinchilla model.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: P01-DC00133/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-DC00009-07084/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8508176; 0 (Smoke); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Otitis Media Research Center, University of Minnesota School of Medicine, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7936688; S0194599894000896 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7936688</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1573</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Dhanani,N.</a1>
<a1>Giannoni,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Impact of resistant pneumococcus on rates of acute mastoiditis</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>190</sp>
<op>194</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hospitalization</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mastoiditis/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Penicillin Resistance</k1>
<k1>Pneumococcal Infections/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pneumoniae/drug effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine whether the rate of acute mastoiditis is rising, specifically as a result of antibiotic-resistant strains of Streptococcus pneumoniae. METHODS: A retrospective chart review of all patients with a discharge diagnosis of acute mastoiditis between July 1, 1987, and June 30, 1997, was performed at our academic, tertiary-care medical center. There were no interventions, and the main outcome measures included the number of cases of acute or coalescent mastoiditis, stratified by pathogen, per year. RESULTS: The rate of acute mastoiditis as a proportion of yearly otorhinolaryngology admissions increased linearly over time (P = 0. 024). Pneumococcal-related rates of acute mastoiditis, expressed as a proportion of yearly hospital and otorhinolaryngology admissions, increased linearly over time (P = 0.002, P = 0.002). All but 1 case of pneumococcal mastoiditis during the past 3 years were caused by penicillin-resistant strains. CONCLUSIONS: The emergence of antibiotic-resistant S pneumoniae may be responsible for an increasing rate of acute mastoiditis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida College of Medicine,Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10471856; S0194599899003861 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10471856</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1602</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Duvall,A. J.,3rd</a1>
<a1>Teitelbaum,S. L.</a1>
<t1>Maxillary sinus atelectasis</t1>
<jf>The Annals of Otology, Rhinology, and Laryngology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Otol.Rhinol.Laryngol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>977</sp>
<op>981</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Maxilla/pathology</k1>
<k1>Maxillary Sinusitis/complications/pathology/surgery</k1>
<ab>Two patients are presented with maxillary bone loss and atelectasis of the sinus walls in association with chronic subclinical maxillary sinusitis. Maxillary sinus atelectasis results in a mild cosmetic deformity, but may also cause diplopia by involving the orbital floor. Ostial obstruction and inflammation-mediated osteopenia are postulated to be the responsible mechanisms. Surgical treatment of the sinusitis may prevent progression of the bone loss.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060515; JID: 0407300; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-4894; 0003-4894</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Minnesota School of Medicine, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1463297</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1463297</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1577</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Garside,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Strickler,S. T.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Computed tomography and the diagnosis of coalescent mastoiditis</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>120</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>350</sp>
<op>354</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Drainage</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mastoiditis/classification/complications/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Observer Variation</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Single-Blind Method</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the sensitivity and accuracy of temporal bone CT findings for the diagnosis of acute coalescent mastoiditis. DESIGN: CT scans were blindly scored for mastoid bone integrity (air cell septae, sigmoid cortical plate, and lateral cortical wall) by an otologist and 2 neuroradiologists. Scores were analyzed to determine their sensitivity and specificity for acute coalescent mastoiditis. SUBJECTS: Twenty-one patients with acute coalescent mastoiditis or acute noncoalescent mastoiditis and 12 patients with chronic mastoiditis. SETTING: Academic tertiary care facility. RESULTS: Pair-wise interobserver agreement was good to excellent (kappa = 0.4 to 0.83) for the sigmoid plate, the lateral cortex, and the septae. Scores for the sigmoid plate were significantly greater (indicative of greater bone destruction) in the coalescent group than in either the noncoalescent group or the chronic group (P &amp;lt; 0.05). Within the coalescent group, scores were highest for the sigmoid plate, followed by the septae and the lateral wall. Sensitivity and specificity for coalescent mastoiditis were both highest for the sigmoid plate (67% and 90%, respectively). CONCLUSIONS: Erosion of the cortical plate overlying the sigmoid sinus is the most sensitive and specific CT finding for distinguishing coalescent from noncoalescent acute mastoiditis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10064637; S0194599899000881 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10064637</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1552</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Abrams,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Huang,X.</a1>
<t1>Fetal central auditory system metabolic response to cochlear implant stimulation</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>127</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>131</sp>
<op>137</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents</k1>
<k1>Auditory Diseases, Central/chemically induced/congenital/diagnosis/metabolism/surgery</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Brain Chemistry</k1>
<k1>Carbon Radioisotopes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Evoked Potentials, Auditory, Brain Stem</k1>
<k1>Fetal Diseases/diagnosis/metabolism/surgery</k1>
<k1>Gestational Age</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Kanamycin</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Neonatal Screening</k1>
<k1>Prenatal Care/methods</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: The purpose of this study was to examine the effects of profound auditory deprivation and its treatment by cochlear implantation and stimulation on the metabolic activity of the central auditory system in fetal sheep. METHODS: Six ovine fetuses at 85% to 90% gestation were bilaterally deafened by kanamycin perfusion and unilaterally implanted with cochlear electrode arrays. Half of the implanted animals were stimulated with an extrauterine sound processor, and half were not. Four animals served as hearing controls. One week postoperatively, central nervous system metabolic activity was evaluated in ambient laboratory noise by quantitative autoradiography using (14)C-deoxyglucose. RESULTS: Kanamycin perfusion deafened all treated animals as verified by auditory brainstem response and scanning electron microscopy. Glucose utilization in the inferior colliculus was markedly lower in deafened and unstimulated animals relative to hearing controls. Glucose utilization in implanted-stimulated animals was similar to normal controls. CONCLUSIONS: Changes in central auditory system metabolic activity associated with congenital deafness may be minimized by prompt auditory habilitation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Carbon Radioisotopes); 59-01-8 (Kanamycin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12297800; S0194599802000645 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12297800</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1583</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Gianoli,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Lundy,L. B.</a1>
<a1>LaRouere,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Kartush,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Early post-laser stapedotomy hearing thresholds</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>443</sp>
<op>446</op>
<k1>Audiometry, Pure-Tone</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Bone Conduction</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laser Therapy</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otosclerosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Speech Discrimination Tests</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Auditory testing is not routinely performed within 4-6 weeks after stapedotomy, because hearing acuity is thought to be transiently depressed. In rare circumstances, postsurgical auditory and vestibular complaints may lead one to test hearing soon after stapedotomy. The early postoperative effects of carbon dioxide (CO2) and potassium titanyl phosphate (KTP) lasers, which now are routinely used to perform stapedotomies, have not been reported. The purpose of this report is to present normative data for auditory thresholds measured within 2 weeks of laser stapedotomy. STUDY DESIGN: The study design was a prospective, unblinded study. SETTING: The study was conducted at three academic medical centers. PATIENTS: Thirty-six subjects undergoing 38 stapedotomies for otosclerosis by 5 surgeons participated. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Behavioral audiometry was performed using standard techniques beginning before surgery and continuing through &amp;gt; 1 year after surgery. RESULTS: The CO2 laser was used in 26 stapedotomies and the KTP laser was used in 12. Nine cases were revision procedures. Bone conduction pure-tone averages and speech discrimination scores did not worsen during the early postoperative period. Bone conduction at 250 and 4,000 Hz dropped slightly within the first 2 weeks (-4.3 and -6.7 dB) but recovered thereafter. Bone conduction at 1,000 Hz actually improved within the first week after surgery (+6.2 dB, p = 0.021). Significant improvements in air conduction thresholds (and air-bone gap) were seen at the second week and late audiometry. The results for CO2 and KTP laser-treated groups were not significantly different. CONCLUSIONS: Cochlear function is not significantly depressed in the early postoperative period after laser (CO2 or KTP) stapedotomy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 7909513; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9661752</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9661752</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1601</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Goycoolea,M. V.</a1>
<a1>Giebink,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Middle ear susceptibility to Pseudomonas infection during acute otitis media</t1>
<jf>The Annals of Otology, Rhinology, and Laryngology</jf>
<jo>Ann.Otol.Rhinol.Laryngol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>531</sp>
<op>536</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Disease Susceptibility</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media, Suppurative/drug therapy/microbiology/mortality</k1>
<k1>Penicillin G Procaine/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/drug therapy/microbiology/mortality</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Pneumococcal otitis media was induced bilaterally, and Pseudomonas was inoculated unilaterally into the middle ears of 36 chinchillas to study the pathogenesis of chronic suppurative otitis media. Half of the animals were treated with penicillin prior to Pseudomonas inoculation (day 7, late Pseudomonas), and half were inoculated with Pseudomonas before penicillin treatment (day 3, early Pseudomonas). A third group of 18 chinchillas received unilateral Pseudomonas inoculation without pneumococcus or penicillin (control). Animals with early Pseudomonas were significantly less susceptible to Pseudomonas infection in the Pseudomonas-inoculated ear than animals with late Pseudomonas and controls. Susceptibility to Pseudomonas infection in the contralateral ears, which were not inoculated with Pseudomonas, was significantly lower in early Pseudomonas and control animals than in late Pseudomonas animals. Increased susceptibility in the late Pseudomonas group might have been due to altered nasopharyngeal microflora or persisting eustachian tube dysfunction--factors that may be important in the pathogenesis of chronic suppurative otitis media in humans.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: 5-T32-NS07084/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: 5P50-DC00133/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0407300; 6130-64-9 (Penicillin G Procaine); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-4894; 0003-4894</sn>
<ad>Otitis Media Research Center, University of Minnesota School of Medicine, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8333675</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8333675</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1603</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Goycoolea,M. V.</a1>
<a1>Giebink,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Pseudomonas otitis media after eustachian tube obstruction</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>511</sp>
<op>515</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Constriction, Pathologic</k1>
<k1>Eustachian Tube/pathology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/etiology</k1>
<ab>Previous experiments have shown that Pseudomonas aeruginosa may infect the middle ears of chinchillas by way of the eustachian tube and that chinchillas with acute otitis media (AOM) are more susceptible to pseudomonas infection than animals without AOM. The purpose of this experiment was to examine the effects of otitis media with effusion (OME), induced by means of eustachian tube obstruction, on middle ear susceptibility to nasal inoculation of P. aeruginosa. Chinchilla eustachian tubes were obstructed with silicone rubber sponge bilaterally; OME developed in eight animals (11 ears)--three bilaterally and five unilaterally--and persisted for 6 months. Ten chinchillas with normal eustachian tube function served as controls. All animals were nasally inoculated with 5 x 10(6) colony-forming units of P. aeruginosa. Pseudomonas otitis media developed in eight of 11 OME ears with effusion, none of five ears without OME, and four of 20 control ears (chi 2 = 11.782, p = 0.003). Therefore, P. aeruginosa can infect the middle ear by way of the eustachian tube. Tubal dysfunction may lead to the development of chronic suppurative otitis media by increasing tubotympanic susceptibility to opportunistic pathogens.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: P50-DC00133/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-DC00009-07084/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Otitis Media Research Center, University of Minnesota School of Medicine, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1437182</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1437182</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1599</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Le,C. T.</a1>
<a1>Giebink,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Acute otitis media increases middle ear susceptibility to nasal injection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>110</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>121</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Administration, Intranasal</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Disease Susceptibility</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Eustachian Tube/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Pneumococcal Infections/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>Pseudomonas aeruginosa was injected intranasally into four groups of chinchillas to determine if these bacteria can invade the middle ear by way of the eustachian tube. One group completed penicillin treatment of bilateral penumococcal otitis media (POM), and the second group started penicillin treatment of bilateral POM at the time of P. aeruginosa injection. A third group had no POM, but completed a course of penicillin treatment before P. aeruginosa injection, and a fourth group had no POM and received no penicillin. Middle ear susceptibility to nasally injected P. aeruginosa was significantly higher in animals with POM (61%) than in animals without POM (32%, p = 0.001). Forced eustachian tube opening pressures did not correlate with P. aeruginosa susceptibility. Thus, P. aeruginosa, the principle pathogen of chronic suppurative otitis media, can invade the middle ear by way of the eustachian tube, and acute otitis media predisposes to middle ear infection by P. aeurginosa.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5-T32-NS07084/NS/NINDS NIH HHS/United States; GR: P01-DC00133/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, School of Public Health, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8290293; S0194599894001580 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8290293</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1534</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Bacterial biofilms may contribute to persistent cochlear implant infection</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>953</sp>
<op>957</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation/methods</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants/adverse effects/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Deafness/therapy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis-Related Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcal Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/isolation &amp; purification/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To determine if bacterial biofilms are present on the surface of extruding or persistently infected cochlear implants. METHODS: Scanning electron microscopy was performed on cochlear implants removed from two patients because of recalcitrant infection, two implants removed secondary to device failure, and two devices that had never been implanted. Preparations were examined by experienced microbiologists for the presence of bacterial biofilms. RESULTS: Microorganisms and amorphous extracellular debris were found on the surface of the infected cochlear implants and the implants removed because of device failure. Biofilm formation was deemed definite in one infected device and possible in the other explanted devices. The never-implanted controls demonstrated microbial contamination without exopolymeric matrix, inconsistent with biofilms. CONCLUSION: Bacterial biofilm formation may play a role in recalcitrant cochlear implant infections. This may have profound implications for the treatment of cochlear implant infections.</ab>
<no>JID: 100961504; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-7129; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15547425; 00129492-200411000-00015 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15547425</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1529</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Lloyd,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<t1>Gastric reflux is uncommon in acute post-tympanostomy otorrhea</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>523</sp>
<op>526</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Causality</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gastroesophageal Reflux/complications/diagnosis/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/epidemiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/epidemiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pepsinogen A/analysis</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/epidemiology/etiology</k1>
<k1>Respiratory Tract Infections/complications/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<k1>Virus Diseases/complications/diagnosis</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Acute post-tympanostomy otorrhea (APTO) is a common complication of tympanostomy tube placement. APTO has been related primarily to viral upper respiratory infections and external ear contamination. Elevated levels of gastric enzymes have been found in a large proportion of chronic middle ear effusions, implicating gastric reflux (GR) in its pathogenesis. Thus, our objective was to determine whether GR may be a contributing factor in the development of APTO. STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: Prospective, nonrandomized design. Otorrhea samples were collected from children with APTO. Total pepsinogen concentrations were measured with a commercial ELISA, using a pepsinogen I-specific capture antibody and horseradish peroxidase detection antibody. RESULTS: Twenty-six samples from 24 patients were collected and analyzed. Eight samples demonstrated measurable pepsinogen I, but the measured concentrations, 2-17 mg/L, were below the normal serum reference ranges. CONCLUSIONS: GR does not play a major role in the development of APTO in children.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 9001-10-9 (Pepsinogen A); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Department of Otolaryngology, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. antopj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15806038; S0194599805000173 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2004.12.004</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15806038</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1595</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Lundy,L. B.</a1>
<a1>Kartush,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Burgio,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Graham,M. D.</a1>
<t1>Mechanical versus CO2 laser occlusion of the posterior semicircular canal in humans</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>416</sp>
<op>420</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Carbon Dioxide</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laser Therapy</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<ab>The purpose of this study was to compare the effectiveness of mechanical and laser-assisted posterior semicircular canal occlusion (PCO) for the treatment of intractable benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV). Twelve consecutive patients with intractable BPPV underwent PCO by three surgeons, six with mechanical PCO and six with CO2 laser-assisted PCO. PCO eliminated positional vertigo in all patients treated with the laser and five of six patients treated without the laser. Dysequilibrium was present in all patients immediately postoperatively. This resolved in all patients treated with the CO2 laser but in only two of six patients treated without the laser (p = 0.03). Patients were hospitalized for dysequilibrium for an average of 5.2 and 2.8 days for the mechanical and laser-assisted groups, respectively. Preoperative and postoperative hearing was not significantly different between the groups. No clinically significant postoperative hearing loss was encountered in either group. These results suggest that PCO is an effective treatment for intractable BPPV. The incidence of dysequilibrium that persists following PCO may be reduced by using the CO2 laser to seal the membranous canal prior to occluding the bony canal.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 7909513; 124-38-9 (Carbon Dioxide); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8817019</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8817019</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1585</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Nall,A. V.</a1>
<a1>Lemmerling,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss with cochlear modiolar defects and large vestibular aqueducts</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>306</sp>
<op>312</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/abnormalities</k1>
<k1>Cognition Disorders/etiology</k1>
<k1>Disease Progression</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Conductive/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Speech Reception Threshold Test</k1>
<k1>Vestibular Aqueduct/abnormalities</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Defects of the cochlear modiolus have been found to be associated with most cases of large vestibular aqueduct. The clinical significance of these modiolar defects has not been studied previously. The purpose of this article is to correlate clinical (functional) parameters, such as hearing outcomes, with the severity of the radiographic findings in these dysplastic inner ears. STUDY DESIGN: The study design was a retrospective chart review, supplemented with telephone interviews and clinic visits. SETTING: The study was conducted at an academic, tertiary care center. PATIENTS: Thirty consecutive patients with large vestibular aqueducts participated. RESULTS: Scores of modiolar deficiencies yielded inconsistent correlations with hearing loss. Vestibular aqueduct morphology and thickness correlated very strongly with the severity of hearing loss. CONCLUSIONS: These observations support the hypothesis that large vestibular aqueduct-related hearing loss may be caused by transmission of subarachnoid pressure forces into the inner ear. However, the thickness and morphology of the vestibular aqueduct may simply be markers for more subtle cochlear dysplasia manifest by modiolar deficiency.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7909513; CIN: Am J Otol. 1999 Jan;20(1):135-6. PMID: 9918185; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9596180</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9596180</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1600</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Parell,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Becker,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Paparella,M. M.</a1>
<t1>Temporal bone pathology in scuba diving deaths</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>109</vo>
<is>3 Pt 1</is>
<sp>514</sp>
<op>521</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Barotrauma/etiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Diving/adverse effects/injuries</k1>
<k1>Ear Diseases/etiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/pathology</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/injuries/pathology</k1>
<k1>Hemorrhage/etiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<ab>Scuba diving has long been associated with otologic injuries; however, little is known about temporal bone pathology in diving-related deaths. We examined 18 temporal bones from 11 divers who died, primarily from complications of rapid ascent. Bleeding into the middle ear and mastoid air cells was nearly universal. Inner ear damage included hemorrhage around Reissner&amp;#39;s membrane and the round window membrane and rupture of the utricle and saccule. Most of the observed inner ear damage was not surgically treatable.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: P01-DC00133/DC/NIDCD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis 55455.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8414572</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8414572</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1505</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Sampson,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Lang,D. M.</a1>
<t1>Safety and efficacy of carbomethylcellulose foam in guinea pig middle ear surgery</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>142</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>405</sp>
<op>408</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Carboxymethylcellulose/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Evoked Potentials, Auditory, Brain Stem</k1>
<k1>Gelatin Sponge, Absorbable</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hyaluronic Acid/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tympanoplasty</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Carbomethylcellulose (CMC) foam has been widely adopted to promote hemostasis and healing in sinus surgery. There has been interest in the use of CMC in middle ear surgery. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the safety and efficacy of CMC foam for use in middle ear surgery. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, controlled. SETTING: Academic research laboratory. SUBJECTS AND METHODS: Adult guinea pigs underwent experimental tympanoplasty followed by packing of the middle ear (n = 19 per group) with CMC, hyaluronic acid (HA), or gelatin sponge (GS). Auditory evoked brainstem response testing and otomicroscopy were performed before and serially for eight weeks after surgery. Tympanic membrane healing, hemostasis, and retention of packing material were assessed. RESULTS: All tympanic membranes treated with CMC healed by week eight. Less postoperative bleeding was observed with CMC than with HA or GS. Surgery elevated auditory thresholds, at least temporarily, in all groups. However, CMC was associated with greater auditory threshold elevation (15-25 dB) at eight weeks across all test frequencies relative to HA or GS (P &amp;lt; 0.01). Residual CMC and scarring were not found in the middle ear, indicating that the hearing loss was sensorineural. No head tilt posturing suggestive of vestibulopathy was seen. CONCLUSION: CMC was associated with hearing loss and may be ototoxic. Therefore, CMC should not be used in human middle ears given the presence of several nontoxic alternative materials.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright 2010; JID: 8508176; 9004-32-4 (Carboxymethylcellulose); 9004-61-9 (Hyaluronic Acid); 2009/09/10 [received]; 2009/11/04 [revised]; 2009/11/10 [accepted]; 2010/01/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pb>American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery Foundation. Published by Mosby, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1097-6817; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. Patrick.Antonelli@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 20172389; S0194-5998(09)01733-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2009.11.009</do>
<wp>20100108</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20172389</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1530</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Cantwell,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Sundin,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Pemberton,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Barr,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Inflammatory proteases in chronic otitis externa</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>115</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>651</sp>
<op>654</op>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Precursors/analysis/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Indoles/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Inflammation Mediators/analysis</k1>
<k1>Leukocyte Elastase/analysis/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 2/analysis/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 9/analysis/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinases/analysis/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otitis Externa/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Protease Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>alpha 1-Antitrypsin/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Proteases are known to contribute to the pathogenesis of chronic inflammatory skin conditions such as atopic dermatitis and psoriasis. Inhibition of these proteases has shown promise in the treatment of these skin conditions. The purpose of this study was to measure the matrix metalloproteinases (MMP) and human neutrophil elastase (HNE) activities in chronic otitis externa (COE) and to determine whether administration of protease inhibitors recombinant alpha 1-antitrypsin (rAAT) and ilomastat might reduce these protease activities. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective and ex vivo. METHODS: Twenty-five ear canals with COE and 34 with no pathology (i.e., controls) were debrided and filled with saline. After a tragal pump and 1 to 2 minutes, the washes were collected and analyzed for MMP and HNE activities and the inhibitory activity of rAAT and ilomastat on these proteases, respectively. RESULTS: MMP and HNE levels were significantly higher (P = .0057 and .0112) in ears with COE than normal ears. MMP activity greater than 3 mAU/minute was observed in 30% of COE and 0% of controls (P = .0270). HNE activity greater than 3 mAU/minute was found in 77% of COE versus 7% of controls (P &amp;lt; .0001). Ilomastat and rAAT inhibited 60% of MMP and 98% of HNE activity, respectively, in COE ears. CONCLUSIONS: Elevated levels of proteases found in COE, MMP, and HNE may be inhibited with ilomastat and rAAT. The therapeutic potential of these protease inhibitors warrants investigation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; 0 (Enzyme Precursors); 0 (Indoles); 0 (Inflammation Mediators); 0 (Protease Inhibitors); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (alpha 1-Antitrypsin); 142880-36-2 (ilomastat); EC 3.4.21.37 (Leukocyte Elastase); EC 3.4.24.- (Matrix Metalloproteinases); EC 3.4.24.24 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 2); EC 3.4.24.35 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 9); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15805875; 00005537-200504000-00017 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.mlg.0000161339.92633.8d</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15805875</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1546</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Kim,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Cantwell,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Sundin,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Pemberton,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Barr,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Alpha 1-antitrypsin and ilomastat inhibit inflammatory proteases present in human middle ear effusions</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>113</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1347</sp>
<op>1351</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Indoles/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Inflammation Mediators/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Leukocyte Elastase/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 2/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 9/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinases/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media, Suppurative/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Recurrence</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>alpha 1-Antitrypsin/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Proteases of both the serine and metalloproteinase families have been shown to play a role in the pathogenesis of otitis media (OM). Inhibitors of proteases from each of these families have been shown to beneficially impact disease progression in a number of related chronic inflammatory conditions, but their use has not been studied in OM. The purpose of this study was to assess the activity of the protease inhibitors recombinant alpha 1-antitrypsin (rAAT) and ilomastat on inflammatory proteases present in human middle ear effusions (MEEs), with a view to their potential utility in the treatment of OM. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective and ex vivo. METHODS: MEEs were collected from 100 patients presenting for middle ear surgery, most commonly tympanostomy tube placement or treatment of acute posttympanostomy otorrhea (APTO). MEEs were analyzed for the presence of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) and human neutrophil elastase (HNE) and the inhibitory activity of rAAT and ilomastat on these proteases, respectively. RESULTS: MMP levels were highest in APTO, and HNE was highest in chronic suppurative OM and APTO. High levels of MMP and HNE (&amp;gt;3 mAU/min) were found in 52% and 37% of MEEs, respectively. Ilomastat and rAAT demonstrated significant inhibition of MMP and HNE activity (&amp;gt;30% reduction), respectively, in 80% and 82% of MEEs with high levels of activity. CONCLUSIONS: Proteases are commonly found in OM. Ilomastat and rAAT are potent inhibitors of proteases in MEEs across a wide range of OM in humans. Investigation into the potential therapeutic benefits of these protease inhibitors is warranted.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; 0 (Indoles); 0 (Inflammation Mediators); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (alpha 1-Antitrypsin); 142880-36-2 (ilomastat); EC 3.4.21.37 (Leukocyte Elastase); EC 3.4.24.- (Matrix Metalloproteinases); EC 3.4.24.24 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 2); EC 3.4.24.35 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 9); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolarynology, University of Florida, Gainesville, 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12897557</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200308000-00015</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12897557</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1521</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Sundin,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Pemberton,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Barr,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Alpha1-antitrypsin single dose adjuvant therapy for acute otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>135</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>111</sp>
<op>115</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/drug therapy/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Pneumococcal Infections/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pneumoniae/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Trypsin Inhibitors/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>alpha 1-Antitrypsin/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Proteases have been shown to play a role in the pathogenesis of otitis media. Inhibition of these proteases can improve treatment outcomes in certain conditions. The goal of this study was to determine if intratympanic administration of a single dose of the protease inhibitor, recombinant alpha 1-antitrypsin (rAAT), can facilitate resolution of acute otitis media (AOM) in the chinchilla. METHODS AND MEASURES: Pneumococcus was injected into both middle ears of 12 chinchillas. After 3 to 4 days, middle ears were cultured, systemic antibiotics were initiated, and rAAT or its vehicle was administered into the middle ears of all animals. Serial tympanic membrane (TM) scoring, tympanometry, and auditory-evoked brain stem response testing were performed. Animals were sacrificed at varying timepoints and temporal bones studied for objective measures of OM. RESULTS: Although not reaching statistical significance, there was a trend to more rapid resolution of AOM in rAAT-treated ears. Tympanometry, auditory thresholds, and quantitative histologic parameters did not differ between rAAT and vehicle treated ears. CONCLUSIONS: A single dose of intratympanic rAAT likely does not facilitate the resolution of antibiotic-treated pneumococcal AOM in the chinchilla model. Serial administration of this protease inhibitor may be necessary to see a significant treatment effect.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Trypsin Inhibitors); 0 (alpha 1-Antitrypsin); 2005/06/13 [received]; 2005/11/22 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16815194; S0194-5998(06)00231-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.11.050</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16815194</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1544</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Sundin,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Pemberton,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Barr,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Protease inhibitors alpha1-antitrypsin and ilomastat are not ototoxic in the chinchilla</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>113</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1764</sp>
<op>1769</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Indoles/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Instillation, Drug</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/pathology</k1>
<k1>alpha 1-Antitrypsin/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacology/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Proteases of both the serine and the metalloprotease families have been shown to play a role in the pathogenesis of otitis media. Inhibitors of proteases from each of these families have been shown to beneficially impact disease progression in a number of related chronic inflammatory conditions. The purpose of this study was to assess the safety of protease inhibitors when instilled into the middle ear, with a view to their potential use in the treatment of human otitis media. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, randomized, controlled trial in the chinchilla model. METHODS: After completing baseline auditory testing and bilateral transpalatal obstruction of the Eustachian tube, chinchillas received weekly transbullar injections of protease inhibitor (alpha1-antitrypsin, ilomastat, or both), vehicle, or saline. After 1 month, hearing was tested and the animals were sacrificed. Temporal bone histopathologic examination was performed. RESULTS: All treatment groups demonstrated a statistically insignificant average loss in long-term hearing (0 dB) for all measures using clicks and tones (P &amp;gt;.15 for all conditions). All treatment groups were statistically insignificantly different from one another (P =.5625). Histopathologic examination revealed no significant inner ear changes. CONCLUSIONS: Protease inhibitors that are currently under study in animal models and humans for the treatment of inflammatory diseases that are related to imbalances between protease and protease inhibitor have no significant toxic effect on the inner ear of chinchillas. These findings support the safety of further clinical trials using these inhibitors to treat middle ear inflammation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; 0 (Indoles); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (alpha 1-Antitrypsin); 142880-36-2 (ilomastat); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Box 100264, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 14520103</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14520103</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1570</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Varela,A. E.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<t1>Diagnostic yield of high-resolution computed tomography for pediatric sensorineural hearing loss</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>109</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1642</sp>
<op>1647</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/radiography</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Logistic Models</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: In recent years, relatively subtle inner ear anomalies have become apparent using high-resolution computed tomography (CT). The purpose of this study was to determine the diagnostic yield of high-resolution CT for pediatric sensorineural hearing loss (HL) (SNHL). METHODS: A review was performed on the records of all children ( .05). The rate of dysplasias did not correlate with SNHL severity, pattern of HL, or type of HL (mixed vs. sensorineural). CONCLUSIONS: These findings suggest that radiographic imaging has a relatively high diagnostic yield in children with SNHL. These findings may be of value in counseling patients and guiding the management of their SNHL.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10522936</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-199910000-00018</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10522936</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1506</id>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Winterstein,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<t1>Topical dexamethasone and tympanic membrane perforation healing in otitis media: a short-term study</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>519</sp>
<op>523</op>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The safety and efficacy of topical corticosteroids have not been established in the treatment of acute otitis media (AOM) with tympanic membrane (TM) perforation. Specific concerns include the risk for nonhealing TM perforations. Previous studies have not been done in models with concurrent AOM. The purpose of this study was to determine whether the addition of dexamethasone to topical ciprofloxacin affects healing of AOM-related TM perforations. METHODS: Bilateral AOM was induced in chinchillas by transbulla injection of Streptococcus pneumoniae, and TMs were perforated with a CO2 laser 3 to 5 days later. Each animal received ciprofloxacin-dexamethasone in one ear and ciprofloxacin in the other, twice daily for 7 days. Tympanic membranes were assessed for 4 weeks. RESULTS: Fifteen of 55 ciprofloxacin-treated and 37 of 55 ciprofloxacin-dexamethasone-treated TMs failed to heal within the 4-week study period (p &amp;lt; 0.001). Exposure to dexamethasone increased the odds for persistent perforation by 5.5 (95% confidence interval, 2.4-12.6). At 4 weeks, mean TM perforation diameter was 0.9 mm in ciprofloxacin-treated ears and 2.1 mm in ciprofloxacin-dexamethasone-treated ears (p &amp;lt; 0.001). CONCLUSION: Topical dexamethasone hinders TM healing in a chinchilla model of AOM at short-term follow-up. Longer follow-up is needed.</ab>
<no>JID: 100961504; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-4505; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Rd., Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, U.S.A. Patrick.Antonelli@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 20010446</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/MAO.0b013e3181ca85cc</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20010446</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1584</id>
<a1>Baylor,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Rojiani,A.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<t1>Facial palsy from Masson&amp;#39;s vegetant intravascular hemangioendothelioma</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>408</sp>
<op>10, 415-7</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Ear Neoplasms/complications/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Facial Paralysis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Hemangioendothelioma/complications/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Labyrinth Diseases/complications</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>Masson&amp;#39;s vegetant intravascular hemangioendothelioma (VIH) is a rare benign tumor that has a propensity for the head and neck but has been overlooked in the otolaryngology literature. Herein, we present the first report of facial palsy resulting from a small VIH growing in the fundus of the internal auditory canal and the labyrinthine segment of the fallopian canal.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9615522</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9615522</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1572</id>
<a1>Baylor,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Mcfeely,W. J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Central nervous system metabolic activity after cochlear implantation in the feline neonatal model</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>121</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>361</sp>
<op>366</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Pathways/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Brain/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Cats</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation</k1>
<k1>Deafness/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Deoxyglucose/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Energy Metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sensory Deprivation/physiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine the effects of deafening and cochlear implant stimulation on central nervous system (CNS) metabolic activity in the feline neonate model. BACKGROUND: Deafening of fetal animals has been shown to result in acute, profound depression of CNS glucose metabolism, in both auditory structures and the cerebral hemispheres. Preliminary studies have suggested that electrical stimulation of the auditory system may increase central nervous metabolic activity after deafening. The purpose of this study was to investigate this possibility. METHODS: This was a prospective, randomized, blinded, and controlled animal study of 13 random-source newborn kittens. It was set in an animal research facility for otologic disorders. OUTCOME: Deoxyglucose metabolism (assessed with autoradiograph densitometry) of brain cross-sections of normal, deafened, and deafened and cochlear-implanted animals after 6 weeks of auditory stimulation or deprivation. RESULTS: Chronic deafening did not result in a profound reduction in CNS metabolic activity. Cochlear implantation and electrical stimulation did not significantly raise the level of CNS metabolic activity within either auditory pathways or the cerebral hemispheres. CONCLUSIONS: Deafening is not associated with significant chronic reduction in CNS metabolic activity. Other parameters of CNS activity and maturation may be necessary to assess the effects of cochlear implantation and stimulation in animal models.</ab>
<no>LR: 20031114; JID: 8508176; 154-17-6 (Deoxyglucose); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10504588; S0194599899004325 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10504588</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1519</id>
<a1>Bhandare,N.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Malayapa,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Ototoxicity after radiotherapy for head and neck tumors</t1>
<jf>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Radiat.Oncol.Biol.Phys.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Feb 1</fd>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>469</sp>
<op>479</op>
<k1>Age Factors</k1>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Dose Fractionation</k1>
<k1>Ear, External/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/drug therapy/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries/complications</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To investigate the incidence of radiation-induced ototoxicity according to the total dose delivered to specific parts of the auditory system, fractionation, and chemotherapy. METHODS AND MATERIALS: Records of 325 patients treated for primary extracranial head and neck tumors with curative intent who received radiotherapy between 1964 and 2000 (median follow-up, 5.4 years) were retrospectively reviewed. Reconstructions of the treatment plans were generated to estimate the doses received by components of the auditory system. RESULTS: Radiotherapy-induced morbidity developed in 41.8% of patients (external ear, 33.2%; middle ear, 28.6%; and inner ear, 26.8%). Univariate/multivariate analyses indicate that total dose received by parts of the auditory system seem to be significant, though fractionation and chemoradiation may contribute to the incidence of ototoxicities. Sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) was observed in 49 patients (15.1%). Univariate and multivariate analyses indicated that age (p = 0.0177 and p = 0.005) and dose to cochlea (p  0.0001) above doses of 60.5 Gy compared to 3% at doses below 60.5 Gy. For patients treated with adjuvant chemotherapy, clinically overt SNHL increased to 30% compared to 18% in the no-chemotherapy group at 10 years (p = 0.0281). CONCLUSION: Radiotherapy toxicity was observed in all parts of the auditory system with median doses for incidence varying between 60 Gy to 66 Gy. Total dose to organ seems to be a significant factor though fractionation and chemo-radiation may contribute to ototoxicities.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071009; JID: 7603616; CIN: Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2007 Aug 1;68(5):1582; author reply 1582. PMID: 17674992; 2006/05/23 [received]; 2006/09/07 [revised]; 2006/09/08 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0360-3016; 0360-3016</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17236969; S0360-3016(06)02996-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ijrobp.2006.09.017</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17236969</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1504</id>
<a1>Bhandare,N.</a1>
<a1>Jackson,A.</a1>
<a1>Eisbruch,A.</a1>
<a1>Pan,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Flickinger,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<t1>Radiation therapy and hearing loss</t1>
<jf>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Radiat.Oncol.Biol.Phys.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar 1</fd>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>3 Suppl</is>
<sp>S50</sp>
<op>7</op>
<k1>Cochlea/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Neuroma, Acoustic/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiosurgery/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<ab>A review of literature on the development of sensorineural hearing loss after high-dose radiation therapy for head-and-neck tumors and stereotactic radiosurgery or fractionated stereotactic radiotherapy for the treatment of vestibular schwannoma is presented. Because of the small volume of the cochlea a dose-volume analysis is not feasible. Instead, the current literature on the effect of the mean dose received by the cochlea and other treatment- and patient-related factors on outcome are evaluated. Based on the data, a specific threshold dose to cochlea for sensorineural hearing loss cannot be determined; therefore, dose-prescription limits are suggested. A standard for evaluating radiation therapy-associated ototoxicity as well as a detailed approach for scoring toxicity is presented.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright 2010; JID: 7603616; RF: 41; 2009/03/18 [received]; 2009/04/23 [revised]; 2009/04/27 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pb>Elsevier Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1879-355X; 0360-3016</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20171518; S0360-3016(09)03298-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Meta-Analysis; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ijrobp.2009.04.096</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20171518</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1512</id>
<a1>Bhandare,N.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiation effects on the auditory and vestibular systems</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>623</sp>
<op>634</op>
<k1>Brain Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Dose Fractionation</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Radiation</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/physiopathology/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiotherapy/ultrasonography</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neuroma, Acoustic/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries/epidemiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Radiobiology</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Vertigo/epidemiology/etiology</k1>
<k1>Vestibule, Labyrinth/physiopathology/radiation effects</k1>
<ab>Definitive or postoperative radiation therapy (RT) is commonly used for the management of intracranial and extracranial head and neck tumors. Because of the variability of tumor location and dimensions, sparing of nontarget normal tissue and organs may not be possible. Treatment modalities that deliver the highest doses of radiation to the auditory system include stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) and fractionated stereotactic radiotherapy (FSRT) for the treatment of vestibular schwannomas (VS), and fractionated radiotherapy (FRT) or intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) for the treatment of head and neck malignancies. Radiation therapy for VS is unique because of its involvement of the inner ear and preexisting auditory and vestibular dysfunction. Auditory and vestibular dysfunction following RT for VS may be limited by limiting the total dose of cranial nerve VIII irradiation and by fractionation.</ab>
<no>JID: 0144042; RF: 69; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1557-8259; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19751868; S0030-6665(09)00057-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otc.2009.04.002</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19751868</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1551</id>
<a1>Carls,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Morris,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>External auditory canal stenosis after radiation therapy</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>112</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1975</sp>
<op>1978</op>
<k1>Constriction, Pathologic</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Radiation</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Life Tables</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To determine whether the risk of external auditory canal stenosis from external-beam radiation therapy is dose dependent. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective chart review. METHODS: The presence of external auditory canal disease was recorded for patients who received low-dose (e.g., lymphoma [20-40 Gy]), medium-dose (e.g., chemodectoma [40-55 Gy]), or high-dose (e.g., parotid and nasopharyngeal neoplasms [55-75 Gy]) external-beam radiation therapy from 6 months to over 8 years following treatment. The incidence of external auditory canal disease was compared between groups. RESULTS: None of 13 low-dose, none of 19 medium-dose, and 8 of 91 (8.7%) high-dose external-beam radiation therapy subjects developed ipsilateral external auditory canal stenosis. No external auditory canal stenosis developed in patients treated with high-dose external-beam radiation therapy in the absence of parotid surgery. External auditory canal stenosis developed only in patients treated with parotidectomy and high-dose external-beam radiation therapy (P =.0059), and all of these cases of external auditory canal stenosis developed within 3 years of radiation therapy. CONCLUSIONS: High dose external-beam radiation therapy alone does not significantly predispose patients to external auditory canal stenosis. However, combined high-dose external-beam radiation therapy and surgery around the external auditory canal do significantly increase the risk of external auditory canal stenosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12439165</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200211000-00012</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12439165</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1515</id>
<a1>Chung,K. K.</a1>
<a1>Schumacher,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Sampson,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Brennan,A. B.</a1>
<t1>Impact of engineered surface microtopography on biofilm formation of Staphylococcus aureus</t1>
<jf>Biointerphases</jf>
<jo>Biointerphases</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>89</sp>
<op>94</op>
<ab>The surface of an indwelling medical device can be colonized by human pathogens that can form biofilms and cause infections. In most cases, these biofilms are resistant to antimicrobial therapy and eventually necessitate removal or replacement of the device. An engineered surface microtopography based on the skin of sharks, Sharklet AF, has been designed on a poly(dimethyl siloxane) elastomer (PDMSe) to disrupt the formation of bacterial biofilms without the use of bactericidal agents. The Sharklet AF PDMSe was tested against smooth PDMSe for biofilm formation of Staphylococcus aureus over the course of 21 days. The smooth surface exhibited early-stage biofilm colonies at 7 days and mature biofilms at 14 days, while the topographical surface did not show evidence of early biofilm colonization until day 21. At 14 days, the mean value of percent area coverage of S. aureus on the smooth surface was 54% compared to 7% for the Sharklet AF surface (p&amp;lt;0.01). These results suggest that surface modification of indwelling medical devices and exposed sterile surfaces with the Sharklet AF engineered topography may be an effective solution in disrupting biofilm formation of S. aureus.</ab>
<no>JID: 101275679; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1559-4106; 1559-4106</sn>
<ad>Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20408641</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.</sf>
<do>10.1116/1.2751405</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20408641</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1531</id>
<a1>Dohar,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Poole,M. D.</a1>
<t1>Tympanostomy tube otorrhea: treating the first infection. Highlights of a roundtable discussion sponsored by Alcon Laboratories, Inc.; Oct. 16, 2004; Fort Worth, Texas</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>2 Suppl 1</is>
<sp>5</sp>
<op>15</op>
<k1>Anti-Infective Agents/administration &amp; dosage/economics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Infections/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Mycoses/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Care/methods</k1>
<k1>Steroids/therapeutic use</k1>
<no>JID: 7701817; 0 (Anti-Infective Agents); 0 (Steroids); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15796450</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15796450</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1516</id>
<a1>Drobbin,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Phelan,S. T.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Dexamethasone does not alter in vitro antibacterial efficacy of gentamicin</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>769</sp>
<op>772</op>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/metabolism/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Anti-Inflammatory Agents/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Dexamethasone/administration &amp; dosage/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Drug Administration Schedule</k1>
<k1>Gentamicins/metabolism/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcal Infections/drug therapy/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Aminoglycoside ototoxicity may be mitigated by administration of dexamethasone; however, dexamethasone could theoretically impair its antibacterial properties. The purpose of this experiment was to determine if dexamethasone decreases the antibacterial activity of gentamicin against Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA) and Staphylococcus aureus (SA). STUDY DESIGN: In vitro microbiological assay. METHODS: Four separate trials of minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) testing were performed for gentamicin against five PA strains and six SA strains, with and without the addition of high and low concentrations of dexamethasone. RESULTS: MICs were not changed by more than one dilution with the addition of either high or low concentrations of dexamethasone for any of the PA and SA strains. CONCLUSION: Dexamethasone does not impair the antibacterial efficacy of gentamicin for PA and SA. This supports the role of dexamethasone as an oto-protectant with aminoglycoside therapy.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Anti-Inflammatory Agents); 0 (Gentamicins); 50-02-2 (Dexamethasone); 2006/09/10 [received]; 2006/11/06 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17478213; S0194-5998(06)03450-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2006.11.015</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17478213</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1541</id>
<a1>Falcone,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss with stapedotomy in otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>666</sp>
<op>673</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pneumococcal Infections</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery/adverse effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Stapes fixation is often found in patients with either active or inactive otitis media (OM). Stapedotomy is generally not performed in ears with OM because of the potential risk of sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL). Recent studies have demonstrated that the inner ear may be fenestrated in the presence of OM without significantly increased risk of SNHL. The goal of this study was to determine if stapedotomy in the presence of OM significantly increases the incidence of postoperative SNHL. METHODS: Streptococcus pneumoniae or Pseudomonas aeruginosa was injected bilaterally into the middle ears of guinea pigs (n = 18 and 16, respectively). A control group (n = 14) was injected with saline solution. Two days postinjection, a unilateral stapedotomy was performed. Auditory thresholds were evaluated by electrocochleography before and after stapedotomy. RESULTS: Bacterial OM was induced in all ears injected with pneumococci and pseudomonas. Auditory thresholds increased in all ears treated with stapedotomy. Stapedotomy performed in the presence of pseudomonas OM resulted in significantly greater SNHL than in control or pneumococcal ears (P = 0.0055). Hearing thresholds were not significantly different between pneumococcal OM and control ears treated with stapedotomy. CONCLUSION: Stapedotomy in the presence of pseudomonas OM, but not pneumococcal OM, significantly increases the risk of SNHL in the guinea pig model. SIGNIFICANCE: Stapedotomy should be avoided in patients with active OM, particularly in the presence of pseudomonas.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14663433; S0194599803017492 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2003.08.009</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14663433</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1557</id>
<a1>Feigenberg,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Friedman,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiosurgery for paraganglioma of the temporal bone</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>384</sp>
<op>389</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</k1>
<k1>Paraganglioma/prevention &amp; control/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiosurgery/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Skull Neoplasms/prevention &amp; control/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To report the outcome of patients with paraganglioma of the temporal bone treated with stereotactic radiosurgery at the University of Florida. METHODS AND MATERIALS: Between January 1997 and June 1999, five patients with paraganglioma of the temporal bone were treated with Linac-based stereotactic radiosurgery at the University of Florida. The ages of the three female and two male patients were between 40 and 88 years (median, 49 years). Four patients were treated at initial presentation, and one had recurrent disease. Treatment volumes ranged from 4.9 cm3 to 18.4 cm3, with a mean of 10.84 cm3. The dose applied to the margin of the tumor varied from 12.5 to 15 Gy (median, 15 Gy). The treatment dose was specified to the 80% isodose shell in two cases and to the 70% isodose shell in three cases. The median follow-up time was 27 months, ranging from 14 to 50 months. RESULTS: One of four previously untreated patients had a relapse at the primary tumor site. Treatment failure occurred at the field margin 6 months after radiosurgery; the patient was subsequently treated with fractionated stereotactic radiotherapy and at the time of analysis had no evidence of disease, 21 months after initiation of salvage therapy. The patient treated at the time of recurrence after conventional radiotherapy had a local recurrence 40 months after radiosurgery. At the time of this recurrence, the patient had biopsy-proven metastatic disease in two cervical lymph nodes, and no salvage therapy was performed. All patients were alive at the time of the analysis, one with disease present. Presenting symptoms improved in two patients and stabilized in one. The two patients who had local recurrence develop had worsening of their symptoms. One patient had a cranial nerve V palsy develop 6 months after treatment, which resolved after a few months. CONCLUSIONS: In this series, the results with stereotactic radiosurgery are discouraging compared with our results with conventional fractionated radiotherapy in patients with paraganglioma of the temporal bone.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 2002; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida Health Science Center, PO Box 100385, Gainesville, FL 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11933180; 10.1002/hed.10064 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11933180</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1549</id>
<a1>Foster,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Computerized physician-order entry: are we there yet?</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1237</sp>
<op>43, vii</op>
<k1>Computer Systems</k1>
<k1>Cost Savings</k1>
<k1>Hospital Information Systems/economics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Medical Errors/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Medical Records Systems, Computerized</k1>
<k1>Software</k1>
<k1>User-Computer Interface</k1>
<ab>Computerized physician-order entry (CPOE) is a system of hardware and software through which a physician enters orders directly into a computer rather than writing them on paper. The advantages of CPOE include order legibility, improved response time, reduction in adverse drug reactions, reduced cost of care, and improved patient outcomes. The maturation of mobile computing platforms, graphical user interfaces, and wireless technologies are making CPOE more practical for both outpatient and inpatient care. Significant barriers to the implementation of CPOE include the reluctance of physicians to change existing practices, doubt about the possible benefits, increased front-end time to enter orders, and system cost.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 0144042; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, PO Box 100225, Gainesville, FL 32610-0225, USA. Fostera@medicine.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12687740</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12687740</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1540</id>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Sedwick,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>A log-normal distribution model of the effect of bacteria and ear fenestration on hearing loss: a Bayesian approach</t1>
<jf>Statistics in medicine</jf>
<jo>Stat.Med.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Feb 15</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>493</sp>
<op>508</op>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Infections/complications/microbiology/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Bayes Theorem</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Ear Diseases/complications/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fenestration, Labyrinth</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Models, Statistical</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<ab>Chronic ear infection is a potentially life-threatening illness that medical doctors typically treat with ear surgery. Despite the success of this treatment, complications can occur due to bacteria infection. Surgeons believe that this infection causes the patient to have clinically significant hearing damage. In order to understand such complications, surgeons must quantify the effect of bacteria, their toxins and ear surgery on hearing loss. To this end, the other two authors of this paper performed two experiments on guinea pigs to measure hearing thresholds following a bacterial infection and surgery of the inner ear. The response variable in these experiments is hearing thresholds measured in decibels (dB). The problem in analysing such experiments is that the hearing threshold observations often suffer from missing data and censoring mechanisms of various types. Additionally, the distribution of hearing thresholds has heavy tails and is peaked. In order to account for the above statistical issues, we present a Bayesian method with a location-shifted log-normal distribution. The method accounts for the uncertainty in the data collection mechanism and the parameters associated with a location-shifted log-normal distribution. We refer to one of the parameters as the &amp;quot;location-shift&amp;quot; parameter. The Bayesian approach provides a posterior distribution of the location-shift parameter that we compare with values estimated in previously published studies. The immediate goal of our proposed method was to quantify the effects of ear surgery and bacteria infection on hearing loss. Thus, we present the merits of the method in the form of a case study, and report posterior distributions of mean hearing loss, probability of clinically significant hearing loss and relative risk. The results show that surgeon 2, using the surgical procedure &amp;quot;oval window&amp;quot;, poses a greater than 40 per cent chance of a 15dB hearing loss regardless of injection of bacteria or not. However, surgeon 1, using the surgical procedure &amp;quot;semicircular canal&amp;quot;, does not pose a significantly greater than 40 per cent chance of a 15dB hearing loss unless there is a Pseudomonas aeruginosa-induced infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; CI: Copyright 2004; JID: 8215016; ppublish</no>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</pb>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0277-6715; 0277-6715</sn>
<ad>Schools of Allied Health and Nursing, The University of Kansas Medical Center, 3901 Rainbow Boulevard, Kansas City, KS 66160, U.S.A.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14748041</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/sim.1606</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14748041</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1579</id>
<a1>Garside,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Singleton,G. T.</a1>
<t1>Canalplasty for chronic tympanic membrane atelectasis</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>2</sp>
<op>6</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Cholesteatoma, Middle Ear/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane/surgery</k1>
<k1>Tympanoplasty</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Canalplasty to prevent accumulation of squamous debris has been proposed as an alternative to tympanoplasty for the treatment of tympanic membrane atelectasis and early cholesteatoma. The goal of this article is to report our experience with canalplasty for the treatment of advanced middle ear atelectasis. MATERIALS AND METHODS: A retrospective review was performed on all patients that underwent tympanoplasty or canalplasty at the University of Florida since 1992. Eight ears (seven patients) with severe atelectasis were found to have been treated with canalplasty (without middle ear reconstruction) to marsupialize the retraction pockets. RESULTS: Follow-up was conducted at an average of 22 months. Four ears required repeat surgical intervention after an average of 12 months: three required canal wall down mastoidectomies for cholesteatoma, and a tympanoplasty was necessary in one case for persistent perforation. Four ears not requiring revision were without cholesteatoma or perforation at an average follow-up time of 26 months. Mean audiometric thresholds were stable or improved, irrespective of the need for revision surgery. CONCLUSIONS: Canalplasty may be an alternative for the treatment of atelectasis in selected patients; however, close follow-up after surgery is necessary because of the potential for progression to cholesteatoma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9950106</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9950106</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1593</id>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Huang,X.</a1>
<a1>Arrington,K. E.</a1>
<a1>Meixner,K.</a1>
<a1>Abrams,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Fetal sheep in utero hear through bone conduction</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Nov-Dec</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>374</sp>
<op>379</op>
<k1>Acoustic Stimulation/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bone Conduction/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Microphonic Potentials/physiology</k1>
<k1>Ear, External/embryology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/embryology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fetus/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Although the air-conduction pathway is the principal mode of sound transmission to the inner ear, this may not be true for the fetus in utero. The fetus detects and responds to sounds in the maternal environment. Exogenous sounds can reach the fetal inner ear through the ear canal and middle ear system, bone conduction, or both. This study was designed to compare the effectiveness of these two routes of sound transmission by recording cochlear microphonic potentials from the fetus in utero in response to airborne sounds. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Cochlear microphonics (CMs) recorded from one round window (RW) of fetal sheep in utero were obtained in three conditions: (1) head uncovered; (2) head covered with a neoprene hood; and (3) head covered with a neoprene hood fashioned with a hole that permitted the pinna and ear canal to be exposed. Tone bursts (0.5, 1.0, and 2.0 kHz) were delivered through a loudspeaker at high intensities (100 to 135 dB sound pressure level) to the flank of the ewe. CMs were detected with indwelling electrodes, amplified, and averaged. CM input-output functions were obtained from the fetus in each of the three conditions described above. RESULTS: CMs recorded with the head uncovered were more sensitive than were the CMs recorded with the hood in place. There was no difference in sensitivity between the condition during which the head was completely covered and the condition in which the pinna and ear canal are exposed. CONCLUSION: The principal mode of sound transmission into the fetal inner ear is through bone conduction.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: HD20084/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Communication Processes and Disorders, University of Florida, Gainesville 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8944295</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8944295</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1510</id>
<a1>Grindal,T. C.</a1>
<a1>Sampson,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>AM-111 prevents hearing loss from semicircular canal injury in otitis media</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>120</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>178</sp>
<op>182</op>
<k1>Administration, Topical</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/complications</k1>
<k1>Peptides/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/complications</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/injuries</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Iatrogenic semicircular canal (SC) transection during mastoidectomy for chronic otitis media often leads to profound hearing loss. AM-111, an apoptosis inhibitor, has been shown to mitigate hearing loss resulting from a variety of inner ear injuries. The goal of this study was to determine if round window application of AM-111 following SC transection in the presence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa otitis media (PA-OM) may reduce the associated hearing loss. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, randomized, controlled study in an animal model. METHODS: PA-OM was induced bilaterally in 34 guinea pigs. After 3 days, both bullae were opened and the lateral SC of one ear was transected. AM-111 or vehicle was applied topically to the round window of the ear that had undergone SC transection. Hearing was assessed with auditory brainstem responses. RESULTS: The mean change in hearing thresholds was significantly less in transected ears treated with AM-111 than those receiving vehicle alone when testing with clicks (22.1 dB vs. 35.0 dB; P = .019) and at 4kHz (11.3 dB vs. 40.0 dB; P = .021). A similar trend was shown with 16 kHz tone pips (27.7 dB vs. 41.1 dB; P = .119). CONCLUSIONS: AM-111 prevents hearing loss from SC transection in the guinea pig model of PA-OM.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; 0 (D-JNKI-1); 0 (Peptides); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19821539</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/lary.20759</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19821539</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1560</id>
<a1>Harris,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Becker,M. O.</a1>
<a1>Holmes,A. E.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Cochlear implant for deafness and blindness from meningitis</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>125</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>403</sp>
<op>405</op>
<k1>Blindness/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Deafness/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Pneumococcal/complications</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11593181; S0194-5998(01)17386-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1067/mhn.2001.116233</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11593181</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1565</id>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Definitive radiotherapy in the management of chemodectomas arising in the temporal bone, carotid body, and glomus vagale</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>363</sp>
<op>371</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Aortic Bodies/surgery</k1>
<k1>Carotid Body Tumor/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Paraganglioma, Extra-Adrenal/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Salvage Therapy</k1>
<k1>Skull Neoplasms/mortality/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To evaluate the results of treatment for 71 patients with 80 chemodectomas of the temporal bone, carotid body, or glomus vagale who were treated with radiation therapy (RT) alone (72 tumors in 71 patients) or subtotal resection and RT (8 tumors) at the University of Florida between 1968 and 1998. METHODS AND MATERIALS: Sixty-six lesions were previously untreated, whereas 14 had undergone prior treatment (surgery, 11 lesions; RT, 1 lesion; or both, 2 lesions) and were treated for locally recurrent disease. All three patients who received prior RT had been treated at other institutions. Patients had minimum follow-up times as follows: 2 years, 66 patients (93%); 5 years, 53 patients (75%); 10 years, 37 patients (52%); 15 years, 29 patients (41%); 20 years, 18 patients (25%); 25 years, 12 patients (17%); and 30 years, 4 patients (6%). RESULTS: There were five local recurrences at 2.6 years, 4.6 years, 5.3 years, 8.3 years, and 18.8 years, respectively. Four were in glomus jugulare tumors and one was a carotid body tumor. Two of the four patients with glomus jugulare failures were salvaged, one with stereotactic radiosurgery and one with surgery and postoperative RT at another institution. Two of the five recurrences had been treated previously at other institutions with RT and/or surgery. Treatment for a third recurrence was discontinued, against medical advice, before receiving the prescribed dose. There were, therefore, only 2 failures in 65 previously untreated lesions receiving the prescribed course of RT. The overall crude local control rate for all 80 lesions was 94%, with an ultimate local control rate of 96% after salvage treatment. The incidence of treatment-related complications was low. CONCLUSIONS: Irradiation offers a high probability of tumor control with relatively minimal risks for patients with chemodectomas of the temporal bone and neck. There were no severe treatment complications.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; CI: Copyright 2001; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida Health Science Center, PO Box 100385, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11295809; 10.1002/hed.1045 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11295809</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1538</id>
<a1>Howard,N. S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Complications of cochlear implant placement with minimal hair shave</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Mar-Apr</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>84</sp>
<op>87</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation/adverse effects/methods/psychology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hair Removal/methods/psychology</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Surgical Wound Infection/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The goal of this study was to determine if a change to minimal-hair shave preparation has altered the incidence of complications after cochlear implant surgery. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Charts were reviewed on 158 consecutive patients that underwent primary cochlear implant surgery for evidence of minor and major surgical complications with full- or minimal-hair shave preparation. RESULTS: Complications were noted within 6 weeks in 5 of 105 patients in the minimal-hair shave group and 3 of 53 in the full-hair shave group (4.8% v 5.7%, P =.53). Delayed complications were noted in 3 within the minimal-shave group and 1 within the full-shave group (2.9% v 1.9%, P =.58). Only 1 wound complication required replacement of the cochlear implant. CONCLUSIONS: There is no evidence that minimal-hair shave adversely affects rates of wound complications in patents undergoing cochlear implant surgery. Therefore, minimal preoperative scalp shave may be an acceptable alternative to the traditional hair shaving technique.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. antonpj@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 14976651; S0196070903001583 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14976651</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1588</id>
<a1>Huang,X.</a1>
<a1>Gerhardt,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Abrams,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Temporary threshold shifts induced by low-pass and high-pass filtered noises in fetal sheep in utero</t1>
<jf>Hearing research</jf>
<jo>Hear.Res.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>113</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>173</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>Acoustic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold/physiology</k1>
<k1>Evoked Potentials, Auditory, Brain Stem/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fetus/physiology</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Noise-Induced/congenital/etiology</k1>
<k1>Noise/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Pregnancy</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<ab>Auditory brainstem responses (ABRs) were obtained from nine late gestational age fetal sheep in utero before and after a 16-h exposure to low-pass (cut-off frequency 1.0 kHz) and high-pass (cut-off frequency 1.0 kHz) noises (approximately 120 dB sound pressure level, recorded in air). Bone-conduction ABRs were elicited by broadband clicks and 0.5, 1.0 and 2.0 kHz tone bursts. Following low-pass noise exposure, ABR thresholds and wave IV latencies increased significantly for 0.5 and 1.0 kHz tone bursts. The high-pass noise exposure produced significant shifts in ABR thresholds and wave IV latencies only for the 1.0 kHz tone bursts. These findings confirm previous reports of low-frequency sound transmission into the fetal inner ear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: HD20084/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7900445; ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0378-5955; 0378-5955</sn>
<ad>Department of Communication Processes and Disorders, University of Florida, Gainesville 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9387996; S0378-5955(97)00139-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9387996</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1575</id>
<a1>Isaacson,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Labyrinthine fenestration in the guinea pig</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>120</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>394</sp>
<op>399</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/injuries</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fenestration, Labyrinth/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incidence</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the auditory effects of single, double, and triple semicircular canal fenestration procedures, with and without sealing the labyrinthine defect. BACKGROUND: Violation of the inner ear remains a feared complication in otologic surgery because it commonly leads to profound sensorineural hearing loss. It has been assumed that the natural history of labyrinthine injury in the guinea pig is similar to that in human beings; however, this assumption has not been rigorously studied. DESIGN: Prospective, randomized, and controlled animal study. SUBJECTS: Sixty pigmented guinea pigs. OUTCOME: Click-evoked electrocochleographic response, with same-ear prefenestration control. RESULTS: All of the fenestration groups had elevated auditory thresholds at 1 hour when compared with controls (P  0.40). CONCLUSIONS: The guinea pig model of labyrinthine fenestration may not be representative of the human condition.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10064645; S0194599899000856 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10064645</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1513</id>
<a1>Jaryszak,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Patel,N. A.</a1>
<a1>Camp,M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Cochlear nerve diameter in normal hearing ears using high-resolution magnetic resonance imaging</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>2042</sp>
<op>2045</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Anatomy, Cross-Sectional</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Nerve/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging/methods</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Deficient cochlear nerves (CN) have been associated with poor cochlear implant performance. Normative data on CN diameter based on radiographic imaging have not been published. The objectives of this study were to determine if CN diameter could be reproducibly measured on parasagittal constructive interference in steady state (CISS)-sequence magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and to establish a normative range for CN diameter. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective review of MRI images by two independent blinded observers. METHODS: Thirty patients (45 ears) with a CISS-sequence MRI done for auditory complaints in patients with normal hearing in one ear were included. CN diameters were measured in a parasagittal plane just medial to the internal auditory canal (IAC) fundus by two independent observers. Cross-sectional areas were calculated and interobserver agreement was evaluated. RESULTS: The CN was identified in 100% of studied ears. In 93%, the diameters were able to be measured by both observers. In 7% of ears, the cochlear nerve was unable to be measured secondary to the proximity of the CN to IAC wall. The CN vertical diameter (1.4 mm +/- 0.21 mm), horizontal diameter (1.0 mm +/- 0.15 mm), and cross-sectional area (1.1 mm +/- 0.26 mm(2)) were normally distributed. There was good interobserver correlation for each measure. CONCLUSIONS: CN diameter can be reliably measured at the IAC fundus. This study establishes normative radiographic data for the CN diameter. These data may be used to evaluate the cause and treatment prognosis in patients with sensorineural hearing loss.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. Eric.Jaryszak@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19650137</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/lary.20516</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19650137</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1507</id>
<a1>Jaryszak,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Sampson,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Biofilm formation by Pseudomonas aeruginosa on ossicular reconstruction prostheses</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov-Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>367</sp>
<op>370</op>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Ear Ossicles/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyapatites/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Ossicular Prosthesis/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media, Suppurative/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Plastics/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis-Related Infections/etiology/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/physiology</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Titanium/chemistry</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Ossicular chain reconstruction may be complicated by prosthesis extrusion. As prostheses are commonly placed in middle ears contaminated with biofilm-forming bacteria, such as Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA), extrusion may be caused by development of a biofilm on the prosthesis and the host response to this biofilm. The purpose of this experiment was to determine if PA forms biofilm on different ossicular chain reconstruction prostheses to a different degree. METHODS: Prostheses made of titanium, hydroxylapatite (HA), and plastic (23 each) were cultured with PA in broth for 96 hours. Biofilm formation was assessed by electron microscopy and quantitative microbiology. RESULTS: Titanium prostheses formed less biofilm than plastic (P = .0003) and HA (P = .003), but there was no difference between HA and plastic. Correction for surface area did not alter these significant differences. CONCLUSIONS: Pseudomonas aeruginosa forms biofilm on ossicular prostheses, particularly those made of plastic and HA. These differences could, in part, explain the extrusion propensity of certain biomaterials.</ab>
<no>JID: 8000029; 0 (Hydroxyapatites); 0 (Plastics); 7440-32-6 (Titanium); 2008/05/22 [received]; 2008/07/06 [accepted]; 2009/03/06 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1532-818X; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA. eric.jaryszak@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19880023; S0196-0709(08)00140-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.amjoto.2008.07.007</do>
<wp>20090306</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19880023</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1511</id>
<a1>Jaryszak,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Sampson,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of ossicular prosthesis biofilms on middle ear scarring and hearing outcomes</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1191</sp>
<op>1195</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Audiometry</k1>
<k1>Bacteria/classification</k1>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Bone Conduction</k1>
<k1>Chronic Disease</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Ear Ossicles/pathology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/pathology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otologic Surgical Procedures</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis-Related Infections/complications/pathology</k1>
<k1>Reoperation</k1>
<k1>Specimen Handling</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Young Adult</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Microbial biofilms have been associated with poor outcomes with a variety of biomedical implants; however, this relationship has not been established with ossicular chain reconstruction prostheses (ORPs). The purpose of this study was to determine if biofilms are present on ORPs in patients undergoing revision ossicular chain reconstruction and if their presence correlates with middle ear scarring or hearing outcomes. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective and blinded. SETTING: Tertiary referral center. PATIENTS: Patients undergoing revision ossicular chain reconstruction with previous ORP placement were enrolled. INTERVENTION/MAIN OUTCOME MEASURE: Ossicular chain reconstruction prostheses associated with poor hearing and residual or recurrent disease were cultured and examined using scanning electron microscopy. Audiometric thresholds and middle ear scarring scores were recorded. RESULTS: Twelve patients were included in the study. Of the prostheses, 25% were culture positive, and 67% had microscopic evidence of biofilm. No difference was found between the middle ear scarring scores (p = 0.31) and hearing outcomes (p = 0.11) of biofilm and nonbiofilm prostheses. There was no correlation between middle ear scarring and degree of conductive hearing loss (R2 = 0.04; p = 0.54). CONCLUSION: Biofilms are commonly found on ORPs at the time of revision ossicular chain reconstruction. The interaction between biofilms and the host environment is complex. Many factors besides biofilms may impact middle ear scarring and hearing.</ab>
<no>JID: 100961504; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1537-4505; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19779385</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/MAO.0b013e3181be64b3</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19779385</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1550</id>
<a1>Jobes,K. E.</a1>
<a1>White,E. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Privacy and security of medical information</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1203</sp>
<op>9, vi</op>
<k1>Computer Security</k1>
<k1>Confidentiality/legislation &amp; jurisprudence</k1>
<k1>Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Patient Rights</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Health Care and Public Health</k1>
<ab>Increasingly, medical information is being stored, accessed, and communicated electronically, which makes this information vulnerable to breaches in security and privacy. Clinicians must be familiar with the best practices for keeping medical information private, as well as the local, state, and federal regulations that govern the security, privacy and patient-identifiable information. Noncompliance carries the potential for civil and criminal penalties.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 0144042; OID: KIE: 116161; OID: NRCBL: VF 8.4; OTO: KIE; GN: KIE: 3 refs.; GN: KIE: KIE Bib: confidentiality; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Shands HealthCare, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0356, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12687737</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; E; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12687737</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1518</id>
<a1>Johnson,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Loeffler,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Jolly,C. N.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Biofilm formation in cochlear implants with cochlear drug delivery channels in an in vitro model</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>577</sp>
<op>582</op>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Drug Delivery Systems/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Models, Anatomic</k1>
<k1>Needles</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/physiology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Cochlear implant (CI) drug delivery (DD) may improve electrophysiological outcomes, but it may also increase the risk of suppurative complications. The aim of this study was to evaluate the development of bacterial biofilms on DD ports when subjected to varying types of penetration. METHODS: Silastic models were constructed to represent CIs with a DD channel, with an intact port, a widely opened port, a noncoring needle penetrating the port, and a noncoring needle removed from the port. CIs were exposed to a culture of a biofilm-forming strain of Staphylococcus aureus for 5 days. Biofilm formation was assessed with quantitative bacterial counts (after eliminating planktonic bacteria) and scanning electron microscopy. RESULTS: Bacterial counts were significantly higher in CIs with widely fenestrated ports than all other port conditions (P = 0.0003). CONCLUSIONS: Biofilm formation may be minimized on CIs with DD by using fine, noncoring needles and limiting the duration of port penetration.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091124; JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); EIN: Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2009 Nov;141(5):665; 2006/09/02 [received]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17418255; S0194-5998(06)03438-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2006.11.006</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17418255</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1606</id>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Tolan,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Giebink,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Goycoolea,M. V.</a1>
<t1>The significance of experimental animal studies in otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>813</sp>
<op>827</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hypersensitivity/complications</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/etiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/etiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media, Suppurative/etiology</k1>
<ab>Animal models have been instrumental in investigating otitis media. Experimental models have allowed for focused research on how such factors as eustachian tube dysfunction and microbial infection contribute to the pathogenesis of otitis media. Antibacterial therapy and immunologic prophylaxis have been developed using these models. Current research is aimed at generating an objective index of middle ear inflammation for guiding patient management.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: 5P50-CD-00133/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 0144042; RF: 104; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Otitis Media Research Center, University of Minnesota School of Medicine, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1870875</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1870875</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1527</id>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Remtulla,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Preoperative antibiotic and steroid therapy and hearing loss caused by semicircular canal transection in pseudomonas otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>896</sp>
<op>901</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Iatrogenic Disease</k1>
<k1>Intraoperative Complications/etiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/complications</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The purpose of this experiment was to determine whether preoperative administration of antibiotics and corticosteroids can attenuate the severity of hearing loss (HL) with semicircular canal (SC) transection in a guinea pig model of Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA) otitis media (OM). Study design and setting Prospective and controlled. METHODS: OM was induced in 64 pigmented guinea pigs by bilateral, transtympanic injection of PA. Two to 4 days later, 1 horizontal SC was randomly transected. In the 1st series, antibiotic therapy was initiated either immediately before or after surgery. In the 2nd series, all animals received preoperative antibiotics, and half received dexamethasone before surgery. Hearing was tested before and after surgery. RESULTS: PA was recovered in all ears. SC transection was associated with significant HL. HL was better in animals given antibiotics preoperatively (clicks, 16 versus 32 dB, P = 0.0220). Addition of preoperative steroids did not significantly further reduce HL (7 versus 14 dB for clicks, P = 0.6919). CONCLUSIONS: HL caused by SC transection in PA OM may be attenuated with preoperative antibiotic therapy in the guinea pig.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15944561; S0194599805002408 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.03.008</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15944561</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1555</id>
<a1>Lehman,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Wilmoth,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Inhibition of matrix metalloproteinases in gerbil cholesteatoma: preliminary findings</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>126</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>404</sp>
<op>408</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cholesteatoma, Middle Ear/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Dipeptides/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Gerbillinae</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 2/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinase 9/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinases/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Protease Inhibitors/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane/drug effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: This study was conducted to examine the role of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) and the impact of a topical MMP inhibitor, ilomostat, on the development of tympanic membrane (TM) atelectasis in the gerbil model. METHODS: Eustachian tubes were cauterized bilaterally in 19 gerbils. Thereafter, both TMs received once-daily topical treatment for 8 weeks with ilomostat or vehicle or no treatment (n = 6 or 7 per group). TM atelectasis was serially graded, and TMs were harvested at 8 weeks. Gelatin zymograms were performed to determine MMP activity. RESULTS: The mean activity levels of proenzyme and active MMP-9 and MMP-2 and degree of atelectasis did not differ between groups. TM atelectasis did not correlate to levels of enzymes across individual samples. CONCLUSIONS: Topical application of an MMP inhibitor did not significantly prevent the development of TM atelectasis. It remains to be determined whether the use of MMP inhibitors may prevent the progression of atelectasis in humans.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Dipeptides); 0 (GM 6001); 0 (Protease Inhibitors); EC 3.4.24.- (Matrix Metalloproteinases); EC 3.4.24.24 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 2); EC 3.4.24.35 (Matrix Metalloproteinase 9); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11997781; S0194599802026797 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11997781</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1590</id>
<a1>Lemmerling,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Normal modiolus: CT appearance in patients with a large vestibular aqueduct</t1>
<jf>Radiology</jf>
<jo>Radiology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>204</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>213</sp>
<op>219</op>
<k1>Abnormalities, Multiple/radiography</k1>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Case-Control Studies</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/abnormalities/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Observer Variation</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<k1>Vestibular Aqueduct/abnormalities/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To determine the computed tomographic (CT) appearance of the normal modiolus and the pathologic alteration in patients with a large vestibular aqueduct and an otherwise normal-appearing cochlea. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Temporal bone CT studies obtained before and after a major upgrade of CT capability in 1992 were reviewed in four groups: Group A (1.5-mm section thickness) comprised 50 normal ears in 43 patients, group B (1-mm section thickness) comprised 75 normal ears in 50 patients, group C (1.5-mm section thickness) comprised 16 ears with a large vestibular aqueduct in 10 patients, and group D (1-mm section thickness) comprised 23 ears with a large vestibular aqueduct in 12 patients. All groups comprised adult and pediatric patients. RESULTS: In groups A and B, the normal modiolus was visualized in 90% and 100% of ears, respectively. In groups C and D, with a total of 39 ears with a large vestibular aqueduct and an otherwise normal cochlea, modiolar deficiency was demonstrated in 100% of ears. CONCLUSION: CT is an excellent technique for depicting the cochlear modiolus. Results suggest that all ears with a large vestibular aqueduct have associated cochlear modiolar deficiencies. Thus, a large vestibular aqueduct may be only occasionally, if ever, an isolated developmental anomaly of the inner ear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0401260; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0033-8419; 0033-8419</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9205250</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9205250</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1592</id>
<a1>Lemmerling,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Stambuk,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>CT of the normal suspensory ligaments of the ossicles in the middle ear</t1>
<jf>AJNR.American journal of neuroradiology</jf>
<jo>AJNR Am.J.Neuroradiol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>471</sp>
<op>477</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Ear Ossicles/radiography</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/radiography</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Image Processing, Computer-Assisted</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Ligaments/radiography</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Stapedius/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tendons/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To establish the range of normal variation in the CT appearance of the middle ear ligaments and the stapedius tendon as an aid in detecting abnormal changes in these structures. METHODS: CT scans of the temporal bone in 75 normal middle ears, obtained with 1-mm-thick sections, were reviewed by two observers, who rated the visibility of the structures of interest on a scale of 1 to 5. RESULTS: The anterior, superior, and lateral malleal ligaments and the medial and lateral parts of the posterior incudal ligament were seen in 68%, 46%, 95%, 26%, and 34% of the ears, respectively. The stapedius tendon was seen in 27% of the cases. When visible, the ligaments were judged to be complete in 90% to 100% of the ears and the stapedius tendon was complete in 65% of cases. Their width varied considerably. Interobserver variability was high for most observations. CONCLUSION: CT scans are more likely to show the malleal than the incudal ligaments. Although the interobserver agreement was statistically significant for most study parameters, the percentage of agreement above that expected by chance was low. When seen, the ligaments usually appeared complete. Understanding the normal range of appearance may help identify abnormalities of the ligaments and tendons of the middle ear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20080214; JID: 8003708; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0195-6108; 0195-6108</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9090405</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9090405</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1591</id>
<a1>Lemmerling,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Stambuk,H. E.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Kubilis,P. S.</a1>
<t1>Normal and opacified middle ears: CT appearance of the stapes and incudostapedial joint</t1>
<jf>Radiology</jf>
<jo>Radiology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>203</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>251</sp>
<op>256</op>
<k1>Ear Diseases/radiography</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle/radiography</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Incus/radiography</k1>
<k1>Observer Variation</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Stapes/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To establish the computed tomographic (CT) visibility of the incudostapedial joint and of the stapes superstructure in normal and opacified middle ears. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Two independent observers reviewed CT studies with 1-mm section thickness of the temporal bone in 75 normal ears and in 33 opacified middle ears (13 of which had definitive proof of disease) to establish the rate of visualization of the stapes and incudostapedial joint. RESULTS: In normal ears, both the stapes crura and the continuity between the incus and stapes were seen in almost 100% of cases, whereas the actual incudostapedial joint was identified in 86% (86 observations) and 67% (67 observations) of cases in the axial and coronal planes, respectively. The position of the incudostapedial joint was below footplate level on the axial images and mostly at or anterior to the midportion of the foot-plate on the coronal images. In 13 clinically confirmed diseased middle ears, the status of the stapes superstructure in all cases and that of the incus in 11 cases was correctly predicted with CT. CONCLUSION: It is now possible to visualize routinely the incudostapedial joint and stapes superstructure at CT. Absence of these structures in an opacified middle ear strongly indicates abnormality.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0401260; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0033-8419; 0033-8419</sn>
<ad>Dienst Radiologie en Medische Beeldvorming, Universitair Ziekenhuis Gent, Belgium.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9122403</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9122403</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1605</id>
<a1>Levine,S. C.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Le,C. T.</a1>
<a1>Haines,S. J.</a1>
<t1>Relative value of diagnostic tests for small acoustic neuromas</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>341</sp>
<op>346</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Evoked Potentials, Auditory, Brain Stem</k1>
<k1>False Negative Reactions</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Neuroma, Acoustic/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Sensitivity and Specificity</k1>
<ab>Auditory brainstem response is now widely employed as a screening test for acoustic neuromas because it is equally sensitive when standardized against computed tomography. We have detected eight small (less than 10 mm) acoustic neuromas using gadolinium enhanced magnetic resonance imaging. In three of these cases, the auditory brainstem response was falsely negative. In contrast, 19 patients with larger tumors (greater than or equal to 10 mm) were found to have no false negative auditory brainstem responses. Auditory brainstem response appears to be less sensitive for detecting small, symptomatic acoustic neuromas.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7909513; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1789302</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1789302</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1607</id>
<a1>Liljemark,W. F.</a1>
<a1>Bloomquist,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Fenner,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Coulter,M. C.</a1>
<t1>Effect of neuraminidase on the adherence to salivary pellicle of Streptococcus sanguis and Streptococcus mitis</t1>
<jf>Caries research</jf>
<jo>Caries Res.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>141</sp>
<op>145</op>
<k1>Acetylgalactosamine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Dental Deposits/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Dental Pellicle</k1>
<k1>Galactose/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyapatites</k1>
<k1>Neuraminidase/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Saliva/drug effects/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sialic Acids/pharmacokinetics</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus sanguis/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<ab>Neuraminidase-sensitive adherence to experimental salivary pellicles was studied using eight strains of Streptococcus sanguis and five strains of Streptococcus mitis. Approximately 60% of the strains of each species showed significantly lower adherence to neuraminidase-treated versus untreated saliva-coated hydroxyapatite. In addition, the adherence of several of these streptococcal strains to saliva-coated hydroxyapatite and neuraminidase-treated saliva-coated hydroxyapatite was inhibited using galactose and N-acetyl-D-galactosamine. Results from these studies suggested that several salivary receptors mediate adherence of these species.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: DE-04614/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0103374; 0 (Hydroxyapatites); 0 (Sialic Acids); 26566-61-0 (Galactose); 31022-50-1 (Acetylgalactosamine); EC 3.2.1.18 (Neuraminidase); ppublish</no>
<pp>SWITZERLAND</pp>
<sn>0008-6568; 0008-6568</sn>
<ad>Microbiology Program, School of Dentistry, Minneapolis, Minn.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2736574</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; D; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2736574</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1545</id>
<a1>Lindberg,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Parell,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hyperbaric compression in the guinea pig with perilymph fistula</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>259</sp>
<op>264</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Evoked Response</k1>
<k1>Barotrauma/complications/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Diseases/complications/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Decompression/methods</k1>
<k1>Eustachian Tube/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Fistula/complications/surgery</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Perilymph/physiology</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Period</k1>
<k1>Random Allocation</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The study goal was to evaluate the effects of hyperbaric therapy on the auditory and vestibular function of guinea pigs compromised by perilymph fistula (PLF). METHODS: Twenty-four pigmented guinea pigs underwent induction of bilateral eustachian tube dysfunction before the creation of a unilateral PLF. Half of the animals were randomly assigned to receive immediate hyperbaric compression treatment of 4 &amp;quot;dives&amp;quot; each. Hearing was tested electrocochleographically, and signs of vestibulopathy were recorded before and after compression. RESULTS: After accounting for the effects of PLF, compression was not associated with significant hearing loss (P = 0.5411). Vestibulopathy was seen only in ears with PLF, and its incidence was similar for compression and noncompression groups. CONCLUSION: Hyperbaric compression does not compromise auditory or vestibular function in guinea pig ears with experimental PLF. SIGNIFICANCE: Our observations support the relative safety of recompression in patients with PLF.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060105; JID: 8508176; CIN: Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2005 Sep;133(3):465-6; author reply 466. PMID: 16143207; CIN: Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2005 Nov;133(5):820-1. PMID: 16274823; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12958577; S0194599803004674 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12958577</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1522</id>
<a1>Lo,T. M.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,M.</a1>
<a1>Young,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss with stapedotomy and treated otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>134</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>674</sp>
<op>679</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Disease Progression</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory, Outer/pathology</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Conductive/etiology/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/complications/microbiology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/complications/microbiology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Risk Factors</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery/adverse effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine if treated Pseudomonas aeruginosa otitis media (PA OM) increases the risk of sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) with stapedotomy. STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: PA OM was induced in 28 guinea pigs. Half of the animals underwent unilateral stapedotomy before antibiotic therapy (untreated), and half underwent stapedotomy after treatment (treated). Control animals underwent saline injections followed by stapedotomy. Electrocochleographic thresholds were measured before and after stapedotomy. Temporal bones were analyzed histomorphologically. RESULTS: Less SNHL was seen after stapedotomy in treated ears than in untreated ears (P = 0.0268). SNHL after stapedotomy in treated ears was similar to controls (P = 0.9370). Severe damage to cochlear outer hair cells was found in untreated ears. CONCLUSIONS: Ears with PA OM treated previously are not at increased risk of SNHL with stapedotomy. SIGNIFICANCE: Stapedotomy may be carried out with caution in the setting of inactive, chronic OM.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 2005/09/23 [received]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16564395; S0194-5998(05)02108-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.11.008</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16564395</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1517</id>
<a1>Loeffler,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Johnson,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Burne,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Biofilm formation in an in vitro model of cochlear implants with removable magnets</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>583</sp>
<op>588</op>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Models, Anatomic</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Design</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/physiology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Cochlear implant (CI) recesses, such as the removable magnet pocket, appear to harbor more biofilm than smooth surfaces. The aim of this study was to examine the impact of removable magnets on biofilm formation in an in vitro model. METHODS: Silastic models were constructed to represent CIs with and without a magnet pocket and with and without a titanium blank in the pocket. CIs were exposed to a culture of a biofilm forming strain of Staphylococcus aureus. Adherence of planktonic bacteria and biofilm formation were assessed with quantitative bacterial counts and scanning electron microscopy. RESULTS: Adherent bacterial counts were significantly higher in CI models with an empty magnet pocket (P = 0.0097). Biofilm formation was significantly lower in CI models without a magnet pocket (P = 0.0121). CONCLUSIONS: CI magnet pockets harbor bacteria that can increase biofilm development in an in vitro model.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091124; JID: 8508176; EIN: Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2009 Nov;141(5):665; 2006/09/02 [received]; 2006/11/01 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17418256; S0194-5998(06)03436-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2006.11.005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17418256</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1611</id>
<a1>MacDonald,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P.</a1>
<a1>Day,A. L.</a1>
<t1>The anterior subtemporal, medial transpetrosal approach to the upper basilar artery and ponto-mesencephalic junction</t1>
<jf>Neurosurgery</jf>
<jo>Neurosurgery</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>84</sp>
<op>89</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Basilar Artery/surgery</k1>
<k1>Cavernous Sinus/surgery</k1>
<k1>Chondroma/surgery</k1>
<k1>Craniotomy/methods</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intracranial Aneurysm/surgery</k1>
<k1>Intracranial Arteriovenous Malformations/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Meningeal Neoplasms/surgery</k1>
<k1>Meningioma/surgery</k1>
<k1>Mesencephalon/blood supply/surgery</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Petrous Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pons/blood supply/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/etiology</k1>
<k1>Skull Neoplasms/surgery</k1>
<k1>Stereotaxic Techniques</k1>
<k1>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage/surgery</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To describe and anatomically analyze the amount of exposure provided by an anterior subtemporal, medial transpetrosal approach to access the upper third of the basilar artery, ventral mesencephalon, pons, and posterior cavernous sinus. PATIENTS AND METHODS: The outcomes of six patients who underwent surgical treatment via the anterior subtemporal, medial transpetrosal approach at our institution during the past 2 years were reviewed. The series included three patients with subarachnoid hemorrhage from low-lying basilar apex aneurysms, one patient with intraparenchymal hemorrhage from a pontine cavernous malformation, and two patients with slowly progressive cranial neuropathies secondary to petroclival tumors. Thirty dry temporal bone specimens were also measured to quantify the height of petrous bone resection and added proximal basilar artery exposure. RESULTS: The surgical exposure was greatly enhanced in each instance, allowing each lesion to be treated in a straightforward manner with minimal added morbidity (one trochlear nerve palsy, one worsening of a preexistent oculomotor nerve palsy). Our subsequent morphometric analysis indicates that an additional 1 to 1.5 cm of basilar artery, clivus, and pons exposure over that of a standard anterior subtemporal approach is provided by this technique. CONCLUSION: This approach combines the wide view of the subtemporal approach with the more proximal exposure afforded by a medial petrosectomy. The widened visualization of the ventral pons and mesencephalon minimizes cranial nerve morbidity, greatly facilitates dissection of low-lying aneurysms, and provides proximal basilar artery control that would otherwise be obscured by the petrous ridge.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7802914; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0148-396X; 0148-396X</sn>
<ad>Division of Neurosurgery, University of Arizona, Tucson, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9657193</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9657193</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1604</id>
<a1>Maisel,R. H.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Iber,C.</a1>
<a1>Mahowald,M.</a1>
<a1>Wilson,K. S.</a1>
<a1>Fiedler,B.</a1>
<a1>Schluter,J.</a1>
<t1>Uvulopalatopharyngoplasty for obstructive sleep apnea: a community&amp;#39;s experience</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>604</sp>
<op>607</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Airway Obstruction/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Body Mass Index</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hospitals, Community</k1>
<k1>Hospitals, Private</k1>
<k1>Hospitals, Teaching</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nasal Septum/surgery</k1>
<k1>Palate/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pharynx/surgery</k1>
<k1>Sleep Apnea Syndromes/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Turbinates/surgery</k1>
<k1>Uvula/surgery</k1>
<ab>Uvulopalatopharyngoplasty (UPPP) has become an accepted method for treating obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), with a reported success rate as high as 77%, depending upon inclusionary and outcome criteria. The authors reviewed the records of 90 patients with moderately severe OSA (apnea plus hypopnea index [AHI] greater than 20) who underwent UPPP at either a private community or an academic hospital. Forty percent of patients experienced more than a 50% reduction in their AHI with UPPP. Only 22 (24%) of the patients had a postoperative AHI less than 50% of the preoperative AHI and less than 20, i.e., met the authors&amp;#39; criteria for surgical success. The success rate for community otolaryngologists was no different than that achieved in the academic institution. When data from previously published reports were analyzed using these criteria for success, similar results were observed. This study suggests that the effectiveness of UPPP performed by the general otolaryngologic community is equivalent to that reported in the literature. However, more rigorous criteria must be applied to UPPP when evaluating its results and in counseling potential candidates for this procedure.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Hennenin County Medical Center, Minneapolis, MN 55415.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1602908</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Comparative Study; Journal Article; Multicenter Study; IM</sf>
<do>10.1288/00005537-199206000-00003</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1602908</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1514</id>
<a1>Malaty,J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of blood and mucus on tympanostomy tube biofilm formation</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>867</sp>
<op>870</op>
<k1>Bacteriology/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Biofilms</k1>
<k1>Blood Proteins/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Cerebrospinal Fluid Otorrhea/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Fibronectins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation</k1>
<k1>Mucus/metabolism/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Tympanostomy tube (TT) biofilm formation may lead to refractory otorrhea and occlusion. The aim of this study was to determine whether TT biofilm formation may be promoted by mucus or blood exposure. STUDY DESIGN: In vitro, controlled. METHODS: Fluoroplastic TTs were exposed to blood, mucoid effusion, or saline. Half were allowed to dry. TTs were cultured with Pseudomonas aeruginosa. After 4 days, gentamicin was added to kill planktonic bacteria. Biofilm formation was assessed by quantitative bacterial counts and scanning electron microscopy. RESULTS: Mucus pretreatment (dry and wet) did not increase biofilm formation. Both dry and wet blood exposure increased biofilm formation by bacterial counts (P &amp;lt; .0001). Biofilm formation was demonstrated by electron microscopy in all groups. CONCLUSIONS: P. aeruginosa biofilm formation on fluoroplastic TTs is enhanced by blood exposure. Care should be taken to minimize bleeding with TT placement to reduce the risk of biofilm formation.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; 0 (Blood Proteins); 0 (Fibronectins); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18520185; 00005537-200805000-00020 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/MLG.0b013e3181671b02</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18520185</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1533</id>
<a1>Malaty,J.</a1>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Zhang,M.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,G.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss and extent of labyrinthine injury in Pseudomonas otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>25</sp>
<op>29</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology</k1>
<k1>Injury Severity Score</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/complications/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/complications</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/injuries</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To determine if the severity of hearing loss due to semicircular canal transection (SCT) in Pseudomonas otitis media (POM) is a function of the extent of the labyrinthine injury. METHODS: POM was induced bilaterally in 45 guinea pigs. After 2 to 4 days, SCT was performed in one 1 on the horizontal canal, the superior canal, or both the horizontal and the superior canals. Auditory-evoked brainstem responses were measured before and after SCT. RESULTS: POM was induced bilaterally in all animals. Elevation of click thresholds was found in almost all SCT ears of all 3 groups; however, there were no significant differences between groups. Comparing the SCT ear to the contralateral, control ear, mean hearing losses in the horizontal, superior, and horizontal + superior SCT groups were 23 dB, 27 dB, and 24 dB, respectively. CONCLUSIONS: Hearing loss does not correlate with extent of labyrinthine injury in POM in the guinea pig. EBM rating: B-2.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15632905; S0194599804018716 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2004.09.088</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15632905</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1509</id>
<a1>Marques,I. L.</a1>
<a1>Nackashi,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Borgo,H. C.</a1>
<a1>Martinelli,A. P.</a1>
<a1>Pegoraro-Krook,M. I.</a1>
<a1>Williams,W. N.</a1>
<a1>Dutka,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Seagle,M. B.</a1>
<a1>Souza,T. V.</a1>
<a1>Garla,L. A.</a1>
<a1>Neto,J. S.</a1>
<a1>Silva,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Graciano,M. I.</a1>
<a1>Moorhead,J.</a1>
<a1>Piazentin-Penna,S. H.</a1>
<a1>Feniman,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Zimmermann,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Bento-Goncalves,C. G.</a1>
<a1>Pimentel,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Boggs,S.</a1>
<a1>Jorge,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Shuster,J.</a1>
<t1>Longitudinal study of growth of children with unilateral cleft-lip palate from birth to two years of age</t1>
<jf>The Cleft palate-craniofacial journal : official publication of the American Cleft Palate-Craniofacial Association</jf>
<jo>Cleft Palate.Craniofac.J.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>603</sp>
<op>609</op>
<k1>Brazil/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Child Development</k1>
<k1>Cleft Lip/epidemiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Cleft Palate/epidemiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Infant, Newborn</k1>
<k1>Longitudinal Studies</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To study the growth of children with complete unilateral cleft lip and palate (UCLP) from birth to 2 years of age and to construct specific UCLP growth curves. DESIGN: Physical growth was a secondary outcome measure of a National Institutes of Health-sponsored longitudinal, prospective clinical trial involving the University of Florida (United States) and the University of Sao Paulo (Brazil). PATIENTS: Six hundred twenty-seven children with UCLP, nonsyndromic, both genders. METHODS: Length, weight, and head circumference were prospectively measured for a group of children enrolled in a clinical trial. Median growth curves for the three parameters (length, weight, head circumference) were performed and compared with the median for the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) curves. The median values for length, weight, and head circumference at birth and 6, 12, 18, and 24 months of age were plotted against NCHS median values and statistically compared at birth and 24 months. SETTING: Hospital de Reabilitacao de Anomalias Craniofaciais, Universidade de Sao Paulo, Bauru, Brazil (HRAC-USP). RESULTS: At birth, children of both genders with UCLP presented with smaller body dimensions in relation to NCHS median values, but the results suggest a catch-up growth for length, weight, and head circumference for girls and for weight (to some degree) and head circumference for boys. CONCLUSIONS: Weight was the most compromised parameter for both genders, followed by length and then head circumference. There was no evidence of short stature. This study established growth curves for children with UCLP.</ab>
<no>GR: R01 DE010437/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-05/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-05S1/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-06/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-07/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-08/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-09/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 DE010437-10/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9102566; NIHMS124848; OID: NLM: NIHMS124848; OID: NLM: PMC2787972; 2009/05/16 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1055-6656; 1055-6656</sn>
<ad>Hospital de Reabilitacao de Anomalias Craniofaciais-Universidade de Sao Paulo, CEP: 17043-900, Bauru, Sao Paulo, Brazil. marquesi@usp.br</ad>
<an>PMID: 19860503; 08-105 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Multicenter Study; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; D; IM</sf>
<do>10.1597/08-105</do>
<wp>20090516</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19860503</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2787972</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1524</id>
<a1>McFadden,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Wilmoth,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Preoperative computed tomography may fail to detect patients at risk for perilymph gusher</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>770, 772</sp>
<op>4</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Ear, Inner/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Perilymph</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>Perilymph gusher (PG) is a very rare occurrence that can lead to an adverse outcome during inner ear surgery. In the absence of a family history of X-linked mixed deafness syndrome, surgeons may have difficulty determining if a patient is at risk preoperatively. Radiographic imaging is often performed in an attempt to identify such a possibility, but there are few data to support the value of negative studies. We conducted a retrospective study of 3 cases of PG in which findings on preoperative high-resolution computed tomography (CT) of the temporal bone had been interpreted as normal. We reviewed these CTs to discern if they did in fact demonstrate any abnormalities that might have indicated a risk of PG, and we found that the original radiologist had missed a dilated internal auditory canal and a deformity of the cochlear modiolus in the affected ear of 1 of these patients. No abnormality was detected on review of the CTs of the other 2 patients. Therefore, we conclude that negative CT findings do not necessarily rule out a risk of PG.</ab>
<no>JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Florida, Box 100264, 1600 S.W. Archer Rd., Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16408555</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16408555</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1582</id>
<a1>McFeely,W. J.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Rodriguez,F. J.</a1>
<a1>Holmes,A. E.</a1>
<t1>Somatosensory phenomena after multichannel cochlear implantation in prelingually deaf adults</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>467</sp>
<op>471</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Age Factors</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Deafness/surgery</k1>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Perceptual Disorders/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Speech Perception/physiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Central auditory system development in thought to be dependent on normal auditory nerve excitation. Central auditory disorganization may differ between prelingual and postlingual deafness. One possible clinical manifestation of such central auditory disorganization is somatosensory perception with cochlear implant stimulation. The purpose of this study was to investigate the incidence and characteristics of somatosensory phenomena in prelingually and postlingually deafened adult cochlear implant subjects. STUDY DESIGN: The study design was a retrospective analysis. SETTING: The study was performed at an academic tertiary referral center. PATIENTS: This study included 32 adult multichannel cochlear implant recipients. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Subjective patient reporting of sensory perception after cochlear implant stimulation was reviewed. RESULTS: All 10 prelingually deaf subjects noted somatosensory phenomena distant from the implanted ear (e.g., chest, abdomen) on implant stimulation. These sensations resolved gradually for all patients. No subject deafened after the age of 2 years reported somatosensory perceptions. CONCLUSIONS: Somatosensory phenomena experienced by prelingually deafened adults suggest that disorganization of central auditory system pathways is more severe in these individuals. Earlier auditory deprivation appears to produce greater central auditory alterations, and perceptible crossover between somatosensory and auditory signals may be the end result.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7909513; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9661756</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9661756</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1586</id>
<a1>McFeely,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Singleton,G. T.</a1>
<a1>Rodriguez,F. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Intratympanic gentamicin treatment for Meniere&amp;#39;s disease</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>589</sp>
<op>596</op>
<k1>Administration, Topical</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Pure-Tone</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Speech</k1>
<k1>Bone Conduction/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Caloric Tests/methods</k1>
<k1>Drug Delivery Systems</k1>
<k1>Ear, Middle</k1>
<k1>Electronystagmography</k1>
<k1>Evaluation Studies as Topic</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Gentamicins/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Hearing Disorders/chemically induced</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/chemically induced</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Ice</k1>
<k1>Intubation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Meniere Disease/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Polyethylenes</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Safety</k1>
<k1>Speech Perception/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane/surgery</k1>
<k1>Vertigo/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: The purpose of this study was to evaluate the safety and efficacy of a modified intratympanic gentamicin technique in patients with intractable unilateral or bilateral Meniere&amp;#39;s disease. METHODS: A retrospective review of 25 consecutive patients who underwent gentamicin treatment for Meniere&amp;#39;s disease was conducted between 1992 and 1996. Two separate delivery systems were used during this study, with the last 13 subjects undergoing placement of the new system (flanged polyethylene tubing). RESULTS: Follow-up averaged 23 months. Absence of vertigo spells was reported in 88%, and substantial control was achieved in 12%. Four of five patients with bilateral disease achieved complete control. Results for the two delivery systems were not significantly different. Absence of ice-water caloric response was seen in 75% (15 of 20) patients. Clinically significant sensorineural hearing loss occurred in 5 (20%) of 25 ears. Nonserviceable hearing developed in only two (8%) patients. CONCLUSIONS: Our results support the previously reported efficacy and relative safety of gentamicin infusion therapy for intractable Meniere&amp;#39;s disease. Polyethylene tubing may be more advantageous than T-tube delivery because of anatomic concerns in certain patients.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Gentamicins); 0 (Ice); 0 (Polyethylenes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9591855; S0194599898001545 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9591855</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1525</id>
<a1>Mehta,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Lee,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Opening plugged tympanostomy tubes: effect of biofilm formation</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>134</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>121</sp>
<op>125</op>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Biofilms/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Instillation, Drug</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Ofloxacin/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Prostheses and Implants/microbiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Failure</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/physiology</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pneumoniae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Treatment Failure</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine if the presence of a bacterial biofilm impacts the rate of clearing of mucoid plugs from tympanostomy tubes (TTs). STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: Ex vivo model. Stainless steel Reuter Bobbin TTs (n = 18) were placed in growth medium with Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Streptococcus pneumoniae for 12 days to promote biofilm formation. Tympanostomy tubes (n = 18) placed in growth medium, without bacteria, for 12 days served as controls. Biofilm formation was assessed by scanning electron microscopy. All TTs were filled with middle ear mucus and allowed to dry, thereby forming a plug. TTs were placed in a model ear chamber, covered with ofloxacin otic solution, and the time to clear each plug was recorded. RESULTS: Biofilm formation was consistently encountered on TTs exposed to bacteria but in no TTs in the control group. There was a significant effect of the biofilm on plug clearance, favoring TTs without a biofilm (P = 0.0333). Although there was no significant difference in the proportion of unplugged TTs (P = 0.264), TTs with a biofilm did not clear plugs as rapidly as TTs without a biofilm (P = 0.0416). CONCLUSIONS: The presence of a biofilm may slow the time to clear mucoid TT plugs, but it does not seem to affect the overall proportion of TTs that are unplugged.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 82419-36-1 (Ofloxacin); 2004/11/23 [received]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16399191; S0194-5998(05)01970-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.10.017</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16399191</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1532</id>
<a1>Mehta,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Opening plugged tympanostomy tubes: effect of inner diameter and shaft length</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>326</op>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Instillation, Drug</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Ofloxacin/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion</k1>
<k1>Pharmaceutical Solutions</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Design</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Failure</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine whether tympanostomy tube (TT) inner diameter or shaft length impacts the rate of mucoid plug clearance. STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: Ex vivo model. Silicone TTs with different inner-diameters (ID) and shaft-length (SL) pairings (1.14 mm ID x 12 mm SL versus 1.14 mm ID x 1 mm SL; 1.14 mm ID x 4.8 mm SL versus 1.32 mm ID x 4.8 mm SL) were plugged with middle-ear mucus (n = 15 per group) and placed in a model ear chamber. Ofloxacin otic solution was instilled into the chamber to cover the plugged TT, and the time to clearance of each plug was recorded. RESULTS: TTs with larger IDs ( P = 0.019) and greater SLs ( P = 0.033) cleared plugs more rapidly. However, the difference in the percentage of tubes that unplugged was not significant ( P = 0.151). CONCLUSIONS: Rate of ex vivo TT plug clearance may be altered by changing TT ID and SL.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Pharmaceutical Solutions); 82419-36-1 (Ofloxacin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15692548; S0194599804020145 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2004.10.006</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15692548</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1576</id>
<a1>Meixner,K. E.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Dohar,J. E.</a1>
<t1>The effects of kanamycin injection into the fetal lamb cochlea</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>196</sp>
<op>8, 203-4</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents/administration &amp; dosage/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Audiometry</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/drug effects/embryology</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory, Inner/drug effects/pathology</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/chemically induced/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Injections, Intralesional</k1>
<k1>Kanamycin/administration &amp; dosage/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Pregnancy</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/drug effects/pathology</k1>
<ab>Mammalian auditory hair cells have minimal capacity for repair or regeneration after a variety of insults, including acoustic trauma and aminoglycoside exposure. Although fetal tissues have a greater potential for repair and regeneration than adult tissues, there have been no reported studies on fetal hair cell response to injury in mammals. The purpose of this research was to investigate the effects of local application of kanamycin on fetal lamb cochlear hair cells. Eleven fetal lambs in the early third trimester underwent kanamycin injection through the left round-window membrane. The right ear served as a control. Click-evoked compound action potentials (CAPs) were serially recorded in 8 fetuses. CAPs were observed in all control ears. None of the 8 kanamycin-injected ears had measurable CAPs on postoperative day 1. One kanamycin-injected ear demonstrated definite CAPs, beginning on postoperative day 6. Hair cells were found to be intact in 6 of 9 kanamycin-treated ears. Hair cells were missing only in animals that went into premature labor. The presence of intact hair cells despite the loss of measurable CAPs in kanamycin-perfused lamb cochleae was striking. This finding may indicate that the fetal auditory epithelium is relatively resistant to aminoglycoside injury or may be capable of prompt repair or regeneration. Further studies on the effects of aminoglycoside injury in the fetal cochleae seem to be warranted.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 7701817; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 59-01-8 (Kanamycin); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10188356</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10188356</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1559</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Villaret,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<t1>Radiotherapy and radiosurgery for skull base tumors</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1065</sp>
<op>77, viii</op>
<k1>Angiofibroma/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Meningeal Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Meningioma/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Neurilemmoma/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Paraganglioma, Extra-Adrenal/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pituitary Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiosurgery</k1>
<k1>Skull Base Neoplasms/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<ab>Tumors arising in the vicinity of the skull base are relatively uncommon; however, lesions that may be successfully treated by radiotherapy and radiosurgery include temporal bone chemodectomas, schwannomas, juvenile angiofibromas, pituitary adenomas, and meningiomas. This article reviews treatment techniques and results and discusses the pertinent literature.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 0144042; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11728932</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11728932</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1537</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Friedman,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Management of acoustic schwannoma</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>38</sp>
<op>47</op>
<k1>Combined Modality Therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microsurgery</k1>
<k1>Neuroma, Acoustic/radiotherapy/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiosurgery</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To discuss the optimal management for patients with acoustic schwannoma. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Review of the pertinent literature. RESULTS: Microsurgery, stereotactic radiosurgery, and fractionated radiotherapy result in cure rates that approximate 90% at 5 years. Depending on tumor extent and surgical approach, the morbidity of microsurgery may exceed that of stereotactic radiosurgery and fractionated radiotherapy. Patients with useful hearing before treatment may have a higher likelihood of hearing preservation after radiotherapy compared with radiosurgery. CONCLUSION: Both microsurgery and radiosurgery are good options for patients with tumors less than 3 cm. Depending on tumor extent and the surgical approach, the morbidity of microsurgery may exceed that of radiosurgery. Patients with useful hearing may have a higher likelihood of hearing preservation after radiotherapy. Microsurgery is preferred for patients in whom the disease progresses after initial irradiation and in patients with tumors larger than 3 cm.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; RF: 56; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15011205; S0196070903001169 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15011205</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1561</id>
<a1>Mendenhall,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Hinerman,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Amdur,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Stringer,S. P.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Singleton,G. T.</a1>
<a1>Cassisi,N. J.</a1>
<t1>Treatment of paragangliomas with radiation therapy</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngologic clinics of North America</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Clin.North Am.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1007</sp>
<op>20, vii-viii</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Head and Neck Neoplasms/diagnosis/mortality/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Paraganglioma/diagnosis/mortality/radiotherapy</k1>
<k1>Prognosis</k1>
<k1>Radiation Dosage</k1>
<k1>Radiation Injuries/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Radiotherapy/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Survival Analysis</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>Paragangliomas of the head and neck may be treated successfully with surgery, radiation therapy, or stereotactic radiosurgery. The choice of treatment depends on the location and extent of the tumor, the presence of multiple tumors, the age and health of the patient, and the preference of the patient and attending physician. This article reviews the role of radiation therapy in the treatment of patients with paragangliomas of the head and neck.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 0144042; RF: 37; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0030-6665; 0030-6665</sn>
<ad>Department of Radiation Oncology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0385, USA. mendewil@shands.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11557452</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11557452</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1613</id>
<a1>Pertzborn,S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Endolymphatic sac surgery</t1>
<yr>2004</yr>
<sp>198</sp>
<op>198-204</op>
<no>ID: 54492663</no>
<a2>Haberman,Rex S.</a2>
<t2>Middle ear and mastoid surgery</t2>
<pb>Thieme</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<sn>1588901734 9781588901736 3131360615 9783131360618</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1548</id>
<a1>Pertzborn,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Reith,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Mancuso,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Epineurial pseudocysts of the intratemporal facial nerve</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>490</sp>
<op>493</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cysts/pathology/radiography</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Facial Nerve Diseases/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Surgical Procedures, Operative/methods</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Facial nerve pseudocysts are infrequently encountered during temporal bone surgery or neurotologic evaluation. This report describes the senior author&amp;#39;s experience with epineurial pseudocysts of the intratemporal facial nerve. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective case review. SETTING: Academic, tertiary referral center. RESULTS: Epineurial pseudocysts were identified on computed tomography in the mastoid segment in seven patients during evaluation for profound sensorineural hearing loss or facial nerve symptoms. Histopathologic examination revealed fibroadipose tissue without nerve tissue in five cases that underwent excision. CONCLUSIONS: Facial nerve epineurial pseudocysts are uncommon, benign lesions of the mastoid segment. Surgical excision may be safely performed for facial motor symptoms or for cochlear implant placement.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 100961504; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-7129; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12806305</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12806305</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1535</id>
<a1>Prevatt,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Sedwick,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss with semicircular canal transection and Pseudomonas aeruginosa otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>131</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>248</sp>
<op>252</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media, Suppurative/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/etiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/surgery</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine if Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA) otitis media (OM) increases the risk of sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) with semicircular canal transection in the guinea pig model. METHODS: PA was injected transtympanically into both middle ears of pigmented guinea pigs. Saline-injected animals served as controls. Two to 4 days after injection, one horizontal semicircular canal was transected and sealed. Hearing was tested using electrocochleography before and after transection. RESULTS: PA-OM was induced in all PA-injected ears. Five days after semicircular canal transection, click-evoked thresholds were significantly elevated in ears with PA-OM (P = 0.00009) but not in saline-injected ears (P = 0.398). CONCLUSION: Violation of the inner ear in the presence of PA-OM is associated with increased risk of SNHL in the guinea pig. SIGNIFICANCE: Factors unique to PA infection may be responsible for SNHL with labyrinthine injury in humans with chronic otitis media.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15365544; S0194599804001652 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2004.01.017</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15365544</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1556</id>
<a1>Richards,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Moorhead,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Sympathetic cochleolabyrinthitis in revision stapedectomy surgery</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>126</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>273</sp>
<op>280</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Autoantibodies/immunology</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/etiology/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Labyrinthitis/etiology/immunology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Otosclerosis/complications/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/etiology</k1>
<k1>Reoperation</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Stapes Surgery/methods</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The purpose of this study was to determine whether revision stapedectomy could precipitate sensorineural hearing loss in the contralateral ear. METHODS: We conducted a retrospective review of 148 patients undergoing primary or revision stapedectomy at an academic, tertiary care facility. RESULTS: Stapedectomy resulted in significant improvements in mean air conduction thresholds in the ipsilateral ear. Overall, there were no significant changes in either the air or bone conduction values of the contralateral ear. Two patients demonstrated a &amp;gt;20-dB decline in speech reception threshold and/or &amp;gt;20% decrease word recognition in the contralateral ear. Both of these patients demonstrated the decline only after revision surgery. CONCLUSION: Revision stapedectomy is on rare occasions associated with hearing loss in the contralateral ear. Contralateral hearing loss after revision stapedectomy may be due to sympathetic cochleolabyrinthitis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; 0 (Autoantibodies); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11956535; S0194599802377568 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11956535</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1528</id>
<a1>Roland,P. S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Dohar,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Poole,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Slattery,W. H.,3rd</a1>
<t1>Managing acute otitis media in children with tympanostomy tubes. Panel discussion</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>4 Suppl 2</is>
<sp>7</sp>
<op>15</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Patient Care Management</k1>
<k1>Recurrence</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15943075</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Congresses; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15943075</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1503</id>
<a1>Rosenwasser,R.</a1>
<a1>Winterstein,A. G.</a1>
<a1>Rosenberg,A. F.</a1>
<a1>Rosenberg,E. I.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Perioperative medication errors in otolaryngology</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>120</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1214</sp>
<op>1219</op>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Medication errors are a common cause of poor clinical outcomes. Information on perioperative medication errors is scarce. This study was aimed at identifying the nature, cause, and potential remedies for medication errors in otolaryngologic surgery. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective and descriptive. METHODS: Clinicians were incentivized for reporting possible medication errors that occurred from the preoperative through the first postoperative clinic visit over a 2-month period. Each report was investigated by an expert panel to determine validity, preventability, contributing factors, and potential preventative measures. A random sample of procedures and clinic visits were monitored for compliance with safe medication practices and information flow. RESULTS: From 589 surgeries, 20 medication errors were reported (two preoperative, four operative, five during hospital admission, two in transition between services, four during discharge, and three postoperative). Errors included wrong dose (seven), omitted dose (six), wrong drug (five), wrong site (two), and unnecessary drug (one). Causes included failure to consider weight-based dosing, use accurate drug references, calculate the total medication supply needed, verify the administration site, consider pertinent patient information (e.g., allergies), reconcile medications upon transfers, and document medication histories. Use of preprinted order forms was flawed, and discharge instructions were insufficient to guide patients postoperatively. CONCLUSIONS: Failure to adhere to safe medication-use practices occurred throughout perioperative care. Improvement in medication documentation, following established safe practices, integration of patient information in prescribing decisions, and use of clinical decision support systems appear necessary to prevent perioperative medication errors in otolaryngology.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-4995; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Pharmaceutical Outcomes and Policy, College of Pharmacy, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20513042</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/lary.20922</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20513042</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1596</id>
<a1>Rust,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Singleton,G. T.</a1>
<a1>Wilson,J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Bioglass middle ear prosthesis: long-term results</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>371</sp>
<op>374</op>
<k1>Audiometry, Pure-Tone</k1>
<k1>Biocompatible Materials</k1>
<k1>Ear Ossicles/physiopathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Conductive/physiopathology/rehabilitation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Ossicular Prosthesis</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Failure</k1>
<ab>The purpose of this study was to review the University of Florida&amp;#39;s long-term results with Bioglass middle ear prostheses. Between April 1984 and November 1987, 37 patients were implanted with Bioglass prostheses (25 total and 12 partial ossicular replacements). Twenty-one patients had postoperative data of at least 24 months (range, 24 to 126 months; mean, 86 months; median, 100 months), and five patients had &amp;gt; 10 years&amp;#39; follow-up. In three cases, portions of fractured prostheses extruded, leaving an intact tympanic membrane. One patient with a total ossicular prosthesis was reexplored at 38 months for conductive hearing loss and found to have a prosthesis fracture (n = 1). There were no extrusions of intact prostheses, even in patients in whom the prosthesis was placed directly under the tympanic membrane or graft (n = 12). After 24 months, the mean pure-tone average air-bone gap was 24 dB (24% had ABG &amp;lt; or = 10 dB; 53% had ABG &amp;lt; or = 20 dB). Air-bone gap closures were stable over time. Our results demonstrated that Bioglass middle ear prostheses have excellent long-term tissue compatibility. The four failures are attributed to fractures in early experimental prototypes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7909513; 0 (Biocompatible Materials); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8817012</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8817012</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1567</id>
<a1>Ryan,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Pneumococcal antibiotic resistance and rates of meningitis in children</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>110</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>961</sp>
<op>964</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Community-Acquired Infections/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Microbial</k1>
<k1>Florida/epidemiology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Bacterial/epidemiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Haemophilus/epidemiology/etiology</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Pneumococcal/epidemiology/etiology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/complications/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Streptococcal Infections</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pneumoniae/drug effects</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Recent studies have shown alarmingly high rates of antibiotic resistance in Streptococcus pneumoniae isolates from patients with otitis media. A recent study has implicated resistant S pneumoniae for rising rates of acute mastoiditis. The purpose of this study was to determine whether S pneumoniae antibiotic resistance has similarly affected the rate of pediatric community-acquired meningitis, the most common intracranial complication of otitis media. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective chart review. METHODS: All cases of pediatric community-acquired meningitis treated at an academic tertiary care hospital during a 10-year period were reviewed, and meningitis rates were calculated as a proportion of yearly admissions. RESULTS: The overall rate of meningitis decreased linearly during the study period (P = .001). This was largely because of a drop in the rate of Haemophilus influenzae meningitis (P = .001), corresponding with the introduction of H influenzae type B vaccine. Annual rates of S pneumoniae meningitis did not change. Only one case of S pneumoniae meningitis was due to a highly penicillin-resistant strain and isolates from four cases had intermediate sensitivity. Twenty-four of 83 cases were associated with antecedent acute otitis media and 63% of these had been treated with antibiotics before admission. Otitis media, as a cause of meningitis, did not increase during the study period. CONCLUSION: S pneumoniae is responsible for a greater proportion of cases of pediatric community-acquired meningitis. However, this is because of a decline in the rate of H influenzae cases, not the rise in S pneumoniae antibiotic resistance.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10852513; 00005537-200006000-00014 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200006000-00014</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10852513</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1563</id>
<a1>Sedwick,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Magnetic resonance imaging in the search for retrocochlear pathology</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>124</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>652</sp>
<op>655</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Image Enhancement</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrocochlear Diseases/diagnosis</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: The purpose of this study is to evaluate the incidence of retrocochlear pathologic conditions that may be seen with full, contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging of the brain, relative to more limited studies of the internal auditory canals (IACs) in patients with unilateral hearing loss or tinnitus with or without dizziness. METHODS: A retrospective study was performed on all patients who had a magnetic resonance imaging of the brain and otologic symptoms over a 7-year period. RESULTS: Abnormalities were found in 11 of 128 patients with only auditory symptoms and in 63 of 282 patients with auditory symptoms and/or dizziness (P = 0.005). Treatable lesions may not have been identified with a limited IAC study in 3 of 128 patients with only unilateral auditory symptoms, and 21 of 282 patients with dizziness (P = 0.045). CONCLUSIONS: Limited MRI of the IACs may serve as an adequate screening test for retrocochlear pathologic conditions in patients with unilateral auditory symptoms and no dizziness.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, 1600 SW Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11391256; S0194599801409430 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11391256</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1610</id>
<a1>Shaw,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Radiology quiz case 1. Fibromyxoid tumor of the petrous apex</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>129, 131</sp>
<op>2</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fibroma/radiography</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Skull Neoplasms/radiography</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<no>LR: 20060328; JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0886-4470; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12525209; orf20000-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12525209</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1523</id>
<a1>Shefelbine,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Young,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Mitigation of hearing loss from semi-circular canal transection in pseudomonas otitis media with ciprofloxacin-dexamethasone irrigation</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>265</sp>
<op>269</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Infective Agents/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Auditory Threshold/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Ciprofloxacin/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Dexamethasone/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Glucocorticoids/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/drug therapy/etiology</k1>
<k1>Irrigation</k1>
<k1>Mastoid</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/microbiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Care</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/drug therapy/etiology</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas Infections/surgery</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals/injuries/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>HYPOTHESIS: Irrigation of the mastoid with a quinolone antibiotic-steroid solution may mitigate hearing loss caused by iatrogenic semicircular canal injury in the presence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA) otitis media (OM). BACKGROUND: Studies have shown the cochlea to be more vulnerable to semicircular canal transection (SCT)-related hearing loss in the presence of PA OM. Prophylactic systemic antibiotics and steroids may decrease this hearing loss, but SCT is usually not planned. The aim of this study was to determine if irrigation with ciprofloxacin-dexamethasone (cipro-dex) could improve hearing outcomes following SCT in PA OM. METHODS: PA OM was induced in 28 animals. After three to five days, unilateral SCT was performed in each animal, with sham SCT on the contralateral ear. At surgery, half of the animals (n = 14) underwent irrigation of the both mastoid bullae with cipro-dex; the second group of animals (n = 14) underwent irrigation of the bullae with sterile saline. Auditory thresholds were obtained immediately prior to SCT and 7-10 days after SCT. RESULTS: SCT ears treated with cipro-dex showed a mean click threshold improvement of 4.6 dB from pre-transection to 7-10 days post-transection, whereas thresholds in the SCT ears treated with saline worsened by 7.5 dB (p = 0.15). CONCLUSION: Irrigation of the guinea pig bulla with cipro-dex following SCT in the setting of PA OM appears safe and may yield beneficial effects on hearing.</ab>
<no>JID: 100961504; 0 (Anti-Infective Agents); 0 (Glucocorticoids); 50-02-2 (Dexamethasone); 85721-33-1 (Ciprofloxacin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-7129; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16436999; 00129492-200602000-00020 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.mao.0000199758.74685.2c</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16436999</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1558</id>
<a1>Shelton,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Hackett,R.</a1>
<t1>Skull base fungal osteomyelitis in an immunocompetent host</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>126</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>76</sp>
<op>78</op>
<k1>Aspergillosis/diagnosis/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Aspergillus niger/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunocompetence</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Osteomyelitis/diagnosis/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Skull Base/microbiology/radiography</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/microbiology/radiography</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11821771; S0194599802570819 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11821771</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1508</id>
<a1>Sherman,E. G.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Tran-Son-Tay,R.</a1>
<t1>In vitro testing of tympanostomy tube occlusion</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>141</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>598</sp>
<op>602</op>
<k1>Equipment Failure</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Models, Anatomic</k1>
<k1>Mucus</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Tympanostomy tubes (TTs) are commonly rendered nonfunctional by mucus plug formation. The purpose of this study was to determine whether an in vitro model could be developed to assess TT plug formation with results consistent with human trials. STUDY DESIGN: An ear chamber was designed to mimic middle ear air and mucus flow conditions in post-TT otorrhea. TT occlusion was tested and correlated to published in vivo results. METHODS: TTs that had previously been studied in vivo (Goode &amp;quot;T&amp;quot; and Reuter Bobbin collar buttons) were placed in the model chamber. Pooled, homogenized human middle ear mucus and an analog, egg white, were delivered at 80 muL per hour through the TTs. An air bolus was delivered every two minutes to simulate swallowing. Chamber pressure was monitored over 2.5 hours. Occlusion was determined by a pressure peak and visual confirmation. RESULTS: Obstruction was found in 60 percent of the Reuter Bobbin and 40 percent of the Goode TTs using the mucus analog. These results are similar to those reported from previous in vivo studies. No plugging was reported for either TT using homogenized human ear mucus. CONCLUSIONS: The in vitro TT chamber simulates the in vivo environment and yields results consistent with in vivo observations. This model system may allow for rapid prototyping and evaluation of new TTs that may be less vulnerable to occlusion.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 2009/05/06 [received]; 2009/07/22 [revised]; 2009/08/19 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1097-6817; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>J Crayton Pruitt Family Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-6250, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19861197; S0194-5998(09)01411-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2009.08.019</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19861197</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1594</id>
<a1>Soumekh,B.</a1>
<a1>Hom,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Levine,S.</a1>
<a1>Juhn,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Treatment of chronic tympanic-membrane perforations with a platelet-derived releasate</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>506</sp>
<op>511</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chinchilla</k1>
<k1>Epidermal Growth Factor/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane Perforation/drug therapy/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Wound Healing</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: Tympanic membrane perforations are very common and often require surgical treatment. Recent studies have suggested that growth factors may be an effective nonsurgical alternative for treating chronic perforations. The purpose of this study was to assess the efficacy of a platelet releasate in the treatment of chronic nonhealing perforations in the chinchilla model. METHODS: Bilateral perforations were created in 47 chinchillas by excising 80% of the tympanic membrane with a thermal myringotomy knife. Bilateral perforations &amp;gt; 50% of its surface area persisted for 10 weeks in 34 animals, and unilateral perforations &amp;gt; 50% of its surface area, in nine animals. Only animals with bilateral chronic perforations were included in this study. After deepithelializing the perforation and packing the middle ear and external ear canals with Gelfoam, we treated the perforations with either platelet releasate or buffered saline. Each animal served as its own control. RESULTS: The tympanic membranes were evaluated over a 12-week period by microscopy, photography, tympanometry, and histology. No statistical difference between treated and control ears in the incidence of perforation closure was evident. Histologically, the treated tympanic membranes consistently had a thicker fibrous layer than the controls. CONCLUSIONS: These data suggest that platelet releasate is not effective in enhancing closure of chronic tympanic membrane perforations in the chinchilla model.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7909513; 62229-50-9 (Epidermal Growth Factor); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis 55455, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8841694</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8841694</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1547</id>
<a1>Tsao,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Stevens,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Opening plugged tympanostomy tubes: effect of tube composition</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>128</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>870</sp>
<op>874</op>
<k1>Biocompatible Materials</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Mucus/physiology</k1>
<k1>Silicones</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: We sought to determine if tympanostomy tube (TT) composition impacts the rate of clearing mucoid plugs. DESIGN: The study used an ex vivo model. METHODS: TTs with a standard shaft length and inner diameter, varying only by composition materials, were studied. Thirty TTs of each biomaterial (stainless steel, titanium, silicone, fluoroplastic, ion-bombarded silicone, and phosphorylcholine-coated fluoroplastic) were plugged with middle-ear mucus and placed in a model ear chamber. Ofloxacin otic solution was instilled into the chamber to cover the plugged TT. Time to clear each plug was recorded. RESULTS: Ion-bombarded silicone TTs cleared more rapidly than plain silicone TTs (P = 0.0042), but no other statistically significant difference among TT materials was observed. CONCLUSIONS: TT composition does not significantly affect the rate or &amp;quot;ease&amp;quot; with which TTs may be opened after they become plugged with mucus ex vivo. The higher rate of plug clearance observed with ion-bombarded silicone relative to untreated silicone suggests that improvements may be possible with alterations in either TT composition or surface preparations.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Biocompatible Materials); 0 (Silicones); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology and Biostatistics, University of Florida, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12825039; S0194599803004704 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12825039</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1609</id>
<a1>Warren,H. G.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Daly,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Cellular telephone use and risk of intratemporal facial nerve tumor</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>113</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>663</sp>
<op>667</op>
<k1>Cellular Phone/statistics &amp; numerical data</k1>
<k1>Cranial Nerve Neoplasms/epidemiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Electromagnetic Fields/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Facial Nerve/pathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Questionnaires</k1>
<k1>Temporal Muscle/pathology</k1>
<k1>United States/epidemiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES/HYPOTHESIS: Microwave radiation exposure from cellular telephone use has been implicated in the development of intracranial tumors. The intratemporal facial nerve (IFN) is exposed to higher levels of cellular telephone radiation than intracranial tissues. The purpose of the study was to determine whether cellular telephone use is associated with an increased risk of IFN tumors. STUDY DESIGN: Case-control using a structured telephone survey at an academic, tertiary-care referral center. METHODS: Patients with IFN tumors (n = 18) were case-matched with patients treated for acoustic neuroma (n = 51), rhinosinusitis (n = 72), and dysphonia or gastroesophageal reflux disease (n = 69). Risk of facial nerve tumorigenesis was compared by extent of cellular telephone use and other risk factors. RESULTS: The odds ratio of developing an IFN tumor was 0.6 (95% CI, 0.2-1.9) with any handheld cellular telephone use and 0.4 (95% CI, 0.1-2.1) with regular cellular telephone use. No factors were associated with an increased risk for IFN tumor development. CONCLUSIONS: Regular cellular telephone use does not appear to be associated with a higher risk of IFN tumor development. The short duration of widespread cellular telephone use precludes definite exclusion as a risk for IFN tumor development.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8607378; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Box 100264, 1600 Southwest Archer Road, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12671425</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200304000-00015</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12671425</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1574</id>
<a1>Welling,D. B.</a1>
<a1>Slater,P. W.</a1>
<a1>Martyn,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Gantz,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Luxford,W. M.</a1>
<a1>Shelton,C.</a1>
<t1>Sensorineural hearing loss after occlusion of the enlarged vestibular aqueduct</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Otology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>338</sp>
<op>343</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Audiometry, Pure-Tone</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Endolymphatic Sac/abnormalities/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Care</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Preoperative Care</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Speech Perception/physiology</k1>
<k1>Syndrome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: This study aimed to report the hearing results of endolymphatic sac occlusion in patients with enlarged vestibular aqueduct syndrome. STUDY DESIGN: The study design was a multiinstitutional retrospective case series. SETTING: The study was conducted at tertiary otologic referral centers. PATIENTS: The study included 10 previously unreported patients with progressive sensorineural hearing loss and vestibular aqueducts greater than 1.5 mm in diameter on computerized tomography. INTERVENTION: Occlusion of the enlarged vestibular aqueduct was performed by means of a transmastoid surgical approach. Either intraluminal endolymphatic sac obliteration (five patients) or extraluminal extradural endolymphatic sac obliteration (five patients) was accomplished with temporalis fascia. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: The postoperative pure tone average (PTA) and speech discrimination scores were compared with the preoperative levels using conventional audiometry. RESULTS: Nine of 10 patients experienced some degree of sensorineural hearing loss. The median change in PTA was a loss of 21 decibels (dB), and 50% of the patients experienced a sensorineural hearing loss greater than 25 dB. Postoperative change in PTA ranged from +10 dB to -59 dB. The median change in speech discrimination score was a loss of 27.5%. Only one patient had an improvement in both speech discrimination score and pure tone averages after surgery. Patients who underwent extraluminal occlusion had a median PTA loss of 12 dB, and patients who underwent open sac occlusion had a median PTA loss of 34 dB. These were not statistically different. CONCLUSION: In this series of 10 patients, 5 had a greater than 25 dB decrease in hearing after occlusion of the enlarged vestibular aqueduct. Surgical occlusion of the enlarged vestibular aqueduct showed no significant benefit in hearing preservation. The otologic surgeon is alerted to the potential for severe sensiorineural hearing loss after occlusion of the enlarged vestibular aqueduct.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 7909513; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0192-9763; 0192-9763</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, The Ohio State University, Columbus, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10337975</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; Multicenter Study; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10337975</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1554</id>
<a1>Westine,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Giannoni,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Defining tympanostomy tube plugs</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>112</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>951</sp>
<op>954</op>
<k1>Amino Acids/analysis</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, High Pressure Liquid</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation</k1>
<k1>Monosaccharides/analysis</k1>
<k1>Mucus/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: To define the composition of tympanostomy tube plugs because selecting or developing effective solvents depends on such knowledge. STUDY DESIGN: Prospective, in vitro laboratory study. METHODS: Luminal contents of 105 plugged, microscopically removed tympanostomy tubes were expressed, pooled, acid hydrolyzed, and passed through a high-performance liquid chromatography column. Retention times were compared with high-performance liquid chromatography standards to develop free amino acid and monosaccharide profiles. Cerumen, blood, and chronic mucoid effusion (collected during myringotomy) were pooled and subjected to the same analysis. The elution profiles of each substance were compared to determine which substance most closely matched the plugs. RESULTS: High-performance liquid chromatography amino acid and monosaccharide analysis demonstrated greatest similarity between tympanostomy tube plugs and mucoid effusion. CONCLUSIONS: Tympanostomy tube plug composition is more similar to mucoid effusion than to blood or cerumen. Solvents to open plugged tympanostomy tubes should be directed against the components of mucoid effusion.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8607378; 0 (Amino Acids); 0 (Monosaccharides); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12160290</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200206000-00003</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12160290</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1553</id>
<a1>Westine,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Giannoni,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Opening plugged tympanostomy tubes</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>112</vo>
<is>8 Pt 1</is>
<sp>1342</sp>
<op>1345</op>
<k1>Equipment Design</k1>
<k1>Middle Ear Ventilation/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Mucus</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media with Effusion/therapy</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications/therapy</k1>
<k1>Solvents/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To determine the most effective solvents for dissolving plugged tympanostomy tubes. STUDY DESIGN: In vitro laboratory study. METHODS: Twelve solvents (including ototopical antibiotics and water) were applied to fluoroplastic tympanostomy tubes (n = 260) plugged with dried mucoid middle ear effusion in an ear canal-tympanic membrane model. Time to clearance of the tympanostomy tubes was both visually and tympanometrically determined. RESULTS: Vinegar (P =.0030) and hyaluronidase solutions (P =.0030) were significantly better solvents than water. CONCLUSION: Vinegar and hyaluronidase solutions are more likely to clear plugged tympanostomy tubes than water and ototopical antibiotics, but vinegar is the preferred solution because of its known relative safety for use in the ear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8607378; 0 (Solvents); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12172242</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/00005537-200208000-00004</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12172242</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1564</id>
<a1>Williams,M. D.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Williams,L. S.</a1>
<a1>Moorhead,J. E.</a1>
<t1>Middle ear prosthesis displacement in high-strength magnetic fields</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>158</sp>
<op>161</op>
<k1>Electromagnetic Fields/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Metals/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Ossicular Prosthesis</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Failure</k1>
<k1>Temporal Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Torque</k1>
<ab>HYPOTHESIS: Middle ear prostheses made from nonmagnetic, magnetic resonance (MR)-compatible metals reportedly displace ex vivo in the presence of high magnetic fields used in MR imaging (MRI). The authors postulate that the prosthesis displacement seen with &amp;quot;nonmagnetic&amp;quot; MR-compatible prostheses ex vivo may not be clinically significant in vivo. METHODS: Middle ear prostheses made from ferromagnetic (420F stainless steel) and nonmagnetic MR-compatible metals (316L stainless steel and platinum) were examined for magnetic field interactions at 4.7 Tesla (T). Ex vivo testing consisted of measurements of the translational and rotational motion of the prosthesis induced by the static magnetic field. In vivo testing was assessed by implanting prostheses in cadaveric temporal bones and performing clinical MRI sequences. Prosthesis displacement was measured semiquantitatively. RESULTS: Angular deflection was observed in all samples made from nonmagnetic stainless steel. The negative control (platinum) demonstrated no deflection, and the positive controls (ferromagnetic stainless steel) deflected &amp;gt;90 degrees. Torque analysis showed movement in five of five nonmagnetic stainless steel prostheses. Prostheses made from nonmagnetic stainless steel remained in place without appreciable loosening in vivo after MRI. Prostheses made with known ferromagnetic properties were displaced at 4.7 T but not at 1.5 T. CONCLUSION: Middle ear prostheses made from low-magnetic stainless steel do move in the presence of high magnetic fields ex vivo; however, this does not appear to be clinically or statistically significant in vivo at 4.7 T. Magnetic resonance imaging should be undertaken with caution in individuals with prostheses made from stainless steel with strong ferromagnetic properties.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 100961504; 0 (Metals); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-7129; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11300262</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11300262</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1543</id>
<a1>Wilmoth,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Matrix metalloproteinases in a gerbil cholesteatoma model</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>402</sp>
<op>407</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cholesteatoma, Middle Ear/enzymology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Gerbillinae</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Period</k1>
<k1>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane/enzymology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The goal of this study was to determine whether expression of matrix metalloproteinases (MMP) and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) occurs in a gerbil cholesteatoma model, which may be involved early in the pathogenesis of cholesteatoma. Study design Atelectasis was induced by transpalatal, bilateral Eustachian tube obstruction on gerbil ears (n = 60). Tympanic membranes were removed at days 0, 3, 7, 14, 28, 56, and 84, and quantitative analysis of TNF-alpha and MMPs was performed. RESULTS: Atelectasis and middle ear inflammation increased with time. TNF-alpha and MMP levels increased (P &amp;lt; 0.0083) with time, inflammation, and atelectatic stage with some variability seen between different MMPs. CONCLUSION: Elevation of TNF-alpha and MMPs associated with progressive tympanic membrane atelectasis suggests a possible role for these inflammatory mediators in the pathogenesis of cholesteatoma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091103; JID: 8508176; 0 (Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha); EC 3.4.24.- (Matrix Metalloproteinases); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14574296; S0194599803013172 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14574296</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1542</id>
<a1>Wilmoth,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Schultz,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Tympanic membrane metalloproteinase inflammatory response</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>129</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>647</sp>
<op>654</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cholesteatoma, Middle Ear/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Culture Techniques</k1>
<k1>Gerbillinae</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Matrix Metalloproteinases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/physiology</k1>
<k1>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Tympanic Membrane/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The goal of this study was to determine whether expression of matrix metalloproteinases (MMP) in tympanic membranes (TM) is stimulated by host tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) and bacterial toxin (lipopolysaccharide, LPS), which may play a role in the pathogenesis of cholesteatoma. STUDY DESIGN: Gerbil TMs (n = 48) were cultured in the presence of either TNF-alpha or LPS. Quantitative analysis of TNF-alpha and MMPs was performed on both the homogenized TMs and the culture media supernatant. RESULTS: Levels of TNF-alpha and MMPs did not increase significantly in TMs with exposure to inflammatory mediators. TNF-alpha levels in supernatant were elevated (P &amp;lt; 0.007) with more concentrated LPS exposure. Supernatant levels of MMP2 were increased (P &amp;lt; 0.007) at most concentrations of LPS and TNF-alpha. CONCLUSION: Cultured TMs expressed MMPs in response to bacterial and host inflammatory mediators. These findings support a link between inflammation and the secretion of potentially destructive MMPs in the TM, which may contribute to the pathogenesis of cholesteatoma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8508176; 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 0 (Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha); EC 3.4.24.- (Matrix Metalloproteinases); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14663430; S0194599803013883 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14663430</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1526</id>
<a1>Yun,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Colburn,M. W.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Cochlear implant magnet displacement with minor head trauma</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>133</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>275</sp>
<op>277</op>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implantation/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Cochlear Implants</k1>
<k1>Craniocerebral Trauma/complications/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Injury Severity Score</k1>
<k1>Magnetics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Prosthesis Failure</k1>
<k1>Registries</k1>
<k1>Reoperation</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Risk Assessment</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVES: Manufacturers have introduced cochlear implants (CIs) with removable magnets to allow for magnetic resonance imaging after placement. The purpose of this study was to describe magnet displacement as a new CI complication and to suggest a possible treatment option to prevent its recurrence. STUDY DESIGN: Retrospective case series. METHODS: The records of 3 young males who experienced CI magnet dislodgement were reviewed and compared against records from the institutional implant database. RESULTS: Magnet displacement was observed only in young males (14% of male children) who received CI with removable magnets. This occurred 13-14 months after CI placement. Magnets were replaced under general anesthesia, and the scalp was bolstered with a dermal allograft. Recurrent magnet dislodgement was encountered in 1 patient, 6 months later. CONCLUSIONS: Magnet displacement may be a relatively common complication after minor head trauma in pediatric patients with certain CIs that have removable magnets.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 2004/08/10 [received]; 2005/02/25 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Departments of Otolaryngology and Communicative Disorders, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16087027; S0194-5998(05)00386-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.02.018</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16087027</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1536</id>
<a1>Yunus,T. M.</a1>
<a1>Molina,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Prevatt,A. R.</a1>
<a1>Gajewski,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Sedwick,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>Hearing loss with semicircular canal fistula in exotoxin A-deficient Pseudomonas otitis media</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>130</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>430</sp>
<op>436</op>
<k1>ADP Ribose Transferases/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Toxins</k1>
<k1>Exotoxins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fistula/complications</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/complications/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Labyrinth Diseases/complications</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Otitis Media/complications/microbiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Semicircular Canals</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors/physiology</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The study goal was to compare the severity of hearing loss with semicircular canal injury in the presence of otitis media (OM) due to an exotoxin A-producing strain of Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PA+) and an exotoxin A-deficient daughter strain (PA-). METHODS: PA+ or PA- was injected bilaterally into guinea pig ears. Three days later, unilateral lateral semicircular canal transection was performed. Hearing was tested before and after transection. RESULTS: PA OM was induced in all injected ears. Significant elevation of click and 12-kHz thresholds (P &amp;lt; 0.0001) were encountered in PA+-infected ears. No significant threshold elevations were encountered in PA--infected ears. CONCLUSION: Hearing loss resulting from canal injury in the presence of Pseudomonas OM may be mediated by exotoxin A. SIGNIFICANCE: Treatment to neutralize the effects of exotoxin A may minimize the risk of hearing loss with canal fistula in chronic OM.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8508176; 0 (Bacterial Toxins); 0 (Exotoxins); 0 (Virulence Factors); EC 2.4.2.- (ADP Ribose Transferases); EC 2.4.2.31 (toxA protein, Pseudomonas aeruginosa); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology,University of Florida, Gainseville, FL 32610-0264, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15100639; S019459980400018X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2003.12.019</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15100639</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1539</id>
<a1>Zhang,M.</a1>
<a1>Antonelli,P. J.</a1>
<t1>An outer hair cell of the inner ear</t1>
<jf>Nature cell biology</jf>
<jo>Nat.Cell Biol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>96</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cochlea/cytology</k1>
<k1>Guinea Pigs</k1>
<k1>Hair Cells, Auditory, Outer/ultrastructure</k1>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 100890575; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1465-7392; 1465-7392</sn>
<ad>College of Health Professions, University of Florida, USA. mzhang@phhp.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 14755272; ncb0204-96 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/ncb0204-96</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14755272</pmid></reference></refworks>
