
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>373</id>
<a1>Bacot,Christopher M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Genetic analysis of the role in virulence of the Salmonella typhimurium spvB gene</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<sp>86</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497343551; CT: 94th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Las Vegas, Nevada, USA; CY: May 23-27, 1994</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>354</id>
<a1>Bourdage,K.</a1>
<a1>Lang,S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Virulence of Vibrio vulnificus is not related to source of the strain or cytotoxicity in INT-407 cell culture models</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>2002</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<sp>511</sp>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is a gram-negative bacterium that inhabits estuarine waters and is a frequent contaminant of oysters. Humans who consume uncooked contaminated oysters or whose wounds are exposed to contaminated water can experience lethal sepsis or necrotizing fasciitis, respectively. However, not all strains of V. vulnificus in oysters are virulent in animal models, and being able to simply assay virulence of strains contaminating oysters would be helpful in increasing food safety. We examined a set of 50 encapsulated strains of V. vulnificus, half clinical and half oyster isolates, obtained in geographically and temporally diverse settings for virulence in both animal and cell culture models. Iron dextran-treated mice were injected subcutaneously (s.c.) with various doses of V. vulnificus, and local and systemic manifestations of disease were quantitated so that each strain could be labeled as virulent, attenuated, or avirulent. Of the 50 strains, 44 were virulent, 5 were attenuated, and 1 was avirulent in mice. The 6 non-virulent strains were equally distributed among clinical and oyster isolates. Therefore, there was no correlation between virulence in mice and the source of the strain. We previously used cytotoxicity assays with human cell lines to examine virulence of V. vulnificus, and results with a small set of strains suggested that cytotoxicity in INT-407 could correlate with virulence. However, upon examining the cytotoxicity of the 50 strains in this study using a crystal violet-staining assay for measurement of detachment, we observed that cytotoxicity did not relate to mouse-virulence or source of the strain. Some highly virulent strains had low cytotoxicity, while some non-virulent strains had high cytotoxicity. These results indicate that most V. vulnificus strains in oysters are highly virulent and that no model examined to date, other than experimental infection of animals, can identify the virulent strains.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200200609158&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 102nd General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Salt Lake City, UT, USA; CY: May 19-23, 2002; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>353</id>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>The rtxA toxin is a major cytotoxic factor but plays a minor role in virulence of Vibrio vulnificus.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<sp>B</sp>
<op>058</op>
<ab>Sepsis and wound infection caused by Vibrio vulnificus result from consumption of seafood and contact of wounds with seawater, respectively. Death can occur within 24 hours after contact with the bacteria, and individuals with hemochromatosis are most susceptible to lethal infections by V. vulnificus. Our genomic sequencing of V. vulnificus strain MO6-24/O identified a clone with homology to the V. cholerae rtxA structural gene. The RtxA toxin of V. cholerae can cause cytotoxic activity against epithelial cells in vitro by inhibition of actin polymerization. To determine the role of rtxA in the pathogenesis of V. vulnificus, we constructed insertion mutations in the rtxA gene of V. vulnificus MO6-24/O. In cell culture models using human intestinal epithelial cells, the rtxA mutant was decreased by 79% for destruction of monolayers and 87% for cell lysis compared with the parental strain. Additionally, the rtxA mutant was decreased 7-fold in its ability to disrupt polarized epithelial cell monolayers (transepithelial electrical resistance) as compared to the parental strain. In subcutaneously inoculated iron dextran-treated mice at the minimum infectious dose of the parental strain (300 CFU), the rtxA mutant did not exhibit a significant decrease in CFU recovered from the skin and liver. The body temperatures of mutant-inoculated mice did not drop as much as for the wild-type strain, indicating that at least one aspect of systemic infection was affected by the loss of rtxA. However, when the inoculum was increased to only 3,000 CFU, the rtxA mutant was not attenuated by any criteria. Therefore, rtxA is the major cytotoxic factor of V. vulnificus for intestinal epithelial cells in tissue culture; however, rtxA appears to exert only a minor role in the virulence of V. vulnificus in a mouse model of human disease.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300519812&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 103rd American Society for Microbiology General Meeting; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: May 18-22, 2003; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>275</id>
<a1>Brown,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Roles of RseB, sigmaE, and DegP in virulence and phase variation of colony morphotype of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>3768</sp>
<op>3781</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Blood Bactericidal Activity</k1>
<k1>Carbohydrates/analysis</k1>
<k1>Complement System Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Heat-Shock Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Periplasmic Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Polysaccharides, Bacterial/analysis</k1>
<k1>Regulon</k1>
<k1>Serine Endopeptidases/physiology</k1>
<k1>Sigma Factor/analysis/physiology</k1>
<k1>Stress, Physiological</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/chemistry/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is an estuarine bacterium capable of causing serious and often fatal wound infections and primary septicemia. We used alkaline phosphatase insertion mutagenesis to identify genes necessary for the virulence of this pathogen. One mutant had an in-frame fusion of &amp;#39;phoA to the gene encoding RseB, a periplasmic negative regulator of the alternative sigma factor sigma(E). sigma(E) controls an extensive regulon involved in responding to cell envelope stresses. Colonies of the rseB mutant were less opaque than wild-type colonies and underwent phase variation between translucent and opaque morphologies. rseB mutants were attenuated for virulence in subcutaneously inoculated iron-dextran-treated mice. To obtain insight into the role of rseB and the extracytoplasmic stress response in V. vulnificus, mutants with defined mutations in rseB and two important members of the extracytoplasmic stress regulon, rpoE and degP, were constructed for analysis of virulence, colony morphology, and stress-associated phenotypes. Deletion of rseB caused reversible phase variation in the colony morphotype that was associated with extracellular polysaccharides. Translucent and transparent morphotype strains were attenuated for virulence. rpoE and degP deletion mutants were sensitive to membrane-perturbing agents and heat but were not significantly attenuated for V. vulnificus virulence in mice. These results reveal complex relationships between regulation of the extracytoplasmic stress response, exopolysaccharides, and the virulence of V. vulnificus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100302; GR: R01 056056/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Carbohydrates); 0 (Heat-Shock Proteins); 0 (Periplasmic Proteins); 0 (Polysaccharides, Bacterial); 0 (Sigma Factor); 0 (sporulation-specific sigma factors); 9007-36-7 (Complement System Proteins); EC 3.4.21.- (DegP protease); EC 3.4.21.- (Serine Endopeptidases); OID: NLM: PMC2738019; 2009/06/29 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5522; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19564391; IAI.00205-09 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/IAI.00205-09</do>
<wp>20090629</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19564391</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2738019</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>278</id>
<a1>Brown,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Regulation of fatty acid metabolism by FadR is essential for Vibrio vulnificus to cause infection of mice</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>190</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>7633</sp>
<op>7644</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/physiology</k1>
<k1>Fatty Acids/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial/physiology</k1>
<k1>Iron-Dextran Complex/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Liver Diseases/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Skin Diseases, Bacterial/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/genetics/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>The opportunistic bacterial pathogen Vibrio vulnificus causes severe wound infection and fatal septicemia. We used alkaline phosphatase insertion mutagenesis in a clinical isolate of V. vulnificus to find genes necessary for virulence, and we identified fadR, which encodes a regulator of fatty acid metabolism. The fadR::mini-Tn5Km2phoA mutant was highly attenuated in a subcutaneously inoculated iron dextran-treated mouse model of V. vulnificus disease, was hypersensitive to the fatty acid synthase inhibitor cerulenin, showed aberrant expression of fatty acid biosynthetic (fab) genes and fatty acid oxidative (fad) genes, produced smaller colonies on agar media, and grew slower in rich broth than did the wild-type parent. Deletion of fadR essentially recapitulated the phenotypes of the insertion mutant, and the DeltafadR mutation was complemented in trans with the wild-type gene. Further characterization of the DeltafadR mutant showed that it was not generally hypersensitive to envelope stresses but had decreased motility and showed an altered membrane lipid profile compared to that of the wild type. Supplementation of broth with the unsaturated fatty acid oleate restored wild-type growth in vitro, and infection with oleate in the inoculum increased the ability of the DeltafadR mutant to infect mice. We conclude that fadR and regulation of fatty acid metabolism are essential for V. vulnificus to be able to cause disease in mammalian hosts.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 AI056056/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (FadR protein, Bacteria); 0 (Fatty Acids); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 9004-66-4 (Iron-Dextran Complex); OID: NLM: PMC2583613; 2008/10/03 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5530; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, P.O. Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18835990; JB.01016-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.01016-08</do>
<wp>20081003</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18835990</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2583613</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>301</id>
<a1>Caldwell,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>The Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid encodes a positive regulator of a plasmid-encoded virulence gene</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>173</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>7176</sp>
<op>7185</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/pathology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The 90-kb virulence plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium is necessary for invasion beyond the Peyer&amp;#39;s patches to the mesenteric lymph nodes and spleens of orally inoculated mice. Two Tn5 insertions located on the left side of a previously identified 14-kb virulence region (P. A. Gulig and R. Curtiss III, Infect. Immun. 58:3262-3271, 1988) and mapping 272 bp from each other exhibited opposite effects on splenic infection of mice after oral inoculation. spvR23::Tn5 decreased splenic infection by 1,000-fold, whereas a spv-14::Tn5 mutant outcompeted wild-type S. typhimurium for splenic infection by 27-fold in mice fed mixtures of mutated and wild-type S. typhimurium. spvR23::Tn5 was complemented by a virulence plasmid subclone with an insert sequence encoding only an 891-bp open reading frame specifying a 33,000-molecular-weight protein. The amino acid sequence of this open reading frame had significant homology to members of the LysR family of positive regulatory proteins; thus, the gene was named spvR (salmonella plasmid virulence). To examine the possible regulatory effects of spvR on other virulence genes, we constructed a lacZ operon fusion in a downstream virulence gene, spvB. When spvR subcloned behind the lac promoter was provided on a separate plasmid in trans to the spvB-lacZ operon fusion, transcription of spvB increased 15-fold. spv-14::Tn5, which conferred a competitive advantage to S. typhimurium, increased the expression of a spvR-lacZ operon fusion in cis. spvR is therefore a positive regulator of spvB and an essential virulence gene of S. typhimurium. As opposed to having spvR subcloned behind the lac promoter, the wild-type spvR gene present on the virulence plasmid did not function to positively regulate spvB-lacZ in trans when salmonellae were grown to the log phase in L broth, suggesting that this regulatory system is activated in vivo during infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/M74110; GR: AI-28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); OID: NLM: PMC209223; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1657882</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1657882</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC209223</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>381</id>
<a1>Caldwell,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Winram,S. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>A Salmonella-Typhimurium Virulence Plasmid Gene Encodes a Positive Regulatory Factor for Other Plasmid-Encoded Virulence Factors</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>Abstract B54</is>
<sp>34</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199141053267; CT: 91ST GENERAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY 1991, DALLAS, TEXAS, USA, MAY 5-9, 1991. ABSTR GEN MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>284</id>
<a1>Cerveny,K. E.</a1>
<a1>DePaola,A.</a1>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Phage therapy of local and systemic disease caused by Vibrio vulnificus in iron-dextran-treated mice</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>70</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>6251</sp>
<op>6262</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacteriophages</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Iron-Dextran Complex/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Ostreidae/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/pathology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is a gram-negative bacterium that contaminates filter-feeding shellfish such as oysters. After ingestion of contaminated oysters, predisposed people may experience highly lethal septicemia. Contamination of wounds with the bacteria can result in devastating necrotizing fasciitis, which can progress to septicemia. The extremely rapid progression of these diseases can render antibiotic treatment ineffective, and death is a frequent outcome. In this study, we examined the potential use of bacteriophages as therapeutic agents against V. vulnificus in an iron-dextran-treated mouse model of V. vulnificus infection. Mice were injected subcutaneously with 10 times the lethal dose of V. vulnificus and injected intravenously, either simultaneously or at various times after infection, with phages. Treatment of mice with phages could prevent death; systemic disease, as measured by CFU per gram of liver and body temperature; and local disease, as measured by CFU per gram of lesion material and histopathologic analysis. Two different phages were effective against three different V. vulnificus strains with various degrees of virulence, while a third phage that required the presence of seawater to lyse bacteria in vitro was ineffective at treating mice. Optimum protection required that the phages be administered within 3 h of bacterial inoculation at doses as high as 10(8) PFU. One of the protective phages had a half-life in blood of over 2 h. These results demonstrate that bacteriophages have therapeutic potential for both localized and systemic infections caused by V. vulnificus in animals. This model should be useful in answering basic questions regarding phage therapy.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 9004-66-4 (Iron-Dextran Complex); OID: NLM: PMC130292; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12379704</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12379704</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC130292</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>359</id>
<a1>Cerveny,K. E.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Escudero,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of bacteriophage as therapy for disease caused by Vibrio vulnificus in iron dextran-treated mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>2000</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<sp>279</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200000390727&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 100th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Los Angeles, California, USA; CY: May 21-25, 2000; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1340</id>
<a1>Curtiss R,3rd</a1>
<a1>Kelly SM</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Gentry-Weeks CR</a1>
<a1>Galan JE.</a1>
<t1>Avirulent Salmonella expressing virulence antigens from other pathogens for use as orally-administered vaccines.</t1>
<yr>1988</yr>
<sp>311</sp>
<op>328</op>
<a2>Roth,James A.</a2>
<t2>Proceedings from the international symposium on virulence mechanisms of veterinary bacterial pathogens</t2>
<pb>American Society of Microbiology</pb>
<pp>Washington DC</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1342</id>
<a1>Curtiss R,3rd</a1>
<a1>Kelly SM</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Nakayama K.</a1>
<t1>Stable recombinant avirulent Salmonella vaccine strains</t1>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>150</vo>
<sp>33</sp>
<op>47</op>
<a2>Atassi,MZ</a2>
<t2>Immunobiology of proteins and peptides V: Vaccines: Mechanism design and applications</t2>
<pb>Plenum Press</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<t3>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</t3>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1341</id>
<a1>Curtiss R,3rd</a1>
<a1>Maurelli AT</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA.</a1>
<t1>Genetic analysis of pathogenesis of enteric bacteria</t1>
<yr>1988</yr>
<sp>67</sp>
<op>82</op>
<a2>Owen,Peter</a2><a2> Foster,Timothy J.</a2>
<t2>Immunochemical and molecular genetic analysis of bacterial pathogens</t2>
<pb>Elsevier</pb>
<pp>Amsterdam</pp>
<t3>FEMS Symposium 40</t3>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>307</id>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,3rd</a1>
<a1>Kelly,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Nakayama,K.</a1>
<t1>Selective delivery of antigens by recombinant bacteria</t1>
<jf>Current topics in microbiology and immunology</jf>
<jo>Curr.Top.Microbiol.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>146</vo>
<sp>35</sp>
<op>49</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/administration &amp; dosage/genetics</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Vaccines/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Lymphoid Tissue/immunology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Salmonella/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>The means to attenuate Salmonella and to endow such avirulent strains with the ability to express colonization and virulence antigens from other pathogens has achieved considerable progress during the past several years. One can therefore begin to design and construct strains with specificity to a given animal host and to express in a defined way specific colonization and virulence antigens in a manner to stimulate long-lasting immunity to the Salmonella and to the pathogen supplying the genetic information for the colonization and virulence antigens. Since most pathogens colonize on or invade through mucosal surfaces, the use of recombinant bivalent Salmonella vaccine strains to stimulate a mucosal immune response would induce the development of a first line of defense against a diversity of pathogens. Mucosal immunity should therefore reduce contagious spread of many pathogens since the dose to overcome the mucosal immune barrier would be increased to result in a diminished likelihood of infection. The fact that the recombinant Salmonella vaccine strains also induce humoral and cellular immune responses justifies their use for induction of long-lasting immunity. Although considerable progress has been made in targeting antigens to the GALT by use of avirulent Salmonella, a similar strategy for delivery of antigens to the BALT has yet to be discovered and developed. In addition to constituting a system for induction of immunity against a diversity of pathogens, the recombinant avirulent Salmonella system should provide a means to explore parameters of the mucosal immune response. This would include investigation of the location and duration of memory, the age dependence of induction of mucosal immunity, and the means for the possible induction of oral tolerance with regard to either the mucosal or humoral response to an antigen expressed by the recombinant Salmonella. It is also possible to contemplate using the avirulent Salmonella to target expression of various modulators of the immune system such as interleukin-2 and interferon-gamma to the GALT and thus further enhance the immune response. Lastly, one can introduce into avirulent Salmonella strains genes for putative colonization antigens in order to investigate whether induction of an immune response against the putative colonization antigen does or does not interfere with infection. This system, therefore, permits another means to analyze the relative importance of various bacterial surface attributes in conferring pathogenicity to the microbe.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 0110513; 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Vaccines); RF: 111; ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0070-217X; 0070-217X</sn>
<an>PMID: 2659274</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2659274</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>306</id>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,3rd</a1>
<a1>Kelly,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Nakayama,K.</a1>
<t1>Stable recombinant avirulent Salmonella vaccine strains</t1>
<jf>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</jf>
<jo>Adv.Exp.Med.Biol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>251</vo>
<sp>33</sp>
<op>47</op>
<k1>Adenylate Cyclase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Vaccines/immunology</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Deletion</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Cyclic AMP/genetics</k1>
<k1>Salmonella/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Vaccines/immunology</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Attenuated/immunology</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Synthetic/immunology</k1>
<no>LR: 20060501; JID: 0121103; 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Vaccines); 0 (Receptors, Cyclic AMP); 0 (Vaccines); 0 (Vaccines, Attenuated); 0 (Vaccines, Synthetic); EC 4.6.1.1 (Adenylate Cyclase); RF: 40; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0065-2598; 0065-2598</sn>
<ad>Department of Biology, Washington University, St. Louis, MO 63130.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2692430</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2692430</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>383</id>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,Iii</a1>
<a1>Kelly,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Avirulent Salmonellae Expressing Virulence Antigens from Other Pathogens for use as Orally Administered Vaccines</t1>
<yr>1988</yr>
<sp>328</sp>
<no>PT: B; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198835032413</no>
<sn>0-914826-99-9 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>338</id>
<a1>Deffense,B. L.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Development of a capture ELISA for detection of vaccinia virus using recombinant antibodies</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>2006</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<sp>630</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800235535; CT: 106th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 21 -25, 2006; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>334</id>
<a1>Deffense,B. L.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Wright,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Recombinant scFv antibodies recognizing proteins of vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>2005</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>601</sp>
<op>602</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800238401; CT: 105th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, GA, USA; CY: June 05 -09, 2005; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>283</id>
<a1>DePaola,A.</a1>
<a1>Nordstrom,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Dalsgaard,A.</a1>
<a1>Forslund,A.</a1>
<a1>Oliver,J.</a1>
<a1>Bates,T.</a1>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of Vibrio vulnificus from market oysters and septicemia cases for virulence markers</t1>
<jf>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>4006</sp>
<op>4011</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacteremia/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Colony Count, Microbial</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/analysis</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Iron-Dextran Complex/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Ostreidae/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Random Amplified Polymorphic DNA Technique</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/classification/growth &amp; development/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Representative encapsulated strains of Vibrio vulnificus from market oysters and oyster-associated primary septicemia cases (25 isolates each) were tested in a blinded fashion for potential virulence markers that may distinguish strains from these two sources. These isolates were analyzed for plasmid content, for the presence of a 460-bp amplicon by randomly amplified polymorphic DNA PCR, and for virulence in subcutaneously (s.c.) inoculated, iron-dextran-treated mice. Similar percentages of market oyster and clinical isolates possessed detectable plasmids (24 and 36%, respectively), produced the 460-bp amplicon (45 and 50%, respectively), and were judged to be virulent in the mouse s.c. inoculation-iron-dextran model (88% for each). Therefore, it appears that nearly all V. vulnificus strains in oysters are virulent and that genetic tests for plasmids and specific PCR size amplicons cannot distinguish between fully virulent and less virulent strains or between clinical and environmental isolates. The inability of these methods to distinguish food and clinical V. vulnificus isolates demonstrates the need for alternative subtyping approaches and virulence assays.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7605801; 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 9004-66-4 (Iron-Dextran Complex); OID: NLM: PMC165197; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0099-2240; 0099-2240</sn>
<ad>Gulf Coast Seafood Laboratory, U.S. Food and Drug Administration, Dauphin Island, AL 36528, USA. adepaola@cfsan.fda.gov</ad>
<an>PMID: 12839775</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12839775</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC165197</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>349</id>
<a1>Depaola,A.</a1>
<a1>Vickery,M. C. L.</a1>
<a1>Nilsson,W. B.</a1>
<a1>Strom,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Dalsgaard,A.</a1>
<a1>Oliver,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of Vibrio vulnificus from oysters and septicemia cases for virulence markers.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<sp>P</sp>
<op>007</op>
<ab>Representative encapsulated strains of Vibrio vulnificus from market oysters and oyster-associated primary septicemia cases (25 isolates each) were tested blindly using various methods for the presence of potential virulence markers that might distinguish strains from these two sources. These isolates were analyzed for plasmid content, the presence of a 460-bp RAPD PCR amplicon, 16S rRNA genotype, and virulence in subcutaneously inoculated, iron dextran-treated mice. A similar percentage of market oyster and clinical isolates possessed detectable plasmids (24% and 36%), produced the 460-bp amplicon (45 and 50%), and was judged to be virulent in the mouse s.c. model (88% for each), respectively. Based on a 17-nucleotide difference throughout the sequence of the small subunit 16S rRNA gene, there appear to be two major groups of V. vulnificus, designated types A and B. RFLP and multiplex real time PCR were used to survey the 16S rRNA genotype in 67 V. vulnificus human clinical and non-clinical strains (including the 50 isolates described above). We determined that the majority of non-clinical isolates were type A (31/33), and that there was a statistically significant association between the type B genotype and human clinical strains (26/34). These results suggest that the type B genotype is associated with higher human virulence than type A, which is the predominant genotype in U.S oysters.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300546387&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 103rd American Society for Microbiology General Meeting; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: May 18-22, 2003; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>285</id>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Bacteriophages: potential treatment for bacterial infections</t1>
<jf>BioDrugs : clinical immunotherapeutics, biopharmaceuticals and gene therapy</jf>
<jo>BioDrugs</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>57</sp>
<op>62</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Bacterial Agents</k1>
<k1>Anti-Infective Agents</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Infections/therapy</k1>
<k1>Bacteriophages/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Technology, Pharmaceutical/methods</k1>
<ab>Bacteriophages (phages) are viruses of bacteria that can kill and lyse the bacteria they infect. After their discovery early in the 20th century, phages were widely used to treat various bacterial diseases in people and animals. After this enthusiastic beginning to phage therapy, problems with inappropriate use and uncontrolled studies and ultimately the development of antibacterials caused a cessation of phage therapy research in the West. However, a few institutions in Eastern Europe continued to study and use phages as therapeutic agents for human infections. The alarming rise in antibacterial resistance among bacteria has led to a review of the Eastern European studies and to the initiation of controlled experiments in animal models. These recent studies have confirmed that phages can be highly effective in treating many different types of bacterial infections. The lethality and specificity of phages for particular bacteria, the ability of phages to replicate within infected animal hosts, and the safety of phages make them efficacious antibacterial agents. Although there are still several hurdles to be overcome, it appears likely that phage therapy will regain a role in both medical and veterinary treatment of infectious diseases, especially in the scenario of emerging antibacterial resistance.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9705305; 0 (Anti-Bacterial Agents); 0 (Anti-Infective Agents); RF: 27; ppublish</no>
<pp>New Zealand</pp>
<sn>1173-8804; 1173-8804</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11909002; 160106 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11909002</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>297</id>
<a1>Ervin,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Small,P. A.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of incompatible plasmids to control expression of antigen by Salmonella typhimurium and analysis of immunogenicity in mice</t1>
<jf>Microbial pathogenesis</jf>
<jo>Microb.Pathog.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>93</sp>
<op>101</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Vaccines/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bile/immunology</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Induction</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli Proteins</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin A/biosynthesis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin G/biosynthesis/blood/immunology</k1>
<k1>Lac Repressors</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Nasal Cavity/immunology</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Repressor Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Saliva/immunology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Attenuated/immunology</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/biosynthesis/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>Salmonella spp. have been investigated as live vaccine vectors because they are heat stable and can elicit humoral, cellular, and secretory immune responses. However, the expression of some foreign antigens is toxic to bacterial vectors. We therefore studied an approach for the controlled expression of antigen in Salmonella typhimurium wherein the antigen is not expressed in vitro but is expressed in vivo. A model antigen, beta-galactosidase, was expressed from the trc promoter on one plasmid, while repression was achieved by Lacl expressed in trans from a second plasmid. The second repressor plasmid was incompatible with the expression plasmid encoding beta-galactosidase. Loss by segregation of the repressor plasmid in vitro correlated with increased expression of beta-galactosidase. Oral inoculation of mice with salmonellae containing both plasmids induced serum IgG but not nasal, salivary, or biliary IgA antibody to beta-galactosidase. Serum IgG as well as biliary IgA anti-S. typhimurium antibody, but not salivary or nasal IgA, were also detected. This salmonella vector system for the controlled expression of recombinant antigens may be of value for inducing systemic but not mucosal immunity to antigens that are toxic to bacterial vectors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: AI-07713/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8606191; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Vaccines); 0 (Escherichia coli Proteins); 0 (Immunoglobulin A); 0 (Immunoglobulin G); 0 (Lac Repressors); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Repressor Proteins); 0 (Vaccines, Attenuated); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0882-4010; 0882-4010</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8255210; S0882-4010(83)71060-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/mpat.1993.1060</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8255210</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>378</id>
<a1>Ervin,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Small,P. A. Jr</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Salmonella as a Vaccine Vector Controlled De-Novo Expression of Antigen in Mice for Immunization with Toxic Proteins</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>92</vo>
<sp>158</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199243048070; CT: 92ND GENERAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA, MAY 26-30, 1992. ABSTR GEN MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>358</id>
<a1>Escudero,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of peritoneal chamber implants to examine host-pathogen interactions in Vibrio vulnificus infection of mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>2000</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<sp>279</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200000390728&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 100th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Los Angeles, California, USA; CY: May 21-25, 2000; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>330</id>
<a1>Frank,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>The Role of SigmaE and DegP of the Extracytoplasmic Stress Response in Stress Resistance, Biofilm Formation, and Virulence of Vibrio Vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>2008</fd>
<vo>108</vo>
<sp>49</sp>
<op>50</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900190335; CT: 108th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Boston, MA, USA; CY: June 01 -05, 2008; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>345</id>
<a1>Frank,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Rseb, a negative regulator of the extracytoplasmic stress response, is essential for virulence of vibrio vulnificus and indirectly affects colony morphology and surface carbohydrate expression</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>2007</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<sp>112</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800188209; CT: 107th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Toronto, CANADA; CY: 2007,; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>342</id>
<a1>Frank,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Regulation of fatty acid metabolism and sigma e activity are essential for virulence of Vibrio vulnificus in iron dextran-treated mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>2006</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<sp>54</sp>
<op>55</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800232859; CT: 106th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 21 -25, 2006; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>336</id>
<a1>Frank,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Qiu,Y.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Alkaline phosphatase fusion-insertion vectors for use in identifying secreted virulence factors of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>2005</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>67</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800235930; CT: 105th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, GA, USA; CY: June 05 -09, 2005; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>362</id>
<a1>Gallman,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Skinner,S. C.</a1>
<a1>Bomeisl,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Parveen,S.</a1>
<a1>Tamplin,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Pathogenesis of infection by virulent and naturally attenuated strains of Vibrio vulnificus in subcutaneously inoculated, iron dextran-treated mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>1999</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<sp>267</sp>
<op>268</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900345586&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 99th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Chicago, Illinois, USA; CY: May 30-June 3, 1999; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>361</id>
<a1>Gallman,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Skinner,S. C.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Both virulent and naturally attenuated Vibrio vulnificus strains are cytotoxic for, but non-invasive into, human intestinal epithelial cell lines</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>1999</fd>
<vo>99</vo>
<sp>268</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199900345588&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 99th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Chicago, Illinois, USA; CY: May 30-June 3, 1999; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1345</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<t1>Pathogenesis of systemic disease</t1>
<yr>1996</yr>
<sp>2774</sp>
<op>2787</op>
<a2>Neidhardt,FC (editor-in-chief)</a2>
<t2>Escherichia coli and Salmonella : cellular and molecular biology </t2>
<ed>2nd</ed>
<pb>ASM Press</pb>
<pp>Washington DC</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1346</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Bourdage KL</a1>
<a1>Starks AM.</a1>
<t1>Phage display methods for detection of bacterial pathogens</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<is>28</is>
<sp>755</sp>
<op>783</op>
<a2>Zourob,M.</a2><a2> Elwary S</a2><a2>Turner A</a2>
<t2>Handbook of bacteria detection: Biosensors, recognition receptors and microsystems</t2>
<pb>Springer</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<do>10.1007/978-0-387-75113-9_28</do>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1244</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Curtiss R,3rd</a1>
<t1>Tn5 mutagenesis of cloned virulence gense of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid</t1>
<jf>Twenty-Seventh Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>No. 1323</vo>
<sp>327</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1243</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Curtiss R,3rd</a1>
<t1>Studies on the virulence plasmid of Salmonella Typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Twenty-Sixth Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</jf>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>no. 1171</vo>
<sp>310</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1336</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>de Crecy-Lagard V</a1>
<a1>Wright AC</a1>
<a1>Walts B</a1>
<a1>Telonis-Scott M</a1>
<a1>McIntyre LM.</a1>
<t1>SOLiD pyrosequencing of four Vibrio vulnificus genomes enables comparative genomic analysis and identfication of candidate Clade-specific virulence genes.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<sp>230/B</sp>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1241</id>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>McCracken GH,Jr</a1>
<a1>Johnston KH</a1>
<a1>Hansen EJ</a1>
<t1>Human antibody response to outer membrane proteins of Haemophilus influenzae type b.</t1>
<jf>Twenty-first Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy.</jf>
<yr>1981</yr>
<sp>No. 701</sp>
<t2>Twenty-first Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy.</t2>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>303</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Virulence plasmids of Salmonella typhimurium and other salmonellae</t1>
<jf>Microbial pathogenesis</jf>
<jo>Microb.Pathog.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>3</sp>
<op>11</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Salmonella/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Related high molecular weight plasmids of several serotypes and species of Salmonella have been associated with virulence in a variety of animal models of infection. The primary virulence plasmid phenotype is in the ability of salmonellae to spread beyond the initial site of infection, the intestines. The mechanism of this plasmid-mediated invasive infection has not been identified, but may be a complex interaction in the host-pathogen relationship. A common region of the salmonella plasmids has been associated with virulence, and specific virulence genes and their products are now being identified; however, much is yet to be accomplished in this field. The combined analysis of pathogenesis and genetics associated with the salmonella virulence plasmids may identify new systems of bacterial virulence and the genetic basis for this virulence.</ab>
<no>LR: 20060501; JID: 8606191; RF: 46; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0882-4010; 0882-4010</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2185396; 0882-4010(90)90003-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2185396</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>280</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<t1>Molecular Pathogenesis of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Journal of microbiology (Seoul, Korea)</jf>
<jo>J.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>43 Spec No 1</vo>
<sp>118</sp>
<op>131</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is an opportunistic pathogen of humans that has the capability of causing rare, yet devastating disease. The bacteria are naturally present in estuarine environments and frequently contaminate seafoods. Within days of consuming uncooked, contaminated seafood, predisposed individuals can succumb to sepsis. Additionally, in otherwise healthy people, V. vulnificus causes wound infection that can require amputation or lead to sepsis. These diseases share the characteristics that the bacteria multiply extremely rapidly in host tissues and cause extensive damage. Despite the analysis of virulence for over 20 years using a combination of animal and cell culture models, surprisingly little is known about the mechanisms by which V. vulnificus causes disease. This is in part because of differences observed using animal models that involve infection with bacteria versus injection of toxins. However, the increasing use of genetic analysis coupled with detailed animal models is revealing new insight into the pathogenesis of V. vulnificus disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI056056/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9703165; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); RF: 120; ppublish</no>
<pp>Korea (South)</pp>
<sn>1225-8873; 1225-8873</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine PO Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA. gulig@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15765065; 2131 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15765065</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>300</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Caldwell,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V. A.</a1>
<t1>Identification, genetic analysis and DNA sequence of a 7.8-kb virulence region of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1395</sp>
<op>1411</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Codon</k1>
<k1>Consensus Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genetic Complementation Test</k1>
<k1>Kanamycin Kinase</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Phosphotransferases/genetics</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>The 90-kilobase (kb) virulence plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium is responsible for invasion from the intestines to mesenteric lymph nodes and spleens of orally inoculated mice. We used Tn5 and aminoglycoside phosphotransferase (aph) gene insertion mutagenesis and deletion mutagenesis of a previously identified 14-kb virulence region to reduce this virulence region to 7.8kb. The 7.8-kb virulence region subcloned into a low copy-number vector conferred a wild-type level of splenic infection to virulence plasmid-cured S. typhimurium and conferred essentially a wild-type oral LD50. Insertion mutagenesis identified five loci essential for virulence, and DNA sequence analysis of the virulence region identified six open reading frames. Expected protein products were identified from four of the six genes, with three of the proteins identified as doublet bands in Escherichia coli minicells. Three of the five mutated genes were able to be complemented by clones containing only the corresponding wild-type gene. Only one of the five deduced amino acid sequences, that of the positive regulatory element, SpvR, possessed significant homology to other proteins. The codon usage for the virulence genes showed no codon bias, which is consistent with the low levels of expression observed for the corresponding proteins. Consensus promoters for several different sigma factors were identified upstream of several of the genes, whereas only consensus Rho-dependent termination sequences were observed between certain of the genes. The operon structure of this virulence region therefore appears to be complex. The construction of the cloned 7.8-kb virulence region and the determination of the DNA sequence will aid in the further genetic analysis of the five plasmid-encoded virulence genes of S. typhimurium.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/Z11557; GENBANK/Z11561; GR: AI07168/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI24533/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI24821/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Codon); 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); EC 2.7.- (Phosphotransferases); EC 2.7.1.95 (Kanamycin Kinase); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1322485</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1322485</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>302</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V. A.</a1>
<t1>Genetic and DNA sequence analysis of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid gene encoding the 28,000-molecular-weight protein</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>58</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>2651</sp>
<op>2658</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genetic Complementation Test</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors</k1>
<ab>We have confirmed that the 28,000-molecular-weight (28K) protein encoded by the virA gene of the 90-kilobase Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid is a virulence factor. It was previously shown that a Tn5 insertion, vir-22::Tn5, located in the virulence plasmid greatly attenuated virulence for mice and inhibited the production of a 28K protein (P.A. Gulig and R. Curtiss III, Infect. Immun. 56:3262-3271, 1988). Plasmid pYA426 fully complemented vir-22::Tn5 to virulence by increasing splenic infection after oral inoculation and encoded the 28K protein. To identify the virulence gene(s) of pYA426 mutated by vir-22::Tn5, we constructed nested deletions in pYA426 and examined deletion derivatives for their abilities to complement vir-22::Tn5. Only derivatives still producing the 28K protein complemented vir-22::Tn5. Furthermore, the smallest complementing derivative encoded only the 28K protein, as determined by DNA sequence analysis. Therefore, the 28K protein is sufficient for complementation of the attenuating mutation vir-22::Tn5 and must be the virulence factor inhibited by the insertion. We determined the nucleotide sequence of the 1.2-kilobase BamHI-EcoRI fragment encoding the 28K protein and identified the structural gene, virA. A 723-base-pair open reading frame which encodes a peptide with a molecular weight of 27,572 was found.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/M33927; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Virulence Factors); OID: NLM: PMC258868; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2164511</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2164511</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC258868</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>382</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V. A.</a1>
<t1>Confirmation of the 28000 Dalton Protein Encoded by the Salmonella-Typhimurium Virulence Plasmid as being a Virulence Factor and Determination of the Nucleic Acid Sequence</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1989</yr>
<vo>89</vo>
<sp>66</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198937053663; CT: 89TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA, MAY 14-18, 1989. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>308</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,3rd</a1>
<t1>Cloning and transposon insertion mutagenesis of virulence genes of the 100-kilobase plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>3262</sp>
<op>3271</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA Mutational Analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA Transposable Elements</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>We have cloned regions of the 100-kilobase (kb) plasmid, pStSR100, of Salmonella typhimurium SR-11 that confer virulence to plasmid-cured S. typhimurium. Cells carrying recombinant plasmids that conferred virulence were selected by inoculating mice orally with recombinant libraries in virulence plasmid-cured S. typhimurium and harvesting isolates that infected spleens. Three plasmids, pYA401, pYA402, and pYA403, constructed with the cosmid vector pCVD305 conferred wild-type levels of virulence to plasmid-cured S. typhimurium and had a common 14-kb DNA insert sequence. Another recombinant plasmid, pYA422, constructed with the vector pACYC184, conferred to plasmid-cured S. typhimurium a wild-type 50% lethal dose (LD50) level, but mice died more slowly than when infected with wild-type S. typhimurium. Furthermore, pYA422 conferred the ability to cause a higher, but not a wild-type, level of splenic infection on plasmid-cured S. typhimurium. pYA422 had a 3.2-kb insert sequence which mapped to the center of the 14-kb common sequence of the cosmid clones. Transposon Tn5 insertion mutations in pYA403 inhibited virulence to various degrees, and when transduced into the native virulence plasmid of S. typhimurium, these Tn5 insertions decreased virulence to degrees similar to those observed when the Tn5 insertions were present in pYA403. vir-22::Tn5 in pStSR100 greatly lowered infection of spleens relative to unmutagenized virulence plasmid, while vir-26::Tn5 and vir-27::Tn5 lowered splenic infection to lesser degrees. At least three proteins were encoded by pYA403 containing 23 kb of insert sequence and subclone pYA420, containing the 14-kb common insert sequence present in all of the cosmid clones. One of these proteins, with an apparent molecular weight of 28,000, was also encoded by pYA422. The Tn5 insertion that most attenuated virulence, vir-22::Tn5, inhibited synthesis of the 28,000-molecular-weight protein. The vir-22::Tn5 insertion was complemented by recombinant plasmids encoding only the 28,000-molecular-weight protein, suggesting a role of this protein in virulence. However, recombinant plasmids, exemplified by pYA422, that encoded only the 28,000-molecular-weight protein did not confer full virulence.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI24533/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE06669/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: F32-AI07168/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA Transposable Elements); OID: NLM: PMC259733; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Biology, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri 63130.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2846443</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2846443</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC259733</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>309</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,3rd</a1>
<t1>Plasmid-associated virulence of Salmonella typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>2891</sp>
<op>2901</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Adhesion</k1>
<k1>Blood Bactericidal Activity</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Congo Red/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Culture Media</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Peyer&#39;s Patches/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Spleen/microbiology</k1>
<ab>We investigated the role of the 100-kilobase (kb) plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium in the virulence of this organism for mice. Three strains, LT2-Z, SR-11, and SL1344, which possessed 100-kb plasmids with identical restriction enzyme digestion profiles, were cured of their respective 100-kb plasmids after Tnmini-tet was used to label plasmids. Curing wild-type virulent strains SR-11 and SL1344 raised peroral 50% lethal doses from 3 x 10(5) and 6 x 10(4) CFU, respectively, to greater than 10(8) CFU. Both wild-type strains had intraperitoneal 50% lethal doses of less than 50 CFU, whereas the intraperitoneal 50% lethal doses for cured SR-11 and SL1344 were less than 50 and 400 CFU, respectively. Reintroduction of the Tnmini-tet-labeled, 100-kb plasmid restored wild-type virulence. Invasion from Peyer&amp;#39;s patches to mesenteric lymph nodes and spleens after peroral inoculation was the stage of pathogenesis most affected by curing S. typhimurium of the 100-kb plasmid. Wild-type S. typhimurium replicated in spleens of mice inoculated intravenously to a greater extent than did plasmid-cured derivatives. Wild-type and cured strains equally adhered to and invaded Henle-407, HEp-2, and CHO cells; furthermore, the presence of the 100-kb plasmid was not necessary for replication of S. typhimurium within CHO cells. The 100-kb plasmid had no effect on phagocytosis and killing of S. typhimurium by murine peritoneal macrophages in vitro and in vivo. Similarly, wild-type and plasmid-cured strains were resistant to killing by 90% normal human, rabbit, and guinea pig sera. All wild-type and plasmid-cured S. typhimurium strains possessed complete lipopolysaccharide, as determined by silver staining solubilized cells in sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gels. We have confirmed the role of the 100-kb plasmid of S. typhimurium in virulence, primarily in invasion to mesenteric lymph nodes and spleens after peroral inoculation of mice. Involvement of the 100-kb plasmid in infection of mesenteric lymph nodes and spleens suggests a role for the plasmid in the complex interaction of S. typhimurium with cells of the reticuloendothelial system.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: F32-AI07168/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-DE06669/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Culture Media); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 573-58-0 (Congo Red); OID: NLM: PMC260003; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Biology, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri 63130.</ad>
<an>PMID: 3316027</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3316027</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC260003</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>384</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,Iii</a1>
<t1>Cloning of Virulence Genes of the 100 Kb Plasmid of Salmonella-Typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<vo>87</vo>
<sp>96,</sp>
<op>Abstract D147</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198732106669; CT: 87TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, ATLANTA, GEORGIA, USA, MARCH 1-6, 1987. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>298</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Danbara,H.</a1>
<a1>Guiney,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Lax,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Norel,F.</a1>
<a1>Rhen,M.</a1>
<t1>Molecular analysis of spv virulence genes of the Salmonella virulence plasmids</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>825</sp>
<op>830</op>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Salmonella/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Genes on an 8 kb region common to the virulence plasmids of several serovars of Salmonella are sufficient to replace the entire plasmid in enabling systemic infection in animal models. This virulence region encompasses five genes which previously have been designated with different names from each investigating laboratory. A common nomenclature has been devised for the five genes, i.e. spv for salmonella plasmid virulence. The first gene, spvR, encodes a positive activator for the following four genes, spvABCD. DNA sequence analysis of the spv genes from Salmonella typhimurium, Salmonella dublin, and Salmonella choleraesuis demonstrated extremely high conservation of the DNA and amino acid sequences. The spv genes are induced at stationary phase and in carbon-poor media, and optimal expression is dependent on the katF locus. The virulence functions of the spv genes are not known, but these genes may increase the growth rate of salmonellae in host cells and affect the interaction of salmonellae with the host immune system.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8712028; RF: 65; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8483415</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8483415</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>299</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<t1>The Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid increases the growth rate of salmonellae in mice</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>504</sp>
<op>511</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>The virulence plasmids of Salmonella typhimurium and other invasive Salmonella serovars have long been associated with the ability of these bacteria to cause systemic infection beyond the intestines in orally inoculated animals. Genetic analysis of virulence genes on the high-molecular-weight plasmids has revealed that no more than five genes spanning a 6.2-kb region are sufficient to replace the entire plasmid for conferring virulence. However, the exact virulence function(s) encoded by these genes has not been elucidated. In this report, we measured the possible effect of the virulence plasmid on the growth rate of S. typhimurium in mice by two complementary procedures. The first procedure used segregation of a temperature-sensitive plasmid in vivo to provide a measure of bacterial divisions and the number of recovered marker plasmid-containing salmonellae as a measure of killing. In the second procedure, aroA deletions were transduced into virulence plasmid-containing and plasmid-cured S. typhimurium. Since AroA- salmonellae are inhibited for growth in vivo, if the virulence plasmid affected only growth rate, no difference in the recoveries of the paired AroA- strains would be seen. Virulence plasmid-containing S. typhimurium segregated the marker plasmid more rapidly than did the virulence plasmid-cured strain, and AroA- derivatives of both strains were recovered equally from mice. Therefore, the S. typhimurium virulence plasmid increased growth rate but had no detectable effect on killing or bacterial movement into deep tissues. To examine whether the plasmid accomplished this function by affecting the intracellular/extracellular location of bacteria, orally infected mice were injected with gentamicin to kill the extracellular bacteria. Wild-type and plasmid-cured S. typhimurium strains were equally resistant to gentamicin in vivo and hence most likely located intracellularly to equal degrees. When wild-type and plasmid-cured S. typhimurium strains were sequestered within peritoneal chambers in mice, the resulting extracellular growth was equal. Therefore, the virulence plasmid increases the growth rate of S. typhimurium in mice, probably within mouse cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; OID: NLM: PMC302757; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8423080</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8423080</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC302757</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>380</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<t1>The Salmonella-Typhimurium Virulence Plasmid Affects the Growth Rate of Salmonellae in Mice Probably within Infected Host Cells</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>92</vo>
<sp>53</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199243047444; CT: 92ND GENERAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA, MAY 26-30, 1992. ABSTR GEN MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>294</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Clare-Salzler,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Maiese,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Matsui,H.</a1>
<t1>Systemic infection of mice by wild-type but not Spv- Salmonella typhimurium is enhanced by neutralization of gamma interferon and tumor necrosis factor alpha</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>5191</sp>
<op>5197</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Interferon-gamma/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/immunology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/immunology</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>The spv genes of the virulence plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium and other nontyphoidal serovars of S. enterica are involved in systemic infection by increasing the replication rate of the bacteria in host tissues beyond the intestines. We considered the possibility that the Spv virulence function is to evade suppression by the host response to infection. To examine this possibility, gamma interferon (IFN-gamma) and/or tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha) were neutralized in BALB/c mice by intraperitoneal administration of monoclonal antibodies. Neutralization of IFN-gamma and/or TNF-alpha resulted in increased splenic infection with wild-type salmonellae after oral inoculation; however, Spv- salmonellae were defective at increasing splenic infection in cytokine-depleted mice. The use of a temperature-sensitive marker plasmid, pHSG422, indicated that neutralization of IFN-gamma caused less killing of wild-type S. typhimurium, while neutralization of TNF-alpha resulted in an increased in vivo replication rate for wild-type salmonellae. These results demonstrate that the Spv virulence function is not to evade suppression of bacterial infection normally mediated by IFN-gamma or TNF-alpha.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha); 82115-62-6 (Interferon-gamma); OID: NLM: PMC175748; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA. gulig@college.med.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 9393815</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9393815</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC175748</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>293</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Hughes,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Matsui,H.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of host cells associated with the Spv-mediated increased intracellular growth rate of Salmonella typhimurium in mice</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2471</sp>
<op>2485</op>
<k1>Agranulocytosis/chemically induced</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cyclophosphamide/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Lymphocytes/immunology</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/immunology/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mice, Mutant Strains</k1>
<k1>Mice, Nude</k1>
<k1>Mice, SCID</k1>
<k1>Neutrophils/immunology</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/growth &amp; development/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Spleen/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors</k1>
<ab>The 90-kb virulence plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium encodes five spv genes which increase the growth rate of the bacteria within host cells within the first week of systemic infection of mice (P. A. Gulig and T. J. Doyle, Infect. Immun. 61:504-511, 1993). The presently described study was aimed at identifying the host cells associated with Spv-mediated virulence by manipulating the mouse host and the salmonellae. To test the effects of T cells and B cells on the Spv phenotype, salmonellae were orally inoculated into nude and SCID BALB/c mice. Relative to normal BALB/c mice, nude and SCID BALB/c mice were unaffected for splenic infection with either the Spv+ or Spv- S. typhimurium strains at 5 days postinoculation. When mice were pretreated with cyclophosphamide to induce granulocytopenia, there was a variable increase in total salmonella infection, but the relative splenic CFU of Spv+ versus Spv- S. typhimurium was not changed after oral inoculation. In contrast, depletion of macrophages from mice by treatment with cyclophosphamide plus liposomes containing dichloromethylene diphosphate resulted in equivalent virulence of Spv+ and Spv- salmonellae. To examine if the spv genes affected the growth of salmonellae in nonphagocytic cells, an invA::aphT mutation was transduced into Spv+ and Spv- S. typhimurium strains. InvA- Spv+ salmonellae were not significantly affected for splenic infection after subcutaneous inoculation compared with the wild-type strain, and InvA- Spv- salmonellae were only slightly attenuated relative to InvA+ Spv- salmonellae. Invasion-defective salmonellae still exhibited the Spv phenotype. Therefore, infection of nonphagocytes is not involved with the Spv virulence function. Taken together, these data demonstrate that macrophages are essential for suppressing the infection by Spv- S. typhimurium, by serving as the primary host cell for Spv-mediated intracellular replication and possibly by inhibiting the replication of salmonellae within other macrophages.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Virulence Factors); 50-18-0 (Cyclophosphamide); OID: NLM: PMC108227; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA. gulig@college.med.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 9596705</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9596705</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC108227</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>357</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Escudero,G. M.</a1>
<t1>Cell culture and mouse peritoneal chamber implant models reveal differences in cytotoxicity between clinical and environmental Vibrio vulnificus strains</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>2001</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<sp>289</sp>
<op>290</op>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is a marine bacterium that contaminates shellfish, primarily oysters. Predisposed humans can die within 24 h from septicemia after consuming contaminated oysters because the bacteria invade through and replicate extensively in tissues. However, not all strains of V. vulnificus can cause disease. Subcutaneous inoculation of iron dextran-treated mice with three clinical strains required 100 CFU to cause lethal infection; however, three environmental strains required up to 1000-fold higher inocula to cause disease. We investigated if the differences in virulence between these strains was due to differences in damage to host cells by using human intestinal cell lines or in the in vivo growth of the bacteria by using peritoneal chamber implants in mice. All six strains translocated through polarized Caco-2 cell monolayers by destroying monolayer integrity. All three clinical strains and one environmental strain caused moderate to high levels of lysis and detachment of epithelial cells. However, the other two environmental isolates caused significantly less damage. Hemolysin and metalloprotease mutants were unaffected in the cell culture assays, and there was no correlation between proteolytic or hemolytic activities and virulence in mice or in cell culture assays. It appears that cytotoxicity is necessary but not sufficient for virulence in mice. In iron dextran-treated mice, all six strains replicated rapidly with doubling times of less than 25 minutes within peritoneal chambers that sequester the bacteria from host cells. Lack of exogenous iron did not affect growth in the chambers, except for one environmental strain and one clinical strain which had two-fold higher doubling times. Differences in in vivo growth rate, if any exist, might require contact of the vibrios with host cells or tissues. In summary, differences in mouse-virulence among clinical and environmental strains of V. vulnificus could be due to unidentified toxins, other than hemolysin and protease, which we detected with cell culture assays.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200200201401&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 101st General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 20-24, 2001; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>314</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,C. F.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>A set of two monoclonal antibodies specific for the cell surface-exposed 39K major outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b defines all strains of this pathogen</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>42</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>516</sp>
<op>524</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Surface/analysis</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/immunology</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Hybridomas/immunology</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Radioimmunoassay</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Six murine plasma cell hybridomas producing monoclonal antibodies (mabs) directed against the 39,000-molecular-weight (39K) major outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b were employed in the antigenic analysis of the 39K protein. The initial characterization of the mabs by radioimmunoprecipitation analysis showed that four of these mabs reacted with antigenic determinants of the 39K protein that are exposed on the bacterial cell surface and accessible to antibody. The other two mabs reacted with antigenic determinants of the 39K protein that are either not exposed on the H. influenzae type b cell surface or not accessible to antibody (internal determinants). A total of 126 clinical isolates of H. influenzae type b obtained from pediatric research centers throughout the United States were examined for reactivity with the six mabs by using a solid-phase radioimmunoassay in which bacterial colony growth from agar plates was placed on filter paper and used as antigen. The reactivities of these strains with two of the mabs recognizing cell surface-exposed antigenic determinants of the 39K protein were used to divide the 126 strains into four different groups. Group 1 strains reacted with mab 12D9, group 2 strains reacted with mab 4C4, group 3 strains reacted with both mabs 12D9 and 4C4, and group 4 strains (only one was found) did not react with either mab. The reactivities of two other mabs recognizing cell surface-exposed antigenic determinants of the 39K protein were used to further divide the four groups into eight subgroups. A single mab recognizing an internal antigenic determinant of the 39K protein reacted with every H. influenzae type b strain examined in this study. These data indicate that only limited antigenic heterogeneity exists among the cell surface-exposed antigenic determinants of the 39K outer membrane proteins among H. influenzae type b strains and that at least one internal antigenic determinant of the 39K protein is universally present in all H. influenzae type b strains. Radioimmunoprecipitation analysis also demonstrated that H. influenzae type b strains which lacked a 39K major outer membrane protein possessed a 38K major outer membrane protein which reacted with the anti-39K mabs, indicating that the 38K and 39K outer membrane proteins of different H. influenzae type b strains are antigenically related.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Surface); 0 (Membrane Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC264459; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 6605924</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6605924</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC264459</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>386</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Co-Immunoprecipitation of Lipopolysaccharide and the 39-Kilodalton Outer Membrane Protein of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B Lipopolysaccharide-Specific Monoclonal Antibody</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>Abstract C178</is>
<sp>329</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198529052418; CT: 85TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, LAS VEGAS, NEV., USA, MAR. 3-7, 1985. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>311</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Coprecipitation of lipopolysaccharide and the 39,000-molecular-weight major outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b by lipopolysaccharide-directed monoclonal antibody</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>819</sp>
<op>827</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Chemical Precipitation</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred Strains</k1>
<ab>The major outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) with an apparent molecular weight of 39,000 (39K) was purified from three different Hib strains and was shown to be free from detectable contamination with other proteins. However, these purified 39K protein preparations were found to contain Hib lipopolysaccharide (LPS). Immunization of rats with these 39K protein preparations resulted in the production of antisera containing both 39K protein-directed and LPS-directed antibodies, as determined by Western blot analysis. The reactivity pattern of the LPS-directed serum antibodies with different Hib strains was identical to the reactivity of these Hib strains with a set of monoclonal antibodies (mabs) previously shown to immunoprecipitate the 39K protein in a radioimmunoprecipitation (RIP) system. Examination of the antigenic specificities of the 39K protein-immunoprecipitating mabs by using Western blot analysis showed that these mabs were actually directed against Hib LPS. RIP analysis of 125I-labeled Hib cells and 32P-labeled Hib cells revealed that the 39K protein and LPS existed as a complex in a RIP system, which resulted in the coprecipitation of both antigens by LPS-directed mabs. The interaction between LPS and the 39K protein was highly selective for this protein and did not involve other outer membrane proteins. The LPS/39K protein complex could be reconstituted by mixing purified LPS and purified 39K protein; it could also be reconstituted with 39K protein from one Hib strain and LPS from another Hib strain. These findings have necessitated the reinterpretation of previous studies involving the 39K protein-immunoprecipitating mabs. Of primary importance is the fact that the demonstrated immunoprotective ability of a 39K protein-immunoprecipitating mab (E. J. Hansen, S. M. Robertson, P. A. Gulig, C. F. Frisch, and E. J. Haanes, Lancet i:366-368, 1982) must now be regarded as evidence that antibody directed against Hib LPS can be protective against experimental Hib disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); OID: NLM: PMC261287; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 3875563</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3875563</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC261287</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>392</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Identification of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B Outer Membrane Proteins Expressed both In-Vitro and In-Vivo</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>Abstract D21</is>
<sp>62</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198426009941; CT: 83RD ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LA., USA, MAR. 6-11, 1983. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>391</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Identification of Immunogenic Proteins in Cell-Free Culture Supernatants of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>Abstract D22</is>
<sp>62</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198426009942; CT: 83RD ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LA., USA, MAR. 6-11, 1983. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>393</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of the Antibody Response of Infant Rats to Outer Membrane Proteins of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>82</vo>
<is>Abstract B48</is>
<sp>26</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198223054839; CT: 82ND ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, ATLANTA, GA., USA, MARCH 7-12, 1982. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>390</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Loftus,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Variability in Antibody Accessibility of Selected Antigenic Determinants of the 39000 Molecular Weight Outer Membrane Protein of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>Abstract D56</is>
<sp>60</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198427009934; CT: 84TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, ST. LOUIS, MO., USA, MAR. 4-9, 1984. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>316</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Frisch,C. F.</a1>
<a1>Johnston,K. H.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Antibody response of infants to cell surface-exposed outer membrane proteins of Haemophilus influenzae type b after systemic Haemophilus disease</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>82</sp>
<op>88</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/analysis</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/classification/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Haemophilus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Precipitin Tests</k1>
<ab>The immune response of nine infants with Haemophilus influenzae type b meningitis was examined by using a radioimmunoprecipitation procedure designed to detect antibodies directed against cell surface-exposed outer membrane proteins of this pathogen. Using intrinsically or extrinsically radiolabeled intact H. influenzae type b cells with acute- and convalescent-phase human sera in this radioimmunoprecipitation system, we found that all of the infants produced an antibody response directed against several different H. influenzae type b outer membrane proteins. Anti-H. influenzae type b outer membrane protein antibodies present in convalescent sera, but not found in acute sera, were directed against cell surface-exposed H. influenzae type b outer membrane proteins. In contrast, both acute and convalescent sera contained antibody activity directed against numerous H. influenzae type b outer membrane proteins whose antigenic determinants were apparently inaccessible to antibody on intact H. influenzae type b cells. The ability of infants to develop an antibody response to cell surface-exposed, antibody-accessible H. influenzae type b outer membrane proteins indicates that these proteins may have vaccinogenic potential.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Membrane Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC347494; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 6980838</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6980838</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC347494</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>313</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Holmans,P. L.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Immunogenic proteins in cell-free culture supernatants of Haemophilus influenzae type b</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>41</sp>
<op>48</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Newborn/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoenzyme Techniques</k1>
<k1>Immunosorbent Techniques</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Meningitis, Haemophilus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred Strains/immunology</k1>
<k1>Subcellular Fractions/analysis</k1>
<ab>Cell-free culture supernatant (CFCS) prepared from Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) was examined for the presence of soluble Hib proteins. Two proteins with apparent molecular weights of 100,000 (100K) and 116K were predominant in the CFCS, and antibodies directed against these proteins could be detected by radioimmunoprecipitation or Western blot analyses of serum from adult rats immunized with Hib. Radioimmunoprecipitation analyses and sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis of these two proteins demonstrated that the 100K CFCS protein was also present on the cell surface of Hib, whereas the 116K CFCS protein was only detectable in culture supernatants. Both the 100K and 116K CFCS proteins were immunogenic in human infants with Hib meningitis and in infant rats systemically infected with Hib. In addition, the first detectable antibodies produced in these Hib-infected rats against Hib proteins were specific for the 100K protein in both its CFCS and cell-associated forms. These two CFCS proteins were also immunogenic in rats immunized with CFCS in the absence of Hib infection. Monoclonal antibody directed against the 100K protein reacted with 34 of 55 Hib strains examined by using a colony blot radioimmunoassay. The immunogenicity of the 100K and 116K CFCS proteins suggests that one or both of these proteins may have potential for vaccine development, either by themselves or covalently coupled to Hib capsular polysaccharide.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-17012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC263464; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 6368394</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6368394</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC263464</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>310</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Patrick,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Hermanstorfer,L.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Conservation of epitopes in the oligosaccharide portion of the lipooligosaccharide of Haemophilus influenzae type b</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>513</sp>
<op>520</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Child</k1>
<k1>Epitopes/immunology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/immunology</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Texas</k1>
<ab>The antigenic characteristics of the lipooligosaccharide (LOS) of Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) were examined in strains obtained over an extended period of time. These Hib strains were isolated from patients with systemic Hib disease in Dallas, Tex., over a 20-year period and in New York City between 1941 and 1956. The antigenic characteristics of the LOS of these Hib strains were examined by using a set of four murine monoclonal antibodies directed against epitopes present in the oligosaccharide portion of the LOS molecule. The same basic set of LOS antigenic determinants that is expressed by recent Hib isolates was also found to be present in this collection of Hib strains spanning a 40-year period. Some variation with time was detected in the distribution of the systemic disease isolates among four Hib LOS antigenic groups; however, only 2 of 188 Hib isolates failed to react with a set of two LOS-specific monoclonal antibodies. Therefore, little variation has occurred among Hib strains with regard to the LOS epitopes defined by these monoclonal antibodies over a considerable period of time.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Epitopes); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 0 (lipid-linked oligosaccharides); OID: NLM: PMC260366; ppublish</no>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 2434425</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2434425</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC260366</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>363</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Roberts,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<t1>Salmonella typhimurium resides primarily within macrophages in spleens and livers after oral and subcutaneous inoculation of BALB/c mice, but does not infect hepatocytes except after intravenous inoculation</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>1998</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<sp>91</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199800415785&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 98th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, Georgia, USA; CY: May 17-21, 1998; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>276</id>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Tucker,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Joseph,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Brown,R. N.</a1>
<t1>USER friendly cloning coupled with chitin-based natural transformation enables rapid mutagenesis of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</jf>
<jo>Appl.Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>15</is>
<sp>4936</sp>
<op>4949</op>
<k1>Chitin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genetic Engineering/methods</k1>
<k1>Molecular Biology/methods</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Transformation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors/genetics</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is a bacterial contaminant of shellfish and causes highly lethal sepsis and destructive wound infections. A definitive identification of virulence factors using the molecular version of Koch&amp;#39;s postulates has been hindered because of difficulties in performing molecular genetic analysis of this opportunistic pathogen. For example, conjugation is required to introduce plasmid DNA, and allelic exchange suicide vectors that rely on sucrose sensitivity for counterselection are not efficient. We therefore incorporated USER friendly cloning techniques into pCVD442-based allelic exchange suicide vectors and other expression vectors to enable the rapid and efficient capture of PCR amplicons. Upstream and downstream DNA sequences flanking genes targeted for deletion were cloned together in a single step. Based on results from Vibrio cholerae, we determined that V. vulnificus becomes naturally transformable with linear DNA during growth on chitin in the form of crab shells. By combining USER friendly cloning and chitin-based transformation, we rapidly and efficiently produced targeted deletions in V. vulnificus, bypassing the need for two-step, suicide vector-mediated allelic exchange. These methods were used to examine the roles of two flagellin loci (flaCDE and flaFBA), the motAB genes, and the cheY-3 gene in motility and to create deletions of rtxC, rtxA1, and fadR. Additionally, chitin-based transformation was useful in moving antibiotic resistance-labeled mutations between V. vulnificus strains by simply coculturing the strains on crab shells. The methods and genetic tools that we developed should be of general use to those performing molecular genetic analysis and manipulation of other gram-negative bacteria.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100202; GR: R01 AI056056/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI060527/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7605801; 0 (Virulence Factors); 1398-61-4 (Chitin); OID: NLM: PMC2725515; 2009/06/05 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5336; 0099-2240</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, 32610-0266, USA. gulig@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19502446; AEM.02564-08 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/AEM.02564-08</do>
<wp>20090605</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19502446</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2725515</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>319</id>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Use of isogenic mutants to study bacterial virulence factors</t1>
<jf>Journal of microbiological methods</jf>
<jo>J.Microbiol.Methods</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>10</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>275</sp>
<op>287</op>
<k1>Bacteria</k1>
<k1>Genetics</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Pathogenesis</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<sn>0167-7012</sn>
<do>DOI: 10.1016/0167-7012(93)90042-G</do>
<ul>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6T30-476TX91-9B/2/bb5ee339e198d7eba8e92d390ae00f6b</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>364</id>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,Thomas J.</a1>
<a1>Vogel,Stefanie N.</a1>
<a1>Benjamin,William H.,Jr.</a1>
<t1>Interactions between Salmonella typhimurium spv genotype and the murine Ity and Lps genotypes during systemic infection</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>1997</fd>
<vo>97</vo>
<sp>99</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199799581345; CT: 97th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Miami Beach, Florida, USA; CY: May 4-8, 1997</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>331</id>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<a1>Martin,Julio L.</a1>
<a1>Messer,Harald G.</a1>
<a1>Deffense,Beverly L.</a1>
<a1>Harpley,Crystal J.</a1>
<t1>Phage Display Methods for Detection of Bacterial Pathogens</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<sp>783</sp>
<ab>There exists a great need for detecting bacterial pathogens in food, water, environmental, and patient samples. Although significant developments are being made in nucleic acid-based detection, e.g., real time-PCR. there are advantages to detecting, microbial antigens using a variety of assays Such as enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), antibody arrays. fiber optics, and surface plasmon resonance. Immunological reagents used to detect microbial antigens have mostly consisted of antisera Or monoclonal antibodies. However. over the past two decades new methods have been developed that use bacteriophages (phages). viruses of bacteria, as tools to express antibody fragments or random peptides that call detect microbes. The most widely used antibody fragment is the single chain F variable (scFv) portion that includes the antigen-binding regions of the heavy and light chains. The genes encoding antibodies can be obtained either from unimmunized animals or from animals immunized with the target antigen or microbe. scFv libraries are Usually constructed in specialized plasmids called phagemids that create fusions of the antibody fragment to it phage coat protein. Phagemids Must be packaged into phage particles by the Use of helper phages during infection of E. coli hosts. Random peptides are usually constructed in phage genomes directly: hence. they do not require helper phages. DNA sequences encoding, random peptides and antibodies are most often fused to the gIII gene of a filamentous phage Such as M13 so that a hybrid pIII protein is expressed on the phage particle. Phage particles that display a fusion peptide that recognizes the desired anti-en are selected from the library by a process called panning. Panning involve, binding phages to the antigen. washing away unbound phages, Outing the specific phages, and amplification by infection of an E. coli host. A major advantage of phage display is that panning and screening of clones can be accomplished in only a few days, as opposed to months for antisera and monoclonal antibodies. Once a phage displaying in antibody fragment or random peptide of desired specificity is isolated, the gene encoding the binding peptide can be genetically manipulated. With scFvs, it is possible to have E. coli cells secrete the protein, rather than relying on the use of the phage particle displaying the scFv protein. This chapter reviews the literature on the use of phage display to detect bacteria in a variety of assays. There has been considerable success in the use of commercially available random peptide phage display libraries. Most reported success with scFv phage display has been from using libraries constructed from immunized animals. In addition to antibodies, other target-binding tools are under development, Such as affibodies. anticalins, ankyrins, and trinectins. The ease, economy, rapidity, and genetic manipulability of phage display make it an effective tool for developing, reagents to detect bacterial pathogens.</ab>
<no>PT: B; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900094865</no>
<a2>Zourob, M Elwary, S Turner,A.</a2>
<sn>978-0-387-75112-2(H) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>375</id>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<a1>Rogers,Julie A.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,Vince A.</a1>
<t1>The Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid-encoded spv operon requires OxyR and RelA for maximal expression and induction</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>Abstract B66</is>
<sp>38</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199345040446; CT: 93rd General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, Georgia, USA; CY: May 16-20, 1993</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1338</id>
<a1>Hansen EJ</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA.</a1>
<t1>Immunogenic proteins on the surface of Haemophilus influenzae type b</t1>
<yr>1985</yr>
<sp>106</sp>
<op>109</op>
<a2>Leive,Loretta</a2>
<t2>Microbiology - 1985</t2>
<pb>American Society for Microbiology</pb>
<pp>Washing DC</pp>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1339</id>
<a1>Hansen EJ</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Kimura A</a1>
<a1>McCracken GH.</a1>
<t1>High molecular weight proteins on the surface of Haemophilus influenzae type b.</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<sp>273</sp>
<op>282</op>
<a2>Robbins JB</a2><a2> Schneerson R</a2><a2> Kline D</a2><a2> Sadoff JC</a2><a2>Hartdegree C.</a2>
<t2>Bacterial vaccines.</t2>
<pb>Praeger</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>385</id>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Immunogenic Proteins on the Surface of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B</t1>
<yr>1985</yr>
<sp>106</sp>
<op>109</op>
<no>PT: B; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198529106092</no>
<a2>LEIVE,L.</a2>
<t2>MICROBIOLOGY-1985; MEETINGS OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY. X+486P</t2>
<pb>AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY</pb>
<pp>WASHINGTON, D.C</pp>
<sn>0-914826-78-6 ER</sn>
<db>BIOSIS</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>387</id>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Loftus,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hart,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Toews,G. B.</a1>
<t1>Intravenous Administration of Monoclonal Antibody Enhances Pulmonary Clearance of Haemophilus-Influenzae</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>Abstract B198</is>
<sp>51</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198529032677; CT: 85TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, LAS VEGAS, NEV., USA, MAR. 3-7, 1985. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>318</id>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Robertson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,C. F.</a1>
<a1>Haanes,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Immunoprotection of rats against Haemophilus influenzae type B disease mediated by monoclonal antibody against a haemophilus outer-membrane protein</t1>
<jf>Lancet</jf>
<jo>Lancet</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Feb 13</fd>
<vo>1</vo>
<is>8268</is>
<sp>366</sp>
<op>368</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Animals, Newborn/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibody Specificity</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus Infections/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunization, Passive</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<ab>Infant rats passively immunised with a murine monoclonal antibody against a cell-surface-exposed outer-membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae by b (Hib) were protected against systemic Hib disease induced by intraperitoneal injection of virulent Hib cells. The immunoprotection mediated by this monoclonal antibody was specific for Hib strains carrying the protein antigenic determinant that it recognised; the antibody gave no protection against disease when passively immunised animals were challenged with a heterologous Hib strain. The immunoprotection given by an antibody against a Hib outer-membrane protein suggests that Hib outer-membrane proteins have potential for development as Hib vaccines.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985213R; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Membrane Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0140-6736; 0140-6736</sn>
<an>PMID: 6120351</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6120351</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>288</id>
<a1>Jeong,K. C.</a1>
<a1>Jeong,H. S.</a1>
<a1>Rhee,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Lee,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Chung,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Escudero,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Choi,S. H.</a1>
<t1>Construction and phenotypic evaluation of a Vibrio vulnificus vvpE mutant for elastolytic protease</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>5096</sp>
<op>5106</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Metalloendopeptidases/deficiency/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Pancreatic Elastase/deficiency/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Vibrio/enzymology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is an opportunistic gram-negative pathogen that commonly contaminates oysters. Predisposed individuals who consume raw oysters can die within days from sepsis, and even otherwise healthy people are susceptible to serious wound infection after contact with contaminated seafood or seawater. Numerous secreted and cell-associated virulence factors have been proposed to account for the fulminating and destructive nature of V. vulnificus infections. Among the putative virulence factors is an elastolytic metalloprotease. We cloned and sequenced the vvpE gene encoding an elastase of V. vulnificus ATCC 29307. The functions of the elastase were assessed by constructing vvpE insertional knockout mutants and evaluating phenotypic changes in vitro and in mice. Although other types of protease activity were still observed in vvpE mutants, elastase activity was completely absent in the mutants and was restored by reintroducing the recombinant vvpE gene. In contrast to previous characterization of elastase as a potential virulence factor, which was demonstrated by injecting the purified protein into animals, inactivation of the V. vulnificus vvpE gene did not affect the ability of the bacteria to infect mice and cause damage, either locally in subcutaneous tissues or systemically in the liver, in both iron-treated and normal mice. Furthermore, a vvpE mutant was not affected with regard to cytolytic activity toward INT407 epithelial cells or detachment of INT407 cells from culture dishes in vitro. Therefore, it appears that elastase is less important in the pathogenesis of V. vulnificus than would have been predicted by examining the effects of administering purified proteins to animals. However, V. vulnificus utilizes a variety of virulence factors; hence, the effects of inactivation of elastase alone could be masked by other compensatory virulence factors.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0246127; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (RNA, Messenger); EC 3.4.21.36 (Pancreatic Elastase); EC 3.4.24.- (Metalloendopeptidases); EC 3.4.24.- (vvP protein, Vibrio vulnificus); OID: NLM: PMC101747; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Food Science and Technology, Institute of Biotechnology, Chonnam National University, Kwang-Ju, 500-757, South Korea.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10948131</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10948131</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC101747</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>329</id>
<a1>Joseph,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>A Phospholipase/Hemolysin of Vibrio vulnificus has no Role in Virulence in a Mouse Model</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>2008</fd>
<vo>108</vo>
<sp>62</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900190396; CT: 108th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Boston, MA, USA; CY: June 01 -05, 2008; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>346</id>
<a1>Joseph,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of the three RTX loci in pathogenesis of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>2007</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<sp>37</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800187846; CT: 107th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Toronto, CANADA; CY: 2007,; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>341</id>
<a1>Joseph,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Roles of RTX toxins of Vibrio vulnificus in cytotoxicity and mouse virulence</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>2006</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<sp>55</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800232861; CT: 106th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 21 -25, 2006; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>388</id>
<a1>Kimura,A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gonzales,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Fritz,E. J.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>A Monoclonal Antibody Recognizes a Virulence-Associated Antigenic Determinant of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B Lipopolysaccharide</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>Abstract B21</is>
<sp>21</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198529032620; CT: 85TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, LAS VEGAS, NEV., USA, MAR. 3-7, 1985. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>312</id>
<a1>Kimura,A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Loftus,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>A minor high-molecular-weight outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b is a protective antigen</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>259</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Epitopes/analysis</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Radioimmunoassay</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Inbred Strains</k1>
<ab>Cell surface-exposed antigenic determinants of several high-molecular-weight outer membrane proteins of Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) have been shown to be consistently immunogenic in human infants convalescing from Hib meningitis. A monoclonal antibody (mab), 6G12, directed against one of these cell surface-exposed outer membrane proteins that has an apparent molecular weight of 98,000 (98K) was identified by radioimmunoprecipitation analysis. Of 120 clinical isolates of Hib, 83 were found to possess antigenic determinants which reacted with mab 6G12 in a colony blot-radioimmunoassay procedure, indicating that the antigenic determinant recognized by mab 6G12 is present in the majority of Hib strains. A different radioimmunoassay, which uses whole Hib cells as antigen, confirmed that strains reactive with mab 6G12 in the colony blot-radioimmunoassay procedure possessed a cell surface-exposed and antibody-accessible antigenic determinant recognized by this mab. Hib strains which did not react with mab 6G12 were found to lack a 98K protein. Passive immunization with mab 6G12 reduced the level of bacteremia that developed in infant rats challenged with the homologous Hib strain against which this mab was raised. In contrast, no protection was observed when the challenge strain was one which lacks the antigenic determinant recognized by mab 6G12. Radioimmunoprecipitation analysis of sera from human infants convalescing from Hib meningitis detected an antibody response directed against the 98K protein. The protection against experimental Hib disease provided by antibody to the 98K protein, the immunogenicity of this protein in human infants, and its presence in a majority of Hib strains indicate that the 98K outer membrane protein may have potential for vaccine development.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-17012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Outer Membrane Proteins); 0 (Epitopes); OID: NLM: PMC261504; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 2578121</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2578121</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC261504</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>389</id>
<a1>Kimura,A.</a1>
<a1>Mccracken,G. H. Jr</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Loftus,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Identification of an Immunogenic High Molecular Weight Outer Membrane Protein of Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B as a Protective Antigen</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>84</vo>
<sp>ABSTRATB99</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198427017144; CT: 84TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, ST. LOUIS, MO., USA, MAR. 4-9, 1984. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>350</id>
<a1>Kramer,M. F.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Lim,D. V.</a1>
<t1>A rapid and automated fiber optic-based biosensor assay for the detection of Salmonella in spent irrigation water used in the sprouting of sprout seeds.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<sp>P</sp>
<op>062</op>
<ab>Several outbreaks of foodborne illness have recently been linked to the consumption of contaminated sprouts. The spent irrigation water used to irrigate sprouts can be a carrier of many microorganisms including pathogenic strains of Escherichia coli and Salmonella enterica. These pathogens are believed to originate from the seeds. The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) recommends that sprout producers conduct microbiological testing of spent irrigation water from each production lot at least 48 hours after seeds have germinated. Microbial analysis for the detection of Salmonella is labor intensive and takes days to complete. A rapid (20 minute) and automated fiber optic-based biosensor assay targeted to detect Salmonella in sprout rinse water was developed in this study. The sandwich immunoassay that was developed consisted of a polyclonal antibody, affinity purified for common structural antigen-1 of Salmonella (Kirkegaard &amp;amp; Perry Laboratories Inc., Gaithersburg, MD), used for Salmonella capture and a monoclonal antibody to S. typhimurium (BiosPacific, Emeryville, CA) used for detection. This antibody combination could directly detect a minimum of 105 CFU/ml of S. typhimurium in alfalfa sprout spent irrigation water. Alfalfa seeds contaminated with various concentrations of S. typhimurium were sprouted. The spent irrigation water was assayed 72 hours after alfalfa seed germination using the RAPTOR (Research International, Woodinville, WA), an automated fiber optic-based detector. S. typhimurium could be positively identified in spent irrigation water when seeds were contaminated with 40 CFU/g of S. typhimurium. This biosensor assay system has the potential to be directly connected to water-lines within the sprout processing facility and to operate automatically requiring manual labor only for preventative maintenance. Therefore the presence of S. typhimurium in spent irrigation water could be continuously and rapidly determined three to five days before completion of the sprouting process.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300534238&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 103rd American Society for Microbiology General Meeting; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: May 18-22, 2003; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>370</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Faberowski,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Multiple use of Monoject syringes</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology (Hagerstown)</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1270</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497536485; CT: Annual Meeting of the American Society of Anesthesiologists; CL: San Francisco, California, USA; CY: October 15-19, 1994</no>
<sn>0003-3022 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>325</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Faverowski,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Multiple-use of Monoject Syringes</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1270</sp>
<op>A1270</op>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. S</no>
<sn>0003-3022</sn>
<an>A1994PJ09101269</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>291</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Roberts,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Skinner,S.</a1>
<a1>Langevin,S. O.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Growth of Staphylococcus aureus in Diprivan and Intralipid: implications on the pathogenesis of infections</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1394</sp>
<op>1400</op>
<k1>Anesthetics, Intravenous/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Edetic Acid</k1>
<k1>Fat Emulsions, Intravenous/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Propofol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcal Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/drug effects/growth &amp; development/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The incidence and severity of infections are increased when Intralipid or Diprivan are administered to patients. Intralipid promotes infection, presumably by inhibiting the reticuloendothelial system, thereby suppressing the host&amp;#39;s constitutive immunity, whereas Diprivan supposedly promotes infection by supporting bacterial growth and increasing the inoculating dose. This study considers whether bacterial replication alone in Intralipid and Diprivan adequately explains the increased risk of infection associated with these agents or whether other factors might also be involved. METHODS: Staphylococcus aureus was cultured in 10% Intralipid or Diprivan at clinically relevant conditions or in Intralipid containing 0.005% (w/v) sodium EDTA, a current additive, to measure growth. To determine whether Intralipid affected infection, New Zealand white rabbits were injected intravenously with S. aureus with or without Intralipid. Twenty-four hours later, bacteria in lung, liver, spleen, and kidney tissues were enumerated. RESULTS: S. aureus failed to grow in Diprivan or Intralipid containing 0.005% EDTA. Whereas S. aureus did replicate in plain Intralipid, growth was delayed until the bacteria conditioned the media. Once initiated, growth was slow at clinically relevant temperatures. The administration of Intralipid to rabbits significantly increased the recovery of staphylococci from the kidneys, P &amp;lt; 0.001, relative to the other tissues 24 h after an intravenous inoculation with S. aureus, compared with rabbits receiving S. aureus with no Intralipid. CONCLUSIONS: These results suggest that Diprivan, and possibly Intralipid, represent poor media for the growth of S. aureus and may promote infection through mechanisms other than increased inoculum size.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 1300217; 0 (Anesthetics, Intravenous); 0 (Fat Emulsions, Intravenous); 2078-54-8 (Propofol); 60-00-4 (Edetic Acid); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-3022; 0003-3022</sn>
<ad>Department of Anesthesiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA. anita@anest2.anest.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 10551591</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10551591</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>296</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<a1>Langevin,S. O.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Epidural catheter reconnection. Safe and unsafe practice</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>883</sp>
<op>888</op>
<k1>Analgesia, Epidural/adverse effects/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Anesthesia, Epidural/adverse effects/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Infections/etiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Catheterization/adverse effects/methods</k1>
<k1>Disinfection/methods</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Evaluation Studies as Topic</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas aeruginosa/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Safety</k1>
<k1>Staphylococcus aureus/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: An in vitro model of epidural catheter contamination was used to determine if disconnected catheters can be safely reconnected. METHODS: Epidural catheters were filled with brain-heart infusion (BHI) broth or preservative-free saline containing 5 micrograms/ml fentanyl. Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, or Staphylococcus aureus (1.10(5) colony-forming units) was injected into the initial 1.1 +/- 0.24 inch (2.75 +/- 0.60 cm) of the catheters. To study the effect of bacteria settling in a vertically oriented catheter on the advancement of bacteria along the catheter, bacteria were incubated with catheters in the vertical and the horizontal positions. To determine if bacteria are swept further into a catheter when fluid in it is displaced, catheters were inclined 30 degrees and the fluid in them was allowed to drain from the distal end to various extents. Bacteria were incubated with the catheter held horizontally. After incubation, the catheters were serially sectioned, and the resulting segments were eluted with buffered saline-containing gelatin (BSG), which was collected on BHI agar plates for colony counts. This determined if a segment of the catheter remained internally sterile distal to the point of disconnection. Effectiveness of decontaminating the exterior of the catheter was also tested as follows: Catheters (n = 10) were first immersed in BSG containing 1.10(5) S, aureus, immediately immersed in betadine for 2 min, exposed to air for 3 min, cut with a sterile instrument, and reconnected to a sterile screw cap catheter connector. Reconnected catheters were perfused with 10 ml BSG for 1 hr. Collected perfusate (100 microliters) was removed for direct colony count; the remaining perfusate was mixed with an equal volume of BHI and incubated overnight. A 100 microliters aliquot of BHI-BSG mixture was sampled the next day. No bacteria were cultured from either the perfusate or BHI-BSG mixture. RESULTS: Eight hours after contamination, as long as the fluid in the catheter was static, no bacteria were detected more than 13 inches (32.5 cm) from the contaminated end of catheters filled with BHI and no more than 8 inches (20 cm) from the end of those filled with fentanyl solution. This finding was not affected by incubation of the catheter in the vertical position. Fluid displacement less than 8 inches (20 cm) had no effect on dissemination, but when fluid was displaced 13 inches (32.5 cm), bacteria were found at the end of the catheter, 35 inches (87.5 cm) away. No bacteria were recovered from the perfusate of reconnected catheters after the catheters were cleaned with betadine and cut with a sterile instrument. CONCLUSIONS: There may be an area distal to the disconnected end of an epidural catheter where its interior remains sterile for at least 8 hr. Such an area exists only when the fluid in the catheter remains static. Furthermore, the exterior of the catheter can be adequately cleaned to prevent bacteria from entering the catheter when reconnected at that point.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 1300217; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0003-3022; 0003-3022</sn>
<ad>Department of Anesthesiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0254, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8873560</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8873560</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>324</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Growth-Characteristics of Staphylococcus-Aureus in Propofol and Intralipid</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1073</sp>
<op>A1073</op>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. S</no>
<sn>0003-3022</sn>
<an>A1995RX68501073</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>323</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Time to Reevaluate Routine 24-Hr Syringe Discard Policy in the Operating-Room</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1037</sp>
<op>A1037</op>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. S</no>
<sn>0003-3022</sn>
<an>A1995RX68501037</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>377</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Epidural Catheter Contamination: Effect of Catheter Position and Meniscus on Extent of Contamination</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology (Hagerstown)</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1041</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199243121912; CT: , , , ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF ANESTHESIOLOGISTS NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USAOCTOBER 17-21, 1992. ANESTHESIOLOGY.</no>
<t2>ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF ANESTHESIOLOGISTS</t2>
<ed>NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA</ed>
<sn>0003-3022 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>376</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<t1>Epidural Catheter Disconnection:  Extent of Contamination</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology (Hagerstown)</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>77</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1055</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199243121926; CT: ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF ANESTHESIOLOGISTS, NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA, OCTOBER 17-21, 1992. ANESTHESIOLOGY.</no>
<t2>ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF ANESTHESIOLOGISTS,</t2>
<ed>NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA</ed>
<sn>0003-3022 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>327</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<a1>Bjoraker,D. G.</a1>
<t1>Propofol - Potentiation of Infections</t1>
<jf>Anesthesiology</jf>
<jo>Anesthesiology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>3A</is>
<sp>A1098</sp>
<no>PT: J; SU: Suppl. S</no>
<sn>0003-3022</sn>
<an>A1993LY10801094</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>369</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<a1>Langevin,S. O.</a1>
<t1>A re-evaluation of the growth rate of Staphylococcus aureus in propofol and intralipid: Implications on infection</t1>
<jf>Anesthesia and Analgesia</jf>
<jo>Anesth.Analg.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>80</vo>
<is>2 SUPPL.</is>
<sp>S263</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598164420; CT: 69th Clinical and Scientific Congress of the International Anesthesia Research Society; CL: Honolulu, Hawaii; CY: March 10-14, 1995</no>
<sn>0003-2999 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>326</id>
<a1>Langevin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gravenstein,N.</a1>
<a1>Woods,C.</a1>
<t1>Propofol and Intralipid - Poor Growth Media but Potent Mediators of Infection</t1>
<jf>Faseb Journal</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>MAR 18</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>A737</sp>
<op>A737</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0892-6638</sn>
<an>A1994ND19700883</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>281</id>
<a1>Lian,W.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Badrane,H.</a1>
<a1>Tan,W.</a1>
<a1>Wu,D.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Lim,D. V.</a1>
<a1>Jin,S.</a1>
<t1>Ultrasensitive detection of biomolecules with fluorescent dye-doped nanoparticles</t1>
<jf>Analytical Biochemistry</jf>
<jo>Anal.Biochem.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov 1</fd>
<vo>334</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>135</sp>
<op>144</op>
<k1>Fluorescent Dyes</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Luminescent Measurements</k1>
<k1>Molecular Probe Techniques</k1>
<k1>Nanostructures/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Protein Array Analysis</k1>
<k1>Silicon Dioxide</k1>
<ab>Fluorescent-labeled molecules have been used extensively for a wide range of applications in biological detection and diagnosis. A new form of highly luminescent and photostable nanoparticles was generated by doping the fluorescent dye tris(2&amp;#39;2-bipyridyl)dichlororuthenium(II)hexahydrate (Rubpy) inside silica material. Because thousands of fluorescent dye molecules are encapsulated in the silica matrix that also serves to protect Rubpy dye from photodamaging oxidation, the Rubpy-dye-doped nanoparticles are extremely bright and photostable. We have used these nanoparticles successfully in various fluorescence labeling techniques, including fluorescent-linked immunosorbent assay, immunocytochemistry, immunohistochemistry, DNA microarray, and protein microarray. By combining the high-intensity luminescent nanoparticles with the specificity of antibody-mediated recognition, ultrasensitive target detection has been achieved. In all cases, assay results clearly demonstrated the superiority of the nanoparticles over organic fluorescent dye molecules and quantum dots in probe labeling for sensitive target detection. These results demonstrate the potential to apply these newly developed fluorescent nanoparticles in various biodetection systems.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: K01 DK02947/DK/NIDDK NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0370535; 0 (Fluorescent Dyes); 7631-86-9 (Silicon Dioxide); 2004/05/11 [received]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0003-2697; 0003-2697</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15464962; S0003-2697(04)00655-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.ab.2004.08.005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15464962</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1335</id>
<a1>Little CS</a1>
<a1>Martin JL</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<t1>Isolation of phage display scFv antibodies to giardia lamblia cysts.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<sp>192/AA</sp>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>333</id>
<a1>Martin,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of genetic tools and microtiter-based phage typing in analyzing the ability of bacteriophage to clear oysters of Vibrio vulnificus contamination</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>2005</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>618</sp>
<op>619</op>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800238480; CT: 105th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, GA, USA; CY: June 05 -09, 2005; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>347</id>
<a1>Martin,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Duckworth,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of bacteriophages to reduce Vibrio vulnificus in experimentally and naturally infected oysters (Crassostrea virginica)</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>2004</fd>
<vo>104</vo>
<sp>396</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200700325013; CT: 104th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: New Orleans, LA, USA; CY: May 23 -27, 2004; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>286</id>
<a1>Matsui,H.</a1>
<a1>Bacot,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Garlington,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Roberts,S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Virulence plasmid-borne spvB and spvC genes can replace the 90-kilobase plasmid in conferring virulence to Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium in subcutaneously inoculated mice</t1>
<jf>Journal of Bacteriology</jf>
<jo>J.Bacteriol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>183</vo>
<is>15</is>
<sp>4652</sp>
<op>4658</op>
<k1>ADP Ribose Transferases/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Codon, Initiator</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial/physiology</k1>
<k1>Injections, Subcutaneous</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors</k1>
<ab>In a mouse model of systemic infection, the spv genes carried on the Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium virulence plasmid increase the replication rate of salmonellae in host cells of the reticuloendothelial system, most likely within macrophages. A nonpolar deletion in the spvB gene greatly decreased virulence but could not be complemented by spvB alone. However, a low-copy-number plasmid expressing spvBC from a constitutive lacUV5 promoter did complement the spvB deletion. By examining a series of spv mutations and cloned spv sequences, we deduced that spvB and spvC could be sufficient to confer plasmid-mediated virulence to S. enterica serovar Typhimurium. The spvBC-bearing plasmid was capable of replacing all of the spv genes, as well as the entire virulence plasmid, of serovar Typhimurium for causing systemic infection in BALB/c mice after subcutaneous, but not oral, inoculation. A point mutation in the spvBC plasmid preventing translation but not transcription of spvC eliminated the ability of the plasmid to confer virulence. Therefore, it appears that both spvB and spvC encode the principal effector factors for Spv- and plasmid-mediated virulence of serovar Typhimurium.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI24821/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985120R; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Codon, Initiator); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (Virulence Factors); EC 2.4.2.- (ADP Ribose Transferases); EC 2.4.2.- (spvB protein, Salmonella enterica virulence plasmid); OID: NLM: PMC95362; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9193; 0021-9193</sn>
<ad>Laboratory of Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Center for Basic Research, The Kitasato Institute, Tokyo, Japan.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11443102</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JB.183.15.4652-4658.2001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11443102</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC95362</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>290</id>
<a1>Matsui,H.</a1>
<a1>Kawakami,T.</a1>
<a1>Ishikawa,S.</a1>
<a1>Danbara,H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Constitutively expressed phoP inhibits mouse-virulence of Salmonella typhimurium in an Spv-dependent manner</t1>
<jf>Microbiology and immunology</jf>
<jo>Microbiol.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>447</sp>
<op>454</op>
<k1>ADP Ribose Transferases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Administration, Oral</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Injections, Subcutaneous</k1>
<k1>Lac Operon</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Spleen/cytology</k1>
<k1>Stem Cells/cytology</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors</k1>
<ab>In Salmonella typhimurium, the transcription of several virulence genes including spvB is regulated by the PhoP/PhoQ regulatory system. To further examine the relationship between the PhoP/PhoQ and Spv systems for virulence in mice, we examined a non-polar phoP mutation combined with different virulence plasmid genotypes for effects on virulence of S. typhimurium in the mouse model. PhoP-/Spv+ and PhoP-/Spv- mutants were not detectably recovered from the spleens of subcutaneously or orally inoculated mice. The phoP gene constitutively expressed from the lacZ promoter of a low copy number vector (phoP(C)) only partially complemented the non-polar phoP mutation for mouse-virulence in both the Spv+ and Spv- backgrounds; both PhoP(C) strains exhibited virulence equal only to a PhoP+/Spv- strain. Interestingly, in a PhoP+ background, the phoP(C) gene reduced splenic infection of the Spv+ but not Spv- salmonellae after subcutaneous or oral inoculation compared with the PhoP+ parents. Additionally, the phoP(C) gene in an Spv+ background reduced the net growth of salmonellae in macrophages in vitro; phoP(C) in an Spv- background was without effect. These data suggest that the constitutive expression of the phoP gene attenuates the virulence of S. typhimurium in mice in an Spv-dependent manner.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI28421/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7703966; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Virulence Factors); 125360-99-8 (PhoP protein, Bacteria); EC 2.4.2.- (ADP Ribose Transferases); EC 2.4.2.- (spvB protein, Salmonella enterica virulence plasmid); ppublish</no>
<pp>JAPAN</pp>
<sn>0385-5600; 0385-5600</sn>
<ad>Laboratory of Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Center for Basic Research, The Kitasato Institute, Tokyo, Japan. matsui-h@kitasato.or.jp</ad>
<an>PMID: 10941927</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10941927</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>368</id>
<a1>Matsui,Hidenori</a1>
<a1>Doyle,Thomas J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>IFN- and TNF- suppress the growth of wild-type but not virulence plasmid-cured Salmonella typhimurium in orally inoculated mice.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>95</vo>
<sp>185</sp>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>371</id>
<a1>Matsui,Hidenori</a1>
<a1>Doyle,Thomas</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of host cells responsible for increased intracellular growth rate by virulence plasmid-containing Salmonella typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<sp>86</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497343555; CT: 94th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Las Vegas, Nevada, USA; CY: May 23-27, 1994</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>365</id>
<a1>Matsui,Hidenori</a1>
<a1>Kawahara,Kazuyoshi</a1>
<a1>Suzuki,Asami</a1>
<a1>Sekiya,Kachiko</a1>
<a1>Danbara,Hirofumi</a1>
<a1>Bacot,Christopher M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>The spvB and spvC genes of the 90-kb Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid can replace the entire plasmid to restore virulence after subcutaneous but not oral inoculation of mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>1997</fd>
<vo>97</vo>
<sp>77</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199799581217; CT: 97th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Miami Beach, Florida, USA; CY: May 4-8, 1997</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>343</id>
<a1>Messer,H. G.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Detection of Listeria monocytogenes using phage display scFv proteins recognizing auto and flagella</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>2007</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<sp>516</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800190084; CT: 107th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Toronto, CANADA; CY: 2007,; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>335</id>
<a1>Messer,H. G.</a1>
<a1>Moose,R. E.</a1>
<a1>Sapparapu,G.</a1>
<a1>Ferrara,J. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Phage display scFv antibodies recognizing flagella to detect bacterial pathogens</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>2005</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>231</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800236677; CT: 105th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, GA, USA; CY: June 05 -09, 2005; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1334</id>
<a1>Morey TE</a1>
<a1>Modell JH</a1>
<a1>Gulig P</a1>
<a1>Mittel A</a1>
<a1>Dennis DM.</a1>
<t1>Microbial growth in propofol micro- and macro-emulsions.</t1>
<jf>Annual Meeting of the American Society of Anesthsiologists</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<sp>A386</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1242</id>
<a1>Murphy TV</a1>
<a1>McCracken GH,Jr</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Hansen EJ.</a1>
<t1>Failure of rifampin prophylaxis to prevent Haemophilus influenzae type b disease in a day care center</t1>
<jf>Twenty-second Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy.</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<is>Abstract No 725</is>
<sp>193</sp>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>315</id>
<a1>Murphy,T. V.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Moore,B. S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Haemophilus influenzae type b disease after rifampin prophylaxis in a day care center: possible reasons for its failure</t1>
<jf>Pediatric infectious disease</jf>
<jo>Pediatr.Infect.Dis.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>May-Jun</fd>
<vo>2</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>193</sp>
<op>198</op>
<k1>Child Day Care Centers</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Disease Outbreaks/epidemiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus Infections/epidemiology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<k1>Microbial Sensitivity Tests</k1>
<k1>Pharynx/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Premedication</k1>
<k1>Public Health Administration</k1>
<k1>Rifampin/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Texas</k1>
<ab>Five infants enrolled in a day care center (DCC) developed invasive disease due to Haemophilus influenzae type b during a 25-week period. The isolates from four patients had identical outer membrane proteins and were biotype 1. Although rifampin prophylaxis was recommended on two different occasions, retrospective surveys demonstrated that 39 and 60%, respectively, of infants failed to receive the agent for various reasons. Pharyngeal cultures were obtained from infants, their families and DCC staff after prophylaxis was given the second time. Forty-seven % of DCC infants had positive cultures, and 59% of their households had at least one carrier of the invasive strain. Rifampin prophylaxis administered a third time to infants and members of their households was unsuccessful in eradicating the invasive Haemophilus influenzae type b strain from DCC infants. The possible reasons for failure of rifampin in this DCC outbreak included incomplete understanding by physicians and health department officials of the factors affecting a DCC outbreak of Haemophilus influenzae type b disease and failure properly to implement rifampin prophylaxis to all contacts and the index cases.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8209468; 13292-46-1 (Rifampin); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0277-9730; 0277-9730</sn>
<an>PMID: 6602974</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6602974</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>322</id>
<a1>Neu,J.</a1>
<a1>DeMarco,V.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Bacterial translocation is exacerbated by inhibition of sphlanchnic glutamine synthetase</t1>
<jf>Pediatric research</jf>
<jo>Pediatr.Res.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1729</sp>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 2 Suppl. S</no>
<sn>0031-3998</sn>
<an>000086155301727</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>360</id>
<a1>Neu,Josef</a1>
<a1>DeMarco,Vincent G.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Bacterial translocation is exacerbated by inhibition of sphlanchnic glutamine synthetase</t1>
<jf>Pediatric research</jf>
<jo>Pediatr.Res.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>April, 2000</fd>
<vo>47</vo>
<is>4 Part 2</is>
<sp>293A</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200000197586&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: Joint Meeting of the Pediatric Academic Societies and the American Academy of Pediatrics.; CL: Boston, Massachusetts, USA; CY: May 12-16, 2000; SP: American Academy of Pediatrics; American Pediatric Society; Society for Pediatric Research</no>
<sn>0031-3998 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>321</id>
<a1>Parikh,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Clare-Salzler,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Southwick,F. S.</a1>
<t1>Loss of the actin filament capping protein CapG increases susceptibility to Listeria monocytogenes, but not Salmonella typhimurium infection.</t1>
<jf>Blood</jf>
<jo>Blood</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>NOV 16</fd>
<vo>100</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1771</sp>
<no>PT: J; PN: Part 1</no>
<sn>0006-4971</sn>
<an>000179184701772</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>282</id>
<a1>Parikh,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Clare-Salzler,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Li,W.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Southwick,F. S.</a1>
<t1>CapG(-/-) mice have specific host defense defects that render them more susceptible than CapG(+/+) mice to Listeria monocytogenes infection but not to Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium infection</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>6582</sp>
<op>6590</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Chemotaxis, Leukocyte</k1>
<k1>Disease Susceptibility</k1>
<k1>Flow Cytometry</k1>
<k1>Lethal Dose 50</k1>
<k1>Listeria Infections/immunology</k1>
<k1>Liver/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Macrophages/immunology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Microfilament Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Neutrophils/immunology</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Phagocytosis</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium</k1>
<k1>Spleen/microbiology</k1>
<ab>Loss of the actin filament capping protein CapG has no apparent effect on the phenotype of mice maintained under sterile conditions; however, bone marrow-derived macrophages from CapG(-/-) mice exhibited distinct motility defects. We examined the ability of CapG(-/-) mice to clear two intracellular bacteria, Listeria monocytogenes and Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium. The 50% lethal dose of Listeria was 10-fold lower for CapG(-/-) mice than for CapG(+/+) mice (6 x 10(3) CFU for CapG(-/-) mice and 6 x 10(4) CFU for CapG(+/+) mice), while no difference was observed for Salmonella: The numbers of Listeria cells in the spleens and livers were significantly higher in CapG(-/-) mice than in CapG(+/+) mice at days 5 to 9, while the bacterial counts were identical on day 5 for Salmonella-infected mice. Microscopic analysis revealed qualitatively similar inflammatory responses in the spleens and livers of the two types of mice. Specific immunofluorescence staining analyzed by fluorescence-activated cell sorting revealed similar numbers of macrophages and dendritic cells in infected CapG(-/-) and CapG(+/+) spleens. However, analysis of bone marrow-derived macrophages revealed a 50% reduction in the rate of phagocytosis of Listeria in CapG(-/-) cells but a normal rate of phagocytosis of Salmonella: Stimulation of bone marrow-derived dendritic cells with granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor resulted in a reduction in the ruffling response of CapG(-/-) cells compared to the response of CapG(+/+) cells, and CapG(-/-) bone-marrowed derived neutrophils migrated at a mean speed that was nearly 50% lower than the mean speed of CapG(+/+) neutrophils. Our findings suggest that specific motility deficits in macrophages, dendritic cells, and neutrophils render CapG(-/-) mice more susceptible than CapG(+/+) mice to Listeria infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 AI-23262/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI-34276/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Microfilament Proteins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 136896-19-0 (Capg protein, mouse); OID: NLM: PMC219612; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14573680</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14573680</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC219612</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>352</id>
<a1>Parikh,S. S.</a1>
<a1>Litherland,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Clare-Salzler,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Li,W.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Southwick,F. S.</a1>
<t1>Loss of the actin filament capping protein CapG increases susceptibility to Listeria monocytogenes, but not Salmonella typhimurium.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<sp>B</sp>
<op>185</op>
<ab>Loss of the actin filament capping protein CapG has no apparent effect on the phenotype of mice maintained under sterile conditions; however CapG null bone marrow macrophages demonstrate distinct motility defects. We have examined the ability of CapG-/- mice to clear two intracellular bacteria, Listeria monocytogenes, which is internalized by receptor-mediated phagocytosis, and Salmonella typhimurium which injects bacterial proteins into host cells to induce ingestion. The intravenous LD50 for Listeria is 10 fold lower in CapG-/- mice as compared to CapG+/+ (6X103 for CapG-/- vs. 6X104 organisms for CapG+/+); while no difference was observed for Salmonella (Intraperitoneal LD50 2X106 for wild type and CapG null animals). L. monocytogenes concentrations in the spleen and liver were over 10-fold higher in CapG-/- as compared to CapG+/+ by day 5 and were approximately 1000-fold by day 9. Organ counts were identical at day 5 for S. typhimurium-infected mice. Microscopic analysis revealed no significant differences in numbers and types of cells infiltrating the spleen or liver, and FACS analysis of splenic cells using antibodies specific to leukocytes markers revealed similar numbers of T lymphocytes, B lymphocytes, macrophages, dendritic cells and granulocytes in CapG-/- and CapG+/+ spleens. However, analysis of bone marrow-derived macrophages demonstrated a 50% reduction in the phagocytic rate of L. monocytogenes in CapG-/- cells but a normal phagocytic rate for salmonellae. Stimulation of bone marrow derived dendritic cells with GMCSF demonstrated a reduction in the ruffling response of CapG-/- as compared to CapG+/+ cells. Conclusions: Our findings suggest that specific motility defects in macrophages and dendritic cells, rather than reduced numbers of phagocytic cells, render CapG-/- mice more susceptible to infection with L. monocytogenes. The ability of S. typhimurium to bypass receptor-mediated phagocytosis may explain its lack of increased virulence in the CapG-/- mouse. Our findings should encourage clinicians to consider the possibility of CapG deficiency in human patients with unexplained Listeriosis.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300519912&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 103rd American Society for Microbiology General Meeting; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: May 18-22, 2003; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1234</id>
<a1>Patrick,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Hall,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Fritz E.H.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Hansen E.H.</a1>
<t1>Haemophilus influenzae type b can sythesize two antgenically distinct lipooligosaccharides.</t1>
<jf>Twenty-Sixth Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</jf>
<yr>1986</yr>
<vo>no. 863</vo>
<sp>256</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>305</id>
<a1>Patrick,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Pelzel,S. E.</a1>
<a1>Miller,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Haanes-Fritz,E.</a1>
<a1>Radolf,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>McCracken,G. H.,Jr</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Antigenic evidence for simultaneous expression of two different lipooligosaccharides by some strains of Haemophilus influenzae type b</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1971</sp>
<op>1978</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites, Antibody</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Lipopolysaccharides/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Oligosaccharides/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Precipitin Tests</k1>
<k1>Radioimmunoassay</k1>
<ab>Isolates of Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) can be divided into three antigenic groups based on their reactivities with a set of two monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) directed against epitopes in the oligosaccharide region of Hib lipooligosaccharide (LOS) (P. A. Gulig, C. C. Patrick, L. Hermanstorfer, G. H. McCracken, Jr., and E. J. Hansen, Infect. Immun. 55:513-520, 1987). Approximately 24% of Hib strains react with both of these LOS-specific MAbs. Immunoprecipitation experiments involving several of these strains indicated that the epitopes recognized by these MAbs resided in two different LOS molecules, both of which were synthesized by these particular Hib strains. In addition, Western blot (immunoblot) analysis of proteinase K-treated cell extracts of these strains that had been subjected to sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gradient gel electrophoresis revealed two different LOS staining patterns when they were probed independently with the two MAbs. Colony blot radioimmunoassay of hundreds of colonies of one of these Hib strains showed that each colony bound both MAbs. Immune electron microscopy confirmed that individual cells of this same Hib strain expressed both types of LOS molecule at the same time. An antibody accessibility radioimmunoassay was used to show that different Hib strains of this type varied in the relative amounts of each of the two MAbs that they could bind to their cell surfaces. These findings indicate that some Hib strains can synthesize two antigenically distinct LOS molecules simultaneously.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AL-17621/PHS HHS/United States; GR: HD-22766/HD/NICHD NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Bacterial); 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Binding Sites, Antibody); 0 (Lipopolysaccharides); 0 (Oligosaccharides); 0 (lipid-linked oligosaccharides); OID: NLM: PMC313829; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, University of Texas, Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas 75235.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2786504</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2786504</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC313829</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>304</id>
<a1>Poppe,C.</a1>
<a1>Curtiss,R.,3rd</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Gyles,C. L.</a1>
<t1>Hybridization studies with a DNA probe derived from the virulence region of the 60 Mdal plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium</t1>
<jf>Canadian journal of veterinary research = Revue canadienne de recherche veterinaire</jf>
<jo>Can.J.Vet.Res.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>53</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>378</sp>
<op>384</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA Probes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Plasmid DNA of 68 strains of Salmonella that belonged to 18 serovars and exhibited 48 different plasmid profiles was examined for hybridization with a 32P-labelled DNA probe which consisted of a 3750 base pairs (bp) HindIII-HindIII fragment derived from the virulence region of the 60 megadalton (Mdal) plasmid of Salmonella typhimurium. The 32 Mdal plasmid of S. cholerae-suis, the 50 Mdal plasmid of S. dublin, the 36 Mdal plasmid of S. enteritidis, the 60 Mdal plasmid of S. gallinarum, the 60 Mdal plasmid of S. pullorum, and the 60 Mdal plasmid of S. typhimurium, plasmids that have been associated with virulence, all hybridized with the probe. Digestion of plasmid DNA of these strains with PvuII and hybridization with the probe revealed that the plasmids of strains of all six serovars contained fragments of approximately 2520 and 1520 bp that hybridized with the probe. Similarly, hybridization with BglI digests of DNA of the virulence-associated plasmids of strains of these six serovars showed that all six plasmids contained a fragment of approximately 3690 bp that hybridized with the probe. No other plasmids of these strains nor any plasmids of 12 other Salmonella serovars hybridized with the probe. Chromosomal DNA did not hybridize with the probe. The 60 Mdal plasmids of S. gallinarum and S. pullorum showed similar digestion patterns with restriction endonucleases BglI, BglII and PvuII.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 8607793; 0 (DNA Probes); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); OID: NLM: PMC1255562; ppublish</no>
<pp>CANADA</pp>
<sn>0830-9000; 0830-9000</sn>
<ad>Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Immunology, Ontario Veterinary College, University of Guelph.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2686827</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2686827</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1255562</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>317</id>
<a1>Robertson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,C. F.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Kettman,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Johnston,K. H.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Monoclonal antibodies directed against a cell surface-exposed outer membrane protein of Haemophilus influenzae type b</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>80</sp>
<op>88</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/analysis</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Bacterial/immunology</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>Epitopes</k1>
<k1>Haemophilus influenzae/immunology</k1>
<k1>Hybridomas</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin G</k1>
<k1>Immunoglobulin M</k1>
<k1>Membrane Proteins/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>Monoclonal antibodies directed against several different Haemophilus influenzae type b outer membrane proteins with apparent molecular weights of 45,000, 39,000, and 37,000 were identified by a radioimmunoprecipitation method. Five monoclonal antibodies, including both immunoglobulin G and M isotypes, were specific for the same H. influenzae type b major outer membrane protein (39,000 molecular weight). One of these immunoglobulin G monoclonal antibodies (6A2) was shown to be directed against a cell surface-exposed antigenic determinant of the 39,000-molecular-weight protein, whereas the other monoclonal antibodies directed against this same protein were apparently specific for antigenic determinants not exposed on the H. Influenzae type b cell surface. The cell surface-exposed protein antigenic determinant recognized by monoclonal antibody 6A2 was not unique to the H. influenzae type b strain used as the source of outer membrane vesicles for generating immune spleen cells, but was found in a majority of independently isolated strains of H. influenzae type b. These data indicate that there is antigenic cross-reactivity among H. influenzae type b strains with regard to cell surface-exposed proteins.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-17012/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-17621/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: NIH 1-PO1-CA-23115/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antigens, Bacterial); 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Epitopes); 0 (Immunoglobulin G); 0 (Immunoglobulin M); 0 (Membrane Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC351187; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<an>PMID: 6176548</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6176548</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC351187</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>394</id>
<a1>Robertson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,C. F.</a1>
<a1>Wischkaemper,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Kettman,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Hansen,E. J.</a1>
<t1>Restricted Murine Mono Clonal Antibody Response to Haemophilus-Influenzae Type B Outer Membrane</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>82</vo>
<sp>ABSTRACT E37</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV198223049416; CT: 82ND ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, ATLANTA, GA., USA, MARCH 7-12, 1982. ABSTR ANNU MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>0094-8519 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1246</id>
<a1>Rogers JA</a1>
<a1>Doyle TJ</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<t1>spvA of the Samonella typhimurium virulence plasmid is induced intracellularly in J774.1 cells.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>93</vo>
<sp>40</sp>
<op>Abstract B78</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>379</id>
<a1>Rogers,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Chiodo,V. A.</a1>
<a1>Schreck,S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Virulence Genes of the Salmonella-Typhimurium Virulence Plasmid are Regulated in Spvr-Dependent and Spvr-Independent Manners by Growth Phase Complexity of Growth Medium and Certain Amino Acids</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<vo>92</vo>
<sp>132</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199243047919; CT: 92ND GENERAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR MICROBIOLOGY, NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA, USA, MAY 26-30, 1992. ABSTR GEN MEET AM SOC MICROBIOL.</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>366</id>
<a1>Rogers,Julie A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Involvement of DNA sequences upstream of spvR in regulation of spvR and plasmid-mediated virulence of Salmonella typhimurium in mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>1996</fd>
<vo>96</vo>
<sp>175</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199698815521; CT: 96th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: New Orleans, Louisiana, USA; CY: May 19-23, 1996</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>372</id>
<a1>Rogers,Julie A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>Expression and molecular regulation of the spvR gene of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>1994</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<sp>86</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199497343553; CT: 94th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Las Vegas, Nevada, USA; CY: May 23-27, 1994</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>367</id>
<a1>Rogers,Julie A.</a1>
<a1>Matsui,Hidenori</a1>
<a1>Gulig,Paul A.</a1>
<t1>SpvA of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid can act as a transcriptional repressor of spvR and is not essential for virulence in orally inoculated mice</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>1995</fd>
<vo>95</vo>
<sp>218</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV199598304871; CT: 95th General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Washington, D.C., USA; CY: May 21-25, 1995</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1245</id>
<a1>Rubino S</a1>
<a1>Rizzu P</a1>
<a1>Erre G</a1>
<a1>Colombo M</a1>
<a1>Leori G</a1>
<a1>Gulig P</a1>
<a1>Doyle TJ</a1>
<a1>Pisano M</a1>
<a1>Uzzau S</a1>
<a1>Cappuccinelli P.</a1>
<t1>Mechanisms of pathogenicity in Salmonella abortusovis and construction of protective mutants.</t1>
<yr>1992</yr>
<k1>presentation</k1>
<t2>Salmonella and Salmonellosis</t2>
<ed>Ploufragan/St. Brieuc, France</ed>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>356</id>
<a1>Smith,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Depaola,A.</a1>
<a1>Wright,A. C.</a1>
<t1>Use of bacteriophage for elimination of Vibrio vulnificus from oysters</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>2001</fd>
<vo>101</vo>
<sp>570</sp>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus causes rapidly fatal human infections associated with consumption of raw oysters. Bacteriophages specific for this bacterium are also indigenous to oysters (Crassostrea virginica) collected from estuaries in the Gulf of Mexico. Recent studies demonstrated that these phages are able to prevent death in mice inoculated with lethal doses of V. vulnificus MO6-24. Thus, lysis of host strains and subsequent reduction of the bacterial numbers during infection appears to be protective in animal models. We have exploited this phage-host interaction for the purpose of reducing the V. vulnificus numbers in oysters. In these studies, uptake of the host V. vulnificus strain (MO6-24/O) and the phage (153A-5) was achieved through natural filtration by oysters incubated in artificial seawater (ASW) at room temperature. Oysters (n=5) were incubated for 18 hours with either ASW alone, ASW+phage, ASW+bacteria, ASW+bacteria+phage, or ASW+bacteria+heat inactivated phage. A bacterial concentration of about 107 CFU/ml and phage concentration of 3X108 PFU/ml were used for inoculations. Surviving bacteria were enumerated by standard plate counts of the water and oyster homogenates on TCBS or L agar. Colony lift hybridization was used to quantitate V. vulnificus using the species-specific gene probe, VVAP, which is derived from the vvh gene. A greater than 2 log reduction (99.8% of total bacteria) was observed in oyster receiving bacteria+phage in comparison to those treated with bacteria+heat inactivated phage. A similar reduction in the numbers of V. vulnificus was also observed in oysters receiving bacteria+phage. The procedure offers a potential method for reduction of V. vulnificus in oysters with applications to the seafood industry for the production of a safer product.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200200233536&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 101st General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 20-24, 2001; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>277</id>
<a1>Srivastava,M.</a1>
<a1>Tucker,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Wright,A. C.</a1>
<t1>Phase variation, capsular polysaccharide, pilus and flagella contribute to uptake of Vibrio vulnificus by the Eastern oyster (Crassostrea virginica)</t1>
<jf>Environmental microbiology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>1934</sp>
<op>1944</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacterial Capsules/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Crassostrea/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Fimbriae, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Flagella/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Seawater/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence Factors/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/physiology</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus infections are associated with raw oyster consumption, and disease reservoirs are determined by the ability of this bacterium to infect and persist in oysters. Surface structures, such as capsular polysaccharide (CPS), pili and flagella, function as virulence factors in mouse infection models. Furthermore, virulence is related to phase variation in colony morphology, which reflects CPS expression and includes opaque (encapsulated, virulent), translucent (reduced encapsulation, avirulent) and rugose (wrinkled, biofilm-enhanced) colony types. The role of these factors in environmental survival is unknown; therefore, mutational analysis and phase variation of V. vulnificus were examined in an oyster infection model. Oysters (Crassostrea virginica) were pre-treated with tetracycline to reduce background bacteria and subsequently inoculated via filter feeding with 10(6) colony-forming units (cfu) ml(-1) of V. vulnificus wild-type strains and phase variants, as well as strains with deletion mutations in genes related to CPS (Delta wza), pili (Delta pilA), flagella (Delta flaCDE/Delta flaFBA) and motility (Delta motAB). All mutants were significantly reduced in their dissemination to oyster haemolymph as compared with wild type; however, recovery of mutants from gills and intestinal tissue was generally similar to wild type. Translucent and rugose inocula showed induction of high-frequency phase variation to the opaque encapsulated phenotype (100% and 72% respectively) during oyster infections that did not occur in strains recovered from seawater. Thus, multiple bacterial factors determine uptake of V. vulnificus in oysters, and phase variation during oyster infection is a likely mechanism for environmental survival and for induction of the more virulent phenotype.</ab>
<no>JID: 100883692; 0 (Bacterial Capsules); 0 (Virulence Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1462-2920; 1462-2912</sn>
<ad>Food Science and Human Nutrition, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19689704; EMI1916 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.01916.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19689704</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>351</id>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>A marker plasmid system for differentiation of replication and death of virulent and attenuated strains of Vibrio vulnificus in iron dextran-treated mice.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>2003</fd>
<vo>103</vo>
<sp>B</sp>
<op>297</op>
<ab>An important question in the study of bacterial pathogenesis is if differences among strains in recovery of bacteria from infected animals are due to differential rates of growth versus killing in the host. We developed a marker plasmid to examine this question using the suicide vector pUT-Km2, which encodes kanamycin resistance. Because the pir gene is expressed from the pBAD promoter, the engineered marker plasmid requires arabinose to enable its replication in bacteria. As the bacteria replicate in the absence of arabinose, the marker plasmid does not replicate and segregates from the bacterial population with exponential kinetics. By determining the proportion of marker plasmid-containing bacteria recovered from animals, based on plating on selective and non-selective media, we measured the in vivo growth rate. By determining the number of recovered versus inoculated marker plasmids, we examined killing. Using an iron dextran-treated mouse model, we determined that virulent, clinical and attenuated, environmental isolates had similar in vivo growth rates but differed in that the environmental strains were 7 to 100 fold more susceptible to killing by the host. Consistent with this result, cyclophosphamide treatment of mice to deplete neutrophils enabled the attenuated, environmental strains to exhibit wild-type virulence. In the absence of iron treatment of mice, both clinical strains replicated more slowly, and one of them was killed 100-fold more relative to infection of iron-treated mice. We also determined that the majority of growth of the bacteria and killing by the host occurs within the first four hours of infection as compared to long term 12 to 15 h infections. We calculated the in vivo doubling times of both clinical and environmental strains to be approximately 16 minutes. We believe that this marker plasmid system is not only useful for examining the in vivo growth rate and susceptibility to host defenses of V. vulnificus, but other gram-negative bacteria as well.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200300520023&lt;br&gt;ME: cd-rom; CT: 103rd American Society for Microbiology General Meeting; CL: Washington, DC, USA; CY: May 18-22, 2003; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 (ISSN print) ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>279</id>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of a marker plasmid to examine differential rates of growth and death between clinical and environmental strains of Vibrio vulnificus in experimentally infected mice</t1>
<jf>Molecular microbiology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Microbiol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>61</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>310</sp>
<op>323</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Proliferation</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Environment</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Genetic Markers</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Iron/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Iron-Dextran Complex/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Skin/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/drug therapy/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio vulnificus/drug effects/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is Gram-negative bacterium that contaminates oysters, causing highly lethal sepsis after consumption of raw oysters and wound infection. We previously described two sets of V. vulnificus strains with different levels of virulence in subcutaneously inoculated iron dextran-treated mice. Both virulent, clinical strains and attenuated, environmental strains could be recovered in high numbers from skin lesions and livers; however, the attenuated environmental strains required significantly higher numbers of colony-forming units (cfu) in the inoculum to produce lethal infection. Using some of these strains and an additional clinical strain, we presently asked if the different abilities to cause infection between the clinical and environmental strains were due to differences in rates of growth or death of the bacteria in the mouse host. We therefore constructed a marker plasmid, pGTR902, that functions as a replicon only in the presence of arabinose, which is not present in significant levels in animal tissues. V. vulnificus strains containing pGTR902 were inoculated into iron dextran-treated and untreated mice. Measuring the proportion of bacteria that had maintained the marker plasmid recovered from mice enabled us to monitor the number of in vivo divisions, hence growth rate; whereas measuring the number of marker plasmid-containing bacteria recovered enabled the measurement of death of the vibrios in the mice. The numbers of bacterial divisions in vivo for all of the strains over a 12-15 h infection period were not significantly different in iron dextran-treated mice; however, the rate of death of one environmental strain was significantly higher compared with the clinical strains. Infection of non-iron dextran-treated mice with clinical strains demonstrated that the greatest effect of iron dextran-treatment was increased growth rate, while one clinical strain also experienced increased death in untreated mice. V. vulnificus inoculated into iron dextran-treated mice replicated extremely rapidly over the first 4 h of infection with doubling times of approximately 15-28 min. In contrast, one of the environmental strains exhibited a reduced early growth rate. These results demonstrate that differences in virulence among naturally occurring V. vulnificus can be explained by diverse abilities to replicate rapidly in or resist defences of the host. The marker plasmid pGTR902 should be useful for examining virulence of bacteria in terms of differentiating growth verses death in animal hosts for most Gram-negative bacteria.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: R01-AI1056056-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8712028; 0 (Genetic Markers); 7439-89-6 (Iron); 9004-66-4 (Iron-Dextran Complex); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0950-382X; 0950-382X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16856938; MMI5227 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05227.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16856938</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>355</id>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Use of in vivo selection for virulence to identify genomic sequences associated with virulence of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>2002</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<sp>56</sp>
<ab>Diseases caused by Vibrio vulnificus result from consumption of seafood (primary sepsis in predisposed individuals) or contact of wounds with seawater (necrotizing fasciitis). Death can occur within 24 hours after contact with the bacteria. We previously characterized the virulence of three clinical and three environmental V. vulnificus isolates using the iron dextran-treated mouse model. The environmental strains could cause disease similar to the clinical strains but required 100 to 1,000 fold higher inocula. Therefore, the differences in pathogenicity between these clinical and environmental strains may be related to growth in the host or susceptibility to host defenses. In this study, we utilized the selective pressure of the iron dextran-treated mouse model to identify from a genomic library of a virulent clinical strain recombinant plasmids that complemented the virulence defect of an environmental strain to result in increased virulence. The genomic library containing Sau3A-generated DNA fragments between 8 and 12 kb was constructed in the plasmid vector pCOS5. This library was moved via conjugation in sets of 200 clones into attenuated, environmental V. vulnificus MLT367. The recombinant MLT367 libraries were inoculated subcutaneously (s.c.) into two iron dextran-treated mice at a sublethal dose. At 40 hours post-inoculation, one mouse exhibited a characteristic s.c. lesion with 8.7 log CFU/g in skin and 5.1 log CFU/g in liver, pGTR600 was the only plasmid recovered from vibrios in the tissues of this mouse. When conjugated back into MLT367, pGTR600 complemented a virulence defect in the environmental strain. Mice infected with MLT367(pGTR600) had higher numbers of bacteria in tissues, larger lesions, and decreased body temperatures than with MLT367(pCOS5). Incomplete DNA sequence analysis of the 8.5 kb insert of pGTR600 has so far revealed two genes encoding homologous proteins of the GGDEF family. We are examining if these genes are involved with virulence. In vivo selection for virulence represents a useful tool to identify virulence genes using naturally occurring attenuated strains with effective animal models.</ab>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200200570970&lt;br&gt;ME: print; CT: 102nd General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology; CL: Salt Lake City, UT, USA; CY: May 19-23, 2002; SP: American Society for Microbiology</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>287</id>
<a1>Starks,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Schoeb,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Tamplin,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Parveen,S.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Bomeisl,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Escudero,G. M.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Pathogenesis of infection by clinical and environmental strains of Vibrio vulnificus in iron-dextran-treated mice</t1>
<jf>Infection and immunity</jf>
<jo>Infect.Immun.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>68</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>5785</sp>
<op>5793</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Iron-Dextran Complex/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Liver/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred ICR</k1>
<k1>Ostreidae/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Seawater/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Skin/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Spleen/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vibrio/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Vibrio Infections/microbiology/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Vibrio vulnificus is an opportunistic pathogen that contaminates oysters harvested from the Gulf of Mexico. In humans with compromising conditions, especially excess levels of iron in plasma and tissues, consumption of contaminated seafood or exposure of wounds to contaminated water can lead to systemic infection and disfiguring skin infection with extremely high mortality. V. vulnificus-associated diseases are noted for the rapid replication of the bacteria in host tissues, with extensive tissue damage. In this study we examined the virulence attributes of three virulent clinical strains and three attenuated oyster or seawater isolates in mouse models of systemic disease. All six V. vulnificus strains caused identical skin lesions in subcutaneously (s.c.) inoculated iron dextran-treated mice in terms of numbers of recovered CFU and histopathology; however, the inocula required for identical frequency and magnitude of infection were at least 350-fold higher for the environmental strains. At lethal doses, all strains caused s. c. skin lesions with extensive edema, necrosis of proximate host cells, vasodilation, and as many as 10(8) CFU/g, especially in perivascular regions. These data suggest that the differences between these clinical and environmental strains may be related to growth in the host or susceptibility to host defenses. In non-iron dextran-treated mice, strains required 10(5)-fold-higher inocula to cause an identical disease process as with iron dextran treatment. These results demonstrate that s.c. inoculation of iron dextran-treated mice is a useful model for studying systemic disease caused by V. vulnificus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0246127; 9004-66-4 (Iron-Dextran Complex); OID: NLM: PMC101538; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0019-9567; 0019-9567</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10992486</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10992486</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC101538</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1337</id>
<a1>Swain RA</a1>
<a1>Jones MK</a1>
<a1>Gulig PA</a1>
<a1>Wright AC.</a1>
<t1>Gac A regulation of iron response in Vibrio vulnificus.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2010</yr>
<sp>322/B</sp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>328</id>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Bourdage,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Evans,M.</a1>
<a1>Wright,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Harwood,V. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Vibrio vulnificus Clade Is Associated with Systemic, as Opposed to Local, Infection in a Mouse Model of Disease</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>2008</fd>
<vo>108</vo>
<sp>103</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200900190594; CT: 108th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Boston, MA, USA; CY: June 01 -05, 2008; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>339</id>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Roles of GGDEF and EAL domains in virulence of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>2006</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<sp>80</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800232979; CT: 106th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 21 -25, 2006; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>337</id>
<a1>Tucker,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Lang,S. -S</a1>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Joseph,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Identification of virulence genes of Vibrio vulnificus using signature-tagged mutagenesis</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>2005</fd>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>67</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800235929; CT: 105th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Atlanta, GA, USA; CY: June 05 -09, 2005; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>340</id>
<a1>Tucker,M. S.</a1>
<a1>Thiaville,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of flagella, motility, and chernotaxis in the pathogenesis of Vibrio vulnificus</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>2006</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<sp>55</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800232862; CT: 106th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Orlando, FL, USA; CY: May 21 -25, 2006; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>289</id>
<a1>Uzzau,S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Paglietti,B.</a1>
<a1>Leori,G.</a1>
<a1>Stocker,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Rubino,S.</a1>
<t1>Role of the Salmonella abortusovis virulence plasmid in the infection of BALB/c mice</t1>
<jf>FEMS microbiology letters</jf>
<jo>FEMS Microbiol.Lett.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jul 1</fd>
<vo>188</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>15</sp>
<op>18</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Lymph Nodes/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mesentery</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Peyer&#39;s Patches/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Salmonella/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Sheep</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>Following oral inoculation of BALB/c mice, Salmonella abortusovis strain SS44 was recovered in lower numbers from the Peyer&amp;#39;s patches and mesenteric lymph nodes compared with S. typhimurium strain SL1344, whereas splenic infections were equivalent between the two serovars. SS44 was cured of its virulence plasmid or subjected to mutagenesis of the spv genes, and the Spv(-) derivatives were tested for virulence in mice. Plasmid-cured S. abortusovis SU40 retained virulence in BALB/c mice when inoculated intraperitoneally. On the other hand, mice infected orally with SU40 had greatly reduced splenic infection compared to those infected with wild-type SS44. Similar results were obtained after Tn5 insertion mutagenesis of the spvR gene or deletion of the spvABCD locus. These results suggest that in the gut-associated lymphoid tissues S. abortusovis may replicate less than S. typhimurium and that the S. abortusovis virulence plasmid primarily affects systemic infection after oral inoculation but not after intraperitoneal administration in the mouse model.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI24821/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 7705721; ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0378-1097; 0378-1097</sn>
<ad>Department of Biomedical Science, University of Sassari, Italy. uzzua@ssmain.uniss.it</ad>
<an>PMID: 10867227; S0378-1097(00)00204-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10867227</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>344</id>
<a1>Vargas-Pinto,S.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Dziejman,M.</a1>
<t1>Analysis of VSP-II genes in V.cholerae</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>2007</fd>
<vo>107</vo>
<sp>262</sp>
<no>PT: J; UT: BIOSIS:PREV200800188876; CT: 107th General Meeting of the American-Society-for-Microbiology; CL: Toronto, CANADA; CY: 2007,; SP: Amer Soc Microbiol</no>
<sn>1060-2011 ER</sn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Abstract</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1333</id>
<a1>Vedam-Mai V</a1>
<a1>Farrell-Evans M</a1>
<a1>Thiaville P</a1>
<a1>Gulig P</a1>
<a1>Wright AC.</a1>
<t1>Distributionof the viuB Gene among Vibrio vulnificus strains does not predict virulence.</t1>
<jf>Abstracts of the General Meeting of the American Society for Microbiology</jf>
<yr>2008</yr>
<vo>108</vo>
<sp>Abstract Q-241</sp>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>295</id>
<a1>Wilson,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Doyle,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Exponential-phase expression of spvA of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid: induction in intracellular salts medium and intracellularly in mice and cultured mammalian cells</t1>
<jf>Microbiology (Reading, England)</jf>
<jo>Microbiology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>143 ( Pt 12)</vo>
<is>Pt 12</is>
<sp>3827</sp>
<op>3839</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Genes, Bacterial</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Intestinal Mucosa</k1>
<k1>Mammals</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Operon</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Salmonella Infections, Animal/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>The spv genes of Salmonella typhimurium and other non-typhoidal Salmonella serovars are essential for efficient systemic infection beyond the intestines in orally inoculated mice as a model for enteric fever. These virulence genes are not significantly expressed by salmonellae during exponential growth in L broth but are induced when the bacteria enter the stationary phase of growth. Using RNase protection analysis to directly measure spvA mRNA from the virulence plasmid of S. typhimurium, we found that spvA was maximally induced in an SpvR- and RpoS-dependent manner during exponential growth in intracellular Salts Medium, which mimics the intracellular environment of mammalian cells. A cloned spvA-lacZ operon fusion in S. typhimurium was induced intracellularly in periotoneal cells of mice, correlating in vivo intracellular gene expression with intracellular function of the spv genes in infected mice. spvA was also induced intracellularly in vitro within both Henle-407 intestinal epithelial cells and J774.A1 macrophage-like cells when the bacteria were replicating with exponential kinetics. Prevention of invasion of salmonellae with cytochalasin D inhibited spvA induction within tissue culture cells, indicating that salmonellae must be internalized for spvA to be induced. The spvA-lacZ fusion was not induced by salmonellae in extracellular fluid of the peritoneal cavity or in serum. Since induction of the spv genes occurs intracellularly during exponential growth of salmonellae, cessation of growth may not be the most relevant inducing signal for spv gene expression.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI24821/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9430468; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1350-0872; 1350-0872</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9421907</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9421907</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>292</id>
<a1>Wilson,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Gulig,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Regulation of the spvR gene of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid during exponential-phase growth in intracellular salts medium and at stationary phase in L broth</t1>
<jf>Microbiology (Reading, England)</jf>
<jo>Microbiology</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>144 ( Pt 7)</vo>
<is>Pt 7</is>
<sp>1823</sp>
<op>1833</op>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Regulator</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plasmids/genetics</k1>
<k1>Salmonella typhimurium/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Sigma Factor/analysis</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/analysis</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>The authors previously showed that the SpvR-regulated spvABCD operon of the Salmonella typhimurium virulence plasmid is highly induced during exponential-phase growth by salmonellae intracellularly in mammalian cells and in a medium designed to mimic the intracellular environment of mammalian cells, intracellular salts medium (ISM), as well as at stationary phase in L broth (LB). The most relevant signal(s) for spv gene expression in vivo is not known. To elucidate the means by which salmonellae regulate the spv genes in response to the environment during the disease process, expression of the spvR gene, encoding the positive regulatory protein SpvR, was examined under these same growth conditions by using RNAse-protection analysis. spvR was expressed at a low, basal level during exponential growth in LB but was induced during exponential growth in ISM and during stationary phase in LB, the same conditions that increased expression of the spvABCD operon. Basal expression of spvR during exponential growth in LB was independent of both SpvR and the alternative sigma factor RpoS, whereas maximal induction of spvR was dependent on both SpvR and RpoS. In an RpoS- background, spvR message was decreased in stationary phase, whereas spvR exhibited residual RpoS-independent induction during exponential growth in ISM. Deletion of spvA from the virulence plasmid of S. typhimurium increased expression of spvR during stationary phase in LB, but not during exponential growth in ISM. These results suggest that expression of spvR is controlled by different regulatory factors, depending on the growth conditions encountered by the salmonellae.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI24821/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9430468; 0 (Sigma Factor); 0 (Transcription Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>1350-0872; 1350-0872</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9695915</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9695915</pmid></reference></refworks>
