
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3849</id>
<a1>Addesso,K. M.</a1>
<a1>McAuslane,H. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Host-marking by female pepper weevils, Anthonomus eugenii</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>125</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>269</sp>
<op>276</op>
<ab>Pepper weevils, Anthonomus eugenii Cano (Coleoptera: Curculionidae), feed and oviposit in flower buds and small fruits of plants in the genus Capsicum, as well as several species of Solanum (Solanaceae). Females chew a small hole into the fruit, deposit a single egg within the cavity, and seal the hole with a clear anal secretion that hardens into an &amp;#39;oviposition plug&amp;#39;. Female oviposition behavior was studied in a series of small-arena bioassays to determine whether previous oviposition in Jalapeno pepper fruit deterred subsequent oviposition and to determine what specific cues from an infested fruit influence female behavior. In choice and no-choice tests, females preferred clean fruit to fruit that had received four eggs 24 h previously (i.e., infested fruit), whether the fruit was infested with conspecific eggs or their own eggs. Further bioassays demonstrated that the presence of female frass, or oviposition plugs alone, in the absence of eggs or any fruit damage, was sufficient to deter oviposition. In addition, females given the choice between an infested fruit with the oviposition plug removed or an unaltered infested fruit preferred the fruit with no plugs, even when eggs, frass, and feeding damage were still present. To determine whether females would avoid infested peppers under more natural conditions, we quantified oviposition on infested and uninfested sentinel pepper fruit within individually caged plants and on clean and infested plants caged together. Females consistently laid more eggs on clean fruit than on infested fruits and moved within and among pepper plants to search for more acceptable oviposition sites. We conclude that oviposition plugs, along with contaminated female, but not male, frass contain a deterrent that, in the absence of any other cue, is enough to alert a female that a patch is occupied.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8703</sn>
<an>000250916300006</an>
<do>10.1111/j.1570-7458.2007.00626.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3841</id>
<a1>Addesso,K. M.</a1>
<a1>McAuslane,H. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Slansky,F.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Artificial Substrates for Oviposition and Larval Development of the Pepper Weevil (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>257</sp>
<op>264</op>
<ab>The pepper weevil, Anthonomus eugenii Cano (Coleoptera: Curculionidae), is a major pest of cultivated peppers (Capsicum spp.) and other cultivated and wild species within the family Solanaceae. Laboratory study of this insect, as well as its biological control agents, will be greatly facilitated by an artificial rearing system that does not rely on pepper fruit. An egg collection method and amendments to a standard larval diet were investigated for use in the rearing of this weevil. Spherical sachets made of Parafilm or netting enclosing leaves of pepper, American black nightshade, eggplant, tomato, potato, and jasmine tobacco induced oviposition. Tomato, potato, and jasmine tobacco leaves were accepted despite the fact that these are not oviposition hosts for pepper weevils in the wild. A standard larval diet formula was modified in an attempt to improve egg hatch, larval survival, developmental time, and adult mass. The diet formula was modified with the addition of freeze-dried jalapeno pepper powder, an additional lipid source, alternate protein sources, and the removal of methyl paraben. None of the aforementioned treatments resulted in a significant improvement over the standard diet. Egg hatch was greater when eggs were incubated on moist paper towels rather than in diet; thus, placement of neonates rather than eggs into diet improved production of adults. Suggestions for more: efficient rearing of weevils on the currently available diet and future directions for the development of an artificial rearing system for pepper weevil are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000263039400036</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3839</id>
<a1>Arevalo,H. A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of Myllocerus Undatus (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) in Valencia Orange with Chlorpyrifos Sprays Directed at Ground and Foliage</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>150</sp>
<op>152</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000264161900023</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3834</id>
<a1>Barr,N. B.</a1>
<a1>Hall,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Weathersbee,A.A.,,III</a1>
<a1>Nguyen,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P.</a1>
<a1>Qureshi,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Flores,D.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of Laboratory Colonies and Field Populations of Tamarixia radiata, an Ectoparasitoid of the Asian Citrus Psyllid, Using Internal Transcribed Spacer and Cytochrome Oxidase Subunit I DNA Sequences</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2325</sp>
<op>2332</op>
<ab>The genetic diversity of Tamarixia radiata Waterston (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) laboratory colonies derived from collections in China, northern Vietnam, Pakistan, and a mixed colony from Taiwan and southern Vietnam was evaluated using the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region 1, ITS-2, and the 5&amp;#39; end of the cytochrome oxidase subunit I gene. The strains share the same ITS sequence, consistent with the morphological hypothesis that the collections represent a single species. The COI marker was variable and could distinguish the northern Vietnam and Pakistan colonies from each other and from the other colonies. Comparison of COI sequences from field-collected populations of Puerto Rico, Guadeloupe, and Texas indicates that Florida is not a likely source of the introduction into Puerto Rico but is a likely source of the introduction into Texas.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000272492800039</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3884</id>
<a1>Butler,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Henneberry,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal Effects of Selected Soaps, Oils and Detergents on the Sweet-Potato Whitefly - (Homoptera, Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>161</sp>
<op>167</op>
<ab>Efficacy against the sweetpotato whitefly (SPWF) Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) of an insecticidal soap, two horticultural oils (one vegetable and the other petroleum based) and 15 detergents was evaluated under greenhouse conditions. Applications were directed to the underside of infested zucchini squash, tomato, or poinsettia leaves. Live nymphs were distinguished by their ability to deposit honeydew on water-sensitive paper held in contact. With the exception of 3 detergents, all materials evaluated at 1% concentration caused greater than 85% mortality of SPWF nymphs compared to applications of water. Similar results with 2 detergents and an insecticidal soap were obtained on infested cucumber leaves treated in the field in Florida. Saf-T-Side (mineral) Oil(TM), Natur&amp;#39;l(TM) (vegetable) oil, New Day(TM) liquid detergent or M-Pede(TM) applied with a mist blower reduced numbers of SPWF adults in heavily infested cucumber plots, although only Saf-T-Side Oil resulted in a significant reduction of nymphs.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1993KV45300012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3886</id>
<a1>Butler,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Henneberry,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal Effects of Selected Soaps, Oils and Detergents on the Sweet-Potato Whitefly - (Homoptera, Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>161</sp>
<op>167</op>
<ab>Efficacy against the sweetpotato whitefly (SPWF) Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) of an insecticidal soap, two horticultural oils (one vegetable and the other petroleum based) and 15 detergents was evaluated under greenhouse conditions. Applications were directed to the underside of infested zucchini squash, tomato, or poinsettia leaves. Live nymphs were distinguished by their ability to deposit honeydew on water-sensitive paper held in contact. With the exception of 3 detergents, all materials evaluated at 1% concentration caused greater than 85% mortality of SPWF nymphs compared to applications of water. Similar results with 2 detergents and an insecticidal soap were obtained on infested cucumber leaves treated in the field in Florida. Saf-T-Side (mineral) Oil(TM), Natur&amp;#39;l(TM) (vegetable) oil, New Day(TM) liquid detergent or M-Pede(TM) applied with a mist blower reduced numbers of SPWF adults in heavily infested cucumber plots, although only Saf-T-Side Oil resulted in a significant reduction of nymphs.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1993KV45300012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3840</id>
<a1>Calvo,Javier</a1>
<a1>Blockmans,Karel</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<a1>Urbaneja,Alberto</a1>
<t1>Predation by Nesidiocoris tenuis on Bemisia tabaci and injury to tomato</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>237</sp>
<op>246</op>
<ab>Tomato is the most important vegetable crop in Spain. The mirid bug Nesidiocoris tenuis (Reuter) commonly appears in large numbers in protected and open-air tomato crops where little or no broad-spectrum insecticides are used. Nesidiocoris tenuis is known to be a predator of whiteflies, thrips and several other pest species. However, it is also considered a pest because it can feed on tomato plants, causing necrotic rings on stems and flowers and punctures in fruits. Our objectives were to evaluate predation by N. tenuis on sweetpotato whitefly Bemisia tabaci Gennadius under greenhouse conditions and establish its relationship to N. tenuis feeding on tomato. Two different release rates of N. tenuis were compared with an untreated control (0, 1 and 4 N. tenuis plant(-1)) in cages of 8 m(2). Significant reductions of greater than 90% of the whitefly population and correspondingly high numbers of N. tenuis were observed with both release rates. Regression analysis showed that necrotic rings on foliage caused by N. tenuis were best explained by the ratio of B. tabaci nymphs:N. tenuis as predicted by the equation y = 15.086x - 0.6359.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>000264091700009</an>
<do>10.1007/s10526-008-9164-y</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3843</id>
<a1>Cherry,Ron</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Phil</a1>
<t1>Abundance and spatial distribution of wireworms (Coleoptera : Elateridae) in Florida sugarcane fields on muck versus sandy soils</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>383</sp>
<op>387</op>
<ab>Wireworms are important insect pests of Florida sugarcane. Our objective was to determine the abundance and spatial distribution of wireworms in Florida sugarcane oil muck versus sandy soils. Fourteen commercial sugarcane fields were sampled for wireworms on farms in southern Florida. Melanotus communis (Gyllenhal) was the most abundant wireworm found in both soil types, Other less abundant wireworms found and discussed are Conoderus spp., Ischiodontus sp., and Glyphonyx bimarginatus Schaeffer. There were no significant differences in densities of G. bimarginatus, M. communis, or total wireworms of all species in muck Versus sand fields. Significantly more Conoderus spp. were found in sandy fields and significantly more Ischiodontus sp. were found in muck fields. The spatial distribution of the wireworms within fields was similar in both soil types. In muck, wireworms in 4 fields were randomly distributed, aggregated in 3 fields, and uniformly distributed in no fields. In sand, wireworms in 3 fields were randomly distributed, aggregated in 4 fields and uniformly distributed in no fields.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000259050500005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3837</id>
<a1>Cicero,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Brown,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Roberts,P. D.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>The Digestive System of Diaphorina citri and Bactericera cockerelli (Hemiptera: Psyllidae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>650</sp>
<op>665</op>
<ab>The psyllids Diaphorina citri (Kuwayama) mid Bactericera cockerelli (Sulc) (Hemiptera: Psyllidae) are vectors of Candidatus Liberibacter spp., bacteria] agents of serious agricultural diseases. The rapidly expanding geographical distributions of these diseases dictate increasing urgency for their control. Therefore, it is important to gain a full understanding of the psyllid digestive system in which the vector-pathogen interactions begin. Their midgut is looped so that the foregut-midgut and midgut-hindgut transitional regions are grafted together to form a composite tube within a filter chamber sheath. Unwanted sap components could thus be extracted directly into the hindgut, bypassing digestion. The esophageal lumen enters the chamber axially to become the inner midgut lumen. The upper half of this midgut section is bulbous while the lower half is tubular. The tube lumen exits the chamber to become the external midgut lumen, which loops through the hemocoel and reenters the chamber, becoming the inner hindgut lumen. The inner hindgut tracks the adherent inner midgut in an antiparallel direction. The composite tube is helically wound and undergoes one hairpin turn. The inner hindgut straps diagonally across the bulb and then exits the chamber next to the esophagus as the outer hindgut to anus. The source of honeydew, whether filtrate, midgut waste, or both, is questioned. Paired, spherical, primary salivary glands each have a digitate accessory gland and a lateral duct that leads to tire stylets. The accessory gland lumen is lined exclusively with intima, whereas the primary gland apical cell membranes are indicated to be more complex.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>000267606100010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3858</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>McCoy,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Graham,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Mizell,R. F.</a1>
<t1>Estimating the relative abundance of adult citrus root weevils (Coleoptera : Curculionidae) with modified Tedders traps</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>939</sp>
<op>946</op>
<ab>Taylor&amp;#39;s power law (s(2) = a (x) over bar (b)) was fitted to the means and variances of numbers of adult Diaprepes abbreviatus L. and Pachnaeus, litus (Germar) caught monthly in modified Tedders traps (citrus Tedders traps). Data for D. abbreviatus were obtained in six Florida citrus groves, two located on the central ridge and the others in the central and southern flatwoods. Parameters for P. litus (a = 2.15, b = 1.17) using data pooled from two sites were consistent with parameters derived from the individual sites. Parameters derived from pooled data for D, abbreviatus were a = 2.69, b = 1.33; however, there was significant variability of the parameter b among sites. For specified levels of precision (confidence interval half-length:mean ratio), from 0-30% fewer traps were needed to estimate numbers of F. litus compared with D. abbreviatus at densities encountered in these groves. Plot size from 0.06 to &amp;gt; 12 ha affected the numbers of traps needed to obtain monthly mean estimates of adult weevils per trap with a given level of precision. In general, sample precision was equal in large and small plots when population density in large plots was double that in small plots. At a given population density, approximate to 70% more traps were required in large compared with small plots to achieve a similar level of precision. Changes in trapped weevil abundance larger than 2.5-fold were detected as significantly different with the sampling plans used in these studies. Seasonality in the numbers of each species was evident at all sites (P = 0.05) because monthly means varied by 30- to 60-fold. In a separate study, the numbers of weevils recovered monthly from citrus Tedders traps were approximately congruent (r = 0.78, n = 33, P = 0.01) with numbers recovered from-cone-shaped ground traps that only recover adult weevils as they emerge from soil. Annual maxima-for both types of traps occurred at the same times during 33 mo, but each year weevil emergence from soil (as measured by cone traps) remained high for 1-2 mo after weevil recovery from citrus Tedders traps declined. Polynomial regression on monthly recovery from citrus Tedders traps explained 66% of the variation in monthly emergence of weevils from soil. Results of this study support the use of citrus Tedders traps in integrated pest management programs to detect the onset of emergence from soil by weevil cohorts, and to measure relative differences in weevil population density due to experimental treatments.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000171801700021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3888</id>
<a1>Evans,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Weekly Economic Injury Levels for Fall Armyworm (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) Infestation of Corn in Lowland Ecuador</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2452</sp>
<op>2454</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1990EM71300060</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3859</id>
<a1>Hall,D. G.</a1>
<a1>Pena,J.</a1>
<a1>Franqui,R.</a1>
<a1>Nguyen,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P.</a1>
<a1>McCoy,C.</a1>
<a1>Lapointe,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Adair,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Bullock,B.</a1>
<t1>Status of biological control by egg parasitoids of Diaprepes abbreviatus (Coleoptera : Curculionidae) in citrus in Florida and Puerto Rico</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>61</sp>
<op>70</op>
<ab>Eggs of Diaprepes abbreviatus (L.) were routinely monitored in citrus groves at ten locations in Florida during 1997 and 1998 to study egg parasitism. One citrus location was studied in Puerto Rico. No native parasitoids were recovered from 1,337 D. abbreviatus egg masses studied in Florida citrus. In contrast, an average of 35.5% (range 12.5 to 68.8%) parasitism of egg masses was reported in Puerto Rico. The parasitoids Aprostocetus gain, Horismenus spp, and Quadrastichus haitiensis were recovered from the eggs of D. abbreviatus studied in Puerto Rico. The Horismenus parasitoids were suspected hyperparasitoids. Releases of the parasitoid Ceratogramma etiennei from Guadeloupe were initiated during 1998 at each of the Florida research sites. By the end of 1998, C. etiennei had been recovered from D. abbreviatus eggs at two of nine locations in Florida citrus. The parasitoid was recovered from 1 of 34 egg masses at one of these locations during the month of September and from 3 of 34 egg masses at the other location during the month of November. Whether or not C, etiennei establishes itself at one or more locations in Florida remains to be seen.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>000167737700004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3854</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Timing and release rates for control of Bemisia tabaci (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) by Nephaspis oculatus (Coleoptera : Coccinellidae) under confined conditions</t1>
<jf>Journal of Entomological Science</jf>
<jo>J.Entomol.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>74</sp>
<op>79</op>
<ab>The potential of a lady beetle, Nephaspis oculatus (Blatchley), to serve as a biological control agent of the sweetpotato whitefly, Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) Biotype &amp;quot;B&amp;quot; (= B. argentifolii Bellows T Perring), was evaluated on hibiscus under confined conditions, in large cages (60 x 60 x 60 cm) and on sweetpotato leaves in small clear cup cages (0.9 L). Nephaspis oculatus suppressed B. tabaci populations and provided marketable hibiscus plants when released 1 d after whitefly introduction in large cages at ratios of 1:4 and 1:20 beetle:whitefly. When beetles were released 7 d after the whitefly infestation, significant pest reduction and marketable plants were obtained with the 1:4 beetle:whitefly ratio but not the 1:20 ratio. In clear cup cages on sweet potato leaves, significant suppression was obtained at beetle:whitefly ratios of 1:6.7, 1:10 and 1:20 when N. oculatus was released 1 d after the whitefly infestation. These results help define release parameters for successful use of N. oculatus as a biological control agent of whiteflies under confined conditions.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0749-8004</sn>
<an>000227930100010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3855</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Lethal and sublethal effects of two insect growth regulators on adult Delphastus catalinae (Coleoptera : Coccinellidae), a predator of whiteflies (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>298</sp>
<op>305</op>
<ab>Pyriproxyfen, a juvenile hormone analog, and buprofezin, a chitin synthesis inhibitor, are two insect growth regulators (IGRs) considered as selective and effective insecticides for controlling whiteflies. Delphastus catalinae (Horn) is a commercially produced whitefly predator considered to be a valuable biological control agent of whiteflies, especially of Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) (B. argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring) in greenhouses. The compatibility of these two control strategies was tested by evaluating the lethal and sublethal effects resulting from ingestion of insect growth regulator (IGR) residues on treated B. tabaci eggs by adult lady beetles in the laboratory. Feeding on pyriproxyfen-treated whitefly eggs caused no significant decrease in longevity of either male or female beetles, whereas feeding on buprofezin-treated eggs reduced longevity significantly. Likewise, preoviposition period was not affected by pyriproxyfen, but was lengthened 3-6 days by buprofezin. Buprofezin reduced D. catalinae egg production and oviposition periods while a 28-day treatment with the low rate of pyriproxyfen actually increased these parameters. Both IGRs reduced D. catalinae egg fertility, especially the higher rate of pyriproxyfen and both rates of buprofezin. However, the process was largely reversed in the case of pyriproxyfen by a transfer of D. catalinae to water-treated whitefly eggs. Because D. catalinae fecundity was actually increased by 28 day exposure to the low rate of pyriproxyfen, there was no net effect on viable egg production. Thus, while both growth regulators negatively impacted D. catalinae, fewest side effects were observed with pyriproxyfen, and the worst of these, egg sterility, was reversible following removal of treated eggs. (C) 2004 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000221175700021</an>
<do>10.1016/j.biocontrol.2004.01.007</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3860</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal activity of surfactants and oils against silverleaf whitefly (Bemisia argentifolii) nymphs (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) on collards and tomato</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>861</sp>
<op>866</op>
<ab>The insecticidal activities of four surfactants (Cide-kick, Silwet L-77, M-Pede and APSA-80), a dishwashing detergent (New Day), a mineral oil (Sunspray oil), a cotton seed oil and a vegetable oil, alone or in combination, were tested against nymphs of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring on collards and tomato. Silwet L-77 was more effective (&amp;gt;95% mortality) than Cide-Kick or APSA-80 at rates from 0.25-1.00g Al litre(-1) but caused severe phytotoxicity to tender tomato leaves at all but the lowest rate. New Day dish detergent at 2.0 ml litre(-1) caused mortality (95%) comparable to M-Pede insecticide soap at 10-fold greater concentration. A New Day ingredient, cocamide DEA, was considerably more active than the other ingredients or the commercial mixture. Additional surfactants added to Sunspray oil increased efficacy in some treatments, but not others. Toxic responses of 2nd-and 3rd- instar whiteflies to vegetable oil and cotton seed oil at 5.0 and 10.0ml litre-l plus 0.4g Al litre(-1) APSA-80 ranged from 22.1 to 79.9% and 66.3-88.7% mortality, respectively. Whitefly mortality was greater on tomato than on collard in six of seven instances when differences between host plants were significant. Our results indicate that the these surfactants and oils have good potential for controlling B argentifolii. (C) 2000 Society of Chemical Industry.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1526-498X</sn>
<an>000089680100005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3861</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Response of Trialeurodes abutiloneus (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) to sweet potato and two species of Hibiscus</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>850</sp>
<op>855</op>
<ab>Life history, survivorship, and adaptation of the bandedwinged whitefly, Trialeurodes abutiloneus (Haldeman), on sweet potato, Ipomoea batatas (L.) Lam, and two species of Hibiscus were studied in laboratory and screen houses. T. abutiloneus deposited significantly more eggs on cotton rose, Hibiscus mutabilis L. (10.3-11.3 eggs per female), and roselle, Hibiscus sabdariffa L. (10.1-11.8 eggs per female), than on sweet potato (6.1-7.3 eggs per female) in a choice test when the whiteflies were previously reared on cotton rose and roselle. Whereas, whiteflies originally reared on sweet potato deposited more eggs on sweet potato (10.4) than on cotton rose (7.3) and roselle (6.1). However, differences in oviposition among these three host plants were not significant in a no-choice test, regardless of their original host plants. Overall developmental times of T abutiloneus were significantly longer on sweet potato (22.3-23.2 d) than on cotton rose (17.0-17.8 d) and roselle (17.1-17.4 d) independent of their original host plants. Survival rate of T. abutiloneus was only 12.3-21.4% on sweet potato compared with 71.5-87.2% on cotton rose and 77.7-90.3% on roselle. Linear regression analysis of the survival rates of all nymphal stages of T. abutiloneus on sweet potato after seven consecutive generations indicated drat the survival rates increased (r(2) = 0.7419-0.8483), albeit the rates were slow. Thus, sweet potato proved to be a relatively poor host plant as well as a relatively nonpreferred one for T. abutiloneus compared with cotton rose and roselle.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>000089632100016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3862</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Searching and feeding behavior of Nephaspis oculatus and Delphastus catalinae (Coleoptera : Coccinellidae), predators of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>901</sp>
<op>906</op>
<ab>The coccinellids Nephaspis oculatus (Blatchley) and Delphastus catalinae (LeConte) [formerly D. pusillus (LeConte)] are predators of whiteflies (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae), and have shown potential for biological control of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring in greenhouses. We observed the searching and feeding behavior of N. oculatus and D. catalinae on hibiscus (Hibiscus rosa-sinensis L.). D. catalinae larvae maintained the entire body in contact with the substrate while moving, whereas N. oculatus larvae planted the uropod on the substrate and swept the body in an are while searching. Estimated movement rates of all stages of D. catalinae were greater than the corresponding stages of N. oculatus. However, the searching areas by different larval stages of D. catalinae were significantly smaller than those by the corresponding larval stages of N. oculatus, which the larvae sweep around while searching. The adults of both coccinellid species traveled in a similar pattern; therefore, D. catalinae, moving at a greater rate, searched a greater area than that of N. oculatus, moving at a slower rate. Larvae and adults of both coccinellid species responded to prey only after contacting prey with their mouthparts or front legs. Younger larvae took significantly longer to consume prey than older larvae or adults. Larvae and adults of the smaller N. oculatus consumed whiteflies at a significantly slower rate than did corresponding stages of D. catalinae.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000083399300019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3865</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Life history of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) on Hibiscus rosa-sinensis (Malvaceae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>437</sp>
<op>445</op>
<ab>Oviposition, development and survivorship of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring, were evaluated on two cultivars of hibiscus (Hibiscus rosa-sinensis L.), &amp;#39;Brilliant Red&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;Pink Versicolor&amp;#39;. B. argentifolii deposited significantly more eggs and survivorship of nymphs was significantly greater in choice tests on &amp;#39;Pink Versicolor&amp;#39; than on &amp;#39;Brilliant Red&amp;#39;. Overall developmental time of B. argentifolii from egg to adult eclosion was longer on &amp;#39;Brilliant Red&amp;#39; than on &amp;#39;Pink Versicolor. Although not all differences between the two cultivars were statistically significant, &amp;#39;Brilliant Red&amp;#39; could be considered a less favorable host for silverleaf whitefly than &amp;#39;Pink Versicolor&amp;#39;. However, based on the intrinsic rate of increase (r = 0.105) and finite rate of increase (lambda = 1.22) of B. argentifolii, even &amp;#39;Pink Versicolor&amp;#39; was a poor host for B. argentifolii compared to published values for eggplant, tomato, sweet potato, cucumber, garden bean, or collard.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000076426200018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3870</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of pyriproxyfen on three species of Encarsia (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae), endoparasitoids of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>404</sp>
<op>411</op>
<ab>Effects of the phenoxy juvenile hormone analog pyriproxyfen were evaluated in the laboratory on larvae, pupae, and adults of the endoparasitoids Encarsia pergandiella Howard, E. transvena (Timberlake), and E. formosa Gahan, as well as on their host, Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring. Although B. argentifolii nymphs reared on sweet potato leaves and treated as 1st, 2nd, or 3rd instars with pyriproxyfen developed to the pupal stage; &amp;lt;5% adult emergence was observed. However, when treated in the 4th instar, adult emergence was greater than or equal to 70%, and when treated as pupae, greater than or equal to 97%. Of the 3 parasitoids tested, pyriproxyfen was least harmful to E. pergandiella and most deleterious to E. formosa. Concentrations of 1.00, 0.05, and 0.01 mg (AI)/liter applied to whitefly nymphs 6.5 d after parasitization caused significant reduction in subsequent adult emergence of E. formosa at the greatest rate, but not of E. pergandiella. Effects of treatment of whitefly nymphs containing E. formosa pupae (11.4 d after parasitization) were even more striking-73.5 and 44.6% reduction in emergence at the 2 highest rates, with wing deformations observed in a large proportion of emerging adults. Development time of all 3 Encarsia species was increased significantly by exposure to pyriproxyfen shortly after oviposition, and parasitization of B. argentifolii by E. formosa adults treated as larvae was reduced 21.4-56.8% compared with untreated parasitoids. However, residues of 2 higher rates reduced the progeny by 30.7-42.3% and rate of emergence by 11.2-27.6% with E. formosa, and to a lesser extent the progeny by 21.7-29.3% and adult emergence by 3.2-11.0% of E. transvena. Thus, pyriproxyfen proved to be effective against B. argentifolii, safe to E. pergandiella, and relatively safe to E. transvena, but relatively toxic to E. formosa, especially pupae.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1997WZ03600025</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3874</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Morphology of Nephaspis oculatus and Delphastus pusillus (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae), predators of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</jf>
<jo>Proc.Entomol.Soc.Wash.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>292</sp>
<op>300</op>
<ab>Two coccinellids, Nephaspis oculatus (Blatchley) and Delphastus pusillus (LeConte), are potentially good biological control agents of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows and Perring in Florida and elsewhere. The two species share many features of morphology and biology. We describe and compare the eggs, larvae, pupae and adults of the two coccinellids and provide detailed illustrations of all stages.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8797</sn>
<an>A1996UJ65000017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3875</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Oviposition, development, and survivorship of Encarsia pergandiella (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae) in four instars of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>96</sp>
<op>102</op>
<ab>Oviposition, development, and mortality of Encarsia pergandiella Howard in the 4 instars of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring were evaluated under choice and no-choice conditions in the laboratory. E. pergandiella oviposited in all nymphal stages of B. argentifolii, but preferred 3rd and 4th instars. Regardless of host stage parasitized, adult wasps emerged from host pupae. The costs of oviposition in younger instars were delayed development, presumably to allow for growth and maturation of the host, and increased mortality of both parasitoid and host. Our results indicate that E. pergandiella can successfully exploit whitefly populations of both high and low densities by favoring large hosts of high quality when abundant, but shifting to, and successfully exploiting younger instar hosts of lower quality when necessary.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>A1996TR36800014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3873</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Pupal orientation and emergence of some aphelinid parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae) of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>385</sp>
<op>390</op>
<ab>Emergences of Encarsia pergandiella Howard and E. formosa Gahan were compared; and pupal orientation of several Encarsia and Eretmocerus species were examined. The species examined for pupal orientation were E. pergandiella from southwest Florida, E. nr. pergandiella from Brazil, E. transvena (Timberlake) from Florida, E. formosa from California (Davis), E. formosa from Georgia (Griffin), E. formosa from Nile Delta, Egypt, Eretmocerus sp. from Hong Kong, Eretmocerus sp. from Padappai, India, E. mundus (Mercet) from Murcia, Spain, E. nr. californicus Howard from Arizona (Tucson), parasitoids of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring [previously B. tabaci (Gennadius)]. The majority (98%) of E. pergandiella pupae from Florida and all other Encarsia species except E. nr. pergandiella from Brazil pupated facing the host venter, regardless of leaf orientation, so that rotation was necessary before emergence. E. nr. pergandiella from Brazil, 2% of E. pergandiella from Florida, and all species of Eretmocerus pupated facing the host dorsum, so that no rotation ws necessary. All E. pergandiella pupae and adults from Florida were pigmented similarly regardless of pupal orientation. Less than 1% of E. pergandiella female pupae were oriented backwards, i.e., with the head toward the host posterior, but again, these were not distinguishable characteristics of color or form. We conclude that a low incidence of unusual pupal orientations represented natural variation in the population of E. pergandiella we studied.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>A1996UP23500011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3872</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Toxicological effects of selected insecticides on Nephaspis oculatus (Col, Coccinellidae), a predator of Bemisia argentifolii (Hem, Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of Applied Entomology-Zeitschrift Fur Angewandte Entomologie</jf>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>120</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>369</sp>
<op>373</op>
<ab>Toxicological effects of selected biorational insecticides were tested in the laboratory against all developmental stages of Nephaspis oculatus (Blatchley), a predator of whiteflies including silverleaf whitefly, Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring. Biorational insecticides included a mineral oil(Sunspray Ultra-Fine Oil), an insecticidal soap (M-Pede), and a mixture of sucrose and glucose esters (a detergent-like extract of Nicotiana gossei Domin). A pyrethroid (Capture 2EC) was used for comparison and water as control. N. oculatus has four distinct instars but the larvae were divided into two size categories (small and large) for bioassays. Pyrethroid was toxic to all developmental stages of N. oculatus and insecticide soap was toxic to larvae, but not to adults, eggs or pupae. Mineral oil was moderately toxic to eggs, but had no significant effect on other stages. Mixture of sucrose and glucose esters was innocuous to all life stages of the beetle. These results indicated that the use of pyrethroid would be incompatible with biological control of whitefly by N. oculatus and that considerable interference with predator activity could be expected from insecticidal soap, depending on the timing of application. On the other hand, mineral oil and especially N. gossei extract could be used against the whitefly with relative impunity to the coccinellids.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0931-2048</sn>
<an>A1996UY43600009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3878</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Deposition and Bioassay of Insecticides Applied by Leaf Dip and Spray Tower Against Bemisia-Argentifolii Nymphs (Homoptera, Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Pesticide Science</jf>
<jo>Pestic.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>317</sp>
<op>322</op>
<ab>Two application methods, spray and leaf dip, were evaluated as bioassays for insecticides to nymphs of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring (formerly Bemisia tabaci Gennadius strain &amp;#39;B&amp;#39;). Sprays were applied at different volumes and pressures with the Potter Spray Tower(R). Spray deposition was evaluated using a tracer dye, and also plain water in the case of the spray tower. Coverage on water-sensitive paper was evaluated with a computerized image-scanning system. Insecticide efficacy was evaluated as mortality to whitefly nymphs. Materials assayed included &amp;#39;M-Pede&amp;#39;(R) (an insecticidal soap), &amp;#39;Sunspray&amp;#39;(R) Ultra-Fine Spray Oil (a mineral oil), &amp;#39;Margosan-O&amp;#39;(R) (an extracted concentration of azadirachtin + 10% neem oil), and bifenthrin (&amp;#39;Brigade&amp;#39;(R) 10WP), a pyrethroid, with purified water as a control. Differing results were obtained with the two bioassay methods, depending on material tested. Mortality of whitefly nymphs from bifenthrin, and to a lesser extent neem extract, was largely independent of application method. In contrast, &amp;#39;Sunspray&amp;#39; (mineral) oil, and to a lesser extent insecticidal soap, was more efficacious when applied as a dip than as a spray. Differences in respect of effects of application method on treatment mortality were attributed to differences between materials in mode of action.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0031-613X</sn>
<an>A1995RQ47600002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3879</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Oviposition by Bemisia-Argentifolii (Homoptera, Aleyrodidae) on Tomato - Effects of Leaf Factors and Insecticide Residues</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>992</sp>
<op>997</op>
<ab>Ovipositional preference based on leaf age, height, surface orientation, and the of insecticidal residues was determined for Bemisia argentfolii Bellows and Perring, formerly B. tabaci (Gennadius), biotype B. Two-leaflet simulated plants were used to study the effects of leaf age, height, and surface orientation in choice and no-choice tests. Whiteflies preferred young leaves to old leaves for oviposition, although this preference was overridden by reversing normal leaf position, that is, placing old leaves high and young leaves low. Preference for the abaxial leaf surface was not increased by reversing orientation, although oviposition on the adaxial surface was increased by this procedure. The effects of insecticide residues on oviposition were studied by exposing whiteflies to individual insecticide-treated tomato leaves. Interactions among leaf ages, leaf heights, and insecticide residues were studied on simulated plants and individual leaves. The fewest eggs were found on young leaves treated with mineral oil, followed by pyrethroid, insecticidal soap, and sucrose and glucose esters in choice and no-choice tests. The effects of leaf age and leaf height were overridden by repellency to residues of bifenthrin and mineral oil. Repellency to residues might be used to improve the efficacy of insecticides by manipulating whitefly distribution within the canopy.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1995RN34800037</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3881</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Toxicity and Repellency of some Biorational Insecticides to Bemisia-Argentifolii on Tomato Plants</t1>
<jf>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</jf>
<jo>Entomol.Exp.Appl.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>74</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>137</sp>
<op>143</op>
<ab>A mineral oil, an insecticidal soap, and a plant-derived surfactant were compared with a broad-spectrum pyrethroid for residual toxicity and repellency to silverleaf whitefly, Bemisia argentifolii Bellows and Perring (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae) on tomatoes (Lycopersicum esculentum Miller, cv. Lanai) under,greenhouse and laboratory conditions. The materials tested were: Sunspray oil (a mineral oil), M-Pede (an insecticidal soap), Nicotiana gossei extract (a sucrose ester surfactant), Garlic Barrier (repellency only), and the pyrethroid bifenthrin (Brigade 10WP), with water as a control. For toxicity studies, whiteflies were confined on leaves which had been dipped in solutions of 0.5 x, 1 x and 2 x field rate concentrations. Insecticide residues were compared when the leaves were wet and dry. Adult mortalities were greatest with bifenthrin and Sunspray oil, followed by M-Pede, N. gossei extract and water. Mortality from dry residue of lower rates of bifenthrin and Sunspray oil was greater than mortality from wet residues, whereas M-Pede lost all activity upon drying. Dual and multiple choice tests for repellency were carried out in the greenhouse or laboratory by spraying plants or individual leaves to runoff with 1 x field concentrations. Bifenthrin and Sunspray oil repelled B. argentifolii adults for up to 7 and 5 days, respectively, followed by M-Pede and extract of N. gossei, whereas Garlic Barrier was not significantly different from the water control in all tests. Numbers of whitefly eggs were significantly reduced on bifenthrin and Sunspray oil-treated leaves, whereas egg numbers in other treatments were not different from water. Sunspray oil as a dip proved to be at least as effective as the synthetic pyrethroid for whitefly control. A multiple-choice leaf-wheel proved to be a useful device to quickly evaluate repellent effects of several different insecticides to whitefly.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8703</sn>
<an>A1995QM67000006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3880</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Toxicity of Biorational Insecticides to Bemisia-Argentifolii (Homoptera, Aleyrodidae) on Tomato Leaves</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>564</sp>
<op>568</op>
<ab>Bioassays were conducted to test tile toxicity of insecticide leaf residue to adults. and contact toxicity to eggs and nymphs of silverleaf whitefly, Bemisia argentifolii Bellows lows and Perring. Four insecticides were tested: insecticidal soap (Sunspray oil). mineral oil (M-Pede), extract of Nicotiana gossei Domin (a detergent-like acylsugar), and bifenthrin (a pyrethroid). Purified tap water was used as a control. Bioassays of adults were conducted by dipping whitefly-free tomato leaves into serial dilutions of the insecticides, air-drying for prescribed periods; and exposing adults to leaves in large cup cages for 24 h. Residue of Sunspray oil caused greatest mortality to adults for up to 5 d after treatment, and the LC(50) of 24 h residue to adults was 0.029%. Two-hour leaf residues of bifenthrin at tile field rate (0.06 g [AI]/liter) or higher (0.12-0.24 g [AI]liter) gave &amp;gt;68% mortality; of adults, but efficacy was reduced with residues of 24 h (LC(50) = 0.031, g [AI]liter) or older. Dried residues of insecticidal soap and N. gossei extract were not effective on adults. Contact bioassays Mere also conducted on tomato leaves infested. with uniform cohorts of eggs or nymphs. Response patterns to insecticides were similar among developmental stages of the whitefly, with young nymphs being the most susceptible, followed hv older nymphs and eggs. LC(50)s of Sunspray oil to young and old nymphs were 0.032 and 0.088%, an;d of bifenthrin were 0.001 and 0.106 g (AI)liter, respectively. Insecticidal soap and N. gossei extract were re all effective on young nymphs, even at very low rates (LC(50), 0.15% and 0.08 g [AI]liter, respectively), but had no significant effect on eggs. N. gossei extract was effective on older nymphs at low rates (LC(50) = 0.14 g [AI]/liter), whereas insecticidal soap was not (LC(50) = 0.51%).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1995RA81700019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3871</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Chortyk,O. T.</a1>
<t1>Insecticidal activity of natural and synthetic sugar esters against Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1233</sp>
<op>1239</op>
<ab>Insecticidal activities of natural sugar ester isolates of Nicotiana spp. and synthetic sugar esters were tested against Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring in laboratory bioassays and a tomato field trial on staked tomato. A mixture of the pyrethroid cyfluthrin and methamidophos, as well as the juvenile analog pyriproxyfen, were used for comparison in the field trial. Mortality of adults immobilized on yellow sticky cards and sprayed to run-off (approximate to 100% coverage) with sugar ester isolates of Nicotiana spp. (including N. gossei) approached 100%. In contrast, mortality of immobilized adults heated in a Potter spray tower (approximate to 70% coverage) with the same concentrations of N. gossei was &amp;lt;50%. Sugar ester isolates of N. gossei, N. amplexicaulis, N. glutinosa, N. langsdorffii, N. trigonophylla, and N. palmeri and a synthetic sucrose ester were more toxic to 2nd-instar nymphs at a rate of 1 g (AI)/liter than were isolates of N. cavicola, N. simulans, N. pauciflora, N. plumbaginifolia, N. noctiflora, and N. otophora. Whitefly populations on tomato sprayed weekly in the field with a sugar ester isolate of N. trigonophylla or 4 synthetic preparations were reduced by 40-98% for immatures and 43-73% for adults compared with untreated plants. Sugar ester isolate and synthetic sugar esters in the field tomato trials compared favorably with commercial insecticides for whitefly control.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1996VN77900029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3868</id>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Hoelmer,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Osborne,L. S.</a1>
<t1>Life history of Nephaspis oculatus (Coleoptera : Coccinellidae), a predator of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>776</sp>
<op>782</op>
<ab>Nephaspis oculatus (Blatchley) is a common introduced coccinellid predator in Florida, which feeds on many whitefly species. We evaluated development, consumption retest survivorship. longevity, and fecundity of a southern Florida (Immokalee) population of this coccinellid on a diet of eggs of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring. Developmental time was 4.6, 3.3, 1.5, 1.5, 3.0, and 5.2 d for eggs, 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th instars, and pupae, respectively, with an average of 19.4 d from oviposition to adult emergence for females and 18.3 d for males. Daily consumption of whitefly eggs by male and female larvae was not significantly different (average 79 for males. and 86 for females) with a mean of 16, 68, 128, and 124 eggs consumed pet larva per day by 1st, 2nd, 3rd, and 4th instars, respectively, totaling 51, 132, 192, and 373 eggs for each successive larval stage. Male-female pairs of adults consumed a mean of 184.1 eggs per day over a period of 16 wk. Adult females from a 2nd population in central Florida (Apopka) consumed an average of 78.0 B. argentifolii egg per day over a period of 5 wk, and males consumed 123.0 eggs per day. The sex ratio of 1,153 beetles was 1.00:0.89 female to male. Adult longevities averaged 56.1 d for males, and 67.5 d for females. After an average 11.3-d preoviposition period, females laid a mean of 3.03 eggs per day. Net reproductive rate was estimated Lv life table analysis at 54.27, generation time was 51.27 d, and doubling time was 8.89 d. Intrinsic rate of population increase was estimated at 0.078, or lambda = 1.08 for finite rate of increase. N. oculatus showed good potential for biological control of B. argentifolii, especially in greenhouses.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>000071731200005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3836</id>
<a1>Liu,Tong-Xian</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Relative Humidity on Efficacy of BotaniGuard (TM) (Beauveria bassiana) on Nymphs of Sweetpotato Whitefly, Bemisia tabaci (Hemiptera: Aleyrodidae), on Hibiscus in Greenhouses</t1>
<jf>Southwestern Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Southwest.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>189</sp>
<op>191</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0147-1724</sn>
<an>000268831600009</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3833</id>
<a1>Medal,J.</a1>
<a1>Bustamante,N.</a1>
<a1>Overholt,W.</a1>
<a1>Diaz,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P.</a1>
<a1>Roda,A.</a1>
<a1>Amalin,D.</a1>
<a1>Hibbard,K.</a1>
<a1>Gaskalla,R.</a1>
<a1>Sellers,B.</a1>
<a1>Hight,S.</a1>
<a1>Cuda,J.</a1>
<t1>Biological Control of Tropical Soda Apple (Solanaceae) in Florida: Post-Release Evaluation</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>130</sp>
<op>132</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000275630200021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3835</id>
<a1>Overholt,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Diaz,R.</a1>
<a1>Hibbard,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Roda,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Amalin,D.</a1>
<a1>Fox,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Hight,S. D.</a1>
<a1>Medal,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Carlisle,B.</a1>
<a1>Walter,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Hogue,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Gary,L. A.</a1>
<a1>Wiggins,L. F.</a1>
<a1>Kirby,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Crawford,S. C.</a1>
<t1>Releases, Distribution and Abundance of Gratiana Boliviana (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), a Biological Control Agent of Tropical Soda Apple (Solanum Viarum, Solanaceae) in Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>450</sp>
<op>457</op>
<ab>From 2003 to 2008, 176,643 Gratiana boliviana Spaeth (Coleoptera: Chrysomehdae) were released in Florida as part of a biological control program targeting tropical soda apple (TSA) Solanum viarum Dunal (Solanaceae). The spatial distribution of releases was clustered with more beetles released in south/central Florida than further north. A survey conducted in the fall of 2008 found G. bolviana present at &amp;gt;70% of randomly selected locations between 26 degrees and 29 degrees latitude, but no beetles were found at sites further north. The presence of beetles and beetle damage were associated with smaller TSA plants and fewer fruits per plant. The absence of beetles in northern Florida may be due to the fewer number released in that area, but also could be influenced by land cover and climate.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000269394900006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3853</id>
<a1>Pluke,R. W. H.</a1>
<a1>Escribano,A.</a1>
<a1>Michaud,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Potential impact of lady beetles on Diaphorina citri (Homoptera : Psyllidae) in Puerto Rico</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>123</sp>
<op>128</op>
<ab>The first detections of Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayama, in North America occurred almost simultaneously in Florida and in the Caribbean (Guadeloupe). Damaging populations on citrus have been reported in Florida but not in Puerto Rico where the psyllid was first detected in 2001, having probably arrived with its parasitoid, Tamarixia radiata Waterston. In an effort to identify additional sources of mortality, the relative abundance of coccinellid species was estimated on 180 citrus trees from early April to early July 2003. The most abundant species were Coelophora inaequalis F. (38.8%) and Cycloneda sanguinea limbifer L. (31.3%), and the least abundant were Cladis nitidula F. (5.9%), Coleomegilla innonata Mulsant (4.8%), Chilocorus cacti L. (2.1%), Scymnus sp. (5.9%), Hippodamia convergens Guerin (2.4%), and Cryptolaemus montrouzieri Mulsant (8.8%). These eight species were collected from citrus production areas in Puerto Rico for a laboratory study of feeding behavior. All eight consumed D. citri nymphs, with C. innonata consuming psyllids at a greater rate than C. cacti or Scymnus sp. Choice tests showed that C. inaequalis and C. s. limbifer preferred brown citrus aphid (BCA) Toxoptera citricida to D. citri as prey, whereas C. nitidula and C. cacti (both Chilochorini) preferred D. citri. Our results suggest that coccinellid species could play an important role as predators of the psyllid in Puerto Rico and contribute to its natural control.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000230583300002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3844</id>
<a1>Pluke,Richard W. H.</a1>
<a1>Qureshi,Jawwad A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<t1>Citrus flushing patterns, Diaphorina citri (Hemiptera : Psyllidae) populations and parasitism by Tamarixia radiata (Hymenoptera : Eulophidae) in Puerto Rico</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>36</sp>
<op>42</op>
<ab>Discovery of citrus greening disease or Huanglongbing in Brazil and Florida has elevated the vector psyllid, Diaphorina citri (Hemiptera: Psyllidae), to key pest status in both regions. Detected in Puerto Rico within 3 years of first detection in Florida, the psyllid appeared to be relatively scarce in the Island&amp;#39;s limited citrus and alternate rutaceous host, orange jasmine, Murraya paniculata. Monthly surveys were conducted at 4 locations during 2004 through 2005 to evaluate citrus flushing patterns, psyllid densities, and prevalence of parasitism by Tamarixia radiata. Although low levels of D. citri are known to be established in the high, cool areas of Adjuntas, a total lack of psyllids at the particular study location was attributed to scarcity of flush except for a short period in Feb. Greatest and most prolonged production of new flush, highest psyllid numbers, and greatest incidence of parasitism occurred at Isabela, the most coastal location and the only one with irrigated citrus. Favorable climate and irrigation resulted in prolonged availability of new foliage needed to maintain populations of psyllids and consequently its parasitoid. There, apparent parasitism of late instars was estimated to average 70% and approached 100% on 3 different occasions. Tamarixia radiata also was found parasitizing psyllid nymphs in orange jasmine at the rate of 48% and 77% at Rio Piedras and San Juan, respectively, approaching 100% on 5 occasions during spring and summer. The corresponding decline in infestation during peak flush in spring and later in the year could indicate that T. radiata made important contributions to the regulation of D. citri populations at these locations. Better understanding of factors favoring high parasitism rates in Puerto Rico could lead to more effective biological control of D. citri in other citrus producing areas.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000254595700007</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3864</id>
<a1>Pomerinke,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Establishment of Ageniaspis citricola (Hymenoptera : Encyrtidae) for biological control of Phyllocnistis citrella (Lepidoptera : Gracillariidae) in Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>361</sp>
<op>372</op>
<ab>The parasitoid Ageniaspis citricola. (Hymenoptera: Encyrtidae), originally from Thailand and obtained from Australia, was released at 52 sites in Southwest Florida between May 1994 and September 1995 as part of a statewide program of biological control. of citrus leafminer, Phyllocnistis citrella (Lepidoptera: Gracillariidae). Establishment and over-wintering was confirmed during spring of 1995 and 1996 in spite of frosts experienced during the previous winters. Parasitism from A., citricola at monitored groves increased from 2% in May 1994 to 86% in October 1995, apparently unhindered by native parasitoids. In contrast, apparent parasitism of citrus leafminer from endemic parasitoids fell from 30% to 2% during the same period. Wind-aided dispersal of A. citricola occurred in all directions and was documented to a maximum of 48 km from the nearest release point A. citricola is now ubiquitous throughout the region and will probably remain a permanent component of the entomophagous complex using citrus leafminer.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000076426200010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3838</id>
<a1>Qureshi,Jawwad A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<t1>Exclusion techniques reveal significant biotic mortality suffered by Asian citrus psyllid Diaphorina citri (Hemiptera: Psyllidae) populations in Florida citrus</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>50</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>129</sp>
<op>136</op>
<ab>Management of &amp;#39;huanglongbing&amp;#39; (HLB) or the Asian form of citrus greening disease caused by the bacterium, Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus, and spread by Diaphorina citri Kuwayama depends largely on the management of the vector insect. Seventeen experiments conducted during 2006-2007 included D. citri colonies initiated with eggs or first instar nymphs on young shoots protected with sleeve cages, sticky barriers or left unprotected through adult emergence to assess the relative impact of abiotic and biotic factors on psyllid populations. Temperatures dropped to 0 degrees C and killed most of the shoots and nymphs in February 2007. Spiders (Araneae) and insects in the families Coccinellidae, Blattellidae, Chrysopidae, Formicidae, Syrphidae, Anthocoridae and Miridae were observed on colonies or caught in sticky barriers. The ladybeetles Olla v-nigrum, Curinus coeruleus, Harmonia axyiidis, and Cycloneda sanguinea, the cockroach Blattella asahinai, lacewings, Ceraeochrysa sp. and Chrysoperla sp., and spiders were most often encountered. Parasitism by Tamarixia radiata provided 1-3% nymphal mortality in relation to adult emergence although a maximum of about 25% was observed. Net reproductive rate (R-0), based on observed survivorship and temperature-dependent fecundity data was estimated to be 5- to 27-fold higher in the colonies protected with full cages compared to the unprotected colonies except during the freeze. At the extreme, R-0 was estimated in caged colonies at 125-285 in Jun 2006 whereas all nymphs disappeared in the unprotected colonies. Intermediate results were observed in colonies protected with sticky barriers or coarse mesh cages. These findings suggest that biotic factors play a vital role in regulating populations of D. citri. Their elimination through reckless pesticide use could increase pest pressure and enhance the spread of the disease. Therefore, integrated control programs based on conservation of natural enemies of D. citri through judicious use of insecticides and releases of new parasitoids are needed for sustainable management of pest and disease. Published by Elsevier Inc.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000266689000007</an>
<do>10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.04.001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3842</id>
<a1>Qureshi,Jawwad A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<t1>Rate, placement and timing of aldicarb applications to control Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemiptera: Psyllidae), in oranges</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>1159</sp>
<op>1169</op>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The Asian citrus psyllid (ACP), Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemiptera: Psyllidae), is a cosmopolitan insect pest of citrus and vectors the bacterium Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus, a suspected causal organism of citrus greening or &amp;#39;huanglongbing&amp;#39; disease. Aldicarb 150 g kg(-1) GR (Temik (R) 15 G) was evaluated at three rates, two placements and three timings for ACP control in orange trees. RESULTS: Application of aldicarb at 5.6, 2.8 and 1.4 kg Al ha(-1) in March 2006 reduced adults by 58-66%, 45-46% and 25-37% respectively compared with untreated controls in two separate trials. No difference was observed in placement (one versus two sides of the tree) or tree size (8 years old versus 12 years old). Application at 5.6 kg ha(-1) in January 2007 reduced adults by 86% and shoot infestation by 77% in spring, and was generally better than the November and especially February applications. Even more striking results were evident on adults caged on treated plants for 25 days in March. Spiders and ladybeetles were equally abundant in treated and untreated trees. CONCLUSION: Aldicarb application at 5.6 kg ha(-1) to the bed side of mature citrus trees 2-3 months before spring growth can suppress ACP through spring without a direct effect on principal psyllid natural enemies. (c) 2008 Society of Chemical Industry</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1526-498X</sn>
<an>000260349700014</an>
<do>10.1002/ps.1612</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3845</id>
<a1>Roberts,P. D.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<a1>Adkins,Scott</a1>
<a1>Webb,Susan</a1>
<a1>Baker,Carlye</a1>
<a1>Bruton,Benny</a1>
<a1>Muchovej,Rosa</a1>
<a1>Achor,Diann</a1>
<a1>Kousik,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Whidden,Alicia L.</a1>
<a1>McAvoy,Gene</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,Phyllis</a1>
<t1>Whitefly (Bemisia tabaci) transmitted squash vein yellowing virus (SqVYV): A component of watermelon vine decline in south Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of Insect Science</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Sci.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JAN 10</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<sp>40</sp>
<op>41</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1536-2442</sn>
<an>000253056900080</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3848</id>
<a1>Rodriguez-Leyva,Esteban</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,David J.</a1>
<a1>Bravo-Mosqueda,Ernesto</a1>
<t1>Diversity and distribution of parasitoids of Anthonomus eugenii (Coleoptera : Curculionidae) from Mexico and prospects for biological control</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>90</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>693</sp>
<op>702</op>
<ab>A survey of parasitoids of the pepper weevil (Anthonomus eugenii Cano), one of the most important pests of peppers in North America, was conducted in Mexico as part of a search for biological control agents of this pest. Surveys were conducted in different years on the Pacific and Atlantic Coasts in Mexico. We recovered parasitoid species belonging to 7 genera: Triaspis eugenii Wharton &amp;amp; Lopez-Martinez, Urosigalphus sp., Bracon spp.; Catolaccus hunteri Crawford; Eurytoma spp.; Eupelmus sp.; and Ceratoneura sp. The latter species might be a newly recorded genus for this pest. Catolaccus hunteri, T. eugenii, and Urosigalphus sp. represented 96% of all recovered specimens. Triaspis eugenii was collected only in Nayarit, and Urosigalphus sp. predominated in Oaxaca; both locations are on the Pacific Coast. Catolaccus hunteri was present at every sample site. The biology of the braconids T. eugenii and Urosigalphus sp. would seem to make them best suited for biological control of pepper weevil due to their presumed host specificity and habit of attacking the host egg.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000251916200014</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3863</id>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Evans,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Bennett,F. D.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<a1>Leibee,G. L.</a1>
<a1>Webb,S. E.</a1>
<t1>A survey of parasitoids of Bemisia spp. whiteflies in Florida, the Caribbean, and Central and South America</t1>
<jf>International Journal of Pest Management</jf>
<jo>Int.J.Pest Manage.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>OCT-DEC</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>255</sp>
<op>260</op>
<ab>Wild and cultivated plants were surveyed in Florida, the Caribbean, and Latin America for parasitoids of Bemisia spp. whiteflies. Foliage samples containing late instar Bemisia nymphs were collected and held in the laboratory for emergence of adult parasitoids. Florida collections were made weekly, biweekly or monthly depending upon the time of year and location. Samples also were collected on an irregular basis in Caribbean and Latin American countries including Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Fl Salvador, Grenada, Guadeloupe, Guatemala, Honduras, Jamaica, Mexico, Puerto Rico and Venezuela. At least 20 species of parasitoids and one species of hyperparasitoid were reared from Bemisia. Encarsia pergandiella Howard (which may be a complex of species including the sympatric species E. tabacivora Viggiani), E. nigricephala Dozier and Eretmocerus sop. were the most abundant parasitoids, accounting for 59%, 16% and 13%, respectively, of the total reared from Bemisia. Encarsia meritoria Gahan, which is a complex of species but which may be mostly E. hispida De Santis in the New World, was rarely collected in Florida but was abundant at some sites in the Caribbean and Latin America.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0967-0874</sn>
<an>000078178400011</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3846</id>
<a1>Schuster,David J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<a1>Gilreath,Phyllis R.</a1>
<a1>Polston,Jane E.</a1>
<t1>Management of bemisia, TYLCV, and insecticide resistance in Florida vegetables</t1>
<jf>Journal of Insect Science</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Sci.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JAN 10</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<sp>43</sp>
<op>44</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1536-2442</sn>
<an>000253056900086</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3857</id>
<a1>Seal,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Influence of temperature and host on life history parameters of Catolaccus hunteri (Hymenoptera : Pteromalidae)</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>354</sp>
<op>360</op>
<ab>Catolaccus hunteri Crawford is an external parasitoid of cryptic Coleoptera, particularly of Bruchidae and Curculionidae in flowerbuds, small fruits, and seeds It is the most common parasitoid of the pepper weevil, Anthonomus eugenii Cano, in the United States. Mexico, and elsewhere, and was introduced from Guatemala to Hawaii for control of this pest. Studies were conducted to assess effects of temperature and host on life history parameters of C. hunter! as a step toward eventual mass rearing and inoculative release for pepper weevil control. Oviposition, postovipostion period and adult longevity were shorter at 30degreesC than at 20 or 25degreesC. Mean number of eggs oviposited per female was greater at the lower temperatures than at the highest temperature. Duration of all development stages was shorter at 30degreesC than at 20 and 25degreesC. Developmental period of C. hunteri was longer and adult longevity was shorter on boll weevil, Anthonomus grandis Boheman, than any other host. Female wasps laid most eggs on the cowpea weevil, Callosobruchus maculatis (F.), larvae. Transferring of C. hunteri reared on C. maculatus to pepper weevil or boll weevil caused a reduction in the mean number of eggs/female. Age-specific life tables and age-specific fecundity for C. hunteri were analyzed using three constant temperature regimes and five sources of host. These tables were used to calculate the innate capacity of natural increase (r(m)), the finite rate of increase (lambda), the mean generation time (T), the net reproduction rate (R-o), and the gross rate of reproduction. The results indicate that C. hunteri populations are capable of increasing in all of the environmental conditions tested in the current study. The optimum temperature for population increase for C. hunteri is 25degreesC. With respect to host suitability, greater numbers of C. hunteri female progeny were produced when this parasitoid was reared constantly and invariably on C. maculatus larvae than on any other host.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000178325900021</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3866</id>
<a1>Shapiro,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Schroeder,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Bioassay and efficacy of Bacillus thuringiensis and an organosilicone surfactant against the citrus leafminer (Lepidoptera : Phyllocnistidae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>210</op>
<ab>Two laboratory bioassays were developed for testing insect pathogens for control of larval citrus leafminer, Phyllocnistis citrella Stainton, in isolated citrus leaves. An organosilicone surfactant and several commercial preparations of Bacillus thuringiensis (Berliner) (Bt) were tested in these bioassays. One bioassay tested the effect of direct contact of a test mixture on second or third instars by injecting the mixture into a leaf mine surrounding the head of a larva. The second bioassay tested the effect of a test mixture when topically applied to the surface of a leaf mine above a larva. Effects in this second bioassay were only observed if the mixture or its components first penetrated through the mine epidermis, and then contacted and affected the insect within the mine. In both bioassays, blue food coloring was included as a tracer to observe movement of liquid into mines and through the gut of the larva. An organosilicone surfactant, Silwet L-77, enhanced penetration of solutions into mines and killed larvae when applied topically at adequate concentrations (LC50 = 0.026% in water) or when injected into mines (LC50 = 0.011%). Three commercial Bt preparations were active when applied topically at high concentrations or when injected at lower concentrations. When L-77 was added at its LC10 (0.01%) to Bt in the topical bioassay, activity of one of the three Bt preparations, or activity of all three preparations considered together, was significantly higher than without the L-77. Up to 90% mortality resulted at 0.01% L-77 and 20% Br. Mortality positively correlated with dose of all of the Bts when topically applied with 0.01% L-77. These results suggested that an increased concentration of surfactant and decreased concentration of Bt at commercial rates might be effective against citrus leafminers in citrus groves or nurseries. This was tested on old nursery trees (3 yr after planting) and young grove trees (2 yr after planting). Application of any of the three Bts plus L-77 in the nursery resulted in reduced populations of live larvae and pupae in new foliage, to approximately 50% of the population in water-treated controls. Bts without L-77 yielded counts that were intermediate to, but not significantly different from, control and combined Bt-L-77 treatments. Br applied with L-77 in the grove did not significantly reduce percentage damage to leaves and number of larvae per leaf when assessed at 14 days. However, when assessed at 21 days, damage and number of larvae were significantly reduced by treatment with Bt plus L-77 or L-77 alone. Bt and L-77 reduced leaf damage and larval numbers to a level not significantly different from treatment with Agri-Mek and spray oil. Assessed at 14 or 21 days, the L-77 treatment resulted in significant reduction of larvae.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>000074478500006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3847</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Biologically based management of Whiteflies in greenhouse vegetable production</t1>
<jf>Journal of Insect Science</jf>
<jo>J.Insect Sci.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>JAN 10</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<sp>45</sp>
<op>46</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1536-2442</sn>
<an>000253056900091</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3891</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Introduction and Evaluation of Chilocorus-Bipustulatus [Col, Coccinellidae] for Control of Parlatoria-Blanchardi [Hom, Diaspididae] in Date Groves of Niger</t1>
<jf>Entomophaga</jf>
<jo>Entomophaga</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>29</sp>
<op>39</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8959</sn>
<an>A1984SH23400004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3851</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Calvo,J.</a1>
<a1>Urbaneja,A.</a1>
<t1>Release rates for control of Bemisia tabaci (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) biotype &amp;quot;Q&amp;quot; with Eretmocerus mundus (Hymenoptera : Aphelinidae) in greenhouse tomato and pepper</t1>
<jf>Biological Control</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>124</sp>
<op>133</op>
<ab>Tomato and sweet pepper are the principal crops grown in protected culture on the southern coast of Spain. Augmentative biological control based on the parasitoid Eretmocerus mundus Mercet promises to be a useful component to manage Bemisia tabaci, the key pest of these and other horticultural crops. The present studies were undertaken with the objective of evaluating control obtained with different release rates under simulated commercial conditions. Experiments were conducted in an air-conditioned plastic greenhouse located on the southern Spanish coast during the two main horticultural cropping seasons of the region (fall-winter and spring). Host plant (tomato and sweet pepper) constituted the main plots and release rate of E. mundus (0, 1.5 and 6 m(-2)) the subplots in split plot design with four replicates. No other management practices were used against whitefly. Whitefly populations in fall reached over 80 nymphs/100 cm(2) leaf surface in pepper and twice this in tomato. Nevertheless, control using the high release rate in fall exceeded 90% in both crops, with no differences between rates in pepper, although the high rate was significantly better in tomato. Whitefly populations on pepper in spring reached densities five times greater than in fall, and yet control equalled or exceeded 95% with the high rate. Adult whiteflies on tomato were reduced by 92% in response to the high rate in spring, but nymphs were only reduced 69%. These experiments suggested that, although higher rates may be required in tomato to achieve the same level of control as in pepper, good suppression of B. tabaci could be achieved in both crops under most conditions using K mundus without recourse to insecticides. 2005 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>000232865700004</an>
<do>10.1016/j.biocontrol.2005.07.004</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3890</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Cate,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Discrimination by Ovipositing Boll-Weevils (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) Against Previously Infested Hampea (Malvaceae) Flower Buds</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1361</sp>
<op>1365</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1984TU20900038</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3883</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Korman,A. K.</a1>
<t1>Parthenogenic Development in Velocitermes Spp (Isoptera, Nasutiterminae)</t1>
<jf>Sociobiology</jf>
<jo>Sociobiology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>13</sp>
<op>24</op>
<ab>Alate reproductives of Velocitermes paucipilis Mathews (1977), Nasutitermes coxipoensis Holmgren, and an unidentified species of Velocitermes (Termitidae: Nasutiterminae) were taken from their termitaria of origin, dealated, and isolated into con-specific all-male, all-female or mixed male and female groups of 2 or 4. All-female groups of Velocitermes spp. produced viable brood consisting predominantly of soldiers, in contrast to the worker-predominant brood produced by maleXfemale groups from both genera. All-female groups of N. coxipoensis failed to produce viable eggs. Microscopic examination of thin sections from founding Velocitermes spp. revealed the presence of sperm in spermathecae of females from mixed groups and the absence in all-female groups. After 65-70 days, no differences in development of internal genitalia between or within groups of Velocitermes spp. could be observed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0361-6525</sn>
<an>A1993LY23200002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3885</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Korman,A. K.</a1>
<t1>Parthenogenic Development in Velocitermes Spp (Isoptera, Nasutiterminae)</t1>
<jf>Sociobiology</jf>
<jo>Sociobiology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>13</sp>
<op>24</op>
<ab>Alate reproductives of Velocitermes paucipilis Mathews (1977), Nasutitermes coxipoensis Holmgren, and an unidentified species of Velocitermes (Termitidae: Nasutiterminae) were taken from their termitaria of origin, dealated, and isolated into con-specific all-male, all-female or mixed male and female groups of 2 or 4. All-female groups of Velocitermes spp. produced viable brood consisting predominantly of soldiers, in contrast to the worker-predominant brood produced by maleXfemale groups from both genera. All-female groups of N. coxipoensis failed to produce viable eggs. Microscopic examination of thin sections from founding Velocitermes spp. revealed the presence of sperm in spermathecae of females from mixed groups and the absence in all-female groups. After 65-70 days, no differences in development of internal genitalia between or within groups of Velocitermes spp. could be observed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0361-6525</sn>
<an>A1993LY23200002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3869</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<t1>Selectivity of insecticides to Encarsia pergandiella (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae), an endoparasitoid of Bemisia argentifolii (Hemiptera: Aleyrodidae)</t1>
<jf>Bulletin of entomological research</jf>
<jo>Bull.Entomol.Res.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>525</sp>
<op>531</op>
<ab>Encarsia pergandiella Howard is the most abundant parasitoid of silverleaf whitefly, Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring, in south Florida vegetable fields and can contribute significantly to natural biological control of this and other whitefly species. However, quality standards, costs, and risks in commercial tomato production are high, resulting in frequent recourse to chemical control. Therefore, successful utilization of biological control could depend on compatibility of the parasitoid with selective insecticides. We tested a wide range of potentially selective insecticides, represented by a mineral oil, an insecticidal soap, a neem seed extract and synthetic and natural sugar esters, against eggs, first and third instar larvae, pupae and adults, using a pyrethroid, Capture(R) (20 g bifenthrin/1 EC), for comparison. Capture(R) residues on nymphs exposed to adult parasitoids reduced parasitization more than other materials tested, and were most toxic to all parasitoid stages. Mineral oil caused high mortality to immature parasitoids, and residues reduced parasitization of E. pergandiella. However, oil residues were much less toxic to adults if applied as a spray to leaf surfaces than as a dip to a leaf and especially glass surfaces. Ln contrast, the toxicity of Capture(R) was high regardless of bioassay method. Neem extract, insecticidal soap and both sugar esters tested had little or no effect on E. pergandiella. These latter materials could be considered selective in respect to E. pergandiella and might be used to suppress B. argentifolii without decimating parasitoid populations.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0007-4853</sn>
<an>A1997YF01600010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3867</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Liu,T. X.</a1>
<a1>Vavrina,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Response of Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera : Aleyrodidae) to imidacloprid under greenhouse, field, and laboratory conditions</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>686</sp>
<op>692</op>
<ab>The systemic insecticide imidacloprid has been used successfully to manage Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Pet-ring and whitefly-borne geminivirus on tomato in south Florida and elsewhere. We evaluated plant and whitefly responses to imidacloprid in greenhouse grown tomato, Lycopersicon esculentum Miller, transplants and field-grown fresh market staked tomato. Seedlings in transplant trays treated with 1 or 2 mg (AI) per plant applied as a drench were protected from egg deposition for up to 6 wk of exposure to a greenhouse colony of whiteflies. In the field, either 280 or 560 g (AI)/ha of imidacloprid applied to the soil at transplanting provided protection from all whitefly stages and was better than or equal to protection obtained with weekly sprays of organophosphate/pyrethroid insecticide mixtures for up to 9 wk, Movement of geminivirus infection vectored by whitefly adults was suppressed in small plots, indicating that imidacloprid acted rapidly on adults. Treated tomato or eggplant, Solanum melongena L. &amp;#39;Black Beauty&amp;#39;, functioned as trap crops by reducing whitefly numbers on adjacent untreated tomato. High application rates and persistence of imidacloprid have combined to increase the likelihood of insecticide resistance and to necessitate the development of an easily reproducible bioassay to facilitate monitoring. A leaf-dip bioassay indicated that the LC50 for 10-d-old whitefly nymphs to imidacloprid was 6.1 mg (AI)/liter and the LC90 was 32.6 mg (AI)/liter. These results could serve as a baseline for whitefly susceptibility in south Florida, given the lack of any previous exposure to imidacloprid of the-tested population.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>000074273400020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3887</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Orellana,G. J.</a1>
<t1>Field Manipulation of Nomuraea-Rileyi (Moniliales, Moniliaceae) - Effects on Soybean Defoliators in Coastal Ecuador</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>2193</sp>
<op>2195</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>A1990EM71300012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3889</id>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Sanchez,W.</a1>
<t1>Biology and Oviposition Behavior of Cydia-Fabivora (Lepidoptera, Tortricidae) in Soybean on Ecuador Coastal-Plain</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>JUN</fd>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>219</sp>
<op>225</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>A1990DK97400001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3852</id>
<a1>Toapanta,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Schuster,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Development and life history of Anthonomus eugenii (Coleoptera : Curculionidae) at constant temperatures</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>999</sp>
<op>1008</op>
<ab>Pepper weevil, Anthonomus eugenii Cano, is the major arthropod pest of peppers, Capsicum spp. L., in tropical and subtropical America. Adult weevils feed and oviposit in buds, flowers, and, especially, fruit. Larvae develop and feed inside those plant structures, thus reducing crop yields. Management is difficult and requires precise knowledge of developmental times and thresholds for maximum efficiency. Therefore, the developmental biology and life history parameters of A. eugenii were characterized in the laboratory on Capsicum annuum &amp;#39;Jalapeno fruits at seven constant temperatures ranging from 15 to 33 degrees C. A. eugenii developed through three instars at all temperatures. Linear regression analysis estimated a lower developmental threshold of 9.6 degrees C and a degree-day requirement of 256.4 for development from egg to adult. Fecundity increased with increasing temperatures to a maximum at 30 degrees C but declined at 33 degrees C. Net reproductive rate (R.), intrinsic rate of increase (r(m)), and finite rate of increase (A) were greatest at 30 degrees C, whereas development time and mortality were least at this temperature regimen. Thus, 30 degrees C proved to be the optimal temperature for population increase because a maximum fecundity of 3.1 eggs/ female/ d, the shortest development time of 12.9 d, minimal mortality, and the highest life history parameters were obtained. This information should prove useful for predicting infestations, timing insecticide applications, and using other control strategies.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>000232405800004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3856</id>
<a1>Urbaneja,A.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Host suitability of different instars of the whitefly Bemisia tabaci &amp;#39;biotype Q&amp;#39; for Eretmocerus mundus</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>153</sp>
<op>161</op>
<ab>Eretmocerus mundus Mercet is a parasitoid of Bemisia tabaci (Genn.) indigenous to the Mediterranean and is used commercially for augmentative biological control in Spain and elsewhere. A better understanding of the suitability of different host instars would help optimize production and field application. Incidence of parasitism, development time, survivorship and sex ratio were evaluated when different nymphal instars of the sweetpotato whitefly Bemisia tabaci biotype &amp;#39;Q&amp;#39; were offered for parasitization. Experiments were conducted on sweet pepper at 25 degreesC, 75% RH and 16: 8 (L: D) photoperiod. E. mundus oviposited in all nymphal instars of B. tabaci except the mature 4th instar or pharate adult (previously designated, &amp;#39;pupa&amp;#39;). Incidence of parasitism was greatest (33.8 +/- 5.1 parasitized nymphs) and development time shortest (14.1 +/- 0.1 d) when oviposition occurred under 2nd and 3rd instar nymphs compared to 1st or 4th instars. Survivorship (85%) and offspring sex ratio (39.8% female) did not differ statistically for parasitoids developing in whiteflies that were parasitized as different instars. Although 2nd and 3rd instars were clearly the most favorable host stage for E. mundus, its capacity to parasitize and develop on a wide range of host stages is a favorable characteristic for both rearing and field application.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>000189207700003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3850</id>
<a1>Urbaneja,Alberto</a1>
<a1>Sanchez,Eugenia</a1>
<a1>Stansly,Philip A.</a1>
<t1>Life history of Eretmocerus mundus, a parasitoid of Bemisia tabaci, on tomato and sweet pepper</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>FEB</fd>
<vo>52</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>25</sp>
<op>39</op>
<ab>Eretmocerus mundus is native to the Mediterranean region where it is often observed to enter greenhouses to parasitize B. tabaci on fruiting vegetables and other host crops. Fecundity on tomato and pepper was evaluated by placing newly emerged pairs (n = 15) of E. mundus on leaf discs infested with second instar B. tabaci, the preferred stage, maintained at 25 degrees C and changed daily until death of the female. All whitefly nymphs were observed for host feeding and inverted to count parasitoid eggs. Adult longevity was estimated at 7.3 +/- 0.8 d on tomato and 10.1 +/- 1.0 d on sweet pepper. Fecundity (number of hosts parasitized) was estimated 147.8 +/- 12.6 per female on tomato and 171.1 +/- 21.5 on pepper. Incidence of host feeding (number of hosts killed) was significantly greater on sweet pepper than on tomato, 15.6 +/- 1.9 vs. 10.4 +/- 1.3 nymphs per female, respectively. No significant differences were detected in the duration of life stages between sweet pepper and tomato. Preimaginal survivorship in clip cages was estimated at 69.5 +/- 11.9% on tomato and 76.6 +/- 10.5% on sweet pepper, with no statistical differences. Net reproductive rate (R (o)) was estimated at 63.8 +/- 8.2 and 51.0 +/- 4.4 on tomato and sweet pepper respectively. Generation time (T) was significantly greater on sweet pepper (19.3 +/- 0.5) than on tomato (17.9 +/- 0.4), but the estimate of intrinsic rate of increase (r (m)) was not statistically different at 0.216 +/- 0.005 and 0.219 +/- 0.004 respectively. These values are well above those reported for B. tabaci on any crop, indicating the potential of E. mundus to control this pest on solanaceous crops in the greenhouse.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1386-6141</sn>
<an>000243602200003</an>
<do>10.1007/s10526-006-9014-8</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3876</id>
<a1>Yang,Y.</a1>
<a1>Allen,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Knapp,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Frequency-Distribution of Citrus Rust Mite (Acari, Eriophyidae) Damage on Fruit in Hamlin Orange Trees</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1018</sp>
<op>1023</op>
<ab>Frequency distribution of the citrus rust mite, Phyllocoptruta oleivora (Ashmead), damage on &amp;#39;Hamlin&amp;#39; orange, Citrus sinensis fruit was studied from 24 August to 13 October 1993, in Lake Alfred, FL. The study plot consisted of 4-yr-old Hamlin orange trees, with a north-south row orientation. Fruit on the north quadrant of the tree were found to have the highest mean surface damage, followed by the east, south, and west quadrants. The frequency distribution of fruit surface damage changed with mean damage levels. When the mean damage was low most of the fruit had no rust mite damage. With increasing mean fruit damage, the proportion of fruit without damage decreased, and the proportion of fruit with higher damage correspondingly increased. The resulting frequency distribution changed from an exponential decay curve to a more or less symmetrical unimodal curve, with the peak shifting toward higher damage classes as mean fruit surface damage was increased. The frequency distribution was fitted to a e-variable logistic distribution function of mean fruit surface damage and damage class, using maximum likelihood estimation method. Fruit without rust mite damage was considered a discrete point at zero, and its relative frequency was determined as the height of the cumulative logistic at zero. The model approximated the actual data well at low mean fruit surface damage, but gave a poor fit at high mean values.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1995TA80500005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3877</id>
<a1>Yang,Y.</a1>
<a1>Allen,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Knapp,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Relationship between Population-Density of Citrus Rust Mite (Acari, Eriophyidae) and Damage to Hamlin Orange Fruit</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1024</sp>
<op>1031</op>
<ab>Six studies were conducted to quantify the relationship between fruit surface damage of &amp;#39;Hamlin&amp;#39; orange, Citrus sinensis, and population denisty of die citrus rust mite, Phyllocoptruta oleivora (Ashmead). Over time, the damage rate per mite-day increased in sigmoid fashion mainly as a result of a sigmoid increase in cumulative mite-days. The sigmoid increase in cumulative mite-days resulted from the single-peaked, more or less symmetrically-shaped mite population growth. Increasing fruit maturity increased susceptibility to mite feeding. This was indicated by a decline in mite-days required to cause a given percentage of surface damage as fruit maturity increased. Tree age and grove location did not seem to have obvious effect on the general trend in damage rate. A mathematical model was developed to describe the relationship between cumulative damage and cumulative mite-days. The model could be used to predict fruit surface damage based on mite population data.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1995TA80500006</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3882</id>
<a1>Yang,Y. B.</a1>
<a1>Allen,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Knapp,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<t1>Citrus Rust Mite (Acari, Eriophyidae) Damage Effects on Hamlin Orange Fruit-Growth and Drop</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>244</sp>
<op>247</op>
<ab>Effects of early-season damage by the citrus rust mite, Phyllocoptruta oleivora (Ashmead), on &amp;#39;Hamlin&amp;#39; orange fruit growth and drop were studied from 8 June through 17 December 1991, in Hendry County, FL. &amp;#39;Hamlin&amp;#39; fruit drop increased with increasing fruit surface damage by the citrus rust mite. The data also indicated a slightly accelerated fruit drop with increasing mite damage and time. The overall data suggested a slight negative relationship between fruit size and mite damage. Cumulative percentage drop and percentage diameter increase were fitted to two-variable logistic functions of damage and time. These functions could be used in management models for calculating volume losses from rust mite damage.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<an>A1994NM71200004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
