<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2695</id>
<a1>Bentley,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Hogsette,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Response of adult mosquitoes to light-emitting diodes placed in resting boxes and in the field</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>285</sp>
<op>291</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal/physiology</k1>
<k1>Color</k1>
<k1>Culicidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Sex Characteristics</k1>
<ab>The response of adult mosquitoes to 4 light-emitting diode (LED) wavelengths was evaluated using diode-equipped sticky cards (DESCs) and diode-equipped resting boxes at 2 sites in north central Florida. Wavelengths evaluated were blue (470 nm), green (502 nm), red (660 nm), and infrared (IR) (860 nm). When trapping with DESCs, 15 mosquito species from 7 genera (Aedes, Anopheles, Coquillettidia, Culex, Mansonia, Psorophora, and Uranotaenia) were captured. Overall, approximately 43.8% of all mosquitoes were trapped on DESCs fitted with green LEDs. Significantly more females of Aedes infirmatus, Aedes vexans, and Culex nigripalpus were captured on DESCs fitted with blue LEDs compared with red or IR LEDs. DESCs with blue LEDs captured significantly more Culex erraticus females than those with IR LEDs. Using resting boxes, 12 species from 5 genera (Anopheles, Coquillettidia, Culex, Mansonia, and Uranotaenia) were collected. Resting boxes without LEDs captured 1,585 mosquitoes (22.2% of total). The fewest number of mosquitoes (16.7%) were collected from boxes affixed with the blue LEDs. Significantly more Anopheles quadrimaculatus females were aspirated from resting boxes fitted with red and IR LEDs than from those with blue or green LEDs, or from the unlit control. Blood-fed mosquitoes were recovered in highest numbers from unlit resting boxes, followed by resting boxes fitted with green, IR, and blue LEDs. Culex erraticus accounted for the majority of blood-fed mosquitoes followed by Coquillettidia perturbans. No blood-fed mosquitoes were recovered from resting boxes fitted with red LEDs.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, Institute of Food and Agriculture Sciences, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19852218</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19852218</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2851</id>
<a1>Costanzo,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Moore,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Lee,R. E. Jr</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Wyman,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Influence of soil hydric parameters on the winter cold hardiness of a burrowing beetle, Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Say)</t1>
<jf>Journal of comparative physiology.B, Biochemical, systemic, and environmental physiology</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>167</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>169</sp>
<op>176</op>
<k1>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</k1>
<k1>overwintering</k1>
<k1>mortality</k1>
<k1>soil water content</k1>
<k1>body water</k1>
<k1>body temperature</k1>
<k1>water balance</k1>
<k1>freezing</k1>
<k1>soil temperature</k1>
<k1>soil water potential</k1>
<k1>soil texture</k1>
<k1>cold tolerance</k1>
<k1>supercooling</k1>
<k1>microenvironments</k1>
<k1>crystallization temperature</k1>
<k1>inoculative freezing</k1>
<k1>L600</k1>
<k1>L001</k1>
<k1>J200</k1>
<k1>F821</k1>
<ab>This investigation examined the influence of soil moisture and associated parameters on the cold hardiness of the Colorado potato beetle (Leptinotarsa decemlineata Say), a temperate-zone species that overwinters in terrestrial burrows. The body mass and water content of adult beetles kept in sand at 4 degrees C varied over a 16-week period of diapause according to the substratum&amp;#39;s moisture content. Changes in body water content, in turn, influenced the crystallization temperature (range -3.3 to -18.4 degrees C; n = 417), indicating that environmental moisture indirectly determined supercooling capacity, a measure of physiological cold hardiness. Beetles held in dry sand readily tolerated a 24-h exposure to temperatures ranging from 0 degrees to -5 degrees C, but those chilled in sand containing as little as 1.7% water (dry mass) had elevated mortality. Thus, burrowing in dry soils not only promotes supercooling via its effect on water balance, but may also inhibit inoculative freezing. Mortality of beetles exposed to -5 degrees C for 24 h was lower in substrates composed of sand, clay and/or peat (36-52%) than in pure silica sand (78%) having an identical water content (17.0% dry mass). In addition to moisture, the texture, structure, water potential, and other physico-chemical attributes of soil may strongly influence the cold hardiness and overwintering survival of burrowing insects.</ab>
<sn>0174-1578</sn>
<an>IND20619560</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL QP33.J681</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2697</id>
<a1>Doyle,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Allan,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of residual bifenthrin applied to landscape vegetation against Aedes albopictus</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>183</op>
<k1>Aedes</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Insecticides</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Pesticide Residues</k1>
<k1>Plants</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<ab>The daytime biting mosquito Aedes albopictus is a nuisance pest commonly found in suburban yards. The recommended course of treatment for Ae. albopictus is to keep yards free of water-holding containers; however, infestations may require additional control methods such as residual pesticide applications to vegetation. Five plants commonly found in yards or in uncultivated areas in Gainesville, FL were chosen as substrates for evaluation of the effectiveness of residual bifenthrin against 5-7-day-old female Ae. albopictus. Knockdown of mosquitoes after 1 h of exposure was highest the day of and 7 days after treatment. Plant species clearly impacted the effectiveness of residual bifenthrin. One-hour knockdown 7 days after treatment remained high (&amp;gt;62%) only on azalea and holly bush vegetation. Knockdown counts 24 h after exposure demonstrated that residual efficacy of bifenthrin was highest on azalea, with &amp;gt;77% mortality for up to 35 days. Additional bioassays revealed significant differences in the knockdown rates of male, female, gravid, and blood-fed Ae. albopictus exposed to residual bifenthrin treatments, with the highest knockdown observed on the day of and 7 days after treatment.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Pesticide Residues); 0 (Pyrethrins); 82657-04-3 (bifenthrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service, Center for Medical, Agricultural, and Veterinary Entomology, 1600 SW 23rd Drive, Gainesville, FL 32608, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19653500</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19653500</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3103</id>
<a1>Fishel,Frederick</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,Phillip E.</a1>
<t1>SM 2 Agricultural Animal Pest Control</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<ed>2nd</ed>
<pb>University of Florida, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, FL</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2819</id>
<a1>Geden,CJ</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,PE</a1>
<t1>Development of Spalangia cameroni and Muscidifurax raptor (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) on Live House Fly (Diptera: Muscidae) Pupae and Pupae Killed by Heat Shock, Irradiation, and Cold</t1>
<jf>Environmental Entomology</jf>
<jo>Environ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>34</sp>
<op>39</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Heat shock</k1>
<k1>Mortality</k1>
<k1>Progeny</k1>
<k1>Parasitoids</k1>
<k1>Temperature effects</k1>
<k1>Biological control</k1>
<k1>Radiation</k1>
<k1>gamma Radiation</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Pteromalidae</k1>
<k1>Muscidifurax raptor</k1>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>Hymenoptera</k1>
<k1>Muscidae</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<ab>The objective of this study was to evaluate the suitability of killed house fly (Musca domestica L) pupae for production of two economically important pupal parasitoids. Two-day-old fly pupae were subjected to heat shock treatments of varying temperatures and durations in an oven at greater than or equal to 70% RH; exposure to temperatures of 55 degree C or higher for 15 min or longer resulted in 100% mortality. Exposure to 50 degree C resulted in 40 and 91% mortality at 15 and 60 min, respectively. All (100%) pupae placed in a -80 degree C freezer were killed after 10-min exposure; exposure times of &amp;lt; 5 min resulted in &amp;lt; 21% mortality. Progeny production of Spalangia cameroni Perkins and Muscidifurax raptor Girault and Sanders (Hymeoptera: Pteromalidae) from pupae killed by heat shock or 50 kR of gamma radiation was not significantly different from production on live hosts on the day when pupae were killed. Freeze-killed pupae produced 16% fewer S. cameroni than live pupae and an equivalent amount of M. raptor progeny on the day when pupae were killed. When killed pupae were stored in freezer bags at 4 degree C for 4 mo, heat-killed, irradiated, and freeze-killed pupae remained as effective for production of M. raptor as live pupae. Production of S. cameroni on heat-killed and irradiated pupae was equal to parasitoid production on live pupae for up to 2 mo of storage, after which production on killed pupae declined to 63% of that observed with live pupae. Production of S. cameroni on freeze-killed pupae was 73-78% of production using live pupae during weeks 2-8 of storage and declined to 41 and 28% after 3 and 4 mo, respectively. Killing pupae by heat shock provides a simple and low-cost method for stockpiling high-quality hosts for mass-rearing both of these filth fly biological control agents.</ab>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Freezer bags; Heat shock; House fly pupae; Ice water submersion; Irradiation; Live house fly pupae; Mortality; Progeny production; Pupae; Sex ratio; Object Taxonomic Terms: Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Pteromalidae; Object Statistical Terms: Analysis of Variance (ANOVA); Mean; P-value; Standard Error; Studentized Score; Tukey Procedure&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 1. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne1%2F00008%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34%2Fobj%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34-t01.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=916e579313a4661e9687493c4209b944&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 1. Mortality of 2-d-old house fly pupae after exposure to heat shock&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Heat shock; House fly pupae; Mortality; Object Taxonomic Terms; Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Object Statistical Terms; Mean; Standard Error&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 2. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne1%2F00008%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34%2Fobj%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34-t02.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=ce746b48c16f58b65ed1629e6945b1da&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 2. Mortality of 2-d-old house fly pupae after exposure to freezing or submersion in an ice water bath&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; House fly pupae; Ice water submersion; Mortality; Object Taxonomic Terms; Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Pteromalidae; Object Statistical Terms; Mean; Standard Error&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 3. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne1%2F00008%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34%2Fobj%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34-t03.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=5aa6943f8029754808884679d28172e6&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 3. Mean (SE) progeny production and sex ratio of M. raptor and S. cameroni on live house fly pupae and pupae killed by either irradiation (50-kR gamma irradiation), heat shock (15 min at 55°C), or cold (10 min at −80°C)&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Heat shock; Irradiation; Live house fly pupae; Progeny production; Sex ratio; Object Taxonomic Terms; Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Pteromalidae; Object Statistical Terms; Analysis of Variance (ANOVA); Mean; P-value; Standard Error&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 4. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne1%2F00008%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34%2Fobj%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34-t04.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=65231343c415e1ce3a1c5a1bfce3dc25&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 4. Mean (SE) progeny production and sex ratio of M. raptor on live house fly pupae and pupae killed by irradiation (50-kR gamma irradiation), heat shock (15 min at 55°C), or cold (10 min at −80°C) and stored at 4°C in freezer bags for 2 wk to 4 mo&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Freezer bags; Heat shock; Irradiation; Live house fly pupae; Pupae; Object Taxonomic Terms; Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Pteromalidae; Object Statistical Terms; Analysis of Variance (ANOVA); Mean; P-value; Standard Error; Studentized Score; Tukey Procedure&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 5. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne1%2F00008%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34%2Fobj%2Fi0046-225X-36-1-34-t05.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=d9e03d5e59c12845294d86795b7c6265&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 5. Mean (SE) progeny production and sex ratio of S. cameroni on live house fly pupae and pupae killed by irradiation (50-kR gamma irradiation), heat shock (15 min at 55°C), or cold (10 min at −80°C) and stored at 4°C in freezer bags for 2 wk to 4 mo&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Freezer bags; Heat shock; Irradiation; Live house fly pupae; Object Taxonomic Terms; Hymenoptera; Muscidae; Muscidifurax raptor; Pteromalidae; Object Statistical Terms; Analysis of Variance (ANOVA); Mean; P-value; Standard Error; Studentized Score; Tukey Procedure</no>
<pb>Entomological Society of America</pb>
<pp>9301 Annapolis Rd. Lanham MD 20706 USA, [mailto:http://www.entsoc.org/]</pp>
<sn>0046-225X</sn>
<ad>USDA-ARS, Center for Medical, Agricultural and Veterinary Entomology, 1600 SW 23rd Dr., Gainesville, FL 32608; and Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620</ad>
<an>7767437</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>D 04040 Ecosystem and Ecology Studies; Z 05340 Ecology and Behavior</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts; Ecology Abstracts; 1B</sf>
<lk>http://journals.allenpress.com/jrnlserv/?request=get-abstract&amp;issn=0046-225X&amp;volume=36&amp;issue=1&amp;page=34</lk>
<do>10.1603/0046-225X(2007)36[34:DOSCAM]2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2703</id>
<a1>Hamm,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Reasor,C. A.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Scott,J. G.</a1>
<t1>Resistance to cyfluthrin and tetrachlorvinphos in the lesser mealworm, Alphitobius diaperinus, collected from the eastern United States</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>62</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>673</sp>
<op>677</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Appalachian Region</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Larva/classification/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Nitriles/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Tenebrio/classification/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Tetrachlorvinphos/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>The lesser mealworm, Alphitobius diaperinus (Panzer), is an important pest in poultry facilities. The toxicity of cyfluthrin and tetrachlorvinphos to five strains of the lesser mealworm was compared with the toxicity to a susceptible laboratory strain. Bioassays were carried out with both larvae and adults. For the susceptible strain, cyfluthrin and tetrachlorvinphos had similar toxicity to adults, but cyfluthrin was 5 times more toxic to larvae when compared with tetrachlorvinphos. High levels of resistance to tetrachlorvinphos in two beetle strains were detected in both larvae and adults, although these strains were heterogeneous and still contained susceptible individuals. Resistance to cyfluthrin ranged from 1.7- to 9.5-fold for adults and from 0.5- to 29-fold for larvae at the LC(95). Overall, the patterns of resistance did not mirror the insecticide use patterns reported at these facilities. The implications of these results to management of the lesser mealworms are discussed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100898744; 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Nitriles); 0 (Pyrethrins); 22248-79-9 (Tetrachlorvinphos); 68359-37-5 (cyfluthrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1526-498X; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Comstock Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853-0901, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16770758</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.1230</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16770758</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3093</id>
<a1>Hoebeke ER</a1>
<a1>Kaufman PE</a1>
<a1>Glenister CS</a1>
<a1>Stringham SM.</a1>
<t1>New neartic record for Epitranus clavatus F. (Hymenoptera: Chalcididae).</t1>
<jo>Proc Entomol Soc Wash</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<vo>105</vo>
<sp>1062</sp>
<op>1063</op>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2852</id>
<a1>Hoy,C. W.</a1>
<a1>Wyman,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Vaughn,T. T.</a1>
<a1>East,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P.</a1>
<t1>Food, ground cover, and Colorado potato beetle (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) dispersal in late summer</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>89</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>963</sp>
<op>969</op>
<k1>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</k1>
<k1>adults</k1>
<k1>overwintering</k1>
<k1>soil</k1>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>leaves</k1>
<k1>tubers</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>depth</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>food availability</k1>
<k1>straw mulches</k1>
<k1>Ohio</k1>
<k1>Wisconsin</k1>
<k1>ground cover</k1>
<k1>availability</k1>
<k1>dispersal</k1>
<k1>spring emergence from soil</k1>
<k1>mulch depth</k1>
<k1>F821</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<ab>Factors that affect adult Colorado potato beetle, Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Say), dispersal before overwintering were examined in field studies. Test plots were established next to a planting of potatoes that served as a source of beetles to test the effects of food type and depth of straw mulch on adult dispersal. Beetle numbers above ground and in the plots during September, number in the soil within plots during late autumn and winter, and number emerging from the plots during spring were measured. In both years of the study and by each measure of beetle abundance, straw mulch had no impact on beetle dispersal but food source did. Availability of foliage as food resulted in a larger number of beetles in the plots, both on plants before overwintering and in the soil, than did potato tubers. Mulch depth had no impact on overwintering depth of beetles in the soil or average date of emergence in the spring. If concentrated in space, beetles might be controlled more efficiently by chemical or nonchemical means, such as propane flaming or manipulation of the soil environment. This study demonstrates that adult dispersal of Colorado potato beetles could be manipulated to concentrate the adults in space before and during overwintering.</ab>
<no>Journal of economic entomology. Aug 1996. v. 89 (4); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>IND20547653</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL 421 J822</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3104</id>
<a1>Kaufman PE</a1>
<a1>Koehler PG</a1>
<a1>Butler JF.</a1>
<t1>How do external parasites impact dairy cattle?</t1>
<jf>Progressive Dairyman</jf>
<jo>Progressive Dairyman</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>January 1, 2008</fd>
<is>1</is>
<sp>31</sp>
<op>35</op>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3102</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Gerry,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Scott,J. G.</a1>
<t1>Monitoring susceptibility of house flies (Musca domestica L.) in the United States to imidacloprid</t1>
<jf>J Agric Urban Entomol</jf>
<jo>J.Agric.Urban Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<vo>23</vo>
<sp>195</sp>
<op>200</op>
<ds>google</ds>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2838</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Burgess,M.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Glenister,C.</a1>
<t1>Population dynamics of manure inhabiting arthropods under an integrated pest management (IPM) program in New York poultry facilities. 3. Case studies</t1>
<jf>Journal of applied poultry research</jf>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Spring</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>90</sp>
<op>103</op>
<k1>hens</k1>
<k1>poultry manure</k1>
<k1>feces</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>case studies</k1>
<k1>parasitoids</k1>
<k1>natural enemies</k1>
<k1>insecticides</k1>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>Alphitobius diaperinus</k1>
<k1>pest control</k1>
<k1>mites</k1>
<k1>carcinops pumilio</k1>
<k1>infestation</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<no>Journal of applied poultry research. Spring 2002. v. 11 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1056-6171</sn>
<an>IND23271608</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SF481.J68</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2699</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Butler,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Nelson,C.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of the Mosquito Sentinel 360 trap in Florida residential environments</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>528</sp>
<op>533</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Carbon Dioxide</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Octanols</k1>
<ab>The Mosquito Sentinel 360 (MS) trap was evaluated in back yards of 6 residences in and near Gainesville, FL. Carbon dioxide and blue-light-emitting diode-modified Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) traps were utilized as a human substitute host to provide a measure of the effectiveness of the MS trap in reducing mosquito presence at the back door area of the houses. At 5 of the 6 residences, a MS trap was operated with or without carbon dioxide, Lurex3 + octenol, or an experimental attractant. All MS traps were operated in tandem with a CDC trap, with the 6th site occupied only by a CDC trap. Over 67,000 mosquitoes from 19 species were recovered over the 12 trial days. Of these species, Anopheles crucians, An. quadrimaculatus, Coquillettidia perturbans, Culex erraticus, and Mansonia titillans were the predominant, nuisance, and medically important species captured and accounted for &amp;gt;92% of specimens recovered. Overall, attractant-modified MS traps captured more mosquitoes than the paired CDC trap. Carbon dioxide was found to greatly increase the capture of mosquitoes; however, the Lurex3 + octenol combination was significant with Cq. perturbans. All attractant-modified MS traps captured more Cx. erraticus and Ma. titillans than did the CDC, CO2-baited host mimic traps. The use of the MS 360 trap will undoubtedly require the addition of baits and perhaps the inclusion of a host masking or repellent approach to ensure protection from nuisance mosquitoes in residential environments.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; 0 (Octanols); 124-38-9 (Carbon Dioxide); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19181060</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19181060</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2706</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Harrington,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Waldron,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>The importance of agricultural tire habitats for mosquitoes of public health importance in New York State</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>171</sp>
<op>176</op>
<k1>Aedes</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anopheles</k1>
<k1>Culex</k1>
<k1>Culicidae</k1>
<k1>Dairying</k1>
<k1>Environment</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Insect Vectors</k1>
<k1>Larva</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Ochlerotatus</k1>
<k1>Reproduction</k1>
<ab>The presence of mosquito species breeding in agricultural &amp;quot;bunker tires&amp;quot; on dairy farms in New York state was evaluated. Twelve species of mosquitoes (Aedes vexans, Anopheles barberi, An. punctipenriis, An. perplexens, Culex pipiens pipiens, Cx. restuans, Cx. salinarius, Cx. territans, Toxorhynchites rutilus septentrionalis, Ochlerotatus atropalpus, Oc. japonicus japonicus, and Oc. triseriatus) were collected from 8 New York state dairy farms in 2001 and from 17 dairy farms in 2002. All but 2 of these species have been found naturally infected with arboviruses and could be important vectors affecting human and animal health. Because of the potential public and animal health importance of the invasive species Oc. j. japonicus, active surveillance to identify breeding sites and distribution of this mosquito is essential. In 2001, Oc. j. japonicus was recovered from 5 of 8 central New York dairy farms surveyed. In 2002, Oc. j. japonicus was recovered from 4 of the same dairy farms plus an additional dairy out of 5 surveyed. This species appears to be established on dairy farms in the south, central, and eastern regions of New York state, with greatest abundance in the southeastern region. A single Oc. j. japonicus larva was collected from the northern region on the final sampling date in September 2002. Our data demonstrate that agricultural tire habitats can be productive breeding sites for arbovirus vectors. As a consequence, these habitats should not be ignored in vector control and surveillance programs.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8511299; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Comstock Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16033118</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16033118</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2849</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Lloyd,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Kumar,R.</a1>
<a1>Campbell,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Boxler,D. J.</a1>
<t1>The differences between horn fly densities on cattle pastured in Wyoming and Nebraska as possibly influenced by elevation</t1>
<jf>Southwestern Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Southwest.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>121</op>
<k1>cows</k1>
<k1>heifers</k1>
<k1>Haematobia irritans</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>altitude</k1>
<k1>pastures</k1>
<k1>temporal variation</k1>
<k1>Wyoming</k1>
<k1>Nebraska</k1>
<k1>infestation</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<no>Southwestern entomologist. June 1999. v. 24 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0147-1724</sn>
<an>IND22039260</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL QL461.S65</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2850</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Lloyd,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Lysyk,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Kumar,R.</a1>
<t1>Horn fly susceptibility to Diazinon, Fenthion, and Permethrin at selected elevations in Wyoming</t1>
<jf>Journal of Agricultural and Urban Entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Agric.Urban Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>141</sp>
<op>157</op>
<k1>Haematobia irritans</k1>
<k1>diazinon</k1>
<k1>fenthion</k1>
<k1>permethrin</k1>
<k1>insecticide resistance</k1>
<k1>altitude</k1>
<k1>heat sums</k1>
<k1>Wyoming</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<no>Journal of agricultural and urban entomology. Apr 1999. v. 16 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1523-5475</sn>
<an>IND22032878</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB599 .J69</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2710</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Long,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Impact of exposure length and pupal source on Muscidifurax raptorellus and Nasonia vitripennis (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) parasitism in a New York poultry facility</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>998</sp>
<op>1003</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Host-Parasite Interactions</k1>
<k1>Houseflies/parasitology</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Pest Control, Biological/methods</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Pupa</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Wasps/physiology</k1>
<ab>Commercially obtained Nasonia vitripennis Walker and Muscidifurax raptorellus Kogan &amp;amp; Legner were released weekly for 12 wk into a high-rise, caged-layer poultry house. After the release period, parasitoids were sampled using sentinel house fly (Musca domestica L.) pupae that were either laboratory-reared or field-collected as larvae and exposed for 2, 4, 7, and 14 d. Parasitoid-induced mortality was observed in 31% of laboratory colony pupae and in 26% of field-collected pupae, whereas successful parasitism rates of 48 and 51% were observed from these pupal sources, respectively. Parasitism was primarily by M. raptorellus (88%), and Muscidifurax raptor Girault &amp;amp; Sanders (11%), while N. vitripennis accounted for &amp;lt;1%. Percent female progeny ranged from 43%, in M. raptorellus to 76% in N. vitripennis. Parasitoid emergence from 2-d exposed sentinel pupae was the lowest of all treatments. Parasitoid emergence from 7-d exposed sentinel pupae was the highest of all treatments. We found no differences between pupal source, suggesting that when sampling for M. raptor, M. raptorellus, and N. vitripennis, in poultry facilities, pupal source is not a confounding factor.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 2985127R; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0493; 0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA. pek4@cornell.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11561864</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11561864</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2714</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Long,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Glenister,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Larval production from field-collected Carcinops pumilio (Coleoptera: Histeridae) following three starvation periods</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>278</sp>
<op>281</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Beetles/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Larva</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Oviposition/physiology</k1>
<k1>Starvation</k1>
<ab>Carcinops pumilio (Erichson) were collected from high-rise, caged-layer poultry facilities using two trapping methods, a blacklight pitfall trap and a mesh-bottomed trap placed on poultry manure. Starvation for 14 d significantly reduced larval production during the first 3-d oviposition period regardless of trapping method. Beetles collected with blacklight traps and subsequently starved for 14 d had higher larval production in the third through fifth oviposition periods than those fed daily, indicating that lack of nutrition was a limiting factor in C. pumilio larval production. No differences were observed in larval production, after the first oviposition period, between the 14-d starved and daily fed groups collected with the mesh-bottom trap. In all blacklight-captured treatments, larval production was lowest during the first oviposition period with the largest differences found among the three starved treatments. Larval production in the 14-d starved treatment increased significantly during the later oviposition periods in mesh-bottom trap studies. Within the fed treatment, larval production was consistently greater among beetles collected with the mesh-bottom trap than among beetles collected with blacklight traps.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11296835</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11296835</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2715</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Long,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Glenister,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Prey- and density-mediated dispersal in Carcinops pumilio (Coleoptera: Histeridae), a predator of house fly (Diptera: Muscidae) eggs and larvae</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>929</sp>
<op>932</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Beetles</k1>
<k1>Demography</k1>
<k1>Houseflies</k1>
<k1>Larva</k1>
<k1>Mites</k1>
<k1>Ovum</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<k1>Predatory Behavior</k1>
<ab>Carcinops pumilio (Erichson) were collected using two trapping methods: a black light pitfall trap and a mesh-bottomed trap placed on poultry manure. C. pumilio collected with black lights and subsequently starved had a significantly higher dispersal rate during days 1-3 than fully fed groups. When densities of &amp;lt; 500 Caloglyphus berlesei (Michael) (Acarina: Acaridae) per 50 C. pumilio were provided, mite availability had a significant effect on dispersal of beetles captured with both black light traps and the mesh-bottomed trap during the day 1-3 period. Our results indicate that the availability of acceptable food sources can delay and possibly prevent dispersal by C. pumilio. Black light-captured beetles appeared to be in a state of dispersal when captured. A subset of dispersing beetles was present in groups captured with the mesh-bottomed trap.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Comstock Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11126552</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11126552</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2713</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Long,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Waldron,J. K.</a1>
<t1>Parasitism rates of Muscidifurax raptorellus and Nasonia vitripennis (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) after individual and paired releases in New York poultry facilities</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>593</sp>
<op>598</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Houseflies/parasitology</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Pest Control, Biological/methods</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Wasps</k1>
<ab>Commercially reared parasitoids were released into three high-rise, caged-layer poultry houses; one house received only N. vitripennis Walker, the second house received only M. raptorellus Kogan &amp;amp; Legner, and the third house received an equal ratio of both species. Overall, house fly parasitism by M. raptorellus was never higher than 7% in any house. Most parasitism in the M. raptorellus release house was attributed to N. vitripennis. Parasitism of house fly pupae by M. raptorellus did not significantly increase during or after the 6-wk release period in the house that received both parasitoids. However, a depression in total parasitism was not detected when releases of the two species were made in this house.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985127R; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0493; 0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11332859</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11332859</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2691</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Mann,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Butler,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of semiochemical toxicity to Aedes aegypti, Ae. albopictus and Anopheles quadrimaculatus (Diptera: Culicidae)</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>497</sp>
<op>504</op>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Mosquitoes are the most important vectors of human pathogens. Wide-scale use of pesticides has led to the development of resistance to most common insecticide groups. The need to develop novel products that have a low impact on human health and the environment is well established. The toxicity of selected semiochemicals with molecular structures indicative of insecticidal activity was determined against adult Aedes aegypti (L.) and Anopheles quadrimaculatus (Say). The two most active insecticides against Ae. aegypti were also evaluated against Ae. albopictus (Skuse). RESULTS: Fifteen semiochemicals classified as terpenoid alcohols, ketones or carboxylic esters showed toxicity to both mosquito species. Geranyl acetone (LC(50) = 38.51 microg cm(-2)) followed by citronellol (LC(50) = 48.55 microg cm(-2)) were the most toxic compounds to Ae. aegypti, while geraniol and lavonax, with LC(50) values of 31.88 and 43.40 microg cm(-2), showed the highest toxicity to An. quadrimaculatus. Both geranyl acetone and citronellol were highly toxic to Ae. albopioctus. No semiochemical showed fumigation activity against either species. All semiochemicals persisted for less than 24 h when tested on filter paper. CONCLUSION: Quantification of LC(50) values of several semiochemicals against Ae. Aegypti, An. quadrimaculatus and Ae. albopioctus showed that semiochemicals not only modify insect behaviors but also hold potential as potent insecticides for mosquito control programs.</ab>
<no>JID: 100898744; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1526-4998; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20127888</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.1899</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20127888</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2694</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Nunez,S. C.</a1>
<a1>Mann,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Geden,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Scharf,M. E.</a1>
<t1>Nicotinoid and pyrethroid insecticide resistance in houseflies (Diptera: Muscidae) collected from Florida dairies</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>290</sp>
<op>294</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Dairying</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Imidazoles/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Insecticide Resistance</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Muscidae/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Nitro Compounds/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Permethrin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The housefly, Musca domestica L., continues to be a major pest of confined livestock operations. Houseflies have developed resistance to most chemical classes, and new chemistries for use in animal agriculture are increasingly slow to emerge. Five adult housefly strains from four Florida dairy farms were evaluated for resistance to four insecticides (beta-cyfluthrin, permethrin, imidacloprid and nithiazine).RESULTS: Significant levels of tolerance were found in most field strains to all insecticides, and in some cases substantial resistance was apparent (as deduced from comparison with prior published results). At the LC(90) level, greater than 20-fold resistance was found in two of the fly strains for permethrin and one fly strain for imidacloprid. Beta-cyfluthrin LC(90) resistance ratios exceeded tenfold resistance in three fly strains. The relatively underutilized insecticide nithiazine had the lowest resistance ratios; however, fourfold LC(90) resistance was observed in one southern Florida fly strain. Farm insecticide use and its impact on resistance selection in Florida housefly populations are discussed.CONCLUSION: Housefly resistance to pyrethroids is widespread in Florida. Imidacloprid resistance is emerging, and tolerance was observed to both imidacloprid and nithiazine. If these insecticides are to retain efficacy, producer use must be restrained.</ab>
<no>JID: 100898744; 0 (Imidazoles); 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Nitro Compounds); 0 (Pyrethrins); 105827-78-9 (imidacloprid); 52645-53-1 (Permethrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1526-4998; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA. pkaufman@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19904713</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.1872</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19904713</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2704</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Reasor,C.</a1>
<a1>Murray,K. D.</a1>
<a1>Waldron,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of a barrier to inhibit lesser mealworm (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) and dermestidae movement in high-rise, caged-layer poultry facilities</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1744</sp>
<op>1749</op>
<k1>Animal Migration</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Beetles/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<k1>Housing, Animal</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Larva</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Tenebrio/growth &amp; development/physiology</k1>
<ab>An evaluation of a mechanical barrier to prevent movement of adult and larval lesser mealworm, Alphitobius diaperinus (Panzer); larder beetle, Dermestes lardarius L.; and hide beetle, Dermestes maculatus De Geer was conducted in caged-layer poultry facilities in New York and Maine. The barrier, a plastic collar wrapped around building support posts, proved highly effective at preventing movement of adult lesser mealworms. Significantly more lesser mealworm larvae were recovered from cardboard collar beetle traps placed below both washed and unwashed barriers than from traps placed above washed and unwashed barriers. Similarly, significantly more adult Dermestes were recovered from traps placed below washed barriers than from above both washed and unwashed barriers. The level of fly specking on the barrier was found to have no significant impact on the numbers of adult lesser mealworms and adult and larval Dermestes recovered either above or below barriers. Fly specking level did significantly impact the numbers of lesser mealworm larvae recovered above the barrier. Although washed barriers provided the greatest deterrent to adult lesser mealworms, the presence of the barrier, regardless of the level of fly specking, provided a significant deterrent to beetle climbing success. Washed barriers further reduced climbing success by lesser mealworm larvae by 17%, Dermestes adults by 7-28%, and Dermestes larvae by 33-38%. The high level of climbing observed by adult lesser mealworms suggests that the impact of adult beetle movement toward birds should be considered in its importance in building damage, disease transmission, feed infestation, and bird productivity and health. Observations on cost and maintenance of the barrier are discussed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985127R; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0493; 0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16334349</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16334349</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2836</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Reasor,C.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Ketzis,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Arends,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Beauveria bassiana applications against adult house fly, Musca domestica, in commercial caged-layer poultry facilities in New York state</t1>
<jf>Biological control : theory and application in pest management</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>360</sp>
<op>367</op>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>Beauveria bassiana</k1>
<k1>entomopathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>biological control agents</k1>
<k1>poultry housing</k1>
<k1>integrated pest management</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>pyrethrins</k1>
<k1>parasitoids</k1>
<k1>Hymenoptera</k1>
<k1>parasitism</k1>
<k1>predatory insects</k1>
<k1>insect control</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Carcinops pumilio</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<ab>Applications of a commercially produced Beauveria bassiana product, balEnce, were compared with pyrethrin treatments for the control of adult house flies in New York high-rise, caged-layer poultry facilities. An integrated fly management program, which included the release of house fly pupal hymenopteran parasitoids, was used at all facilities. Adult house fly populations were lower in B. bassiana-treated facilities during the spray and post-spray periods, as recorded on spot cards. Concurrently, the numbers of house fly larvae recovered in B. bassiana-treated facilities were less than one-half that of the pyrethrin-treated facilities. House fly pupal parasitism levels were low, but similar under both treatment regimes. The numbers of adult and larval Carcinops pumilio, a predatory beetle, recovered from B. bassiana-treated facilities were 43 and 66% greater than from the pyrethrin-treated facilities, respectively.</ab>
<no>Biological control : theory and application in pest management. 2005 June, v. 33, no. 3; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>IND43710387</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB925.B5</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2705</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Reasor,C.</a1>
<a1>Waldron,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of adult lesser mealworm (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) using soil incorporation of poultry manure</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>98</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1739</sp>
<op>1743</op>
<k1>Agriculture/methods</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Manure</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Soil</k1>
<k1>Tenebrio/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>The effectiveness of manure incorporation in reducing the numbers of adult lesser mealworms emerging from caged-layer poultry manure applied to agricultural fields was examined in summer 2002 and 2004. Incorporation treatments included control (no incorporation), disk (7-cm depth), harrow (15-cm depth), chisel plow (30-cm depth), and moldboard plow (33-cm depth) on silt loam soils in New York state. An estimated 55,192 and 183,500 live adult lesser mealworms were applied to the field in 2002 and 2004, respectively. Mortality due to the action of the manure spreader was 32.4% in 2002 and 6.5% in 2004. No significant differences were observed between treatments in 2002. However, moldboard plowing significantly reduced beetle emergence compared with no tillage in 2004. Peak beetle flight was observed 10 and 17 d after manure application in 2002 and 2004, respectively.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985127R; 0 (Manure); 0 (Soil); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0493; 0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16334348</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16334348</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2709</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of house flies (Diptera: Muscidae) exposed to commercial insecticides on painted and unpainted plywood panels</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>58</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>174</sp>
<op>178</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biological Assay</k1>
<k1>Dimethoate/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Houseflies/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Latex/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Nitriles</k1>
<k1>Paint/parasitology</k1>
<k1>Permethrin/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins/toxicity</k1>
<k1>Wood</k1>
<ab>House flies were collected from dairies in New York state and the levels of resistance to commercially available insecticide formulations were measured on painted and unpainted plywood panels. Dimethoate was ineffective on all surfaces. The wettable powder permethrin formulation was more toxic than the emulsifiable concentrate formulation. The wettable powder cyfluthrin formulation was also more toxic than the recently developed liquid formulation. In general, the best house fly control was obtained on flat latex painted plywood panels and the poorest control on gloss latex painted panels. It is highly unlikely that producers obtain adequate control with dimethoate and permethrin.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100898744; 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Latex); 0 (Nitriles); 0 (Pyrethrins); 52645-53-1 (Permethrin); 60-51-5 (Dimethoate); 68359-37-5 (cyfluthrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1526-498X; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Comstock Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York 14853, USA. pek4@CORNELL.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11852642</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.436</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11852642</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2712</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Doscher,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Albright,R.</a1>
<t1>Efficacy of chlorfenapyr (AC 303630) experimental pour-on and CyLence formulations against naturally acquired louse infestations on cattle in New York</t1>
<jf>Veterinary parasitology</jf>
<jo>Vet.Parasitol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>May 22</fd>
<vo>97</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>123</sp>
<op>129</op>
<k1>Administration, Topical</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Cattle Diseases/drug therapy</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Least-Squares Analysis</k1>
<k1>Lice/classification/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Lice Infestations/drug therapy/veterinary</k1>
<k1>Nitriles</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins/administration &amp; dosage/therapeutic use</k1>
<ab>The four chlorfenapyr formulations examined provided 100% control of both the nymphal and adult stages of naturally acquired Bovicola bovis (L.) on cattle up to 35 days after application. Treatment with 6mg chlorfenapyr per kg BW in a 0.12ml per kg BW formulation was as effective as treatment with CyLence (cyfluthrin) in controlling naturally acquired Solenopotes capillatus (Enderlein) on cattle for 35 days. Percent reduction was never greater than 90% with any chlorfenapyr application against Linognathus vituli (L.). However, percent reduction was greater than 90% with CyLence from day 21 through 35. No adverse effects were noted on cattle from any of the chlorfenapyr dosages used.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051117; JID: 7602745; 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Nitriles); 0 (Pyrethrins); 0 (chlorfenapyr); 68359-37-5 (cyfluthrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0304-4017; 0304-4017</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Comstock Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14817, USA. pek4@cornell.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11358627; S0304-4017(00)00439-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Clinical Trial; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11358627</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2707</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,S.</a1>
<t1>Large sticky traps for capturing house flies and stable flies in dairy calf greenhouse facilities</t1>
<jf>Journal of dairy science</jf>
<jo>J.Dairy Sci.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>176</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Houseflies</k1>
<k1>Housing, Animal</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Muscidae</k1>
<k1>Pheromones</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<ab>Large sticky traps were evaluated for stable fly, Stomoxys calcitrans (L.), and house fly, Musca domestica L., (Diptera: Muscidae) capture under field conditions in 5 dairy calf greenhouse facilities in New York. The farm with the highest stable fly capture had the highest house fly capture, and the farm with the lowest stable fly capture had the lowest house fly capture, suggesting that fly management practices greatly influenced trap captures. In general, stable fly populations, as reflected by increased trap capture, generally rose during the summer. Numbers of flies counted on calves did not increase, however, suggesting that the traps greatly reduced the potential stable fly pressure on the calves as the fly population increased. Estimated number of stable flies and house flies captured during this 10-wk study exceeded 142,000 and 900,000, respectively. Producers were generally pleased with the trap performance and most felt that these traps reduced flies in their calf greenhouses to acceptable levels.</ab>
<no>JID: 2985126R; 0 (Pheromones); 0 (insect attractants); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-0302; 0022-0302</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA. pek4@cornell.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 15591381; 88/1/176 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15591381</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2845</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Frisch,S.</a1>
<t1>Sticky traps for large scale house fly (Diptera: Muscidae) trapping in New York poultry facilities</t1>
<jf>Journal of Agricultural and Urban Entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Agric.Urban Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>43</sp>
<op>49</op>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>trapping</k1>
<k1>sticky traps</k1>
<k1>length</k1>
<k1>longevity</k1>
<k1>insect control</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>poultry housing</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>physical control</k1>
<k1>efficacy</k1>
<k1>trap length</k1>
<k1>trap longevity</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<no>Journal of agricultural and urban entomology. Jan 2001. v. 18 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1523-5475</sn>
<an>IND23229228</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB599 .J69</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2708</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Waldron,J. K.</a1>
<t1>Seasonal variation in Carcinops pumilio (Coleoptera: Histeridae) dispersal and potential for suppression of dispersal behavior</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>106</sp>
<op>111</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Beetles</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal</k1>
<k1>Demography</k1>
<k1>Seasons</k1>
<ab>Seasonal dispersal of Carcinops pumilio (Erichson) was evaluated using two trapping methods-a black-light pitfall trap and a mesh-bottomed trap placed on poultry manure. The black-light trap collected larger numbers than the mesh-bottomed trap from March through June. The mesh-bottomed trap gathered larger numbers of beetles from June through August and numbers were less variable throughout the year. Often, when very low numbers of beetles were recovered from manure cores, large numbers of beetles could be collected with the black-light trap suggesting that beetle density may not be an important factor in dispersal behavior. The greatest dispersal in the dispersal arenas (approximately 90%) occurred using beetles collected by both trap types in June 2000. Beginning in March and ending in August, a cyclic rise and then fall pattern in both laboratory dispersal and beetle collections was observed. Trap collection patterns were similar in both years of the study. In January and March, we were unable to prevent dispersal behavior of beetles captured in black-light traps. However, in May, after beetles had been in a dispersal phase for several months, we were able to suppress dispersal. In contrast, dispersal behavior among beetles captured with the mesh-bottomed trap did not change following the photoperiod-altered exposure.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11931240</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11931240</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2848</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Scholl,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Dose confirmation study of a 10 g liter-1 non-aqueous injectable formulation of moxidectin against naturally acquired infestations of cattle lice on cattle in New York</t1>
<jf>Pesticide Science</jf>
<jo>Pestic.Sci.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Sept</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>919</sp>
<op>922</op>
<k1>moxidectin</k1>
<k1>Haematopinus eurysternus</k1>
<k1>Linognathus vituli</k1>
<k1>cattle</k1>
<k1>insect control</k1>
<k1>solenopotes capillatus</k1>
<k1>infestation</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<ab>This study demonstrated that a moxidectin 10 g liter-1 non-aqueous injectable formulation, injected subcutaneously in cattle at a dose of either 0.2 or 0.3 mg moxidectin kg-1 body weight was safe and highly effective in the almost complete elimination (&amp;gt;99% efficacy) for 56 days of both the nymphal and adult stages of naturally acquired infestations of the three species of sucking lice commonly found on cattle, Haematopinus eurysternus (Nitzsch), Linognathus vituli (L), and Solenopotes capillatus (Enderlein). The level of efficacy was never greater than 90% with either dose against Bovicola bovis (L). No adverse effects were noted on cattle from either of the moxidectin doses used.</ab>
<no>Pesticide science Sept 1999. v. 55 (9); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0031-613X</sn>
<an>IND22060133</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB951.P47</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2711</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Scott,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Monitoring insecticide resistance in house flies (Diptera: Muscidae) from New York dairies</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>57</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>514</sp>
<op>521</op>
<k1>Adaptation, Physiological/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Animal Husbandry</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biological Assay/methods</k1>
<k1>Dairying/statistics &amp; numerical data</k1>
<k1>Environmental Monitoring</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Houseflies</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Insecticide Resistance</k1>
<k1>Insecticides</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>New York</k1>
<k1>Tissue Survival/drug effects</k1>
<ab>House flies were collected from dairies across New York state and the levels of resistance to seven insecticides were measured using standard laboratory assays with three to five diagnostic concentrations. The highest levels of resistance were found for tetrachlorvinphos, permethrin and cyfluthrin. Although levels of resistance to methomyl were somewhat lower, they were among the highest ever reported for field-collected house flies. Resistance to pyrethrins was limited primarily to the lowest diagnostic concentration. House flies were susceptible to fipronil at all dairies, suggesting that this material would be highly effective for fly control. The levels of resistance were similar at all the dairies, irrespective of their insecticide use, suggesting substantial movement of flies between facilities. Relative to resistance levels found at New York dairies in 1987, resistance levels had increased for permethrin, were unchanged for tetrachlorvinphos and had decreased for dimethoate. To identify a single diagnostic concentration that could be used in the laboratory assays to assess accurately resistance levels in future studies, we carried out a &amp;#39;simulated&amp;#39; field bioassay using formulated materials. A diagnostic concentration for each insecticide is proposed on the basis of a comparison of our bioassays.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100898744; 0 (Insecticides); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1526-498X; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York 14853-0999, USA. pek4@CORNELL.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11407027</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.319</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11407027</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2701</id>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Strong,C.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of lesser mealworm (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) adults and larvae exposed to two commercial insecticides on unpainted plywood panels</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>108</sp>
<op>111</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Beetles/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Denmark</k1>
<k1>Housing, Animal</k1>
<k1>Insecticide Resistance/physiology</k1>
<k1>Insecticides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Larva/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Nitriles/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Paint</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Pyrethrins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Tetrachlorvinphos/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<k1>Wood</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The susceptibilities of adult and larval lesser mealworms, Alphitobius diaperinus (Panzer), to two commercially formulated insecticides, cyfluthrin and tetrachlorvinphos, were examined through exposure on treated plywood panels. Lesser mealworms were collected from four caged-layer poultry farms, three in New York and one in Maine. An additional strain was obtained from an infestation occurring in a cricket colony. RESULTS: In all poultry farm derived strains, a portion of the population (1.8-16.2%) survived cyfluthrin exposure. The Maine and cricket colony strains were tolerant of tetrachlorvinphos exposure as both larvae and adults, with 55-74% mortality, whereas nearly 100% mortality was observed with New York strains. The cricket colony adult beetles were highly susceptible to cyfluthrin, with 100% mortality following exposure, but larvae were considerably less susceptible (87.7%). Pesticide use histories for the poultry farms and their impact on the results are discussed. CONCLUSION: The results document that tetrachlorvinphos, an active ingredient with a long use history, may be losing its effectiveness against lesser mealworms in some poultry operations; however, it is still effective in many others.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100323; JID: 100898744; 0 (Insecticides); 0 (Nitriles); 0 (Pyrethrins); 22248-79-9 (Tetrachlorvinphos); 68359-37-5 (cyfluthrin); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1526-498X; 1526-498X</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA. pkaufman@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17912691</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/ps.1475</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17912691</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2824</id>
<a1>Kaufman,PE</a1>
<a1>Long,SJ</a1>
<a1>Rutz,DA</a1>
<t1>Impact of Exposure Length and Pupal Source on Muscidifurax raptorellus and Nasonia vitripennis (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) Parasitism in a New York Poultry Facility</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>94</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>998</sp>
<op>1003</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Parasitism</k1>
<k1>Poultry</k1>
<k1>Exposure</k1>
<k1>Pest control</k1>
<k1>Parasitoids</k1>
<k1>Biological control</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Pteromalidae</k1>
<k1>Nasonia vitripennis</k1>
<k1>Muscidifurax raptorellus</k1>
<k1>Article Geographic Terms: USA, New York</k1>
<k1>Diptera</k1>
<k1>Hymenoptera</k1>
<k1>pupae</k1>
<k1>Pteromalid wasps</k1>
<ab>Commercially obtained Nasonia vitripennis Walker and Muscidifurax raptorellus Kogan &amp;amp; Legner were released weekly for 12 wk into a high-rise, caged-layer poultry house. After the release period, parasitoids were sampled using sentinel house fly (Musca domestica L.) pupae that were either laboratory-reared or field-collected as larvae and exposed for 2, 4, 7, and 14 d. Parasitoid-induced mortality was observed in 31% of laboratory colony pupae and in 26% of field-collected pupae, whereas successful parasitism rates of 48 and 51% were observed from these pupal sources, respectively. Parasitism was primarily by M. raptorellus (88%), and Muscidifurax raptor Girault &amp;amp; Sanders (11%), while N. vitripennis accounted for &amp;lt;1%. Percent female progeny ranged from 43% in M. raptorellus to 76% in N. vitripennis. Parasitoid emergence from 2-d exposed sentinel pupae was the lowest of all treatments. Parasitoid emergence from 7-d exposed sentinel pupae was the highest of all treatments. We found no differences between pupal source, suggesting that when sampling for M. raptor, M. raptorellus, and N. vitripennis, in poultry facilities, pupal source is not a confounding factor.</ab>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Parasitoid-induced mortality; Recovered parasitoids; Species composition; Successful parasitism; Object Taxonomic Terms: Muscidifurax raptorellus; Nasonia vitripennis; Object Geographic Terms: USA, New York; Object Statistical Terms: Degrees of Freedom; Mean; Standard Error; Tukey Procedure&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 2. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00010%2Fi0022-0493-094-04-0998%2Fobj%2Fi0022-0493-094-04-0998-t02.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=3814b22621a3a39e537887d64af44ae6&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 2. Successful parasitism, parasitoid-induced mortality, and killed sentinel house fly pupae exposed for various time periods in a New York high-rise, caged-layer poultry facility following release of N. vitripennis and M. raptorellus&lt;br&gt;M1: Table&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Successful parasitism; Parasitoid-induced mortality; Object Taxonomic Terms; Nasonia vitripennis; Muscidifurax raptorellus; Object Statistical Terms; Standard Error; Degrees of Freedom; Tukey Procedure; Mean&lt;br&gt;IF: Table 3. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00010%2Fi0022-0493-094-04-0998%2Fobj%2Fi0022-0493-094-04-0998-t03.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=91abe1d2a2e4b0345914774f046489ed&lt;br&gt;C1: Table 3. Species composition of parasitoids recovered from sentinel house fly pupae exposed for various time periods in a New York high-rise, caged-layer poultry facility following release of N. vitripennis and M. raptorellus&lt;br&gt;M1: Table&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Species composition; Recovered parasitoids; Object Taxonomic Terms; Nasonia vitripennis; Muscidifurax raptorellus; Object Geographic Terms; USA, New York</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA, [mailto:pek4@cornell.edu]</ad>
<an>5222187</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05201 Parasitism: entomophagous</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; 1B; Entomology Abstracts; OB</sf>
<lk>[URL:http://journals.allenpress.com/jrnlserv/?request=get-abstract &amp;issn=0022-0493&amp;volume=94&amp;page=998]</lk>
<do>10.1043/0022-0493(2001)094(0998:IOELAP)2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2809</id>
<a1>Kaufman,Phillip E.</a1>
<a1>Geden,Christopher J.</a1>
<t1>Development of Spalangia cameroni and Muscidifurax raptor (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) on Live and Freeze-Killed House Fly (Diptera: Muscidae) Pupae</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sept</fd>
<vo>92</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>492</sp>
<op>496</op>
<k1>Spalangia cameroni</k1>
<k1>Muscidifurax raptor</k1>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>parasitoids</k1>
<k1>host-parasite relationships</k1>
<k1>pupae</k1>
<k1>freezing</k1>
<k1>freezers</k1>
<k1>frozen storage</k1>
<k1>storage time</k1>
<k1>parasitism</k1>
<k1>insect development</k1>
<k1>insect reproduction</k1>
<k1>biological control agents</k1>
<k1>live hosts</k1>
<k1>dead hosts</k1>
<k1>host suitability for parasitism</k1>
<k1>frostfree freezers</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<k1>L600</k1>
<k1>L001</k1>
<ab>The use of pteromalid parasitoids for muscoid fly control is becoming increasingly common. Two species that are often recommended for releases are Spalangia cameroni Perkins and Muscidifurax raptor Girault and Sanders. This study was conducted to determine if the reduced suitability of freeze-killed pupae for Pteromalidae, particularly S. cameroni, is due to freezing, freezing duration, or the type of freezer used. Processing pupae through freezing had a considerably greater negative effect on rearing of S. cameroni than on M. raptor. Although freezing pupae did reduce M. raptor progeny production, there was no effect of length of storage or type of freezer used. Freezing pupae for 5 months resulted in significantly fewer S. cameroni progeny than freezing pupae for 2 weeks. Although not significant, pupae held in a frostfree freezer produced more progeny than those in a non-frostfree freezer. Measurements of weights of parasitized pupae over time indicated that freezing did not result in accelerated desiccation of hosts. These results document that the use of prolonged freezing and type of freezer minimally impacts M. raptor, but that commercial insectaries and researchers should be cautious in the use of frozen pupae when rearing or surveying for S. cameroni.</ab>
<no>Florida entomologist. 2009 Sept., v. 92, no. 3; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>IND44273794</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://hdl.handle.net/10113/34891];[URL:http://www.bioone.org/doi/full/10.1653/024.092.0311</lk>
<cn>DNAL 420 F662</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2818</id>
<a1>Kaufman,Phillip E.</a1>
<a1>Wood,Lois A.</a1>
<a1>Goldberg,Jeffrey I.</a1>
<a1>Long,Stefan J.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,Donald A.</a1>
<t1>Host age and pathogen exposure level as factors in the susceptibility of the house fly, Musca domestica (Diptera: Muscidae) to Beauveria bassiana</t1>
<jf>Biocontrol Science and Technology</jf>
<jo>Biocontrol Sci.Technol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>2008</fd>
<vo>18</vo>
<is>7-8</is>
<sp>841</sp>
<op>847</op>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>insect pests</k1>
<k1>commensalism</k1>
<k1>Beauveria bassiana</k1>
<k1>entomopathogenic fungi</k1>
<k1>mycoinsecticides</k1>
<k1>hosts</k1>
<k1>animal age</k1>
<k1>inoculum density</k1>
<k1>strains</k1>
<k1>strain differences</k1>
<k1>conidia</k1>
<k1>mortality</k1>
<k1>disease incidence</k1>
<k1>temporal variation</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<ab>Adult house flies, Musca domestica L., of four ages, &amp;lt;1, 3, 7, and 14 day post-eclosion, were exposed to three strains of Beauveria bassiana (P89, L90 and 447). Flies were exposed to moistened filter paper treated with either a low (1.57x10⁴ conidia/cm2) or high (1.57x10⁵ conidia/cm2) concentration of each fungal strain for 6 h. Strain 447 was superior to the two house fly-derived B. bassiana strains in inducing host infection and mortality. Significant spikes in infection and mortality occurred as early as 5 days post-exposure with higher concentration exposures acting more quickly. Few differences were observed in either infection or mortality among the four fly age classes. On Day 10 post-exposure, 77% of the high-concentration, 447-exposed flies were infected, compared with only 24% of the flies from the P89 low-concentration exposure. Potential applications of these results in integrated house fly management programs are discussed.</ab>
<no>Biocontrol science and technology. 2008, v. 18, no. 7-8; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0958-3157</sn>
<an>IND44132609</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB975.B562</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2853</id>
<a1>Lee,R. E. Jr</a1>
<a1>Costanzo,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Lee,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Wyman,J. A.</a1>
<t1>Ice-nucleating active bacteria reduce the cold-hardiness of the freeze-intolerant Colorado potato beetle (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>377</sp>
<op>381</op>
<k1>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</k1>
<k1>reduction</k1>
<k1>Pseudomonas syringae</k1>
<k1>cold tolerance</k1>
<k1>ice nucleating bacteria</k1>
<k1>F821</k1>
<ab>In laboratory experiments, a freeze-dried concentrated form of the ice-nucleating active bacteria, Pseudomonas syringae, was used to decrease the supercooling capacity of field-collected diapausing Colorado potato beetles, Leptinotarsa decemlineata (Say). Application of the P. syringae to adult beetles increased their mean supercooling point values from -7.6 +/- 0.2 degrees C (untreated) to -3.7 +/- 0.1 degrees C (1,000 ppm). No beetles survived cooling to temperatures below their supercooling point, indicating that this species is freeze-intolerant. During tests conducted in 1991 and 1992, the increase in the supercooling point was directly dependent on the amount of P. syringae added to soil containing the beetles. Cumulative freezing distributions indicated that 80% of beetles treated with 100 ppm of P. syringae would be expected to freeze and die when exposed to -5 degrees C; in contrast, none or very few of the untreated control beetles would be expected to freeze at this temperature. Other experiments demonstrated that the capacity of P. syringae treatments to increase the supercooling point of the beetles decreased after 2 wk of exposure at 4 degrees C and when experiments were done at 10 degrees C. If delivery systems were developed that would expose adult beetles to ice nucleating agents and preserve their ice nucleating activity until critical low-temperature exposure occurs in mid-winter, these nucleating agents could be used in conjunction with cultural control strategies for increasing winter mortality.</ab>
<no>Journal of economic entomology. Apr 1994. v. 87 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<an>IND20408461</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL 421 J822</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2700</id>
<a1>Lloyd,A. M.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Hogsette,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Allan,S. A.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of two commercial traps for the collection of Culicoides (Diptera: Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>262</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Ceratopogonidae</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<k1>Seasons</k1>
<ab>Two types of commercial propane-powered traps, mosquito magnet (MM) (American Biophysics Corporation) MM-Freedom (Freedom) and MM-Liberty Plus (Liberty Plus), were evaluated for the collection of Culicoides. Trap preference and seasonal characteristics for the 3 major species, Culicoides furens, Culicoides barbosai, and Culicoides mississippiensis, were recorded from July 7, 2005, to July 24, 2006. Over 35 million Culicoides were captured during our study. When species were evaluated separately, analysis of overall mean trap collections yielded 5 months (February, March, June, September, and October) with significant trap effects. The Freedom trap captured more C. furens in June and October; the Liberty Plus trap captured more C. mississippiensis in February, March, and April, and more C. barbosai in September. The high numbers of Culicoides captured during our study suggest that the number of host-seeking Culicoides could potentially be reduced by continuous trapping during times when they are prevalent. Results of these investigations will be used to guide future control efforts.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Center for Medical, Agricultural, and Veterinary Entomology, USDA/ARS, 1600/1700 SW 23rd Drive, Gainesville, FL 32608, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18666534</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Evaluation Studies; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18666534</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2690</id>
<a1>Mann,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<t1>The seasonal abundance of phlebotomine sand flies, Lutzomyia species in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>10</sp>
<op>17</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Appetitive Behavior</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<k1>Psychodidae</k1>
<k1>Seasons</k1>
<ab>The seasonality of phlebotomine sand flies was studied in Florida, utilizing colored light-emitting diode- and attractant-baited Mosquito Magnet MM-X traps from September 2006 to September 2008 at San Felasco Hammock Preserve State Park, Gainesville, FL. A total of 6,278 sand flies were collected from 314 actual nights and 1,692 total trap-nights, yielding 3.7 sand flies per trap-night. Lutzomyia shannoni was the predominant species, constituting 55% to 80% of the total sand fly populations collected during the studies. Both L. shannoni and L. vexator populations were highly seasonal and were moderately influenced by weather factors. Lutzomyia shannoni populations peaked in May and showed reduced activity during December, January, and February. This species was active throughout the year and showed positive and negative correlations with average monthly temperature and relative humidity, respectively. Lutzomyia vexator showed peak activity during August and October with an activity lull from December to March. This species showed a positive correlation with average monthly temperature. No correlations were observed with either species for average daily, weekly, or 1- to 8-wk-lagging precipitation, number of rainy days, wind speed, or lunar phases. Lutzomyia shannoni abundance was weakly correlated to L. vexator abundance. No other Lutzomyia spp. were collected during the study.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Entomology &amp; Nematology Department, P.O. Box 110620, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20402345</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20402345</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2696</id>
<a1>Mann,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Butler,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Lutzomyia spp. (Diptera: Psychodidae) response to olfactory attractant- and light emitting diode-modified Mosquito Magnet X (MM-X) traps</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1052</sp>
<op>1061</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Odors</k1>
<k1>Psychodidae</k1>
<ab>Mosquito Magnet-X traps were modified for use with blue, green, red, and blue-green-red light-emitting diodes and olfactory attractants to determine the response of Lutzomyia shannoni (Dyar) and Lutzomyia vexator (Coquillett) (Diptera: Psychodidae) field populations to these attractants. Red and blue-green-red-baited traps captured the highest numbers of Lu. shannoni and Lu. vexator, respectively, although, there were no significant differences between the colors. Baiting the traps with CO, attracted significantly higher numbers of Lu. shannoni but showed no effect on Lu. vexator capture. In comparison with CO, alone, Lu. shannoni preferred 1-octen-3-ol and 1-hexen-3-ol (0.05 g per trap) in combination with CO.</ab>
<no>JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, Building 970, Natural Area Drive, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620, USA. mannrs@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19769036</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19769036</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2692</id>
<a1>Obenauer,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Buss,L. J.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<t1>Utilizing Auto-Montage technology for identifying field-collected container-inhabiting mosquito eggs</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>517</sp>
<op>520</op>
<k1>Aedes</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Ovum</k1>
<k1>Photomicrography</k1>
<k1>Software</k1>
<ab>We describe the methodology used to take images of the eggs of 3 container-breeding mosquito species recovered from ovitraps in north-central Florida using the Auto-Montage software package. This software allows for high-resolution imagery, thereby providing a new tool for mosquito egg identification. Images, as well as a brief comparison of the mosquito eggs using previously described literature, are provided.</ab>
<no>JID: 8511299; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>8756-971X; 8756-971X</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, P.O. Box 110620, Building 970, Natural Area Drive, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20099602</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20099602</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2698</id>
<a1>Obenauer,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Allan,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<t1>Host-seeking height preferences of Aedes albopictus (Diptera: Culicidae) in north central Florida suburban and sylvatic locales</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>900</sp>
<op>908</op>
<k1>Aedes/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Feeding Behavior</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mosquito Control</k1>
<ab>The response of Aedes albopictus to the BG-Sentinel, Omni-directional-Fay-Prince, and Mosquito MagnetX traps was evaluated in four suburban and four sylvatic habitats in north-central Florida to ascertain potential height preference of this species. These traps, which are primarily designed to attract diurnal mosquitoes, were set at 1 and 6 m and were evaluated during 40 trapping periods over 4 mo. We collected 45,640 mosquitoes, representing 26 species from 10 genera, the most common being Aedes albopictus, Ae. vexans, Coquilletidia perturbans, Culex nigripalpus, Aedes infirmatus, Ae. triseriatus, and Psorophora ferox. Although significantly more Ae. albopictus were captured at 1 m above ground than at 6 m, fewer were captured in sylvatic habitats than suburban habitats. Although not statistically different, the BG-Sentinel caught more Ae. albopictus compared with the other two traps regardless of locale. These results suggest that, although Ae. albopictus was captured as high as 6 m, the majority seek hosts at or below 1-m heights. This further supports prior research that, although Ae. albopictus has been shown to disseminate West Nile virus, it has not been implicated as a major vector for the virus, which is likely because of its propensity to feed on ground-dwelling hosts. The study also shows how trap type, trap heights, and environments influence sampling estimates when determining species abundance.</ab>
<no>JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, PO Box 110620, Bldg. 970, Natural Area Dr., Gainesville, FL 32611, USA. pjoben@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19645296</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19645296</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2693</id>
<a1>Obenauer,P. J.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Allan,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Kline,D. L.</a1>
<t1>Infusion-baited ovitraps to survey ovipositional height preferences of container-inhabiting mosquitoes in two Florida habitats</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>46</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1507</sp>
<op>1513</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Behavior, Animal</k1>
<k1>Culicidae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Environment</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Oviposition</k1>
<k1>Ovum/classification</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>To ascertain mosquito species-specific oviposition height preferences, a study was conducted evaluating the response of field populations of container-inhabiting mosquitoes to water, oak (Quercus spp.),or oak-pine (Pinus spp.) infusion-baited ovitraps in four suburban and four sylvatic habitats in north central Florida. In total, 48 ovitraps, 24 suspended at each height of 1 or 6 m (near the ground or tree canopy, respectively), were monitored weekly for 5 mo. Throughout our study, we collected 13,276 mosquito eggs, representing five species from four genera, the most common being Aedes triseriatus (Say), Aedes albopictus Skuse, and Orthopodomyia signifera (Coquillett). Significantly more Ae. triseriatus and Ae. albopictus eggs were oviposited in containers with oak and oak-pine infusions compared with water alone. Significantly more Ae. albopictus eggs were recovered from traps at 1 m in suburban habitats, whereas more Ae. triseriatus eggs were recovered at 6 m in sylvatic habitats.</ab>
<no>JID: 0375400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-2585; 0022-2585</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, P.O. Box 110620, Bldg. 970, Natural Area Dr., University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA. pjoben@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19960705</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19960705</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Generic</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3105</id>
<a1>Scott C</a1>
<a1>Kaufman PE</a1>
<t1>Buck moth, &lt;I&gt;Hemileuca maia&lt;/I&gt; (Drury)</t1>
<yr>2009</yr>
<vo>Publication #EENY464</vo>
<no>5 pp.  EENY-464 (DLN: IN834)</no>
<lk>http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/in834</lk>
<ol>English(30)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2847</id>
<a1>Scott,J. G.</a1>
<a1>Alefantis,T. G.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<t1>Insecticide resistance in house flies from caged-layer poultry facilities</t1>
<jf>Pest management science</jf>
<jo>Pest Manag.Sci.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>56</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>147</sp>
<op>153</op>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>strains</k1>
<k1>insecticides</k1>
<k1>insecticide resistance</k1>
<k1>mortality</k1>
<k1>poultry housing</k1>
<k1>L821L200</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<k1>L200</k1>
<ab>The frequency of resistance of eight strains of house flies, Musca domestica L., collected from caged-layer poultry facilities across New York state, to nine insecticides (dimethoate, tetrachlorvinphos, permethrin, cyfluthrin, pyrethrins, methomyl, fipronil, spinosad and cyromazine) was measured relative to a laboratory susceptible strain. Percentage survival was evaluated at five diagnostic concentrations: susceptible strain LC99, 3 x LC99, 10 x LC99, 30 x LC99 and 100 x LC99. The highest levels of resistance were noted for tetrachlorvinphos, permethrin and cyfluthrin. There was substantial variation in the levels of resistance to the different insecticides from one facility to another, independent of their geographical location. There was very little cross-resistance detected in these populations to either fipronil or spinosad. Overall, there was a good correlation between insecticide use histories and the levels of resistance. The apparent isolation of fly populations within poultry facilities suggests that there are good opportunities for the implementation of successful resistance management strategies at these facilities. Differences between these results and those of a resistance survey on New York dairy farms in 1987 are discussed.</ab>
<no>Pest management science. Feb 2000. v. 56 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1526-498X</sn>
<an>IND22072596</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://www.interscience.wiley.com/jpages/1526-498X/</lk>
<cn>DNAL SB951 .P47</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2814</id>
<a1>Slansky,Frank</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,Phillip E.</a1>
<a1>Bailey,Mark</a1>
<t1>First Record of Cuterebra fontinella (Diptera: Oestridae) Larvae Infesting a Florida Rat (Rodentia: Muridae)</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>706</sp>
<op>708</op>
<k1>Cuterebra fontinella</k1>
<k1>new host records</k1>
<k1>Neotoma</k1>
<k1>rats</k1>
<k1>myiasis</k1>
<k1>larvae</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>Neotoma floridana</k1>
<k1>cuterebrosis</k1>
<k1>parasite identification</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<no>Florida entomologist. 2008 Dec., v. 91, no. 4; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<an>IND44147092</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://www.fcla.edu/FlaEnt/</lk>
<cn>DNAL 420 F662</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2844</id>
<a1>Watson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,P. E.</a1>
<a1>Rutz,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Glenister,C. S.</a1>
<t1>Impact of the darkling beetle Alphitobius diaperinus (Panzer) on establishment of the predaceous beetle Carcinops pumilio (Erichson) for Musca domestica control in caged-layer poultry houses</t1>
<jf>Biological control : theory and applications in pest management</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>8</sp>
<op>15</op>
<k1>Alphitobius diaperinus</k1>
<k1>Musca domestica</k1>
<k1>predator-prey relationships</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>age structure</k1>
<k1>mortality</k1>
<k1>poultry manure</k1>
<k1>poultry housing</k1>
<k1>biological control</k1>
<k1>predators</k1>
<k1>interactions</k1>
<k1>predators of insect pests</k1>
<k1>carcinops pumilio</k1>
<k1>L821</k1>
<ab>Understanding the insect natural history in a caged-layer poultry house is essential to developing Integrated Pest Management strategies. In this study we observed the interaction of three insects commonly found in poultry manure: a filth fly predator, Carcinops pumilio (Erichson) (Histeridae), and two poultry pests, the house fly, Musca domestica L. (Muscidae), and the darkling beetle, Alphitobius diaperinus (Panzer) (Tenebrionidae). Manure samples were collected weekly and the insects were extracted using Berlese-Tullgren funnels. Collected insects were identified to species and life stage. When C. pumilio populations equaled or exceeded those of the larval house fly, subsequent adult house fly populations were not considered pestiferous. C. pumilio adult and larval cohorts varied significantly among poultry houses. Few C. pumilio larvae were found in houses with abundant darkling beetle populations, suggesting a negative impact on the establishment of C. pumilio. Laboratory studies confirmed that larval darkling beetles significantly reduce the survival of C. pumilio eggs and larvae. Adult darkling beetles did not reduce C. pumilio egg or larval survival.</ab>
<no>Biological control : theory and applications in pest management. Jan 2001. v. 20 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jun 29, 2010)</no>
<sn>1049-9644</sn>
<an>IND23284222</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB925.B5</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2816</id>
<a1>Wood,Lois A.</a1>
<a1>Kaufman,Phillip E.</a1>
<t1>Euoniticellus intermedius (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae: Tribe Coprini): Its Presence and Relative Abundance in Cattle Pastures in Northcentral Florida</t1>
<jf>Florida Entomologist</jf>
<jo>Fla.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>91</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>128</sp>
<op>130</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: Abundance</k1>
<k1>Pasture</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Coleoptera</k1>
<k1>Euoniticellus intermedius</k1>
<k1>Scarabaeidae</k1>
<no>OD: Object Subject Terms: Cattle pastures; Relative abundance; Sex; Time; Object Taxonomic Terms: Euoniticellus intermedius&lt;br&gt;IF: Figure 1. http://www.csa.com/ids70/gateway.php?mode=thumb&amp;amp;key=BioOne%2F00086%2Fi0015-4040-91-1-128%2Fobj%2Fi0015-4040-91-1-128-f01.gif&amp;amp;db=objectsclust-agr-set-c&amp;amp;s1=32cdd90b99bcdef9dc87f74431817646&amp;amp;s2=e571fe635258e0a7352832a94e9eefaf&lt;br&gt;C1: Figure 1. Male (a, b) and female (c, d) Euoniticellus intermedius (Reiche) collected in northcentral Florida, 2005. Image by L. Buss, editing by J. Medley, University of Florida.&lt;br&gt;M1: Organism Photograph&lt;br&gt;OD: Object Subject Terms; Sex; Time; Cattle pastures; Relative abundance; Object Taxonomic Terms; Euoniticellus intermedius</no>
<pb>Florida Entomological Society</pb>
<pp>PO Box 1007</pp>
<sn>0015-4040</sn>
<ad>Entomology and Nematology Department, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0620 USA</ad>
<an>8692329</an>
<la>English; English; Spanish</la>
<cl>D 04040 Ecosystem and Ecology Studies; Z 05300 General</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts; Ecology Abstracts; 1B</sf>
<do>10.1653/0015-4040(2008)091[0128:EICSST]2.0.CO;2</do>
<db>ProQuest Deep Indexing: Agriculture</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
