
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2969</id>
<a1>Adams,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Rice,A. D.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Rabbitpox virus and vaccinia virus infection of rabbits as a model for human smallpox</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>20</is>
<sp>11084</sp>
<op>11095</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Cytosine/analogs &amp; derivatives/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Phosphonic Acids/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/drug therapy/pathology/transmission</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Smallpox</k1>
<k1>Survival Rate</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus</k1>
<k1>Viremia</k1>
<ab>The threat of smallpox release and use as a bioweapon has encouraged the search for new vaccines and antiviral drugs, as well as development of new small-animal models in which their efficacy can be determined. Here, we reinvestigate a rabbit model in which the intradermal infection of rabbits with very low doses of either rabbitpox virus (RPV) or vaccinia virus Western Reserve (VV-WR) recapitulates many of the clinical features of human smallpox. Following intradermal inoculation with RPV, rabbits develop systemic disease characterized by extensive viremia, numerous secondary lesions on the skin and mucocutaneous tissues, severe respiratory disease, death by 9 days postinfection, and, importantly, natural aerosol transmission between animals. Contrary to previous reports, intradermal infection with VV-WR also resulted in a very similar lethal systemic disease in rabbits, again with natural aerosol transmission between animals. When sentinel and index animals were cohoused, transmission rates approached 100% with either virus, with sentinel animals exhibiting a similar, severe disease. Lower rates of transmission were observed when index and sentinel animals were housed in separate cages. Sentinel animals infected with RPV with one exception succumbed to the disease. However, the majority of VV-WR-infected sentinel animals, while becoming seriously ill, survived. Finally, we tested the efficacy of the drug 1-O-hexadecyloxypropyl-cidofovir in the RPV/rabbit model and found that an oral dose of 5 mg/kg twice a day for 5 days beginning 1 day before infection was able to completely protect rabbits from lethal disease.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 1U01-AI05723301/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01-AI15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: U54-AI057157/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (Phosphonic Acids); 113852-37-2 (cidofovir); 71-30-7 (Cytosine); OID: NLM: PMC2045566; 2007/08/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Box 100266, 1600 SW Archer Road, ARB R2-231, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 17686856; JVI.00423-07 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.00423-07</do>
<wp>20070808</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17686856</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2045566</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3022</id>
<a1>Ali,A. N.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Brooks,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The SPI-1 gene of rabbitpox virus determines host range and is required for hemorrhagic pock formation</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>202</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>305</sp>
<op>314</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Peptides/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>Wild-type rabbitpox virus (RPV) and cowpox virus (CPV) produce red hemorrhagic lesions or pocks upon infection of the chicken chorioallantoic membrane (CAM) of 11-day-old embryonated chicken eggs. However, white, nonhemorrhagic pock variants arise spontaneously within wild-type (wt) populations of either virus at a frequency of about 1%, reflective of complex deletions/rearrangements in the termini of the viral DNA. A subpopulation of the RPV white-pock mutants fail to plaque on pig kidney (PK-15) cells and are referred to as host-range (hr) mutants. In the case of CPV, white-pock formation has been linked to mutations in the SPI-2 (crmA) gene. We show that five spontaneous RPV white-pock host-range mutants (RPV mu hr8sm, RPV mu hr23, RPV mu hr28, RPV mu hr30, and RPV mu hr31) each contain a SPI-2 (crmA) gene and express the crmA protein but lack instead a functional SPI-1 gene. Two other spontaneous RPV white-pock mutants, RPV mu 9 and RPV mu 12, which plaque on PK-15 cells (nonhost-range mutants) contain and express a SPI-1 gene but lack instead a functional SPI-2 gene. Targeted disruption of either the SPI-1 or SPI-2 genes of wtRPV, but only the SPI-2 gene of wtCPV, generates mutants which produce white pocks. The RPV delta SPI-1 mutant fails to plaque on PK-15 or human A549 cells, whereas the RPV delta SPI-2 mutant has a normal host range. No changes in host range compared to wtCPV for either the CPV delta SPI-1 or CPV delta SPI-2 mutants were noted. These differences in phenotypes observed between the two viruses may be reflective of either small sequence variations between the highly conserved SPI-1 or SPI-2 genes or the aggregate phenotypes provided by the other remaining genes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/U07763; GENBANK/U07766; GENBANK/U07767; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Peptides); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 129712-62-5 (lambda Spi-1); 129712-63-6 (lambda Spi-2); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8009842; S0042-6822(84)71347-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1994.1347</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8009842</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3004</id>
<a1>Atkinson,E. A.</a1>
<a1>Barry,M.</a1>
<a1>Darmon,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Shostak,I.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Bleackley,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Cytotoxic T lymphocyte-assisted suicide. Caspase 3 activation is primarily the result of the direct action of granzyme B</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Aug 14</fd>
<vo>273</vo>
<is>33</is>
<sp>21261</sp>
<op>21266</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Chloromethyl Ketones/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Caspase 3</k1>
<k1>Caspases</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Activation</k1>
<k1>Granzymes</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Jurkat Cells</k1>
<k1>Leukemia L1210/pathology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Oligopeptides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Protein Processing, Post-Translational</k1>
<k1>Serine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocytes, Cytotoxic/immunology</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<ab>Cytototoxic T lymphocyte-induced apoptosis can occur either through the directed exocytosis of granzyme B and perforin or via ligation of Fas. Both pathways involve the activation of a family of cysteine proteinases, the caspases, that cleave substrates at aspartic acid and are themselves activated by cleavage at internal aspartate residues. Fas recruits caspase 8, which initiates the death program through the subsequent activation of caspase 3. Granzyme B can process both caspase 8 and 3 in vitro, suggesting that both Fas and granzyme B access the apoptotic program in the same way. Here we demonstrate that although the two mechanisms are similar, the events that lead to activation of caspase 3 can be distinguished in vivo on the basis of their sensitivities to both pharmacological and virus-encoded caspase inhibitors. In cytotoxic T lymphocytes-mediated death the initial cleavage event on caspase 3 is insensitive to benzyloxycarbonyl-Val-Ala-Asp fluoromethyl ketone (zVAD-fmk) inhibition in both mouse and human systems. During Fas-mediated death, however, activation of caspase 3 is completely inhibited to zVAD-fmk. In addition, the viral serpin SPI-2, a homologue of cytokine response modifier A (crmA), is an effective inhibitor of the Fas but not the granzyme pathway. Our results demonstrate that whereas Fas-mediated activation of caspase 3 requires an upstream caspase activity that is zVAD-fmk-sensitive, the initial cleavage of caspase 3 during granule-mediated cell death is insensitive to zVAD-fmk, suggesting that caspase 3 is cleaved directly by granzyme B in vivo.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 25722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Amino Acid Chloromethyl Ketones); 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Oligopeptides); 0 (benzoylcarbonyl-aspartyl-glutamyl-valyl-aspartyl-fluoromethyl ketone); 0 (benzyloxycarbonylvalyl-alanyl-aspartyl fluoromethyl ketone); EC 3.4.21.- (GZMB protein, human); EC 3.4.21.- (Granzymes); EC 3.4.21.- (Gzmb protein, mouse); EC 3.4.21.- (Serine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP3 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (Casp3 protein, mouse); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 3); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); EC 3.4.22.- (Cysteine Endopeptidases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta T6G 2H7, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9694885</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9694885</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2992</id>
<a1>Barry,M.</a1>
<a1>Heibein,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Pinkoski,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Lee,S. F.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Green,D. R.</a1>
<a1>Bleackley,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Granzyme B short-circuits the need for caspase 8 activity during granule-mediated cytotoxic T-lymphocyte killing by directly cleaving Bid</t1>
<jf>Molecular and cellular biology</jf>
<jo>Mol.Cell.Biol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>3781</sp>
<op>3794</op>
<k1>Antigens, CD95/immunology</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis/immunology</k1>
<k1>BH3 Interacting Domain Death Agonist Protein</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Caspase 8</k1>
<k1>Caspase 9</k1>
<k1>Caspases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasmic Granules/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytotoxicity, Immunologic/immunology</k1>
<k1>DNA Fragmentation</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Activation</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Granzymes</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Jurkat Cells</k1>
<k1>Serine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocytes, Cytotoxic/immunology</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins</k1>
<ab>Cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL) can trigger an apoptotic signal through the Fas receptor or by the exocytosis of granzyme B and perforin. Caspase activation is an important component of both pathways. Granzyme B, a serine proteinase contained in granules, has been shown to proteolytically process and activate members of the caspase family in vitro. In order to gain an understanding of the contributions of caspases 8 and 3 during granule-induced apoptosis in intact cells, we have used target cells that either stably express the rabbitpox virus-encoded caspase inhibitor SPI-2 or are devoid of caspase 3. The overexpression of SPI-2 in target cells significantly inhibited DNA fragmentation, phosphatidylserine externalization, and mitochondrial disruption during Fas-mediated cell death. In contrast, SPI-2 expression in target cells provided no protection against granzyme-mediated apoptosis, mitochondrial collapse, or cytolysis, leading us to conclude that SPI-2-inhibited caspases are not an essential requirement for the granzyme pathway. Caspase 3-deficient MCF-7 cells were found to be resistant to CTL-mediated DNA fragmentation but not to CTL-mediated cytolysis and loss of the mitochondrial inner membrane potential. Furthermore, we demonstrate that granzyme B directly cleaves the proapoptotic molecule Bid, bypassing the need for caspase 8 activation of Bid. These results provide evidence for a two-pronged strategy for mediating target cell destruction and provide evidence of a direct link between granzyme B activity, Bid cleavage, and caspase 3 activation in whole cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 8109087; 0 (Antigens, CD95); 0 (BH3 Interacting Domain Death Agonist Protein); 0 (BID protein, human); 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 3.4.21.- (GZMB protein, human); EC 3.4.21.- (Granzymes); EC 3.4.21.- (Serine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP8 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP9 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 8); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 9); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); OID: NLM: PMC85698; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0270-7306; 0270-7306</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta T6G 2H7, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10805722</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10805722</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC85698</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2989</id>
<a1>Bawden,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Glassberg,K. J.</a1>
<a1>Diggans,J.</a1>
<a1>Shaw,R.</a1>
<a1>Farmerie,W.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Complete genomic sequence of the Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus: analysis and comparison with other poxviruses</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Aug 15</fd>
<vo>274</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>120</sp>
<op>139</op>
<k1>ATP-Binding Cassette Transporters/genetics</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Consensus Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Insects</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Moths/virology</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Peptides</k1>
<k1>Plant Proteins</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Trypsin Inhibitors/genetics</k1>
<ab>The genome of the genus B entomopoxvirus from Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) was sequenced and found to contain 232,392 bases with 279 unique open reading frames (ORFs) of greater than 60 amino acids. The central core of the viral chromosome is flanked by 9.4-kb inverted terminal repeats (ITRs), each of which contains 13 ORFs, raising the total number of ORFs within the viral chromosome to 292. ORFs with no known homology to other poxvirus genes were shown to constitute 33.6% of the viral genome. Approximately 28.6% of the AmEPV genome encodes homologs of the mammalian poxvirus colinear core genes, which are found dispersed throughout the AmEPV chromosome. There is also no significant gene order conservation between AmEPV and the orthopteran genus B poxvirus of Melanoplus sanguinipes (MsEPV). Novel AmEPV genes include those encoding a putative ABC transporter and a Kunitz-motif protease inhibitor. The most unusual feature of the AmEPV genome relates to the viral encoded poly(A) polymerase. In all other poxviruses this heterodimeric enzyme consists of a single large and a single small subunit. However, AmEPV appears to encode one large and two distinct small poly(A) polymerase subunits. AmEPV is one of the few entomopoxviruses which can be grown and manipulated in cell culture. The complete genomic sequence of AmEPV paves the way for an understanding and comparison of the molecular properties and pathogenesis between the entomopoxviruses of insects and the more intensively studied vertebrate poxviruses.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; CI: Copyright 2000; GENBANK/AF250284; JID: 0110674; 0 (ATP-Binding Cassette Transporters); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Kunitz-type protease inhibitor, plant); 0 (Peptides); 0 (Plant Proteins); 0 (Trypsin Inhibitors); EC 2.7.7.7 (DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10936094; S0042-6822(00)90449-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.2000.0449</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10936094</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2978</id>
<a1>Becker,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Greenleaf,W. B.</a1>
<a1>Ostrov,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus expresses an active superoxide dismutase</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>78</vo>
<is>19</is>
<sp>10265</sp>
<op>10275</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Copper/analysis</k1>
<k1>Dimerization</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/enzymology/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Lepidoptera/virology</k1>
<k1>Models, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Superoxide Dismutase/chemistry/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Zinc/analysis</k1>
<ab>The entomopoxvirus from Amsacta moorei serves as the prototype of the group B entomopoxviruses. One of the interesting genes found in Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus (AmEPV) is a superoxide dismutase (sod) (open reading frame AMV255). Superoxide dismutases (SODs) catalyze the conversion of superoxide radicals to hydrogen peroxide and oxygen. Many vertebrate poxviruses contain a sod gene, but to date, none have been demonstrated to be active. There are three families of SODs, characterized by their metal ion-binding partners, Fe, Mn, or Cu and Zn. Poxvirus enzymes belong to the Cu-Zn SOD family. Unlike inactive vertebrate poxvirus SODs, AMVSOD contains all the amino acids necessary for function. We expressed and purified a 6X-His-tagged version of the AMVSOD in Escherichia coli. The recombinant AMVSOD demonstrates superoxide dismutase activity both in an in situ gel assay and by stopped flow spectrophotometry. The k(cat)/K(m) for AMVSOD is 4 x 10(7) M(-1)s(-1). In infected cells, the AMVSOD protein behaves as a dimer and is catalytically active; however, disruption of the gene in AMEPV has little or no effect on growth of the virus in cell culture. An analysis of mRNA expression indicates that AMVsod is expressed late during infection of Lymantria dispar (Ld652) cells and produces a discrete nonpolydisperse transcript. Characterization of protein expression with a monoclonal antibody generated against AMVSOD confirms that the AMVSOD protein can be classified as a late, postreplicative gene. Therefore, AMVSOD is the first example of an active poxvirus SOD.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI46479/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM54903/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 7440-50-8 (Copper); 7440-66-6 (Zinc); EC 1.15.1.1 (Superoxide Dismutase); OID: NLM: PMC516379; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, P.O. Box 100266, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15367592; 78/19/10265 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.78.19.10265-10275.2004</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15367592</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC516379</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2966</id>
<a1>Becker,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Obraztsova,M.</a1>
<a1>Kern,E. R.</a1>
<a1>Quenelle,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Keith,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Prichard,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Luo,M.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and characterization of cidofovir resistant vaccinia viruses</t1>
<jf>Virology journal</jf>
<jo>Virol.J.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May 14</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<sp>58</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cytosine/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Viral</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Models, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Phosphonic Acids/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/mortality/virology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects/isolation &amp; purification/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The emergence of drug resistant viruses, together with the possibility of increased virulence, is an important concern in the development of new antiviral compounds. Cidofovir (CDV) is a phosphonate nucleotide that is approved for use against cytomegalovirus retinitis and for the emergency treatment of smallpox or complications following vaccination. One mode of action for CDV has been demonstrated to be the inhibition of the viral DNA polymerase. RESULTS: We have isolated several CDV resistant (CDVR) vaccinia viruses through a one step process, two of which have unique single mutations within the DNA polymerase. An additional resistant virus isolate provides evidence of a second site mutation within the genome involved in CDV resistance. The CDVR viruses were 3-7 fold more resistant to the drug than the parental viruses. The virulence of the CDVR viruses was tested in mice inoculated intranasally and all were found to be attenuated. CONCLUSION: Resistance to CDV in vaccinia virus can be conferred individually by at least two different mutations within the DNA polymerase gene. Additional genes may be involved. This one step approach for isolating resistant viruses without serial passage and in the presence of low doses of drug minimizes unintended secondary mutations and is applicable to other potential antiviral agents.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 1-U54-AI-057157/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101231645; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (Phosphonic Acids); 113852-37-2 (cidofovir); 71-30-7 (Cytosine); EC 2.7.7.7 (DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); OID: NLM: PMC2397383; 2008/04/18 [received]; 2008/05/14 [accepted]; 2008/05/14 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1743-422X</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA. mnbecker@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18479513; 1743-422X-5-58 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1743-422X-5-58</do>
<wp>20080514</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18479513</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2397383</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2967</id>
<a1>Becker,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Todd,T. M.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>An Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus ortholog of the poly(A) polymerase small subunit exhibits methyltransferase activity and is non-essential for virus growth</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun 5</fd>
<vo>375</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>624</sp>
<op>636</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Larva/virology</k1>
<k1>Methyltransferases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Moths/virology</k1>
<k1>Polynucleotide Adenylyltransferase/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Subunits/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Unlike the heterodimeric poly(A) polymerase (PAP) of vaccinia virus (VACV), the PAP from the Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus, AMEV, is potentially derived from three subunits: a single large and two small subunits (AMV060 and AMV115). The VACV small subunit serves as a 2&amp;#39;-O-methyltransferase, a processivity factor for mRNA polyadenylation, and a transcription elongation factor. We wished to determine the structure-function relationships of the three putative AMEV PAP subunits. We show that AMV060 is expressed as an early gene persisting throughout infection, whereas AMV115 is expressed late. We demonstrate that AMV060 exhibits 2&amp;#39;-O-methyltransferase activity but the gene is not essential for virus growth. Absence of the AMV060 protein has no effect on the length of the poly(A) tails present in mRNA. No physical association was found between any of the putative AMEV PAP subunits. We therefore propose that mRNA polyadenylation does not require interactions between these three proteins.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 AI 46479/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI046479-05/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Protein Subunits); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 2.1.1.- (Methyltransferases); EC 2.7.7.19 (Polynucleotide Adenylyltransferase); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); NIHMS53520; OID: NLM: NIHMS53520; OID: NLM: PMC2478561; 2008/01/23 [received]; 2008/02/08 [revised]; 2008/02/20 [accepted]; 2008/03/26 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. mnbecker@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18367228; S0042-6822(08)00136-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2008.02.023</do>
<wp>20080326</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18367228</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2478561</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3037</id>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Edwards,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Hager,C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Identification and characterization of two nonessential regions of the rabbitpox virus genome involved in virulence</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>1530</sp>
<op>1542</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Lethal Dose 50</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence/genetics</k1>
<ab>We have developed a means to identify genes associated with particular aspects of virulence. By beginning with an avirulent deletion mutant of rabbitpox virus and systematically reintroducing overlapping segments of the deleted region, we have identified two regions of the viral genome associated with increased virulence in mice. Evaluation of illness has been aided by the exploitation of weight loss as an indicator of pathogenesis. One of the regions identified by this method contains several open reading frames and includes two previously described genes. A third, as yet undescribed, gene within this region potentially encodes a product related to the C5 protein of human complement. The second region of DNA associated with increased virulence is the HindIII M fragment, which contains only one complete open reading frame. Analysis of this previously unreported gene shows coding potential for a polypeptide of 254 amino acids (approximately 25 kDa) which is related to the C4 component of human complement. The elucidation of two new viral genes related to complement components, taken together with the recent report of the biological activity of a poxvirus-encoded complement-binding protein, suggests the importance of interactions of the virus with the complement system during a normal infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/M59884; GENBANK/M59885; GENBANK/M59886; GENBANK/M59887; GENBANK/M59888; GENBANK/M59889; GENBANK/M59890; GENBANK/M59891; GENBANK/M59892; GENBANK/M60387; GR: AI15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); OID: NLM: PMC239934; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1847470</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1847470</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC239934</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3043</id>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Massung,R.</a1>
<a1>Savage,L.</a1>
<a1>Morrison,D. K.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Recruitment to the cytoplasm of a cellular lamin-like protein from the nucleus during a poxvirus infection</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>169</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>126</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Carcinoma</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/analysis</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm/analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunoblotting</k1>
<k1>Lamins</k1>
<k1>Lung Neoplasms</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Repetitive Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>Monoclonal antibodies (Mabs) directed against core proteins of rabbit poxvirus (RPV) have proven effective in the identification of host cell proteins such as RNA polymerase II (Pol II) that may play a role in the infectious process (D. K. Morrison and R. W. Moyer, 1986, Cell 44, 587-596). In this article we describe a Mab that has allowed the detection and characterization of a lamin-like protein derived from the nucleus of the infected cell, which like Pol II is recruited to the cytoplasm following RPV infection. A portion of the gene encoding this protein has been isolated through the screening of a lambda gt11 expression vector library. Sequence analysis of the gene shows it to be derived from a member of the HindIII 1.9-kb repetitive element, a family of mammalian repetitive sequences that are highly conserved. Immunoblot analysis and sequence analysis of the open reading frame show divergent relatedness to certain nuclear lamins. The protein is not, however, one of the three principal lamins characterized to date, but instead appears to be a perinuclear protein related to the highly conserved nuclear lamins that is recruited to the cytoplasm during the infectious process.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/M24732; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA09085-05/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Lamins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 9007-49-2 (DNA); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Microbiology, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee 37232.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2538026</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2538026</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3027</id>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Stern,R.</a1>
<a1>Duke,M.</a1>
<a1>Smith,D.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>A revised HindIII map and sequence analysis of a large &amp;#39;left-hand&amp;#39; non-essential region of the rabbit poxvirus genome</t1>
<jf>Virus research</jf>
<jo>Virus Res.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>125</sp>
<op>140</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Deoxyribonuclease HindIII</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics</k1>
<ab>Sequence analysis of a 21.5 kb region of the left-hand non-essential region of rabbit poxvirus (RPV) was performed to analyze the structure and gene organization of this region. Initial mapping and cloning studies revealed that the early published HindIII maps are incorrect in that the location of the terminal HindIII B and C fragments, as previously published, are reversed. The sequence of this region was compared to similar regions of several strains of vaccinia virus. The results indicate that this region of RPV has a high degree of homology with a similar region of vaccinia. Analysis of the translated open reading frames (ORFs) has facilitated the detection of several previously unreported ORFs related to human complement proteins. In addition, two defective copies of a homologue of the 77 kDa cowpox virus (CPV) host range gene which allows CPV to grow on Chinese hamster ovary cells have been detected, suggesting a gene duplication has occurred. However, one copy of this gene is segmented into three separate ORFs. Analysis has also identified a large number of indirect repeat elements. A possible role of these repeats in the generation of deletions and gene duplications is suggested.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/M60387; GR: AI15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8410979; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.1.21.- (Deoxyribonuclease HindIII); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0168-1702; 0168-1702</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8391191</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8391191</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2961</id>
<a1>Boyd,O.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moussatche,N.</a1>
<t1>The E6 protein from vaccinia virus is required for the formation of immature virions</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Apr 10</fd>
<vo>399</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>211</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Isopropyl Thiogalactoside</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Core Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virion/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>An IPTG-inducible mutant in the E6R gene of vaccinia virus was used to study the role of the E6 virion core protein in viral replication. In the absence of the inducer, the mutant exhibited a normal pattern DNA replication, concatemer resolution and late gene expression, but it showed an inhibition of virion structural protein processing it failed to produce infectious particles. Electron microscopic analysis showed that in the absence of IPTG viral morphogenesis was arrested before IV formation: crescents, aberrant or empty IV-like structures, and large aggregated virosomes were observed throughout the cytoplasm. The addition of IPTG to release a 12-h block showed that virus infectious particles could be formed in the absence of de novo DNA synthesis. Our observations show that in the absence of E6 the association of viroplasm with viral membrane crescents is impaired.</ab>
<no>CI: Published by Elsevier Inc.; GR: R01 AI055560/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Core Proteins); 367-93-1 (Isopropyl Thiogalactoside); NIHMS171036; OID: NLM: NIHMS171036 [Available on 04/10/11]; OID: NLM: PMC2830302 [Available on 04/10/11]; 2009/10/02 [received]; 2010/01/04 [revised]; 2010/01/07 [accepted]; 2010/02/08 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1096-0341; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 20116821; S0042-6822(10)00029-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2010.01.012</do>
<wp>20100208</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20116821</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2830302</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3073</id>
<a1>BOYER,P. D.</a1>
<a1>HULTQUIST,D. E.</a1>
<a1>PETER,J. B.</a1>
<a1>KREIL,G.</a1>
<a1>MITCHELL,R. A.</a1>
<a1>DELUCA,M.</a1>
<a1>HINKSON,J. W.</a1>
<a1>BUTLER,L. G.</a1>
<a1>MOYER,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Role of the Phosphorylated Imidazole Group in Phosphorylation and Energy Transfer Reactions</t1>
<jf>Federation proceedings</jf>
<jo>Fed.Proc.</jo>
<yr>1963</yr>
<fd>Jul-Aug</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<sp>1080</sp>
<op>1087</op>
<k1>Histidine</k1>
<k1>Imidazoles</k1>
<k1>Metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mitochondria</k1>
<k1>Research</k1>
<k1>EXPERIMENTAL LAB STUDY</k1>
<no>LR: 20070301; JID: 0372771; 0 (Imidazoles); 71-00-1 (Histidine); OTO: NLM; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0014-9446; 0014-9446</sn>
<an>PMID: 14046283</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; OM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14046283</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3017</id>
<a1>Brooks,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Ali,A. N.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>A rabbitpox virus serpin gene controls host range by inhibiting apoptosis in restrictive cells</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>7688</sp>
<op>7698</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/chemistry/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Rabbits/immunology</k1>
<k1>Serpins/analysis/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/physiology/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Poxviruses are unique among viruses in encoding members of the serine proteinase inhibitor (serpin) superfamily. Orthopoxviruses contain three serpins, designated SPI-1, SPI-2, and SPI-3. SPI-1 encodes a 40-kDa protein that is required for the replication of rabbitpox virus (RPV) in PK-15 or A549 cells in culture (A. N. Ali, P. C. Turner, M. A. Brooks, and R. W. Moyer, Virology 202:305-314, 1994). Examination of nonpermissive human A549 cells infected with an RPV mutant disrupted in the SPI-1 gene (RPV delta SPI-1) suggests there are no gross defects in protein or DNA synthesis. The proteolytic processing of late viral structural proteins, a feature of orthopoxvirus infections associated with the maturation of virus particles, also appears relatively normal. However, very few mature virus particles of any kind are produced compared with the level found in infections with wild-type RPV. Morphological examination of RPV delta SPI-1-infected A549 cells, together with an observed fragmentation of cellular DNA, suggests that the host range defect is associated with the onset of apoptosis. Apoptosis is seen only in RPV delta SPI-1 infection of nonpermissive (A549 or PK-15) cells and is absent in all wild-type RPV infections and RPV delta SPI-2 mutant infections examined to date. Although the SPI-1 gene is expressed early, before DNA replication, the triggering apoptotic event occurs late in the infection, as RPV delta SPI-1-infected A549 cells do not undergo apoptosis when infections are carried out in the presence of cytosine arabinoside. While the SPI-2 (crmA) gene, when transfected into cells, has been shown to inhibit apoptosis, our experiments provide the first indication that a poxvirus serpin protein can inhibit apoptosis during a poxvirus infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antibodies); 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Serpins); OID: NLM: PMC189710; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7494278</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7494278</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC189710</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3036</id>
<a1>Brown,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Bloom,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The nature of naturally occurring mutations in the hemagglutinin gene of vaccinia virus and the sequence of immediately adjacent genes</t1>
<jf>Virus genes</jf>
<jo>Virus Genes</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>235</sp>
<op>242</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>The expression of the vaccinia IHD-J hemagglutinin (HA) gene is regulated by two promoters, an early/late and a second distinct late promoter. The first promoter results in transcripts that begin early and are synthesized throughout the infection. All transcripts from this promoter initiate at the same 5&amp;#39; site. A second promoter is only active late in infection and initiates transcription some distance upstream of the first promoter. We have previously shown that the transcriptional start site controlled by this second, &amp;quot;late only&amp;quot; promoter lies within the coding sequence of an upstream reading frame (p16-ORF), whereas the termination of early transcription of the HA gene utilizes a transcription termination signal (TTTTTNT) located just beyond the coding region of an immediately downstream reading frame (p17-ORF). In order to assist our understanding of HA gene expression, we report here the sequence of these two ORFs adjacent to the HA gene. The HA-ORF itself consists of 945 bp, whereas the upstream p16-ORF consists of 429 bp and the downstream p17-ORF of 453 bp, sufficient to encode polypeptides of 16 and 17 kD, respectively. While many strains of vaccinia are HA+, rabbitpox virus and the variant of vaccinia IHD-J, designated IHD-W, are HA-. We report and compare here the HA gene sequences of wild-type rabbit poxvirus, two spontaneous HA+ revertants of rabbit poxvirus, and the HA- vaccinia strain IHD-W to that of the previously sequenced (1) prototype HA+ IHD-J strain of vaccinia. All differences were found to occur within the HA open reading frame.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/UNKNOWN; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8803967; 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0920-8569; 0920-8569</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1771764</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1771764</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3035</id>
<a1>Brown,C. K.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Molecular characterization of the vaccinia virus hemagglutinin gene</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>3598</sp>
<op>3606</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Structural Proteins/genetics</k1>
<ab>The vaccinia virus hemagglutinin (HA) is a glycoprotein found on the plasma membrane of infected cells and the envelope of extracellular virus. Two forms of HA (85 and 68 kDa) are detected by immunoblot analysis. Although hemagglutination activity is only readily detectable late in infection, the 85-kDa HA appears early and accumulates throughout infection, whereas the 68-kDa form appears only late in the cycle. Production of the 68-kDa HA but not the 85-kDa HA was inhibited by either cytosine arabinoside or rifampin. Analysis of HA gene expression reveals a complex pattern of expression. The HA gene is transcribed early to yield a 1.65-kb dicistronic early transcript, consisting of the 945-bp HA open reading frame (ORF) fused to a 453-bp downstream ORF. Transcription from this site initiates 7 bases upstream of the AUG initiating codon of the HA ORF. Due to the discrepancy between the calculated size of the HA protein (33 kDa) and that reported for the unglycosylated HA protein derived from in vitro translation (58 kDa), we placed an early transcription termination signal (TTTTTAT) directly downstream of the 945-bp HA ORF. This led to a reduction in size of the early HA mRNA to 1.2 kb, as expected, but had no effect on the formation of either the 85- or 68-kDa protein. Transcripts originating from the early promoter are found throughout the infection cycle. However, after DNA replication, transcription from a second, late promoter ensues. The transcriptional start site of the late promoter is within a consensus TAAATG sequence located 135 bases upstream of the transcriptional start site of the first promoter. The late transcriptional start site is also found within an upstream ORF.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Structural Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC241363; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2041086</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2041086</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC241363</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3050</id>
<a1>Brown,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The white pock mutants of rabbit poxvirus: V. In vitro translation of early host range mutant mRNA</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Apr 15</fd>
<vo>126</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>381</sp>
<op>390</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyurea/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>The abortive infections of pig kidney (PK) cells by both RP mu hr23 and RP mu hr31, two early (DNA minus) white pock (mu) host range (hr) mutants of rabbit poxvirus (RPV), are characterized by the in vivo inhibition of both host and viral protein synthesis by 10 hr postinfection although viral RNA synthesis continues. Further analysis reveals that large quantities of functional viral mRNA can be isolated from PK cells abortively infected with RP mu hr23 and translated in vitro throughout the 10-hr period of infection, even though these mRNAs are almost totally inactive in vivo. The in vitro translation of accumulated mRNA isolated from PK cells abortively infected by RP mu hr31 shows a quite different pattern where the maximum amount of RNA translatable in vitro is found at 6 hr postinfection with lesser amounts at 10 hr postinfection. Although early or prereplicative viral proteins are detected with each mutant both in vivo and after in vitro translation of isolated RNA, few, if any, late proteins are observed under any conditions.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); 127-07-1 (Hydroxyurea); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<an>PMID: 6302993</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6302993</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3049</id>
<a1>Brown,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Peluso,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>A simple method for the preparation of extracts from animal cells which catalyze efficient in vitro protein synthesis</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Dec 10</fd>
<vo>258</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>14309</sp>
<op>14314</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Extracts/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cricetinae</k1>
<k1>Kidney/cytology</k1>
<k1>Methods</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Tissue Extracts/metabolism</k1>
<ab>A rapid, simple procedure is described for the preparation of cell-free extracts of both uninfected and virus-infected pig kidney and baby hamster kidney cells which are very active in the in vitro translation of not only endogenous mRNA, but also of exogenous mRNA added to extracts that had been depleted of endogenous mRNA by treatment with micrococcal nuclease. This procedure appears to be adaptable with only minor variations to many eukaryotic cell lines and should greatly facilitate in vitro molecular studies of protein synthesis and gene regulation at the level of translation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 14594/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Cell Extracts); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Tissue Extracts); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 6643481</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6643481</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2980</id>
<a1>Brum,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Lopez,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Varela,J. C.</a1>
<a1>Baker,H. V.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Microarray analysis of A549 cells infected with rabbitpox virus (RPV): a comparison of wild-type RPV and RPV deleted for the host range gene, SPI-1</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Oct 25</fd>
<vo>315</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>334</op>
<k1>Actins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Profiling</k1>
<k1>HSP70 Heat-Shock Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Histones/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Peptides/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/analysis</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>A documented consequence of poxvirus infections is global inhibition of host protein synthesis and reduction in mRNA levels. We examined this mRNA decrease by infecting A549 cells, derived from a human lung carcinoma, with rabbitpox virus (RPV), or RPV deleted for the serine protease inhibitor SPI-1 (RPVDeltaSPI-1), which exhibits a growth defect on A549 cells. At various times postinfection, mRNA profiles were analyzed using Affymetrix U95AV2 microarrays. There was a decline in overall cellular mRNA levels beginning at 2.5 hpi, and by 5 hpi, mRNA levels were drastically reduced for the majority of genes. However, several mRNAs increased, including those of heat-shock genes. Finally, a comparison of host mRNA profiles of RPV- to RPVDeltaSPI-1-infected cells revealed subtle differences in mRNA levels at 5 and 12 hpi. In summary, while there was a global decrease of host mRNA levels, the induction of selected mRNAs may be required for a successful poxvirus infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Actins); 0 (HSP70 Heat-Shock Proteins); 0 (Histones); 0 (Peptides); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 129712-62-5 (lambda Spi-1); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology and The Genetics Institute, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 14585335; S0042682203005324 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14585335</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2981</id>
<a1>Brum,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Devick,H.</a1>
<a1>Baquero,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Plasma membrane localization and fusion inhibitory activity of the cowpox virus serpin SPI-3 require a functional signal sequence and the virus encoded hemagglutinin</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Feb 15</fd>
<vo>306</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>289</sp>
<op>302</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/virology</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Glycosylation</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/chemistry/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Membrane Fusion/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Protein Sorting Signals/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Serpins/chemistry/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/chemistry/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>The cowpox virus (CPV) glycoprotein serpin SPI-3, a functional protease inhibitor, and the viral hemagglutinin (HA) are required to prevent fusion of wt CPV infected cells. SPI-3 and HA from CPV infected cells co-localize to the plasma membrane and are found in extracellular enveloped virus (EEV). We also show that an N-terminal SPI-3 signal sequence, but not glycosylation, is required for membrane localization and fusion inhibition. In the absence of HA (CPVDeltaHA), no SPI-3 is found on the membrane and infected cells fuse. Conversely, HA from both wt CPV and CPVDeltaSPI-3 infections is on the membrane, indicating a requirement of HA for SPI-3 plasma membrane localization. In the absence of HA, secretion of SPI-3 or SPI-3 N-glyc(-) was markedly enhanced, suggesting HA serves to retain SPI-3 on the plasma membrane,thereby preventing cell fusion.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); 0 (Protein Sorting Signals); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 12642102; S004268220200017X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12642102</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3074</id>
<a1>DELUCA,M.</a1>
<a1>EBNER,K. E.</a1>
<a1>HULTQUIST,D. E.</a1>
<a1>KREIL,G.</a1>
<a1>PETER,J. B.</a1>
<a1>MOYER,R. W.</a1>
<a1>BOYER,P. D.</a1>
<t1>The Isolation and Identification of Phosphohistidine from Mitochondrial Protein</t1>
<jf>Biochemische Zeitschrift</jf>
<jo>Biochem.Z.</jo>
<yr>1963</yr>
<vo>338</vo>
<sp>512</sp>
<op>525</op>
<k1>Cattle</k1>
<k1>Chromatography</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis</k1>
<k1>Histidine</k1>
<k1>Liver/cytology</k1>
<k1>Proteins</k1>
<k1>Research</k1>
<k1>EXPERIMENTAL LAB STUDY</k1>
<k1>LIVER CYTOLOGY</k1>
<no>LR: 20091027; JID: 15540070R; 0 (Proteins); 71-00-1 (Histidine); OTO: NLM; ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY, WEST</pp>
<sn>0366-0753; 0366-0753</sn>
<an>PMID: 14087319</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; OM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>14087319</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3044</id>
<a1>Edwards,K. M.</a1>
<a1>Andrews,T. C.</a1>
<a1>Van Savage,J.</a1>
<a1>Palmer,P. S.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Poxvirus deletion mutants: virulence and immunogenicity</t1>
<jf>Microbial pathogenesis</jf>
<jo>Microb.Pathog.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>4</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>325</sp>
<op>333</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Brain/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Liver/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Lung/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/immunology</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Skin/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Specific Pathogen-Free Organisms</k1>
<k1>Spleen/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Vaccination</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development/immunology/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Post-vaccinial encephalitis and disseminated vaccinia are major concerns with the use of vaccinia virus recombinants as immunization vectors in man. To identify and characterize possible attenuated poxvirus vectors, rabbitpox virus (RPV) (closely related to vaccinia) and four deletion mutants of RPV were studied for organ tropism, neurovirulence, and protection from wild-type challenge in BALB/c mice. Intraperitoneal (IP) inoculation with 10(7) PFU wild-type (wt) RPV or with two mutants 8 sm and 28 (containing approximately 12 kilobase deletions) showed titers of greater than 10(3) PFU/g tissue in multiple organs. In contrast, IP inoculation of 10(7) PFU of mutants 31 or 23 (containing approximately 30 kilobase deletions) showed markedly reduced growth in all organs. Neurovirulence of wt and mutant RPV was determined by intracerebral (IC) inoculation of mice. Wt and mutants 8 sm, and 28 RPV had LD50 less than 10(2) PFU; in contrast, 31 and 23 had LD50 greater than 10(5) PFU. Finally, 10(6) PFU of mutants 31 or 23, were administered to mice by scarification, the normal route of vaccinia immunization. Both 31 and 23 grew locally in the skin and protected mice challenged IC at 21 days with 100 LD50 of wt RPV, while all unimmunized controls died. We conclude that deletion mutants 31 and 23 demonstrate markedly reduced invasiveness and neurovirulence while retaining immunogenicity. Similar deletion mutations in vaccinia may create avirulent, but effective vaccine vectors for man.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: N0IA102645/PHS HHS/United States; JID: 8606191; ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0882-4010; 0882-4010</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee 37232.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2853813; 0882-4010(88)90060-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2853813</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2972</id>
<a1>Empig,C.</a1>
<a1>Kenner,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Perret-Gentil,M.</a1>
<a1>Youree,B. E.</a1>
<a1>Bell,E.</a1>
<a1>Chen,A.</a1>
<a1>Gurwith,M.</a1>
<a1>Higgins,K.</a1>
<a1>Lock,M.</a1>
<a1>Rice,A. D.</a1>
<a1>Schriewer,J.</a1>
<a1>Sinangil,F.</a1>
<a1>White,E.</a1>
<a1>Buller,R. M.</a1>
<a1>Dermody,T. S.</a1>
<a1>Isaacs,S. N.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Highly attenuated smallpox vaccine protects rabbits and mice against pathogenic orthopoxvirus challenge</t1>
<jf>Vaccine</jf>
<jo>Vaccine</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Apr 24</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>3686</sp>
<op>3694</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Viral/blood</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Orthopoxvirus</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Smallpox Vaccine/immunology</k1>
<k1>Vaccination</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Attenuated/immunology</k1>
<ab>The possible reemergence of smallpox through bioterrorism requires the preparation of adequate stockpiles of vaccine. Dryvax, the only US-licensed vaccinia virus smallpox vaccine, has an unacceptable safety profile in the pre-event setting. LC16m8 is a Japanese-licensed attenuated vaccinia virus strain that has been safely used in over 50,000 persons. Until now, efficacy of this vaccine was unproven. Using two animal models, we show that LC16m8 and Dryvax elicit comparable humoral immune responses after a single vaccination and equivalently protect against lethal poxvirus disease. Thus, LC16m8 shows promise as a safe and effective smallpox vaccine with the potential for replacing Dryvax.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8406899; 0 (Antibodies, Viral); 0 (Smallpox Vaccine); 0 (Vaccines, Attenuated); 2004/10/06 [received]; 2005/02/28 [revised]; 2005/03/24 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0264-410X; 0264-410X</sn>
<ad>VaxGen Inc., 347 Oyster Point Boulevard, Suite 102, South San Francisco, CA 94080, USA. cempig@vaxgen.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 16430997; S0264-410X(05)00412-3 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.vaccine.2005.03.029</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16430997</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2988</id>
<a1>Fang,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The effects of the conserved extreme 3&amp;#39; end sequence of hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA on the in vitro stabilization and translation of the HCV RNA genome</t1>
<jf>Journal of hepatology</jf>
<jo>J.Hepatol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>632</sp>
<op>639</op>
<k1>3&#39; Untranslated Regions/genetics</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Conserved Sequence</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genotype</k1>
<k1>Hepacivirus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Mammals</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/genetics</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND/AIMS: The discovery of an additional 98-base in the extreme 3&amp;#39; end of the hepatitis C virus (HCV) has fueled much speculation as to the role of this sequence on the behavior of the virus. It is now known that this additional 98-base sequence is present and conserved amongst HCV genotypes. This sequence is capable of forming complex and stable high-order structures that may be important in stabilizing the RNA to degradation, facilitating translation and regulating replication of the virus. We have examined the possible role of the HCV extreme 3&amp;#39; end sequence in stabilizing the HCV RNA genome and regulating translation in vitro. METHODS: The extreme 3&amp;#39; end sequence was cloned to downstream of two pre-existing two HCV clones: HCV1 (genotype 1a) and HCV-BK (genotype 1b). The reconstructed full-length clones were then tested in vitro for their stability and translation efficiency. RESULTS: We showed that the addition of the conserved 3&amp;#39; end sequence greatly enhanced the stability of HCV1 RNA but had only minimal effect on HCV-BK RNA in mammalian cytoplasmic extracts, suggesting that the requirements for HCV RNA stability vary amongst isolates. Following the optimization of in vitro translation conditions, it was demonstrated that the addition of this 3&amp;#39; end sequence did not affect the translation level from either HCV clone. CONCLUSIONS: The conserved 3&amp;#39; end of the HCV genome confers differential stabilizing effects on two HCV genotype 1 isolates and has no obvious role in the in vitro translation of either clone.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8503886; 0 (3&amp;#39; Untranslated Regions); 0 (RNA, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>DENMARK</pp>
<sn>0168-8278; 0168-8278</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, University of Florida, Gainesville, USA. jfang@ICNpharm.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 11059869; S0168-8278(00)80016-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11059869</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3034</id>
<a1>Feller,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Gibbs,E. P.</a1>
<a1>Bockamp,E. O.</a1>
<a1>Beloso,A.</a1>
<a1>Talavera,A.</a1>
<a1>Vinuela,E.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and molecular characterization of the swinepox virus thymidine kinase gene</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>183</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>578</sp>
<op>585</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Bromodeoxyuridine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Chromosome Mapping</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Drug Resistance, Microbial/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Thymidine Kinase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>Swinepox virus (SPV), the only member of the Suipoxvirus genus, shows little antigenic relatedness or DNA homology to members of the other poxvirus genera. A SPV thymidine kinase (TK) gene was detected and mapped to the left end of the HindIII G fragment using degenerate oligonucleotide probes. Cloning and sequencing of a 1.8-kb HindIII-BamHI fragment containing the SPV TK gene revealed an open reading frame (ORF) of 181 amino acids yielding a predicted polypeptide of Mr 20.6 kDa with significant homology to both poxvirus and vertebrate thymidine kinases. Comparison with other TK protein sequences showed that the SPV thymidine kinase was closely related to the TK genes of avipoxviruses (52.0%) and vertebrates (57.1-59.7%). The TK gene from African swine fever virus (ASF) showed little homology (30.5%) to the SPV TK gene suggesting that these two viruses are not closely related though they share many biochemical features and infect a single, common mammalian host (swine). The SPV TK gene, like that of other poxviruses, is transcribed early, and when cloned into a TK- strain of vaccinia converted the virus to a TK+ phenotype. BUdRR mutants of SPV contained frameshift, deletion, and missense mutations in the TK ORF.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/M55466; GENBANK/M55467; GENBANK/M55468; GENBANK/M60799; GENBANK/M60800; GENBANK/M64000; GENBANK/M69093; GENBANK/M69096; GENBANK/S41807; GENBANK/S41810; GR: 5T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 59-14-3 (Bromodeoxyuridine); EC 2.7.1.21 (Thymidine Kinase); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1853562; 0042-6822(91)90986-L [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1853562</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2999</id>
<a1>Ferguson,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Nicotine phase shifts the 6-sulphatoxymelatonin rhythm and induces c-Fos in the SCN of rats</t1>
<jf>Brain research bulletin</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.Bull.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar 15</fd>
<vo>48</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>527</sp>
<op>538</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biological Markers/urine</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mecamylamine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/analogs &amp; derivatives/urine</k1>
<k1>Muscarinic Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Nicotine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Nicotinic Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Nicotinic Antagonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Oxotremorine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<ab>The neurotransmitter acetylcholine is not found in the major suprachiasmatic nuclei afferents reported to mediate light effects on entrainment and phase shifts in mammals; however it clearly has some role in the control of circadian rhythmicity. This study examined the effect of the cholinergic agonists nicotine and oxotremorine on (1) the rhythmic production of melatonin using the metabolite, 6-sulphatoxymelatonin as a marker, and (2) the expression of c-Fos protein in the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN) of the rat. Nicotine administration (1 mg/kg, s.c.) caused phase delays in the timing of the onset of 6-sulphatoxymelatonin excretion (compared to the pre-treatment night), when administered at circadian time (CT)16 (1.7+/-0.3 h delay) and CT18 (1.7+/-0.2 h delay) but not at CT14 (0.8+/-0.3 h delay), whereas oxotremorine and saline administration had no effect on the timing of the melatonin rhythm. Nicotine administration also caused the induction of c-Fos-like immunoreactivity in the SCN in a dose- and time-dependent manner. Further, pre-treatment with the nicotinic antagonist mecamylamine reduced the number of nicotine-induced c-Fos-positive cells in the SCN by 65%. These data indicate that cholinergic neurons may alter the timing of the onset of melatonin excretion by a direct or indirect effect on the SCN possibly mediated by the nicotinic receptor.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7605818; 0 (Biological Markers); 0 (Muscarinic Agonists); 0 (Nicotinic Agonists); 0 (Nicotinic Antagonists); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 2208-40-4 (6-sulfatoxymelatonin); 54-11-5 (Nicotine); 60-40-2 (Mecamylamine); 70-22-4 (Oxotremorine); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0361-9230; 0361-9230</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Adelaide, Medical School, South Australia, Australia. sferguso@medicine.adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 10372514; S0361-9230(99)00033-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10372514</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3056</id>
<a1>Ficht,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and characterization of a putative bacteriophage T5 transcription.replication enzyme complex from infected Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Jul 25</fd>
<vo>255</vo>
<is>14</is>
<sp>7040</sp>
<op>7048</op>
<k1>DNA Helicases/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Deoxyribonucleases/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Multienzyme Complexes/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Phosphoproteins/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>T-Phages/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>A well defined enzyme comples of approximately 5 X 10(6) daltons that contains phage and host cell components known to be required for the processes of phage transcription and DNA replication has been isolated from bacteriophage T5-infected Escherichia coli cells. In addition to the RNA polymerase of the host cell, the complex contains the phage-encoded: gpC2 which has been implicated genetically as a controlling element of late transcription; gpD9, the DNA polymerase required for T5 DNA replication; the proteins gpD5 (DNA-binding protein), and gpD15 (nuclease) which are both known to be essential for T5 DNA replication and for the initiation of late transcription. The viral gpD5 derived from the purified complex is a phosphoprotein. The enzyme complex also contains, protected from the action of nuclease, double-stranded DNA with an approximate molecular weight of 1 to 2 X 10(6) (2 to 3% of the size of the T5 genome) which is derived preferentially from the center of the T5 DNA molecule. The composition of the enzyme complex suggests that the processes of transcription and replication are integrated in T5-infected cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Multienzyme Complexes); 0 (Phosphoproteins); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); EC 2.7.7.7 (DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); EC 3.1.- (Deoxyribonucleases); EC 3.6.1.- (DNA Helicases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 6248541</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6248541</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2994</id>
<a1>Firth,B. T.</a1>
<a1>Belan,I.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Thermocyclic entrainment of lizard blood plasma melatonin rhythms in constant and cyclic photic environments</t1>
<jf>The American Journal of Physiology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Physiol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>277</vo>
<is>6 Pt 2</is>
<sp>R1620</sp>
<op>6</op>
<k1>Acclimatization/physiology</k1>
<k1>Analysis of Variance</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cold Temperature</k1>
<k1>Darkness</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Lizards/blood/physiology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/blood</k1>
<k1>Sleep</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<ab>We assessed how chronic exposure to 6-h cryophase temperatures of 15 degrees C in an otherwise 33 degrees C environment entrains the rhythm of blood plasma melatonin rhythms in lizards (Tiliqua rugosa) subjected to constant dark (DD), constant light (LL), and to 12:12-h light-dark cycles (12L:12D). The peak of the melatonin rhythm was entrained by the cryophase temperature of the thermocycle in DD and LL, irrespective of the time at which the cryophase temperature was applied. Comparable thermocycles of 6 h at 15 degrees C imposed on a 12L:12D photocycle, however, affected the amplitude and phase of the melatonin rhythm, depending on the phase relationship between light and temperature. Cold pulses in the early light period and at midday resulted, respectively, either in low amplitude or nonexistent melatonin rhythms, whereas those centered in or around the dark phase elicited rhythms of high amplitude. Supplementary experiments in 12L:12D using two intermittent 6-h 15 degrees C cryophases, one delivered in the midscotophase and another in the midphotophase, elicited melatonin rhythms comparable to those in lizards subjected to constant 33 degrees C and 12L:12D. In contrast, lizards subjected to 12L:12D and a 33 degrees C:15 degrees C thermocycle, whose thermophase was aligned with the photophase, produced a threefold increase in the amplitude of the melatonin rhythm. Taken together, these results support the notion that there is an interaction between the external light and temperature cycle and a circadian clock in determining melatonin rhythms in Tiliqua rugosa.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0370511; 73-31-4 (Melatonin); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0002-9513; 0002-9513</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomical Sciences, University of Adelaide, Adelaide, SA 5005, Australia. bruce.firth@adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 10600907</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10600907</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2977</id>
<a1>Flood,W. D.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tsykin,A.</a1>
<a1>Sutherland,G. R.</a1>
<a1>Koblar,S. A.</a1>
<t1>Nxf and Fbxo33: novel seizure-responsive genes in mice</t1>
<jf>The European journal of neuroscience</jf>
<jo>Eur.J.Neurosci.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>1819</sp>
<op>1826</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Brain/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>DNA-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Hippocampus/physiology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>In Situ Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Nerve Tissue Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Oligonucleotide Array Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Reference Values</k1>
<k1>Seizures/genetics/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Transcription Factors/genetics</k1>
<ab>Much is understood about the response of the brain to seizure but little is known in relation to the underlying molecular mechanisms involved. We used microarray technology to investigate the complex genetic response of the brain to generalized seizure. For this investigation a seizure-specific mouse brain cDNA library was generated and spotted onto microarray slides with the aim of increasing the likelihood of identifying novel genes responsive to seizure. Microarray analysis was performed on mouse hippocampus 1 h after generalized seizure pharmacologically induced by pentylenetetrazol (PTZ). Using the custom microarray slides, six genes were identified as being up-regulated in this seizure model and results were validated by real-time PCR. Four of the seizure-responsive genes had previously-reported roles in apoptosis, proliferation or differentiation of neural cells. Two of the genes were novel and in situ hybridization analysis demonstrated heightened mRNA expression in the hippocampus 1 h following generalized convulsive seizure, in a pattern which is typical for other activity-dependant genes expressed in this structure. In addition to being up-regulated postseizure, the genes described in this paper appear to be expressed normally in the adult hippocampus and during development.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8918110; 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (DNA-Binding Proteins); 0 (Fbxo33 protein, mouse); 0 (Nerve Tissue Proteins); 0 (Nfx1 protein, mouse); 0 (Transcription Factors); ppublish</no>
<pp>France</pp>
<sn>0953-816X; 0953-816X</sn>
<ad>Department of Genetic Medicine, Women&#39;s and Children&#39;s Hospital, North Adelaide, SA, Australia 5006.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15380003; EJN3646 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03646.x</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15380003</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3012</id>
<a1>Graham,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Lalani,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Macen,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Ness,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Barry,M.</a1>
<a1>Liu,L. Y.</a1>
<a1>Lucas,A.</a1>
<a1>Clark-Lewis,I.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<t1>The T1/35kDa family of poxvirus-secreted proteins bind chemokines and modulate leukocyte influx into virus-infected tissues</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar 3</fd>
<vo>229</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>12</sp>
<op>24</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Chemokines/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Chemotaxis, Leukocyte</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Leukocytes/cytology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Viral Nonstructural Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Immunomodulatory proteins encoded by the larger DNA viruses interact with a wide spectrum of immune effector molecules that regulate the antiviral response in the infected host. Here we show that certain poxviruses, including myxoma virus. Shope fibroma virus, rabbitpox virus, vaccinia virus (strain Lister), cowpox virus, and raccoonpox virus, express a new family of secreted proteins which interact with members of both the CC and CXC superfamilies of chemokines. However, swinepox virus and vaccinia virus (strain WR) do not express this activity Using a recombinant poxviruses, the myxoma M-T1 and rabbitpox virus 35kDa secreted proteins were identified as prototypic members of this family of chemokine binding proteins. Members of this T1/35kDa family of poxvirus-secreted proteins share multiple stretches of identical sequence motifs, including eight conserved cysteine residues, but are otherwise unrelated to any cellular genes in the database. The affinity of the CC chemokine RANTES interaction with M-T1 was assessed by Scatchard analysis and yielded a Kd of approximately 73 nM. In rabbits infected with a mutant rabbitpox virus, in which the 35kDa gene is deleted, there was an increased number of extravasating leukocytes in the deep dermis during the early phases of infection. These observations suggest that members of the T1/35kDa class of secreted viral proteins bind multiple members of the chemokine superfamily in vitro and modulate the influx of inflammatory cells into virus-infected tissues in vivo.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/U62677; GENBANK/U64724; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (Chemokines); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Nonstructural Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9123853; S0042-6822(96)98423-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1996.8423</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9123853</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3032</id>
<a1>Gruidl,M. E.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Mapping and molecular characterization of a functional thymidine kinase from Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>186</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>507</sp>
<op>516</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Insect Viruses/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Lepidoptera/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Thymidine Kinase/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>A thymidine kinase (TK) gene from the entomopoxvirus of Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) has been identified, mapped, cloned, and sequenced. The AmEPV TK was shown to be biologically functional as cloning of the gene into a TK-derivative of the orthopoxvirus vaccinia creates a TK+ virus. The gene has been localized to a 1.5-kb EcoRI-Q DNA fragment which maps to the far left end of the viral genome. Sequence analysis reveals an open reading frame (ORF) of 182 amino acids potentially encoding a polypeptide of 21.2 kDa. Amino acid homology comparisons indicate that the gene is most closely related to the TKs of a variety of poxviruses (approximately 45%) and less so to the TKs of vertebrates (approximately 40%). The TK from African swine fever virus (ASF) showed the least homology (31.4%) to the AmEPV TK gene, suggesting that these two viruses are not closely related although ASF shares some biological features of poxviruses, and both ASF and AmEPV can replicate within arthropod hosts.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/M80924; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); EC 2.7.1.21 (Thymidine Kinase); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, JHMHC, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1733099</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1733099</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3015</id>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Li,Y.</a1>
<a1>Feller,J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus spheroidin gene is improperly transcribed in vertebrate poxviruses</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Oct 15</fd>
<vo>224</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>427</sp>
<op>436</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Lac Operon</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Structural Proteins</k1>
<ab>The Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus (AmEPv) spheroidin is the most highly expressed late viral gene product in infected insect cells. However, when a cassette containing the spheroidin gene and putative promoter was inserted into cowpox (CPV) or vaccinia viruses, only very low levels of spheroldin gene expression were observed. Primer extension analysis suggests much lower spheroidin gene transcript levels than seen either for the highly expressed CPV A-type inclusion gene or for the spheroidin gene within infected insect cells, indicating that in vertebrate cells, the spheroidin promoter functions poorly if at all. Examination of the spheroidin mRNA synthesized in recombinant CPV shows that the 5&amp;#39; start site of the spheroidin transcript was also unexpectedly imprecise and upstream (approximately 31 bp) of the well-defined start site normally observed in AmEPV-infected insect cells. Sequencing of the 5&amp;#39; terminus of the CPV recombinant spheroidin mRNA suggested that 5&amp;#39; poly(A), a characteristic feature of late poxvirus mRNAs and spheroidin mRNA derived from insect cells, was absent, despite the presence of the typical vertebrate poxvirus late promoter consensus sequence, TAAATG. Our results indicate that insect and vertebrate poxvirus promoters may not be universally interchangeable and imply that there are regulatory features of gene expression unique to the infected insect cell environment.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0110674; 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Structural Proteins); 0 (spheroidin protein, Entomopoxvirus); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology; College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8874503; S0042-6822(96)90549-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1996.0549</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8874503</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3028</id>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Identification of an Amsacta spheroidin-like protein within the occlusion bodies of Choristoneura entomopoxviruses</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>192</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>179</sp>
<op>187</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Viral/immunology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Insect Viruses/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Sequence Alignment</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/chemistry/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Viral Structural Proteins/genetics</k1>
<ab>Like baculoviruses, a characteristic feature of entomopoxviruses is the amalgamation of virions within environmentally stable occlusion bodies. It is this occluded form of the virus that is primarily responsible for dissemination to other insects. While the major protein (polyhedrin) of baculovirus occlusions is quite similar between viruses, it has been reported that the major occlusion body protein (spheroidin) of two group B entomopoxviruses, Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) and Choristoneura biennis (CbEPV) is quite different both in terms of amino acid sequence and coding capacity of the corresponding spheroidin genes (115 and 47 kDa for AmEPV and CbEPV, respectively). We report the discovery of a AmEPV spheroidin gene homolog in both CbEPV and a second Choristoneura virus, Choristoneura fumiferana (CfEPV). Antibodies directed against the AmEPV 115-kDa spheroidin reacted with the major protein of approximately 115 kDa found within the occlusion body preparation from both Choristoneura viruses. Direct protein microsequencing of small portions of the 115-kDa protein from CbEPV has resulted in peptide sequences identical to those of corresponding regions of the AmEPV spheroidin gene. We suggest that it is this Choristoneura gene which encodes spheroidin. All attempts, however, to find a homolog of the previously reported CbEPV spheroidin gene within AmEPV have been unsuccessful. We also show this newly identified Choristoneura homolog of the AmEPV spheroidin gene as well as the AmEPV spheroidin gene itself are both located at the 3&amp;#39; end of an NPH I gene and are highly homologous in all three viruses, indicating that this region of the genome in the three viruses is co-linear. These results and others suggest that while the insect viruses lack the traditional central core of conserved genes observed for the vertebrate poxviruses, the insect poxviruses may have also evolved an alternative central core of conserved genes, unique to the invertebrate poxviruses.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/L02637; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI-07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antibodies, Viral); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Structural Proteins); 0 (spheroidin protein, Entomopoxvirus); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8517016; S0042-6822(83)71020-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1993.1020</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8517016</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3033</id>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Identification, cloning, and sequencing of a fragment of Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus DNA containing the spheroidin gene and three vaccinia virus-related open reading frames</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>6516</sp>
<op>6527</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Composition</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Insect Viruses/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Insects</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron, Scanning</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Structural Proteins</k1>
<ab>Entomopoxvirus virions are frequently contained within crystalline occlusion bodies, which are composed of primarily a single protein, spheroidin, which is analogous to the polyhedrin protein of baculovirus. The spheroidin gene of Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus was identified following the microsequencing of polypeptides generated from cyanogen bromide treatment of spheroidin and the subsequent synthesis of oligonucleotide hybridization probes. DNA sequencing of a 6.8-kb region of DNA containing the spheroidin gene showed that the spheroidin protein is derived from a 3.0-kb open reading frame potentially encoding a protein of 115 kDa. Three copies of the heptanucleotide, TTTTTNT, a sequence associated with early gene transcription in the vertebrate poxviruses, and four in-frame translational termination signals were found within 60 bp upstream of the putative spheroidin gene promoter (TAAATG). The spheroidin gene promoter region contains the sequence TAAATG, which is found in many late promoters of the vertebrate poxviruses and which serves as the site of transcriptional initiation, as shown by primer extension. Primer extension experiments also showed that spheroidin gene transcripts contain 5&amp;#39; poly(A) sequences typical of vertebrate poxvirus late transcripts. The 92 bases upstream of the initiating TAAATG are unusually A + T rich and contain only 7 G or C residues. An analysis of open reading frames around the spheroidin gene suggests that the colinear core of &amp;quot;essential genes&amp;quot; typical of the vertebrate poxviruses is absent in A. moorei entomopoxvirus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/M64578; GENBANK/M64579; GENBANK/M64580; GENBANK/M64581; GENBANK/M64582; GENBANK/M64583; GENBANK/M74720; GENBANK/M77182; GENBANK/S59503; GENBANK/S59651; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI-07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Structural Proteins); 0 (spheroidin protein, Entomopoxvirus); OID: NLM: PMC250701; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1942245</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1942245</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC250701</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3055</id>
<a1>Hamilton,D. H.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,S. A.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of the non-permissive infection of rabbit cornea cells by vesicular stomatitis virus</t1>
<jf>The Journal of general virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>49</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>273</sp>
<op>287</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cornea</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique</k1>
<k1>Helper Viruses/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>RNA Caps/analysis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Ribonucleoproteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vesicular stomatitis Indiana virus/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Rabbit cornea cells (RC-60) restrict the reproduction of vesicular stomatitis virus (VSV) (Thacore &amp;amp; Youngner, 1975). In cells infected with VSV alone, an inhibition in the synthesis of VSV genome RNA is observed. A number of parameters which could affect virus RNA synthesis have been examined: virus transcription and post-transcriptional modification, translation, modification of proteins and migration of the G protein to the surface of the cell; they all appear to be normal, although somewhat diminished, in the restricted system. In these cells, therefore, it is the replication of VSV RNA that is directly inhibited, although limited synthesis of both (+) and (-) strand genome length RNA does occur. When the cells are co-infected with rabbit poxvirus (RPV) as a helper virus, however, VSV production is normal. Our studies suggest that RPV plays a role in the maturation as well as in the replication of VSV RNA in RC-60 cells. Certain mutants of RPV have been found to lack the helper function and are unable to convert the RC-60 cells into a permissive host for VSV. These mutants should facilitate the elucidation of the mechanism by which RPV is able to overcome the restriction in these cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; GR: 1 R01-14594-01/PHS HHS/United States; GR: 5T32GM07319/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0077340; 0 (RNA Caps); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Ribonucleoproteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-1317; 0022-1317</sn>
<an>PMID: 6255068</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6255068</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3061</id>
<a1>Herman,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>In vivo repair of bacteriophage t5 DNA: an assay for viral growth control</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>393</sp>
<op>407</op>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Calcium/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/enzymology/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Repair/drug effects</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Agar Gel</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Polynucleotide Ligases/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); 7440-70-2 (Calcium); EC 6.5.1.- (Polynucleotide Ligases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<an>PMID: 1098275</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1098275</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3064</id>
<a1>Herman,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>In vivo repair of the single-strand interruptions contained in bacteriophage T5 DNA</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1974</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>680</sp>
<op>684</op>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Repair</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA Viruses/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Lysogeny</k1>
<k1>Phosphorus Radioisotopes</k1>
<ab>Bacteriophage T5 is known to contain several unique single-strand interruptions in only one strand of the duplex DNA. Analysis of labeled parental phage DNA from infected Escherichia coli shows that these nicks are repaired in vivo to yield intact double-stranded molecules. Sealing begins at about 6 min after infection and is independent of DNA replication. Repair may be an ordered process that starts at a unique end of the molecule.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Phosphorus Radioisotopes); OID: NLM: PMC388076; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 4522782</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4522782</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC388076</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3072</id>
<a1>Hultquist,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Boyer,P. D.</a1>
<t1>The preparation and characterization of 1-phosphohistidine and 3-phosphohistidine</t1>
<jf>Biochemistry</jf>
<jo>Biochemistry</jo>
<yr>1966</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>331</op>
<k1>Amides</k1>
<k1>Chemical Phenomena</k1>
<k1>Chemistry</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, Ion Exchange</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis</k1>
<k1>Histidine</k1>
<k1>Hydrogen-Ion Concentration</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy</k1>
<k1>Phosphates</k1>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0370623; 0 (Amides); 0 (Phosphates); 71-00-1 (Histidine); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0006-2960; 0006-2960</sn>
<an>PMID: 5938947</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>5938947</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2995</id>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>MK-801 administration blocks the effects of a 5-HT(2A/2C) agonist on melatonin rhythmicity and c-fos induction in the suprachiasmatic nucleus</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Oct 16</fd>
<vo>845</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>102</sp>
<op>106</op>
<k1>Activity Cycles/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Dizocilpine Maleate/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Excitatory Amino Acid Antagonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Indophenol/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/analogs &amp; derivatives/metabolism/urine</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C</k1>
<k1>Receptors, N-Methyl-D-Aspartate/physiology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Serotonin/physiology</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/chemistry/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Both excitatory amino acids and serotonin have been implicated in the photic control of rhythms, but they have rarely been considered to interact. This study investigated the effects of the NMDA receptor antagonist, MK-801 on the phase shift of the melatonin rhythm and the induction of c-fos in the rat suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) provoked by the administration of the serotonin agonist DOI ((+/-)-1-(4-Iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-2-aminopropane hydrochloride). The urinary excretion rate rhythm of the melatonin metabolite, 6-sulphatoxymelatonin was delayed by administration of DOI (0.5 mg/kg) at CT18 (6 h after subjective darkness onset) as previously reported by our group. Administration of MK-801 (3 mg/kg) 30 min before DOI blocked the shift in the onset of excretion of the melatonin metabolite on the following nights. Pre-treatment with MK-801 also inhibited by approximately 90% the induction of c-fos in the SCN by DOI at ZT18 (6 h after actual darkness onset) as determined by immunohistochemistry. These results provide evidence for a role of excitatory amino acids in the photomimetic effects of serotonin 5-HT(2C) agonists in the rat.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0045503; 0 (Excitatory Amino Acid Antagonists); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C); 0 (Receptors, N-Methyl-D-Aspartate); 0 (Receptors, Serotonin); 0 (Serotonin Agonists); 0 (dimethoxy-4-indophenyl-2-aminopropane); 2208-40-4 (6-sulfatoxymelatonin); 500-85-6 (Indophenol); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); 77086-22-7 (Dizocilpine Maleate); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Adelaide, Medical School, Frome Road, Adelaide, Australia.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10529449; S0006-8993(99)01951-4 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10529449</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3002</id>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Serotonin 5-HT2c agonists mimic the effect of light pulses on circadian rhythms</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Sep 28</fd>
<vo>806</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>257</sp>
<op>270</op>
<k1>Amphetamines/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Body Temperature/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/drug effects/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Ketanserin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Periodicity</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation/methods</k1>
<k1>Piperazines/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Ritanserin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Antagonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The serotonin agonist quipazine has been shown to cause phase shifts in melatonin and activity rhythms and to induce c-fos in the suprachiasmatic nucleus of rats. In this study, in vivo pharmacological characterisation of the phase shifting properties of serotonin agonists has been performed, with a view to determining the receptor sub-types involved. Agonists for the 5-HT2a/2c receptors, (+/-)-1-(4-iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-2-aminopropane hydrochloride (DOI, 0.1 mg/k), 1-(3-chlorophenyl)-piperazine HCl (mCPP, 2 mg/kg) and N-(3-trifluoromethylphenyl)-piperazine HCl (TFMPP, 2 mg/kg) injected at CT18 resulted in acute transient inhibition of melatonin production and delays in the onset of production on the following nights of 1.2+/-0.2, 1.7+/-0.3 and 1. 4+/-0.8 h respectively. Drugs specific for 5-HT1a/7 and 5-HT3 receptors failed to affect melatonin production. At a dose of 0.07 micromole/kg, the serotonin antagonist, ritanserin inhibited the DOI induced phase delay whereas ketanserin was ineffective at this dose, providing strong evidence that DOI was acting through 5-HT2c receptors. DOI (0.5 mg/kg) at CT18 provoked a phase delay in the core body temperature rhythm of similar magnitude to that following a light pulse. Administration of DOI but not agonists active at other receptor sites resulted in the appearance of c-Fos in the ventrolateral division of the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) at CT18 but not at CT6. Ritanserin was more potent than ketanserin at inhibiting the DOI induced increase in c-Fos labelled cells in the SCN. When rats were pre-treated with metergoline (15 mg/kg), ritanserin (3 mg/kg) or LY 53,857 (3 mg/kg) prior to a 2 lx/ 1 min light pulse, none of the drugs significantly inhibited the responses to light. The results of these experiments indicate that serotonergic agonists active at the 5-HT2c receptor mimic the effects of light on 2 independent rhythms and activate SCN neurones in the rat.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 1998; JID: 0045503; 0 (Amphetamines); 0 (Piperazines); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 0 (Serotonin Agonists); 0 (Serotonin Antagonists); 15532-75-9 (1-(3-trifluoromethylphenyl)piperazine); 64584-34-5 (4-iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenylisopropylamine); 6640-24-0 (1-(3-chlorophenyl)piperazine); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); 74050-98-9 (Ketanserin); 87051-43-2 (Ritanserin); ppublish</no>
<pb>Elsevier Science B.V</pb>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, The University of Adelaide, Frome Road, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005, Australia.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9739147; S0006-8993(98)00746-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9739147</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2987</id>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Voultsios,A.</a1>
<a1>Varcoe,T. J.</a1>
<t1>Serotonin, excitatory amino acids and the photic control of melatonin rhythms and SCN c-FOS in the rat</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Apr 6</fd>
<vo>897</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>36</sp>
<op>43</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Dizocilpine Maleate/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Excitatory Amino Acid Antagonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Excitatory Amino Acids/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Immediate-Early/physiology</k1>
<k1>Indophenol/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/physiology</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C</k1>
<k1>Receptors, N-Methyl-D-Aspartate/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Serotonin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serotonin/physiology</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/physiology</k1>
<ab>There is a growing acceptance that serotonergic pathways to the suprachiasmatic nucleus play an important role in the mediation and modulation of light entrainment of rhythms. In this study administration of the 5-HT(2A/2C) agonist (+/-)-1-(4-iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-2-aminopropane (DOI, 0.5 mg/kg) at mid dark caused a phase shift in the onset of the urinary excretion of 6-sulphatoxymelatonin in rats that was sustained for at least 8 days and was blocked by the specific 5-HT(2C) antagonist SB-242084. Administration of DOI (2 mg/kg) across the night resulted in the appearance of c-FOS in the nucleus of cells in the suprachiasmatic nucleus during subjective darkness, but did not cause induction at the time of expected lights on (CT0). By contrast light exposure induced c-fos throughout the night including CT0. Administration of the NMDA receptor antagonist MK-801 (3 mg/kg) prior to light pulses had no effect on c-fos in the first part of the night, but towards the expected time of lights on, became progressively more potent, such that by CT0, light induction of c-fos was almost completely inhibited. These results provide further evidence that serotonin plays a role in the mediation of light effects on rhythms in the rat.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0045503; 0 (Excitatory Amino Acid Antagonists); 0 (Excitatory Amino Acids); 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C); 0 (Receptors, N-Methyl-D-Aspartate); 0 (Receptors, Serotonin); 0 (Serotonin Agonists); 0 (dimethoxy-4-indophenyl-2-aminopropane); 50-67-9 (Serotonin); 500-85-6 (Indophenol); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); 77086-22-7 (Dizocilpine Maleate); ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Adelaide University, Medical School, Frome Road, South Australia, 5005, Adelaide, Australia. david.kennaway@adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 11282356; S0006-8993(01)02091-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11282356</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2982</id>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Voultsios,A.</a1>
<a1>Varcoe,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Melatonin and activity rhythm responses to light pulses in mice with the Clock mutation</t1>
<jf>American journal of physiology.Regulatory, integrative and comparative physiology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Physiol.Regul.Integr.Comp.Physiol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>284</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>R1231</sp>
<op>40</op>
<k1>Activity Cycles</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>CLOCK Proteins</k1>
<k1>Darkness</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Isoproterenol</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/blood/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Motor Activity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Mutation/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Pineal Gland/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Trans-Activators/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Melatonin and wheel-running rhythmicity and the effects of acute and chronic light pulses on these rhythms were studied in Clock(Delta19) mutant mice selectively bred to synthesize melatonin. Homozygous melatonin-proficient Clock(Delta19) mutant mice (Clock(Delta19/Delta19)-MEL) produced melatonin rhythmically, with peak production 2 h later than the wild-type controls (i.e., just before lights on). By contrast, the time of onset of wheel-running activity occurred within a 20-min period around lights off, irrespective of the genotype. Melatonin production in the mutants spontaneously decreased within 1 h of the expected time of lights on. On placement of the mice in continuous darkness, the melatonin rhythm persisted, and the peak occurred 2 h later in each cycle over the first two cycles, consistent with the endogenous period of the mutant. This contrasted with the onset of wheel-running activity, which did not shift for several days in constant darkness. A light pulse around the time of expected lights on followed by constant darkness reduced the expected 2-h delay of the melatonin peak of the mutants to approximately 1 h and advanced the time of the melatonin peak in the wild-type mice. When the Clock(Delta19/Delta19)-MEL mice were maintained in a skeleton photoperiod of daily 15-min light pulses, a higher proportion entrained to the schedule (57%) than melatonin-deficient mutants (9%). These results provide compelling evidence that mice with the Clock(Delta19) mutation express essentially normal rhythmicity, albeit with an underlying endogenous period of 26-27 h, and they can be entrained by brief exposure to light. They also raise important questions about the role of Clock in rhythmicity and the usefulness of monitoring behavioral rhythms compared with hormonal rhythms.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 100901230; 0 (Trans-Activators); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); 7683-59-2 (Isoproterenol); EC 2.3.1.48 (CLOCK Proteins); EC 2.3.1.48 (Clock protein, mouse); 2003/01/09 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0363-6119; 0363-6119</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Adelaide Medical School, Adelaide, South Australia 5005, Australia. david.kennaway@adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 12521925; 00697.2002 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM; S</sf>
<do>10.1152/ajpregu.00697.2002</do>
<wp>20030109</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12521925</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2984</id>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Voultsios,A.</a1>
<a1>Varcoe,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Melatonin in mice: rhythms, response to light, adrenergic stimulation, and metabolism</t1>
<jf>American journal of physiology.Regulatory, integrative and comparative physiology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Physiol.Regul.Integr.Comp.Physiol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>282</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>R358</sp>
<op>65</op>
<k1>Adrenergic beta-Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/physiology</k1>
<k1>Isoproterenol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Lighting</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/analogs &amp; derivatives/blood/pharmacology/urine</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred CBA</k1>
<k1>Photoperiod</k1>
<k1>Pineal Gland/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Radioimmunoassay</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<ab>There has been relatively little research conducted on pineal melatonin production in laboratory mice, in part, due to the lack of appropriate assays. We studied the pineal and plasma rhythm, response to light, adrenergic stimulation, and metabolism of melatonin in CBA mice. With the use of a sensitive and specific melatonin RIA, melatonin was detected in the pineal glands at all times of the day &amp;gt;21 fmol/gland in CBA mice but not in C57Bl mice. Both plasma and pineal melatonin levels peaked 2 h before dawn in a 12:12-h light-dark photoperiod (162 +/- 31 pM and 1,804 +/- 514 fmol/gland, respectively). A brief light pulse (200 lx/15 min), 2 h before lights on, suppressed both plasma and pineal melatonin to near basal levels within 30 min. Exposure to light pulses 4 h after lights off or 2 h before lights on resulted in delays and advances, respectively, in the early morning decline of plasma and pineal melatonin on the next cycle. Administration of the beta-adrenergic agonist isoproterenol (20 mg/kg) 2 and 4 h after lights on in the morning resulted in a fivefold increase in plasma and pineal melatonin 2.5 to 3 h after the first injection. In the mouse, unlike the rat, melatonin was shown to be metabolized almost exclusively to 6-glucuronylmelatonin rather than 6-sulphatoxymelatonin. These studies have shown that the appropriate methodological tools are now available for studying melatonin rhythms in mice.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 100901230; 0 (Adrenergic beta-Agonists); 2208-40-4 (6-sulfatoxymelatonin); 73-31-4 (Melatonin); 7683-59-2 (Isoproterenol); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0363-6119; 0363-6119</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Adelaide University, Medical School, Adelaide, South Australia 5005. david.kennaway@adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 11792644</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1152/ajpregu.00360.2001</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11792644</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3001</id>
<a1>Lalani,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Ness,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Singh,R.</a1>
<a1>Harrison,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Seet,B. T.</a1>
<a1>Kelvin,D. J.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Functional comparisons among members of the poxvirus T1/35kDa family of soluble CC-chemokine inhibitor glycoproteins</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Oct 10</fd>
<vo>250</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>173</sp>
<op>184</op>
<k1>Calcium/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Chemokines/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Chemotaxis, Leukocyte</k1>
<k1>Glycoproteins/chemistry/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Glycosylation</k1>
<k1>HL-60 Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Monocytes/cytology</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Neutrophils/cytology</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Chemokine</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/immunology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/chemistry/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Many poxviruses express a 35-40-kDa secreted protein, termed &amp;quot;T1&amp;quot; (for leporipoxviruses) or &amp;quot;35kDa&amp;quot; (for orthopoxviruses), that binds CC-chemokines with high affinity but is unrelated to any known cellular proteins. Many previously identified poxvirus cytokine-binding proteins display strict species ligand-binding specificity. Because the T1 and 35kDa proteins share only 40% amino acid identity, we compared the abilities of purified myxoma virus-T1 (M-T1) and vaccinia virus (strain Lister)- and rabbitpox virus-35kDa proteins to inhibit human CC-chemokines in vitro. All three proteins were equally effective in preventing several human CC-chemokines from binding to target chemokine receptors and blocking subsequent intracellular calcium release. The inhibitory affinities were comparable (Ki = 0.07-1.02 nM). These proteins also displayed similar abilities to inhibit (IC50 = 6.3-10.5 nM) human macrophage inflammatory protein-1alpha-mediated chemotaxis of human monocytes. None of the viral proteins blocked interleukin-8-mediated calcium flux or chemotaxis of human neutrophils, confirming that the biological specificity of the T1/35kDa family is targeted inhibition of CC-chemokines. Despite the significant sequence divergence between the leporipoxvirus T1 and orthopoxvirus 35kDa proteins, our data suggest that their CC-chemokine binding and inhibitory properties appear to be species nonspecific and that the critical motifs most likely reside within the limited regions of conservation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; CI: Copyright 1998; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Chemokines); 0 (Glycoproteins); 0 (Receptors, Chemokine); 0 (Viral Proteins); 7440-70-2 (Calcium); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2H7, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9770431; S0042-6822(98)99340-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1998.9340</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9770431</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2976</id>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Liston,P.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Functional analysis of the inhibitor of apoptosis (iap) gene carried by the entomopoxvirus of Amsacta moorei</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>2335</sp>
<op>2345</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral/physiology</k1>
<k1>Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins</k1>
<k1>Lepidoptera/virology</k1>
<k1>Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>The entomopoxvirus from Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) contains none of the commonly recognized vertebrate poxvirus apoptotic suppressor genes. However, AmEPV carries a single inhibitor of apoptosis (iap) gene (AMViap) not present in vertebrate poxviruses. The AMViap gene was active when coexpressed with the Drosophila proapoptotic gene hid in Ld652 cells and can rescue cells from apoptosis as shown by increased number of surviving cells and reduced levels of caspase-3-like activity. We also showed that expression of the AMViap gene rescued polyhedron production in Autographa californica M nucleopolyhedrovirus (AcMNPV)Deltap35-infected Sf9 cells during an otherwise abortive infection induced by apoptosis. Surprisingly, deletion of the AMViap gene from the AmEPV genome led to only a modest (10-fold) loss of virion production in infected Ld652 cells, indicating that the AMViap gene is nonessential for virus replication under these conditions. However, infection of Ld652 cells by AmEPV lacking a functional iap gene led to a more rapid induction of cytotoxicity and increased levels of caspase-3-like activity. Similar results were observed and were more pronounced in infected Sf9 and S2 cells. The purified AMVIAP protein also inhibits the enzymatic activities of human caspase-9 and caspase-3 in vitro. Our results indicate that while the AMViap gene was active in controlling apoptosis through the intrinsic pathway, the virus likely encodes additional proteins that also regulate apoptosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 5R01AI046479-04/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins); 0 (Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC546542; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15681434; 79/4/2335 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.79.4.2335-2345.2005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15681434</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC546542</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2975</id>
<a1>Li,Q.</a1>
<a1>Liston,P.</a1>
<a1>Schokman,N.</a1>
<a1>Ho,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Amsacta moorei Entomopoxvirus inhibitor of apoptosis suppresses cell death by binding Grim and Hid</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>3684</sp>
<op>3691</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Carrier Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Drosophila Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/physiology</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins</k1>
<k1>Intracellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins</k1>
<k1>Mitochondrial Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Neuropeptides/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Peptide Library</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Protein Interaction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Inhibitor of apoptosis (iap) genes have been identified in the genomes of two independent families of insect viruses, the Baculoviridae and the Entomopoxvirinae. In this report, we examined the functional attributes of the Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus-encoded IAP protein (AMV-IAP). The binding specificity of the individual baculoviral IAP repeat (BIR) domains of AMV-IAP was investigated by using a random-peptide, phage display library, and sequences similar to the amino termini of proapoptotic Drosophila proteins in the Reaper/Hid/Grim family were identified. Furthermore, the BIR domains of AMV-IAP protein were demonstrated to bind the mammalian IAP inhibitor Smac through the AVPI tetrapeptide sequence, suggesting that the peptide binding pocket and groove found in the insect and mammalian IAPs is conserved in this viral protein. Interaction analysis implicated BIR1 as the high-affinity site for Grim, while BIR2 interacted more strongly with Hid. Both Grim and Hid were demonstrated to interact with AMV-IAP in vivo, and Grim- or Hid-induced cell death was suppressed when AMV-IAP was coexpressed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 5R01AI046479-04/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Carrier Proteins); 0 (DIABLO protein, human); 0 (Drosophila Proteins); 0 (Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins); 0 (Intracellular Signaling Peptides and Proteins); 0 (Mitochondrial Proteins); 0 (Neuropeptides); 0 (Peptide Library); 0 (Proteins); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (grim protein, Drosophila); 0 (wrinkled protein, Drosophila); OID: NLM: PMC1075740; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15731262; 79/6/3684 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.79.6.3684-3691.2005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15731262</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1075740</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3007</id>
<a1>Li,Y.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Transient, nonlethal expression of genes in vertebrate cells by recombinant entomopoxviruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>71</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>9557</sp>
<op>9562</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Lac Operon</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Virion</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<ab>The group B entomopoxvirus (EPV) from Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) productively infects only insect cells. A series of AmEPV-lacZ recombinants was constructed in which the lacZ gene was regulated by either late (the AmEPV spheroidin or the cowpox virus A-type inclusion [ATI]) or early (the AmEPV esp [early strong promoter; derived from a 42-kDa AmEPV protein] or the Melolontha melolontha EPV fusolin, fus) virus promoters. When the AmEPV recombinants were used to infect vertebrate cells, beta-galactosidase expression occurred (in &amp;gt;30% of the cells) when lacZ was regulated by either the fus or esp early promoters but not when lacZ was regulated by the late promoters (spheroidin or ATI). Therefore, AmEPV enters vertebrate cells and undergoes at least a partial uncoating and early, but not late, viral genes are expressed. Neither viral DNA synthesis nor cytopathic effects were observed under any infection conditions. When an AmEPV recombinant virus containing the Aequorea victoria green fluorescent protein gene (gfp) under the control of the esp promoter was used to infect vertebrate cells at a low multiplicity of infection, single fluorescent cells resulted, which continued to divide over a period of several days, ultimately forming fluorescent cell clusters, suggesting that vertebrate cells survive the infection and continue to grow. Therefore, AmEPV may prove to be a highly efficient, nontoxic method of gene delivery into vertebrate cells for transient gene expression.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); OID: NLM: PMC230263; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9371619</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9371619</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC230263</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3006</id>
<a1>Li,Y.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Yuan,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>High-level expression of Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus spheroidin depends on sequences within the gene</t1>
<jf>The Journal of general virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>79 ( Pt 3)</vo>
<is>Pt 3</is>
<sp>613</sp>
<op>622</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Reporter</k1>
<k1>Insects</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Promoter Regions, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Structural Proteins</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Spheroidin (SPH) is the most highly expressed gene of the entomopoxvirus isolated from Amsacta moorei (AmEPV). The level of expression of poxvirus genes is believed to be governed in large part by the promoter. Poxvirus promoters generally consist of approximately 40 bp which frequently terminate at the 3&amp;#39; end with a translation initiating TAAATG sequence. We have examined the requirements for high levels of SPH gene expression by constructing AmEPV recombinants containing either the SPH promoter or the late vertebrate poxvirus promoter derived from the cowpox virus A-type inclusion (ATI) gene. In addition, we have examined SPH promoter derivatives which extend beyond the 3&amp;#39; TAAATG to include 2 or 20 bp of the 5&amp;#39; coding sequence of the SPH gene. Examination of insect cells infected with these AmEPV ATI-lacZ or SPH-lacZ recombinants suggests that ATI-lacZ expression begins 12 h before and is essentially complete prior to any SPH-lacZ expression, allowing functional distinction between the ATI and SPH promoters and implying that different factors regulate the two promoters within the insect environment. SPH promoter-regulated expression is significantly enhanced within infected insect cells by including the additional 20 bp of the N-terminal SPH coding sequences as part of the promoter. However, when any of the SPH promoter constructs, including those containing the downstream sequences, were inserted into vaccinia virus, only very low levels of beta-galactosidase expression were observed. These results imply that downstream coding sequences within the SPH gene enhance SPH gene expression only within the insect environment.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0077340; 0 (A-type inclusion protein, poxvirus); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (Viral Structural Proteins); 0 (spheroidin protein, Entomopoxvirus); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-1317; 0022-1317</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9519842</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9519842</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3003</id>
<a1>Li,Y.</a1>
<a1>Yuan,S.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The non-permissive infection of insect (gypsy moth) LD-652 cells by Vaccinia virus</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Aug 15</fd>
<vo>248</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>74</sp>
<op>82</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Moths</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Vertebrates</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<k1>beta-Galactosidase/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>The members of Poxviridae family are among the most complex of animal viruses and subfamily members infect both vertebrate (Chordopoxvirinae) and invertebrate (Entomopoxvirinae) hosts, respectively. Vaccinia virus (VV) is the most commonly studied vertebrate virus and the entomopoxvirus of Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) is the prototypic insect virus. AmEPV, while not able to productively infect vertebrate cells, does enter vertebrate cells and expresses early genes after which the infection aborts although the cells survive (Y. Li, R. L. Hall, and R. W. Moyer. J.Virol. 71(12), 95579562, 1997). We show here that a recombinant VV, containing the lacZ gene regulated by the cowpox virus A-type inclusion (ATI) late promoter, likewise does not productively infect insect cells. Our results suggest that the recombinant VV enters insect cells, host protein synthesis is inhibited, early gene expression is normal, and viral DNA replication occurs as does late protein synthesis. However, little if any proteolytic processing of late viral proteins, typical of morphogenesis, is observed. Electron micrographs of infected cells suggest that while cytoplasmic virosomes (factories) are formed, there is little indication of further morphogenesis or any formation of mature virions. Therefore, while both orthopoxviruses and entomopoxviruses fail to replicate in heterologous hosts, the nature of abortive infections is quite different.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; CI: Copyright 1998; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.2.1.23 (beta-Galactosidase); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, 32010-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9705257; S0042-6822(98)99241-8 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1998.9241</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9705257</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2974</id>
<a1>Luttge,B. G.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Suppressors of a host range mutation in the rabbitpox virus serpin SPI-1 map to proteins essential for viral DNA replication</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>79</vo>
<is>14</is>
<sp>9168</sp>
<op>9179</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Suppressor</k1>
<k1>Genomic Library</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>The orthopoxvirus serpin SPI-1 is an intracellular serine protease inhibitor that is active against cathepsin G in vitro. Rabbitpox virus (RPV) mutants with deletions of the SPI-1 gene grow on monkey kidney cells (CV-1) but do not plaque on normally permissive human lung carcinoma cells (A549). This reduced-host-range (hr) phenotype suggests that SPI-1 may interact with cellular and/or other viral proteins. We devised a genetic screen for suppressors of SPI-1 hr mutations by first introducing a mutation into SPI-1 (T309R) at residue P14 of the serpin reactive center loop. The SPI-1 T309R serpin is inactive as a protease inhibitor in vitro. Introduction of the mutation into RPV leads to the same restricted hr phenotype as deletion of the SPI-1 gene. Second-site suppressors were selected by restoration of growth of the RPV SPI-1 T309R hr mutant on A549 cells. Both intragenic and extragenic suppressors of the T309R mutation were identified. One novel intragenic suppressor mutation, T309C, restored protease inhibition by SPI-1 in vitro. Extragenic suppressor mutations were mapped by a new procedure utilizing overlapping PCR products encompassing the entire genome in conjunction with marker rescue. One suppressor mutation, which also rendered the virus temperature sensitive for growth, mapped to the DNA polymerase gene (E9L). Several other suppressors mapped to gene D5R, an NTPase required for DNA replication. These results unexpectedly suggest that the host range function of SPI-1 may be associated with viral DNA replication by an as yet unknown mechanism.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (Serpins); EC 2.7.7.7 (DNA-Directed DNA Polymerase); OID: NLM: PMC1168772; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, P.O. Box 100266, Gainesville, FL 32610. rmoyer@ufl.edu.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15994811; 79/14/9168 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.79.14.9168-9179.2005</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15994811</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC1168772</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3005</id>
<a1>Macen,J.</a1>
<a1>Takahashi,A.</a1>
<a1>Moon,K. B.</a1>
<a1>Nathaniel,R.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Activation of caspases in pig kidney cells infected with wild-type and CrmA/SPI-2 mutants of cowpox and rabbitpox viruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>72</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>3524</sp>
<op>3533</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Biotin</k1>
<k1>Caspase 1</k1>
<k1>Caspase 3</k1>
<k1>Caspases</k1>
<k1>Cell Extracts</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Activation</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Kidney/enzymology</k1>
<k1>LLC-PK1 Cells</k1>
<k1>Lamin Type A</k1>
<k1>Lamins</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Protein Processing, Post-Translational</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The cowpox virus (CPV) CrmA and the equivalent rabbitpox virus (RPV) SPI-2 proteins have anti-inflammatory and antiapoptosis activity by virtue of their ability to inhibit caspases, including the interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme (ICE; caspase-1). Infection of LLC-PK1 pig kidney cells with a CPV CrmA mutant, but not with wild-type (wt) CPV, results in the induction of many of the morphological features of apoptosis (C. A. Ray and D. J. Pickup, Virology 217:384-391, 1996). In our study, LLC-PK1 cells infected with CPV delta crmA, but not those infected with wt CPV, showed induction of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP)- and lamin A-cleaving activities and processing of the CPP32 (caspase-3) precursor to a mature 18-kDa form. Surprisingly, infection of LLC-PK1 cells with either wt RPV (despite the presence of the SPI-2 protein) or RPV delta SPI-2 resulted in cleavage activity against PARP and lamin A and the appearance of the mature subunit of CPP32/caspase-3. The biotinylated specific peptide inhibitor Ac-Tyr-Val-Lys(biotinyl)-Asp-2,6-dimethylbenzoyloxymethylketone [AcYV(bio)KD-aomk] labeled active caspase subunits of 18, 19, and 21 kDa in extracts from LLC-PK1 cells infected with CPV delta crmA, wt RPV, or RPV delta SPI-2 but not wt CPV. Mixed infection of LLC-PK1 cells with wt RPV and wt CPV gave no PARP-cleaving activity, and all PARP cleavage mediated by SPI-2 and CrmA mutants of RPV and CPV, respectively, could be eliminated by coinfection with wt CPV. These results suggest that the RPV SPI-2 and CPV CrmA proteins are not functionally equivalent and that CrmA, but not SPI-2 protein, can completely prevent apoptosis in LLC-PK1 cells under these conditions.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Cell Extracts); 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Lamin Type A); 0 (Lamins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 58-85-5 (Biotin); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 2.4.2.30 (Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP3 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (Casp3 protein, mouse); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 3); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); EC 3.4.22.- (Cysteine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.36 (Caspase 1); OID: NLM: PMC109571; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9557631</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9557631</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC109571</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3016</id>
<a1>Macen,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Garner,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Musy,P. Y.</a1>
<a1>Brooks,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<a1>Bleackley,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Differential inhibition of the Fas- and granule-mediated cytolysis pathways by the orthopoxvirus cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2 and SPI-1 protein</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Aug 20</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>17</is>
<sp>9108</sp>
<op>9113</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, CD95/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasmic Granules/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cytotoxicity, Immunologic</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Orthopoxvirus/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Peptides/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Cytotoxic T lymphocytes are important effectors of antiviral immunity, and they induce target cell death either by secretion of cytoplasmic granules containing perforin and granzymes or by signaling through the Fas cell surface antigen. Although it is not known whether the granule-mediated and Fas-mediated cytolytic mechanisms share common components, proteinase activity has been implicated as an important feature of both pathways. The orthopoxviruses cowpox virus and rabbitpox virus each encode three members of the serpin family of proteinase inhibitors, designated SPI-1, SPI-2, and SPI-3. Of these, SPI-2 (also referred to as cytokine response modifier A in cowpox virus) has been shown to inhibit the proteolytic activity of both members of the interleukin 1 beta converting enzyme family and granzyme B. We report here that cells infected with cowpox or rabbitpox viruses exhibit resistance to cytolysis by either cytolytic mechanism. Whereas mutation of the cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2 gene was necessary to relieve inhibition of Fasmediated cytolysis, in some cell types mutation of SPI-1, in addition to cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2, was necessary to completely abrogate inhibition. In contrast, viral inhibition of granule-mediated killing was unaffected by mutation of cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2 alone, and it was relieved only when both the cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2 and SPI-1 genes were inactivated. These results suggest that an interleukin 1 beta converting enzyme-like enzymatic activity is involved in both killing mechanisms and indicate that two viral proteins, SPI-1 and cytokine response modifier A/SPI-2, are necessary to inhibit both cytolysis pathways.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (Antigens, CD95); 0 (Peptides); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 129712-62-5 (lambda Spi-1); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); OID: NLM: PMC38603; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<ad>Department of Biochemistry, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8799162</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8799162</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC38603</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2964</id>
<a1>MacNeill,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Moldawer,L. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The role of the cowpox virus crmA gene during intratracheal and intradermal infection of C57BL/6 mice</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Feb 5</fd>
<vo>384</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>160</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Caspases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cowpox/enzymology/mortality/physiopathology/veterinary</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Smallpox/virology</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Intratracheal (i.t.) infection of mice with cowpox virus (CPXV), is lethal at a lower dose than intranasal (i.n.) inoculation. CPXV deleted for cytokine response modifier A (CPXVDeltacrmA) was attenuated compared to CPXV after i.t. inoculation. This attenuation could not be attributed to differences in virus replication, immunomodulators, or cells infiltrating the lungs. Deletion of crmA also caused attenuation during intradermal (i.d.) infection. In contrast to i.t.-inoculated virus, deletion of crmA reduced virus replication at the site of infection. This difference correlated to increased numbers of CD3(+) cells in CPXVDeltacrmA-associated dermal lesions. Thus, crmA is a virulence factor in mice during either pulmonary or dermal cowpox infection; however the influence of crmA is more evident during i.d. inoculation. This suggests that the host immune response differs in the two routes of infection and emphasizes the need to consider the effect of route of infection when examining functions of virulence factors in vivo.</ab>
<no>GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE-07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; GR: R56 AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); 2008/08/25 [received]; 2008/09/24 [revised]; 2008/10/29 [accepted]; 2008/12/04 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1096-0341; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Pathobiology, University of Illinois College of Veterinary Medicine, Urbana, IL 61802, USA. almac@illinois.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 19056101; S0042-6822(08)00715-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2008.10.041</do>
<wp>20081204</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19056101</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2971</id>
<a1>MacNeill,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Mutation of the Myxoma virus SERP2 P1-site to prevent proteinase inhibition causes apoptosis in cultured RK-13 cells and attenuates disease in rabbits, but mutation to alter specificity causes apoptosis without reducing virulence</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Dec 5-20</fd>
<vo>356</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>12</sp>
<op>22</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Granzymes/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Myxomatosis, Infectious/mortality/physiopathology/virology</k1>
<k1>Peptide Hydrolases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Myxoma virus (MYX) prevents apoptosis in RK-13 cells and forms thick dermal lesions with 100% mortality in rabbits. MYX encodes the virulence factor SERP2, a serine proteinase inhibitor (serpin). SERP2 was mutated to evaluate SERP2 function during MYX infection. MYXDeltaSERP2::lacZ (deleted for SERP2) did not inhibit apoptosis in RK-13 cells; infected rabbits had thin dermal lesions and &amp;lt;10% mortality. MYX-SERP2-D294A, a P1-site aspartate to alanine mutant, inactivated the serpin; infection was indistinguishable from MYXDeltaSERP2::lacZ. SERP2-D294E prevented inhibition of caspase-8, caspase-10 and granzyme-B; and MYX-SERP2-D294E failed to block apoptosis in RK-13 cells, but was fully virulent in rabbits. MYXDeltaSERP2::crmA expressed crmA instead of SERP2 and inhibited apoptosis in cell culture, but caused thin lesions and only 70% mortality in rabbits, hence crmA cannot fully substitute for SERP2. Control of apoptosis in culture does not correlate with virulence in rabbits. Virulence may instead depend on inhibition of proinflammatory proteinases by SERP2.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071203; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: DE-07200/DE/NIDCR NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Serp2 protein, myxoma virus); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.4.- (Peptide Hydrolases); EC 3.4.21.- (Granzymes); 2006/02/17 [received]; 2006/06/13 [revised]; 2006/07/11 [accepted]; 2006/09/07 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>University of Illinois College of Veterinary Medicine, Department of Pathobiology, 2001 S. Lincoln Ave., Urbana, IL 61802, USA. almac@uiuc.edu &lt;almac@uiuc.edu&gt;</ad>
<an>PMID: 16959285; S0042-6822(06)00448-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2006.07.049</do>
<wp>20060907</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16959285</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3026</id>
<a1>Martinez-Pomares,L.</a1>
<a1>Stern,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The ps/hr gene (B5R open reading frame homolog) of rabbitpox virus controls pock color, is a component of extracellular enveloped virus, and is secreted into the medium</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>67</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>5450</sp>
<op>5462</op>
<k1>Allantois</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Chorion</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fibroblasts</k1>
<k1>Gene Products, env/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Oligodeoxyribonucleotides</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Rifampin/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects/genetics/growth &amp; development/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<k1>Viral Envelope Proteins/biosynthesis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<ab>Wild-type rabbitpox virus (RPV) produces red hemorrhagic pocks on the chorioallantoic membranes (CAMs) of embryonated chicken eggs. Like the crmA (SPI-2) gene of cowpox virus, disruption of the RPV ps/hr gene results in a mutant which produces white pocks on the CAMs. An examination of the properties of the RPV(ps/hr) mutant in cell culture also reveals a significantly reduced host range, defined as the inability to form plaques, compared with wild-type virus. One of several cell types on which RPV(ps/hr) mutants fail to produce plaques is chicken embryo fibroblasts, cells which have been traditionally used to propagate spontaneously arising white pock mutants isolated from CAMs. The inability of the RPV(ps/hr) mutant to form plaques in chicken embryo fibroblasts correlates with a failure of a low multiplicity of infection to spread to neighboring cells and to form extracellular enveloped virus (EEV), although the formation and yields of infectious intracellular naked virus appear relatively normal. The gene product of the ps/hr gene, initially synthesized as a 45-kDa glycoprotein, is found as a component of EEV, but not intracellular naked virus, and as a smaller, secreted soluble protein of 35 kDa. Production of the secreted 35-kDa protein was found to be independent of any viral morphogenesis, suggesting two distinct pathways for release of the ps/hr gene product from the cell, i.e., as a component of the EEV particle and as a separately secreted glycoprotein.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI 07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Gene Products, env); 0 (Oligodeoxyribonucleotides); 0 (Viral Envelope Proteins); 0 (ps-hr protein, Rabbitpox virus); 13292-46-1 (Rifampin); OID: NLM: PMC237947; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, JHMHC, College of Medicine University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8394457</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM; X</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8394457</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC237947</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3021</id>
<a1>Martinez-Pomares,L.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Mapping and investigation of the role in pathogenesis of the major unique secreted 35-kDa protein of rabbitpox virus</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Jan 10</fd>
<vo>206</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>591</sp>
<op>600</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/virology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Following infection, many secreted poxvirus proteins are able to modulate the host immune response through interactions with cytokines or components of the complement pathway. A comparison of the secreted protein profiles from cells infected with vaccinia Western Reserve (VV-WR), cowpox virus Brighton strain, or rabbitpox virus (RPV) showed an abundant 35-kDa protein present only in the supernatants from RPV-infected cells. The gene encoding this protein was identified and mapped by N-terminal sequencing of the protein. Examination of the predicted amino acid sequence showed it to be identical to the 35-kDa secreted protein of the Lister strain of vaccinia virus described by Patel et al. (1990, J. Gen. Virol. 71, 2013-2021). The counterpart of this gene in the commonly studied VV-WR strain is truncated and encodes a 7.5-kDa protein under control of the well-characterized p7.5 promoter. While nonessential for replication in cell culture, conservation of this gene in at least two orthopoxvirus strains suggested that this protein might play an important role in vivo. Following intranasal inoculation of Balb/c mice at several doses (10(3), 10(4), or 10(5) PFU), a mutant of RPV lacking a functional 35-kDa gene (RPV delta 35) appeared to induce an earlier onset and more severe illness at low, sublethal doses (10(3) PFU) than was observed with wild-type (wt) RPV. At higher doses (10(4) or 10(5) PFU), the behavior of wt RPV and RPV delta 35 became indistinguishable and the overall LD50 values were similar. Intradermal infection of rabbits simultaneously, at separate sites, with RPV and RPV delta 35 showed no gross or microscopic differences between either primary skin lesions or viremic extension of each virus into the lungs. Therefore, this abundant secreted protein does not appear to play a major role in the virulence of the virus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7831815; S0042-6822(95)80076-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7831815</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3024</id>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Jayarama,V.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>DNA sequence analysis of conserved and unique regions of swinepox virus: identification of genetic elements supporting phenotypic observations including a novel G protein-coupled receptor homologue</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>197</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>511</sp>
<op>528</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Conserved Sequence</k1>
<k1>GTP-Binding Proteins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Regulatory Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Sequence Analysis, DNA</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Suipoxvirus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<ab>Swinepox virus (SPV) contains a double-stranded cross-linked linear DNA genome of approximately 175 kilobase pairs with terminal inverted repetitions (TIRs) of 4.3 kb. The nucleotide sequence was determined for fragments from several regions of the genome including a 2.85-kb fragment from the central potentially conserved portion and two fragments within the presumed variable near-terminal regions which tend to be unique to a given poxvirus. The core sequence contains one partial and two complete open reading frames that are highly conserved and colinear with three contiguous ORFs within the HindIII D fragment of vaccinia virus (VV). The two near-terminal fragments, encompassing 14.2 and 3.6 kb, are respectively located 2.1 kb internal to the left and right cross-linked termini of the DNA and span the TIR junctions. The sequences encode 25 open reading frames including numerous proteins predicted to be membrane-bound or secreted in infected cells. Several ORFs unique to SPV were identified that may be involved in cell attachment, immune modulation, and pathogenesis including a novel poxvirus G protein-coupled receptor. In addition, several polypeptides encoded within the near-terminal regions of vaccinia virus DNA that function as host range or virulence factors are lacking within this region of swinepox virus including the VV growth factor, complement-binding protein, and ORFs C7L and K1L, associated with host range. The lack of these functional homologues could explain the characteristic attenuated phenotype and limited host range of SPV.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/L21931; GENBANK/L22012; GENBANK/L22013; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; EC 3.6.1.- (GTP-Binding Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, JHMHC, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8249275; S0042-6822(83)71625-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1993.1625</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8249275</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3030</id>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Nucleotide sequence analysis of a unique near-terminal region of the tumorigenic poxvirus, Shope fibroma virus</t1>
<jf>The Journal of general virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>73 ( Pt 11)</vo>
<is>Pt 11</is>
<sp>2903</sp>
<op>2911</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Ankyrins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Fibroma Virus, Rabbit/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Repetitive Sequences, Nucleic Acid/genetics</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>Shope fibroma virus (SFV), a tumorigenic poxvirus, has a DNA genome of approximately 160 kb. Previous DNA sequence analysis of SFV has been mainly limited to the terminal inverted repetitions (about 12 kb at each end of the genome) and immediately adjacent regions. We have sequenced a 4 kb fragment located approximately 20 kb from the right-terminal hairpin. Within this region three complete and two partial open reading frames (ORFs) have been identified. Each of the putative polypeptides has sequence similarity to one or more previously identified poxvirus or cellular proteins, with homology to protein kinases, erythrocyte ankyrin and a vaccinia virus virulence-related protein (ORF N1L). The potential significance of these gene products with regard to the phenotype of SFV is discussed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/D10738; GENBANK/M65166; GENBANK/M65167; GENBANK/M65168; GENBANK/M65169; GENBANK/M65170; GENBANK/M65171; GENBANK/M65172; GENBANK/M65173; GENBANK/M65174; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0077340; 0 (Ankyrins); 0 (DNA, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0022-1317; 0022-1317</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1331293</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1331293</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3038</id>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The molecular biology of swinepox virus. I. A characterization of the viral DNA</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>180</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>347</sp>
<op>354</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Repetitive Sequences, Nucleic Acid</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<ab>Swinepox virus (SPV), the prototype member of the Suipoxvirus genus, is uncharacterized at the molecular level. We have analyzed the DNA of SPV and demonstrate that the genome is 175 kb in size and like the more commonly studied Orthopoxvirus, Avipoxvirus, and Leporipoxvirus genera, is terminally cross-linked and contains inverted terminal repetitions (ITRs). In addition, the ITRs are unstable, probably due to the presence of a variable number of direct repeats of approximately 70 bp in length. Restriction enzyme cleavage maps for the enzymes HindIII, AvaI, HaeII, KpnI, BglI, SalI, and XhoI are also presented.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 16722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1984655</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1984655</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3039</id>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The molecular biology of swinepox virus. II. The infectious cycle</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>180</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>355</sp>
<op>364</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Viral/immunology</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Northern</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>Cytopathogenic Effect, Viral</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/classification/physiology</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/genetics</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<ab>Studies based on low-stringency hybridizations of radiolabeled swinepox virus (SPV) DNA to Southern blots containing DNA of representative members of the Orthopoxvirus, Leporipoxvirus, and Avipoxvirus genera and the Entomopoxvirus subfamily have revealed no DNA homology at this level of resolution. Antigenic relatedness between SPV and vaccinia was also analyzed using immunoprecipitations and revealed little if any cross-reactivity. The growth characteristics of SPV in tissue culture were examined by light microscopy and revealed both a delayed and a different cytopathology than that of vaccinia virus. SPV causes foci in pig kidney cells that are not evident until at least 4 days postinfection, whereas vaccinia rapidly generates plaques on these cells. The kinetics of DNA accumulation, protein expression, and RNA transcription of SPV have been examined and indicate that each of these facets of the SPV growth cycle is also considerably delayed when compared to vaccinia virus. Our data indicate that swinepox virus is unique from other poxviruses characterized to date and supports the classification of swinepox virus into a separate genus, Suipoxvirus, within the poxvirus family.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antigens, Viral); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1845830</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1845830</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3040</id>
<a1>Massung,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Orthopoxvirus gene expression in Xenopus laevis oocytes: a component of the virion is needed for late gene expression</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>2280</sp>
<op>2289</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genetic Techniques</k1>
<k1>Microinjections</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Oocytes/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/metabolism/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virion/genetics</k1>
<k1>Xenopus laevis</k1>
<ab>We have examined the feasibility of using Xenopus laevis oocytes microinjected with rabbit poxvirus as a system to study poxvirus gene expression. The injection of either intact virus or subviral cores resulted in accurate synthesis of viral proteins. This expression was dependent on the multiplicity of injected virus, with the optimal injected dose being equivalent to approximately 300 PFU per oocyte. Extensive viral gene expression including late viral protein synthesis was observed when intact virions were microinjected into the oocyte. However, the injection of subviral cores resulted in only early protein synthesis. When oocytes were injected with a mixture of subviral cores and the nonionic detergent-soluble fraction was removed from virus during the preparation of cores, both early and late viral proteins were synthesized. Therefore, the detergent-soluble fraction appears to contain a factor(s) required for the transition from early to late gene expression.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antibodies); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); OID: NLM: PMC249389; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, J. Hills Miller Health Center, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2157885</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2157885</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC249389</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3059</id>
<a1>McCorquodale,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Gossling,J.</a1>
<a1>Benzinger,R.</a1>
<a1>Chesney,R.</a1>
<a1>Lawhorne,L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Gene D5 product of bacteriophage T5: DNA-binding protein affecting DNA replication and late gene expression</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>322</sp>
<op>327</op>
<k1>Coliphages/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Helicases/biosynthesis/physiology</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis/physiology</k1>
<ab>Gene D5 is not only necessary for replication of bacteriophage T5 DNA and for shutoff of expression of some early genes, but has been found to be necessary also for the expression of late T5 genes. The polypeptide product of gene D5 has been identified, an intragenic map of gene D5 has been constructed, and the direction of transcription of gene D5 has been established. The polypeptide coded by gene D5 has been shown to be a DNA-binding protein with affinity for both double- and single-stranded DNA.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.6.1.- (DNA Helicases); OID: NLM: PMC353123; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 219226</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>219226</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC353123</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3048</id>
<a1>Minnigan,H.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Intracellular location of rabbit poxvirus nucleic acid within infected cells as determined by in situ hybridization</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>634</sp>
<op>643</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/analysis</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Cycloheximide/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm/analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Hydroxyurea/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/microbiology</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/analysis</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>The intracellular location of rabbit poxvirus DNA within cells during the course of infection has been determined by the hybridization in situ of labeled viral DNA probes to uninfected and infected cells under various conditions. Extensive control experiments were performed to demonstrate that DNA could be detected selectively and accurately within the cell. Our results suggest that rabbit poxvirus DNA is located only within the cytoplasm during the reproductive cycle, and we found no evidence that viral DNA enters the cell nucleus. The pattern of hybridization of viral DNA at early times (1 and 2 h postinfection) and in the presence of inhibitors of viral DNA synthesis suggests that there may be an association between the input viral DNA and some structural component of the host cell. A number of observations support the hypothesis that the host cell nucleus is required for a productive poxvirus infection. Our results are discussed in terms of the possible role of the nucleus in the replication of poxviruses.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM-07319/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Viral); 127-07-1 (Hydroxyurea); 66-81-9 (Cycloheximide); OID: NLM: PMC255027; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 2991586</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2991586</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC255027</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2962</id>
<a1>Mohamed,M. R.</a1>
<a1>Rahman,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Rice,A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Werden,S. J.</a1>
<a1>McFadden,G.</a1>
<t1>Cowpox virus expresses a novel ankyrin repeat NF-kappaB inhibitor that controls inflammatory cell influx into virus-infected tissues and is critical for virus pathogenesis</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>18</is>
<sp>9223</sp>
<op>9236</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Ankyrin Repeat</k1>
<k1>Cell Movement/immunology</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/chemistry/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Cytokines</k1>
<k1>Inflammation/pathology</k1>
<k1>Lung Diseases/pathology/virology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Myeloid Cells/virology</k1>
<k1>NF-kappa B p50 Subunit/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Signal Transduction</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/physiology</k1>
<ab>Many pathogenic orthopoxviruses like variola virus, monkeypox virus, and cowpox virus (CPXV), but not vaccinia virus, encode a unique family of ankyrin (ANK) repeat-containing proteins that interact directly with NF-kappaB1/p105 and inhibit the NF-kappaB signaling pathway. Here, we present the in vitro and in vivo characterization of the targeted gene knockout of this novel NF-kappaB inhibitor in CPXV. Our results demonstrate that the vCpx-006KO uniquely induces a variety of NF-kappaB-controlled proinflammatory cytokines from infected myeloid cells, accompanied by a rapid phosphorylation of the IkappaB kinase complex and subsequent degradation of the NF-kappaB cellular inhibitors IkappaBalpha and NF-kappaB1/p105. Moreover, the vCpx-006KO virus was attenuated for virulence in mice and induced a significantly elevated cellular inflammatory process at tissue sites of virus replication in the lung. These results indicate that members of this ANK repeat family are utilized specifically by pathogenic orthopoxviruses to repress the NF-kappaB signaling pathway at tissue sites of virus replication in situ.</ab>
<no>LR: 20100302; JID: 0113724; 0 (Cytokines); 0 (NF-kappa B p50 Subunit); 0 (Viral Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC2738262; 2009/07/01 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1098-5514; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19570875; JVI.00861-09 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1128/JVI.00861-09</do>
<wp>20090701</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19570875</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2738262</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2996</id>
<a1>Moon,K. B.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>SPI-1-dependent host range of rabbitpox virus and complex formation with cathepsin G is associated with serpin motifs</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>8999</sp>
<op>9010</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Motifs</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Caspase 3</k1>
<k1>Caspases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cathepsin G</k1>
<k1>Cathepsins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Chymotrypsin/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Peptides/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism/pathogenicity</k1>
<ab>Serpins are a superfamily of serine proteinase inhibitors which function to regulate a number of key biological processes including fibrinolysis, inflammation, and cell migration. Poxviruses are the only viruses known to encode functional serpins. While some poxvirus serpins regulate inflammation (myxoma virus SERP1 and cowpox virus [CPV] crmA/SPI-2) or apoptosis (myxoma virus SERP2 and CPV crmA/SPI-2), the function of other poxvirus serpins remains unknown. The rabbitpox virus (RPV) SPI-1 protein is 47% identical to crmA and shares all of the serpin structural motifs. However, no serpin-like activity has been demonstrated for SPI-1 to date. Earlier we showed that RPV with the SPI-1 gene deleted, unlike wild-type virus, fails to grow on A549 or PK15 cells (A. Ali, P. C. Turner, M. A. Brooks, and R. W. Moyer, Virology 202:306-314, 1994). Here we demonstrate that in the absence of a functional SPI-1 protein, infected nonpermissive cells which exhibit the morphological features of apoptosis fail to activate terminal caspases or cleave the death substrates PARP or lamin A. We show that SPI-1 forms a stable complex in vitro with cathepsin G, a member of the chymotrypsin family of serine proteinases, consistent with serpin activity. SPI-1 reactive-site loop (RSL) mutations of the critical P1 and P14 residues abolish this activity. Viruses containing the SPI-1 RSL P1 or P14 mutations also fail to grow on A549 or PK15 cells. These results suggest that the full virus host range depends on the serpin activity of SPI-1 and that in restrictive cells SPI-1 inhibits a proteinase with chymotrypsin-like activity and may function to inhibit a caspase-independent pathway of apoptosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-AI-07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Peptides); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 129712-62-5 (lambda Spi-1); EC 3.4.- (Cathepsins); EC 3.4.21.- (Serine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.21.1 (Chymotrypsin); EC 3.4.21.20 (CTSG protein, human); EC 3.4.21.20 (Cathepsin G); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP3 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 3); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); OID: NLM: PMC112932; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10516006</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10516006</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC112932</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3047</id>
<a1>Morrison,D. K.</a1>
<a1>Carter,J. K.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and characterization of monoclonal antibodies directed against two subunits of rabbit poxvirus-associated, DNA-directed RNA polymerase</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>670</sp>
<op>680</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/immunology</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Fluorescent Antibody Technique</k1>
<k1>Hybridomas</k1>
<k1>Immunization</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/enzymology/immunology</k1>
<ab>A library of monoclonal antibodies directed against individual proteins of the rabbit poxvirus (RPV) virion within a complex immunogenic mixture has been generated through the use of in vivo and in vitro immunization regimens. The relative efficacies of the two procedures were compared. Based on immunoblot analysis, the in vitro immunization regimen led both to a wider variety of monoclonal antibodies to different proteins and to a larger number of antibodies directed against proteins of higher molecular weights. Each method, however, has advantages, and the two procedures appear to be complementary. A simple method to recognize antibodies directed against the virion DNA-directed RNA polymerase was developed. Monoclonal antibodies directed against two subunits (137 and 34 kilodaltons [kDa]) of the RNA polymerase were identified and used to study the biogenesis of the enzyme and to map the two corresponding genes within the viral genome by using an RPV DNA library cloned into the lambda gtll expression vector. Both proteins are synthesized late in the infectious cycle and are restricted totally to the cytoplasm. Preliminary mapping data place the genes encoding the 137-kDa protein within the HindIII H fragment, whereas the gene for the 34-kDa protein is located within the left most region of the HindIII A fragment.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA-09385/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: GM-07319/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: etc.; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); OID: NLM: PMC255039; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 2991589</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2991589</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC255039</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3046</id>
<a1>Morrison,D. K.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Detection of a subunit of cellular Pol II within highly purified preparations of RNA polymerase isolated from rabbit poxvirus virions</t1>
<jf>Cell</jf>
<jo>Cell</jo>
<yr>1986</yr>
<fd>Feb 28</fd>
<vo>44</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>587</sp>
<op>596</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Antibody Specificity</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Cross Reactions</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm/enzymology</k1>
<k1>DNA/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/genetics/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Hela Cells/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/enzymology</k1>
<k1>RNA Polymerase II/genetics/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Virion/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>A large (approximately 200 kd) subunit of cellular RNA polymerase II (Pol II) and a virus-encoded subunit of rabbit poxvirus (RPV) RNA polymerase (137 kd) react with common monoclonal antibodies. Hybridization studies with viral and cellular DNA clones confirm that the viral and cellular proteins are related. Following RPV infection, the Pol II subunit is translocated from the nucleus to the cytoplasmic virosomes, then packaged into mature virus, and is found associated with the viral RNA polymerase purified from virions. The results suggest that the cellular Pol II subunit may be directly involved in the transcription of viral genes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA-09385/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0413066; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Macromolecular Substances); 9007-49-2 (DNA); EC 2.7.7.- (RNA Polymerase II); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0092-8674; 0092-8674</sn>
<an>PMID: 3004740; 0092-8674(86)90268-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3004740</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3045</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The role of the host cell nucleus in vaccinia virus morphogenesis</t1>
<jf>Virus research</jf>
<jo>Virus Res.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>8</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>173</sp>
<op>191</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Nucleus/enzymology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasm/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>RNA Polymerase II/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/growth &amp; development</k1>
<ab>Despite the fact that cells infected with wild type vaccinia virus synthesize viral DNA and assemble progeny virus particles within the cytoplasm, the host cell nucleus is required for a productive infection. Recent evidence suggests that vaccinia virus selectively recruits components from the host cell nucleus into the cytoplasm for use by the developing virus. One of these components is the largest subunit of the cellular RNA polymerase II (Pol II).</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8410979; EC 2.7.7.- (RNA Polymerase II); RF: 126; ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0168-1702; 0168-1702</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 3318210; 0168-1702(87)90014-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>3318210</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3054</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Brown,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Graves,R. L.</a1>
<t1>The white pock mutants of rabbit poxvirus. II. The early white pock (mu) host range (hr) mutants of rabbit poxvirus uncouple transcription and translation in nonpermissive cells</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Oct 30</fd>
<vo>106</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>234</sp>
<op>249</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poly A/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); 24937-83-5 (Poly A); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<an>PMID: 6254249</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6254249</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3067</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Buchanan,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Effect of calcium ions on synthesis of T5-specific proteins</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1970</yr>
<fd>Nov 25</fd>
<vo>245</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>5897</sp>
<op>5903</op>
<k1>Acrylates</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Calcium/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Carbon Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/growth &amp; development/metabolism/radiation effects</k1>
<k1>Gels</k1>
<k1>Radiation Effects</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<no>LR: 20091027; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Acrylates); 0 (Carbon Isotopes); 0 (Gels); 0 (Viral Proteins); 7440-70-2 (Calcium); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 4921964</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4921964</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3066</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Buchanan,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Effect of calcium ions on synthesis of T5-specific ribonucleic acid</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1970</yr>
<fd>Nov 25</fd>
<vo>245</vo>
<is>22</is>
<sp>5904</sp>
<op>5913</op>
<k1>Acrylates</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Calcium/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Carbon Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gels</k1>
<k1>Hybridization, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Nucleosides/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA/classification</k1>
<k1>RNA, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/metabolism</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Tritium</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<no>LR: 20021101; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Acrylates); 0 (Carbon Isotopes); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Gels); 0 (Nucleosides); 0 (RNA, Bacterial); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 10028-17-8 (Tritium); 63231-63-0 (RNA); 7440-70-2 (Calcium); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 4921965</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4921965</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3068</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Buchanan,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Patterns of RNA synthesis in T5-infected cells. I. As studied by the technique of DNA-RNA hybridization-competition</t1>
<jf>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</jf>
<jo>Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A.</jo>
<yr>1969</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>64</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1249</sp>
<op>1256</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Chloramphenicol/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Coliphages</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Denaturation</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Tritium</k1>
<ab>The RNA-labeling patterns obtained after T5 infection of Escherichia coli F agree with the patterns of protein labeling published by McCorquodale and Buchanan.(1) Three distinct classes of RNA formed sequentially during the period of viral development can be recognized by the DNA-RNA hybridization-competition technique. Class I RNA is formed within 5 minutes after the beginning of viral metabolism and corresponds to the RNA synthesized in response to infection with the 8 per cent segment of T5 DNA. Protein synthesis directed by this 8 per cent segment is required in some capacity for the cessation of class I synthesis and the beginning of the synthesis of class II at 4 to 5 min after infection. Class III RNA synthesis begins between 9 and 12 minutes. Its appearance is prevented when chloramphenicol is added immediately after complete expression of class I functions.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 7505876; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (RNA, Viral); 10028-17-8 (Tritium); 56-75-7 (Chloramphenicol); OID: NLM: PMC223276; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0027-8424; 0027-8424</sn>
<an>PMID: 4916923</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4916923</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC223276</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3013</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Firth,B. T.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of variable temperatures, darkness and light on the secretion of melatonin by pineal explants in the gecko, Christinus marmoratus</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Feb 7</fd>
<vo>747</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>230</sp>
<op>235</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/physiology</k1>
<k1>Darkness</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Lizards/physiology</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/secretion</k1>
<k1>Pineal Gland/secretion</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<ab>This study examined the combined effect of thermocycles with either variable or constant photic conditions on melatonin production by pineal organs in vitro in the gecko, Christinus marmoratus. A 30 degrees C:15 degrees C thermocycle elicited a rhythm of melatonin production under conditions of 12L:12D, constant light or constant darkness when the cryophase coincided with the dark phase of the photocycle or with the subjective night. A 6 h advance of the thermocycle with respect to the photocycle produced an advance in the onset and offset of melatonin production in subsequent nights. When the thermocycle was 180 degrees out of phase with the photoperiod, the rhythm of melatonin production was disrupted, suggesting a differential pattern of sensitivity to photothermal stimuli. It was concluded that both light and temperature are important modulators of pineal function although their combined effects on pineal melatonin production is complex and unclear.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0045503; 73-31-4 (Melatonin); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Histology, University of Adelaide, SA, Australia. rmoyer@medicine.adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 9045997; S0006899396012668 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9045997</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3020</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Firth,B. T.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Effect of constant temperatures, darkness and light on the secretion of melatonin by pineal explants and retinas in the gecko Christinus marmoratus</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Mar 27</fd>
<vo>675</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>345</sp>
<op>348</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/physiology</k1>
<k1>Darkness</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Lizards/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Melatonin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Perfusion</k1>
<k1>Pineal Gland/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Retina/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<ab>The effects of temperature and lighting conditions on the secretion of melatonin by the pineal organ of the nocturnal gecko Christinus marmoratus was studied using in vitro perifusion. In a 12L:12D lighting regime, a high-amplitude melatonin rhythm was detectable at a constant temperature of 20 and 30 degrees C but not at 10 or 37 degrees C. There were sustained high levels of melatonin in constant darkness and sustained low levels in constant light. No retinal melatonin was detected using static and perifusion culture techniques. These results show that the pineal organ of C. marmoratus maintains light sensitivity in vitro but does not contain an oscillator coupled to the melatonin synthetic pathway.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0045503; 73-31-4 (Melatonin); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Anatomy and Histology, University of Adelaide, Australia.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7796151; 0006-8993(95)00073-Y [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>In Vitro; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7796151</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3065</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Fu,A. S.</a1>
<a1>Szabo,C.</a1>
<t1>Regulation of bacteriophage T5 development by ColI factors</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1972</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>804</sp>
<op>812</op>
<k1>Adenine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Adsorption</k1>
<k1>Autoradiography</k1>
<k1>Carbon Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Colicins/metabolism/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/enzymology/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>DNA Nucleotidyltransferases/analysis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Disc</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli</k1>
<k1>Extrachromosomal Inheritance</k1>
<k1>Leucine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phosphorus Isotopes</k1>
<k1>RNA, Messenger/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Thymidine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Thymine/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Tritium</k1>
<k1>Uracil/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>The I-type colicinogenic factor ColIb transforms Escherichia coli from a permissive to a nonpermissive host for bacteriophage T5 reproduction by preventing complete expression of the phage genome. T5-infected ColIb(+) cells synthesize only class I (early) phage protein and ribonucleic acid (RNA). Neither phage-specific class II proteins [associated with viral deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) replication] nor class III proteins (phage structural components) are formed due to the failure of the infected ColIb(+) cells to synthesize class II or class III phage-specific messenger RNA. Comparable studies with T5-infected cells colicinogenic for the related ColIa factor revealed no decrease in the yield of progeny phage although the presence of the ColIa factor leads to a significant reduction in the amount of phage-directed class III protein synthesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (Carbon Isotopes); 0 (Colicins); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Phosphorus Isotopes); 0 (RNA, Messenger); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); 10028-17-8 (Tritium); 50-89-5 (Thymidine); 61-90-5 (Leucine); 65-71-4 (Thymine); 66-22-8 (Uracil); 73-24-5 (Adenine); EC 2.7.7.- (DNA Nucleotidyltransferases); OID: NLM: PMC356377; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 4554465</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4554465</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC356377</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3051</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Graves,R. L.</a1>
<t1>The white pock mutants of rabbit poxvirus. IV. The late white pock (mu) host range (hr) mutants of rabbit poxvirus are blocked in morphogenesis</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>119</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>332</sp>
<op>346</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Viral/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Kidney</k1>
<k1>Morphogenesis</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antigens, Viral); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<an>PMID: 6281977</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6281977</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3052</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Graves,R. L.</a1>
<t1>The mechanism of cytoplasmic orthopoxvirus DNA replication</t1>
<jf>Cell</jf>
<jo>Cell</jo>
<yr>1981</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>2 Pt 1</is>
<sp>391</sp>
<op>401</op>
<k1>Cytoplasm/ultrastructure</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>Densitometry</k1>
<k1>Genetic Variation</k1>
<k1>Models, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>Orthopoxvirus DNA replication occurs in the cytoplasm of infected cells within discrete foci designated as virosomes. We show that newly synthesized rabbit poxvirus (RPV) virosomal DNA consists predominantly of concatamers wherein unit length molecules are joined by fusion of two left (LL) or right (RR) ends, resulting in genomes aligned in alternating head-to-head and tail-to tail mirror image arrays. These concatameric molecules serve as the substrates from which unit length DNA molecules are excised during morphogenesis. We propose a mechanism by which internal deletions within these concatameric arrays prior to genome excision and packaging could create inverted terminal repeats and generate gene duplications.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 0413066; EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0092-8674; 0092-8674</sn>
<an>PMID: 6277506; 0092-8674(81)90422-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6277506</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3053</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Graves,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Rothe,C. T.</a1>
<t1>The white pock (mu) mutants of rabbit poxvirus. III. Terminal DNA sequence duplication and transposition in rabbit poxvirus</t1>
<jf>Cell</jf>
<jo>Cell</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>2 Pt 2</is>
<sp>545</sp>
<op>553</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Linkage (Genetics)</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Translocation, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>The restriction fragment patterns of the DNA of three white pock (mu) nonhost range mutants RPmu mutants) of rabbit poxvirus (RPV) show the presence of net insertions of DNA. Two of the mutants (RPmu21 and RPmu7) contain two molar quantities of 13 X 10(6) and 15 X 10(6) daltons, respectively, of the left-most viral DNA sequences. The extra copy of these sequences was inserted into the right-most region of the viral genome which in both cases had been modified by deletion of 10 X 10(6) daltons of the original extreme right-most DNA sequences. Hence two mutants with &amp;quot;left-hand&amp;quot; mirror image termini of 13 X 10(6) and 15 X 10(6) daltons of DNA were generated with an overall net increase in mass of 3 X 10(6) and 5 X 10(6) daltons of DNA to yield genome molecular weights of 121 X 10(6) and 123 X 10(6) for RPmu21 and 7, respectively. A third mutant (RPmu81g) contained 28 X 10(6) daltons of the right-most parental DNA sequences inserted into the left end of the genome, which had deleted 6 X 10(6) daltons of the extreme left-hand sequences. This variant contains &amp;quot;right-hand&amp;quot; mirror image termini of 28 X 10(6) daltons of DNA and a net increase in molecular weight of 22 X 10(6) daltons of DNA to yield a genome molecular weight of 140 X 10(6). The cross-linked end of the transposed sequences is retained in all cases. Our data suggest that the terminal DNA sequences at either end of the virus are not essential for a productive infection in certain host cells and that the pathogenicity of orthopoxviruses may be related in part to a series of varied and interchangeable DNA sequences located at both extremes of a high conserved genome core.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0413066; 0 (DNA, Viral); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0092-8674; 0092-8674</sn>
<an>PMID: 6256085; 0092-8674(80)90364-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6256085</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2993</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Serotonin depletion decreases light induced c-fos in the rat suprachiasmatic nucleus</t1>
<jf>Neuroreport</jf>
<jo>Neuroreport</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Apr 7</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1021</sp>
<op>1024</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Count</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Fenclonine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Neurons/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Photic Stimulation</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/analysis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Serotonin/analysis/deficiency</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Antagonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/cytology/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) is the locus of the biological clock in mammals. Daily light cycles entrain the endogenous circadian rhythms in mammals through direct and indirect neural pathways from the retinae to the suprachiasmatic nucleus. We have studied the effect of serotonin depletion on the photic induction of the early response gene c-fas in the SCN of rats. Serotonin depletion, verified by immunohistochemistry, produced a significant decrease (42%) in the number of c-FOS positive cells in the ventrolateral portion of the SCN. These results support the involvement of serotonin as a mediator of photic information to the SCN through the retinal projection to the dorsal raphe nucleus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 9100935; 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 0 (Serotonin Antagonists); 50-67-9 (Serotonin); 7424-00-2 (Fenclonine); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0959-4965; 0959-4965</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Adelaide Medical School, Australia.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10790876</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10790876</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2997</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Immunohistochemical localization of serotonin receptors in the rat suprachiasmatic nucleus</t1>
<jf>Neuroscience letters</jf>
<jo>Neurosci.Lett.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Aug 27</fd>
<vo>271</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>147</sp>
<op>150</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal</k1>
<k1>Circadian Rhythm/physiology</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Lighting</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A</k1>
<k1>Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C</k1>
<k1>Receptors, Serotonin/analysis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/chemistry</k1>
<ab>Serotonin (5-HT) has been implicated in the regulation of circadian rhythms through its actions on the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN). Recent data suggests that, along with excitatory amino acids, serotonin may be important in the neural pathway that mediates the transmission of photic information to the circadian system. The present study uses immunohistochemistry to examine the presence of three different 5-HT receptor subtypes in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (5-HT2a, 5-HT2c and 5-HT7) in male albino Wistar rats. In the SCN, there was a considerable amount of 5-HT2c-receptor-like immunoreactivity, a lesser amount of 5-HT2a positive fibres and no staining with antiserum against the 5-HT7 receptor subtype. These results are compatible with previous pharmacological evidence obtained in our laboratory showing that serotonin acting through the 5-HT2c receptor subtype may be important in the phase shifting effects of light on the circadian system.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 7600130; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2A); 0 (Receptor, Serotonin, 5-HT2C); 0 (Receptors, Serotonin); 0 (serotonin 7 receptor); ppublish</no>
<pp>IRELAND</pp>
<sn>0304-3940; 0304-3940</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Medical School-University of Adelaide, South Australia, Australia. rmoyer@medicine.adelaide.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 10507690; S0304394099005364 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10507690</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3008</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Kennaway,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Ferguson,S. A.</a1>
<a1>Dijstelbloem,Y. P.</a1>
<t1>Quipazine and light have similar effects on c-fos induction in the rat suprachiasmatic nucleus</t1>
<jf>Brain research</jf>
<jo>Brain Res.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Aug 15</fd>
<vo>765</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>337</sp>
<op>342</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Light</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos/biosynthesis/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Quipazine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Rats</k1>
<k1>Rats, Wistar</k1>
<k1>Serotonin Agonists/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Suprachiasmatic Nucleus/drug effects/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The effects of the serotonin agonist, quipazine, on the induction of c-fos in the suprachiasmatic nucleus of the rat was examined at different times of the 24 h cycle. Quipazine administered at night induced Fos production in a dose dependent manner (1, 3, 10, 30 mumol/kg) in the ventrolateral portion of the suprachiasmatic nucleus at ZT18. Administration of the highest dose at other times resulted in c-fos induction at ZT15 but not at other times of the day or subjective day examined (CT6 and ZT12). When compared to the effects of light pulses (2 lux/1 min), quipazine only caused c-fos induction at times when light caused induction. Our results support a role of serotonergic pathways in the transmission or modulation of photic information from the retina to the suprachiasmatic nucleus of the rat.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0045503; 0 (Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-fos); 0 (Serotonin Agonists); 4774-24-7 (Quipazine); ppublish</no>
<pp>NETHERLANDS</pp>
<sn>0006-8993; 0006-8993</sn>
<ad>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Adelaide, Medical School, S.A., Australia.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9313909; S0006-8993(97)00685-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9313909</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3070</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Ramaley,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Butler,L. G.</a1>
<a1>Boyer,P. D.</a1>
<t1>The formation and reactions of a nonphosphorylated high energy form of succinyl coenzyme A synthetase</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1967</yr>
<fd>Oct 10</fd>
<vo>242</vo>
<is>19</is>
<sp>4299</sp>
<op>4309</op>
<k1>Adenine Nucleotides</k1>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Catalysis</k1>
<k1>Coenzyme A</k1>
<k1>Energy Transfer</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Ligases</k1>
<k1>Oxygen Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Phosphorus Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Spectrophotometry</k1>
<k1>Succinates</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Adenine Nucleotides); 0 (Oxygen Isotopes); 0 (Phosphorus Isotopes); 0 (Succinates); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); 85-61-0 (Coenzyme A); EC 6.- (Ligases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 4863738</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4863738</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3057</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Rothe,C. T.</a1>
<t1>The white pock mutants of rabbit poxvirus. I. Spontaneous host range mutants contain deletions</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Apr 15</fd>
<vo>102</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>119</sp>
<op>132</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, Viral</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>DNA Restriction Enzymes</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development/metabolism</k1>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antigens, Viral); 0 (DNA, Viral); EC 3.1.21.- (DNA Restriction Enzymes); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<an>PMID: 6245500</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>6245500</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3060</id>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Rothe,C. T.</a1>
<t1>Role of the T5 gene D15 nuclease in the generation of nicked bacteriophage T5 DNA</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1977</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>177</sp>
<op>193</op>
<k1>Coliphages/enzymology/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/biosynthesis/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Deoxyribonucleases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<ab>The processing of newly replicated concatameric T5 DNA into both single stranded DNA changed of unit length and single-stranded fragments of sizes comparable to those found in mature T5 virion DNA occurs in the absence of late T5 protein synthesis. The formation of unit-length, single-stranded DNA chains does not require the early T5 gene D15 nuclease: however, the subsequent formation of the single-stranded fragments does require that the D15 nuclease be functional. A reexamination of the properties of the purified D15 nuclease under a variety of conditions showed that, in addition to functioning as a 5&amp;#39; leads to 3&amp;#39; exonuclease, the enzyme can also introduce endonucleolytic scissions into mature T5 DNA in a reaction that requires duplex T5 DNA and preexisting, single-stranded interruptions.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.1.- (Deoxyribonucleases); OID: NLM: PMC515921; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 904023</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>904023</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC515921</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3000</id>
<a1>Mullbacher,A.</a1>
<a1>Wallich,R.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Simon,M. M.</a1>
<t1>Poxvirus-encoded serpins do not prevent cytolytic T cell-mediated recovery from primary infections</t1>
<jf>Journal of immunology (Baltimore, Md.: 1950)</jf>
<jo>J.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Jun 15</fd>
<vo>162</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>7315</sp>
<op>7321</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, CD95/physiology</k1>
<k1>Cell Death/immunology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/immunology/metabolism/virology</k1>
<k1>Cytoplasmic Granules/immunology/virology</k1>
<k1>Cytotoxicity, Immunologic/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Exocytosis/immunology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>H-2 Antigens/biosynthesis/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Immunity, Innate</k1>
<k1>Immunosuppressive Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C3H</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred C57BL</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred CBA</k1>
<k1>Mice, Knockout</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/enzymology/immunology</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocyte Subsets/immunology</k1>
<k1>T-Lymphocytes, Cytotoxic/enzymology/immunology/virology</k1>
<ab>Previous observations that the highly conserved poxvirus-encoded serpins inhibit cytotoxic activities of alloreactive CTL via granule and/or Fas-mediated pathways was taken to indicate their involvement in immune evasion by poxviruses. We now show that interference with 51Cr release from target cells by ectromelia and cowpoxvirus is limited to alloreactive but not MHC-restricted CTL. The data are in support of the paramount importance of CTL and its effector molecule perforin in the recovery from primary ectromelia virus infection and question the role of serpins in the evasion of poxviruses from killing by CTL. Further analysis of poxvirus interference with target cell lysis by alloreactive CTL revealed that suppression primarily affects the Fas-mediated, and to a lesser extent, the granule exocytosis pathway. Serpin-2 is the main contributor to suppression for both killing pathways. In addition, inhibition of lysis was shown to be both target cell type- and MHC allotype-dependent. We hypothesize that differences in TCR affinities and/or state of activation between alloreactive and MHC-restricted CTL as well as the quality (origin) of target cells are responsible for the observed phenomenon.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081121; JID: 2985117R; 0 (Antigens, CD95); 0 (H-2 Antigens); 0 (Immunosuppressive Agents); 0 (Serpins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-1767; 0022-1767</sn>
<ad>Division of Immunology and Cell Biology, John Curtin School of Medical Research, Australian National University, Canberra. arno.mullbacher@anu.edu.au</ad>
<an>PMID: 10358181</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; AIM; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10358181</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3069</id>
<a1>Murphy,W. W.</a1>
<a1>Krusemark,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Increased crew activities scheduling effectiveness through the use of computer techniques</t1>
<jf>Human factors</jf>
<jo>Hum.Factors</jo>
<yr>1968</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>57</sp>
<op>62</op>
<k1>Computers</k1>
<k1>Diving</k1>
<k1>Efficiency</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Man-Machine Systems</k1>
<k1>Space Flight</k1>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 0374660; OID: NASA: 68328903; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0018-7208; 0018-7208</sn>
<an>PMID: 5662642</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM; S</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>5662642</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2979</id>
<a1>Nathaniel,R.</a1>
<a1>MacNeill,A. L.</a1>
<a1>Wang,Y. X.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Cowpox virus CrmA, Myxoma virus SERP2 and baculovirus P35 are not functionally interchangeable caspase inhibitors in poxvirus infections</t1>
<jf>The Journal of general virology</jf>
<jo>J.Gen.Virol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>Pt 5</is>
<sp>1267</sp>
<op>1278</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Caspases/antagonists &amp; inhibitors</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/metabolism/virology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Serpins/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<ab>Cowpox virus (CPV) expresses the serpin (serine proteinase inhibitor) CrmA, an anti-inflammatory, anti-apoptotic protein required for production of red pocks on chicken chorioallantoic membranes (CAMs). In vitro, CrmA inhibits several caspases and granzyme B. Altering the critical P1-aspartate in the CrmA reactive centre loop to alanine resulted in a virus (CPV-CrmA-D303A) that resembled CPV deleted for CrmA (CPVDeltaCrmA : : lacZ); on CAMs it produced white, inflammatory pocks with activated caspase-3 and reduced virus yields, suggesting that CrmA activities are mediated via proteinase inhibition. CrmA in CPV was replaced with SERP2 from Myxoma virus (MYX) or baculovirus P35, which inhibit similar proteinases in vitro. SERP2 and P35 each blocked caspase-3-mediated apoptosis but were unable to control inflammation of CAMs. However, SERP2 and P35 restored virus yields, indicating that the decreased virus titres seen with CPVDeltaCrmA : : lacZ resulted from apoptosis rather than inflammation. To compare the activities of CrmA and SERP2 further, rabbits were infected with MYX recombinant viruses. Intradermal infection of rabbits with MYX was uniformly lethal, generating raised primary lesions and many secondary lesions. In contrast, deletion of SERP2 from MYX (MYXDeltaSERP2 : : lacZ) caused little mortality and produced flat primary lesions with few secondary lesions. Replacement of SERP2 with CrmA (MYXDeltaSERP2 : : CrmA) resulted in partial complementation with flat primary lesions, many secondary lesions and death in 70 % of the rabbits. Therefore, CrmA and SERP2 were not functionally interchangeable during infection of CAMs or rabbits, implying that these serpins have activities that are not evident from biochemical studies with human caspases.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0077340; 0 (Inhibitor of Apoptosis Proteins); 0 (Serp2 protein, myxoma virus); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (inhibitor of apoptosis, Nucleopolyhedrovirus); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0022-1317; 0022-1317</sn>
<ad>University of Florida, College of Medicine, Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, PO Box 100266, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15105544</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15105544</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3011</id>
<a1>Petersen,B. O.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Shuman,S.</a1>
<t1>Characterization of a DNA topoisomerase encoded by Amsacta moore entomopoxvirus</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Apr 14</fd>
<vo>230</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>197</sp>
<op>206</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>DNA Topoisomerases, Type I/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Insects/virology</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/chemistry/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<ab>We have identified an Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus (AmEPV) gene encoding a DNA topoisomerase. The 333-amino acid AmEPV topoisomerase displays instructive sequence similarities to the previously identified topoisomerases encoded by five genera of vertebrate poxviruses. One hundred nine amino acids are identical or conserved among the six proteins. The gene encoding AmEPV topoisomerase was expressed in bacteria and the recombinant enzyme was partially purified. AmEPV topoisomerase is a monomeric enzyme that catalyzes the relaxation of supercoiled DNA. Like the vaccinia, Shope fibroma virus, and Orf virus enzymes, the AmEPV topoisomerase forms a covalent adduct with duplex DNA at the target sequence CCCTT decreases. The kinetic and equilibrium parameters of the DNA cleavage reaction of AmEPV topoisomerase (Kobs = 0.08 sec-1; Kcl = 0.22) are similar to those of the vaccinia virus enzyme.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GENBANK/U80056; GR: GM46330/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); EC 5.99.1.2 (DNA Topoisomerases, Type I); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Molecular Biology Program, Sloan-Kettering Institute, New York, New York 10021, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9143275; S0042682297984956 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9143275</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2968</id>
<a1>Prichard,M. N.</a1>
<a1>Kern,E. R.</a1>
<a1>Quenelle,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Keith,K. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<t1>Vaccinia virus lacking the deoxyuridine triphosphatase gene (F2L) replicates well in vitro and in vivo, but is hypersensitive to the antiviral drug (N)-methanocarbathymidine</t1>
<jf>Virology journal</jf>
<jo>Virol.J.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar 5</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<sp>39</sp>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Green Fluorescent Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Pyrimidines/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Pyrophosphatases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Thymidine/analogs &amp; derivatives/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/virology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/drug effects/enzymology/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The vaccinia virus (VV) F2L gene encodes a functional deoxyuridine triphosphatase (dUTPase) that catalyzes the conversion of dUTP to dUMP and is thought to minimize the incorporation of deoxyuridine residues into the viral genome. Previous studies with with a complex, multigene deletion in this virus suggested that the gene was not required for viral replication, but the impact of deleting this gene alone has not been determined in vitro or in vivo. Although the crystal structure for this enzyme has been determined, its potential as a target for antiviral therapy is unclear. RESULTS: The F2L gene was replaced with GFP in the WR strain of VV to assess its effect on viral replication. The resulting virus replicated well in cell culture and its replication kinetics were almost indistinguishable from those of the wt virus and attained similar titers. The virus also appeared to be as pathogenic as the WR strain suggesting that it also replicated well in mice. Cells infected with the dUTPase mutant would be predicted to affect pyrimidine deoxynucleotide pools and might be expected to exhibit altered susceptibility to pyrimidine analogs. The antiviral activity of cidofovir and four thymidine analogs were evaluated both in the mutant and the parent strain of this virus. The dUTPase knockout remained fully susceptible to cidofovir and idoxuridine, but was hypersensitive to the drug (N)-methanocarbathymidine, suggesting that pyrimidine metabolism was altered in cells infected with the mutant virus. The absence of dUTPase should reduce cellular dUMP pools and may result in a reduced conversion to dTMP by thymidylate synthetase or an increased reliance on the salvage of thymidine by the viral thymidine kinase. CONCLUSION: We confirmed that F2L was not required for replication in cell culture and determined that it does not play a significant role on virulence of the virus in intranasally infected mice. The recombinant virus is hypersensitive to (N)-methanocarbathymidine and may reflect metabolic differences in the mutant virus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: 2R56AI015722-25/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: I-U54-AI-057157/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-AI-15439/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: N01-AI-30049/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 101231645; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (N-methanocarbathymidine); 0 (Pyrimidines); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 147336-22-9 (Green Fluorescent Proteins); 289-95-2 (pyrimidine); 50-89-5 (Thymidine); EC 3.6.1.- (Pyrophosphatases); EC 3.6.1.23 (dUTP pyrophosphatase); OID: NLM: PMC2276199; 2008/01/24 [received]; 2008/03/05 [accepted]; 2008/03/05 [aheadofprint]; epublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>1743-422X</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama School of Medicine, Birmingham, AL 35233, USA. mprichard@peds.uab.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18321387; 1743-422X-5-39 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1186/1743-422X-5-39</do>
<wp>20080305</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18321387</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2276199</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3071</id>
<a1>Ramaley,R. F.</a1>
<a1>Bridger,W. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Boyer,P. D.</a1>
<t1>The preparation, properties, and reactions of succinyl coenzyme A synthetase and its phosphorylated form</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1967</yr>
<fd>Oct 10</fd>
<vo>242</vo>
<is>19</is>
<sp>4287</sp>
<op>4298</op>
<k1>Adenine Nucleotides</k1>
<k1>Adenosine Triphosphate</k1>
<k1>Binding Sites</k1>
<k1>Cellulose</k1>
<k1>Chemical Precipitation</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, Gel</k1>
<k1>Chromatography, Ion Exchange</k1>
<k1>Coenzyme A</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Ligases/analysis</k1>
<k1>Magnesium</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Phosphates</k1>
<k1>Phosphorus Isotopes</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Succinates</k1>
<k1>Ultrasonics</k1>
<no>LR: 20091119; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Adenine Nucleotides); 0 (Phosphates); 0 (Phosphorus Isotopes); 0 (Succinates); 56-65-5 (Adenosine Triphosphate); 7439-95-4 (Magnesium); 85-61-0 (Coenzyme A); 9004-34-6 (Cellulose); EC 6.- (Ligases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 4863737</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>4863737</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3058</id>
<a1>Rice,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Ficht,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Holladay,L. A.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The purification and properties of a double-stranded DNA-binding protein encoded by the gene D5 of bacteriophage T5</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<fd>Aug 25</fd>
<vo>254</vo>
<is>16</is>
<sp>8042</sp>
<op>8051</op>
<k1>Amino Acids/analysis</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Helicases/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Bacterial/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<ab>We have purified a DNA-binding protein from bacteriophage T5-infected cells. The protein is the product of the T5 gene D5 and is produced in quantities ultimately exceeding 2% of the total cell protein. The protein has no tendency to aggregate and exists in solution as a monomer of about 29,000 daltons. Although the protein binds with a high affinity to both single-stranded (fd, T7) and duplex DNA (T5, T7), there is a preferred binding to duplex DNA. The binding of the gene D5 protein to duplex DNA is cooperative with an estimated dissociation constant of 6.27 x 10(-10) M and leads to the production of a more condensed form of the DNA. In contrast, binding of the gene D5 protein to single-stranded DNA is noncooperative with an estimated dissociation constant of only 1.85 x 10(-8) M and produces a sedimentation shift in the DNA proportional to the added mass of the protein. The protein product of the gene D5 of bacteriophage T5 is known to be required for both T5 DNA replication and for the inhibition of early phage gene expression. We also show here that the protein is required to initiate transcription of the late region of the T5 genome.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Amino Acids); 0 (DNA, Bacterial); 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); EC 3.6.1.- (DNA Helicases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<an>PMID: 224043</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>224043</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2986</id>
<a1>Silverman,G. A.</a1>
<a1>Bird,P. I.</a1>
<a1>Carrell,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Church,F. C.</a1>
<a1>Coughlin,P. B.</a1>
<a1>Gettins,P. G.</a1>
<a1>Irving,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Lomas,D. A.</a1>
<a1>Luke,C. J.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Pemberton,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Remold-O&#39;Donnell,E.</a1>
<a1>Salvesen,G. S.</a1>
<a1>Travis,J.</a1>
<a1>Whisstock,J. C.</a1>
<t1>The serpins are an expanding superfamily of structurally similar but functionally diverse proteins. Evolution, mechanism of inhibition, novel functions, and a revised nomenclature</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Sep 7</fd>
<vo>276</vo>
<is>36</is>
<sp>33293</sp>
<op>33296</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Models, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Multigene Family</k1>
<k1>Protein Conformation</k1>
<k1>Serpins/chemistry/physiology</k1>
<k1>Species Specificity</k1>
<k1>Structure-Activity Relationship</k1>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Serpins); RF: 41; 2001/07/02 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Newborn Medicine, Children&#39;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts 02115, USA. gary.silverman@tch.harvard.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 11435447; R100016200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1074/jbc.R100016200</do>
<wp>20010702</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11435447</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2985</id>
<a1>Sriskanda,V.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Shuman,S.</a1>
<t1>NAD+-dependent DNA ligase encoded by a eukaryotic virus</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Sep 28</fd>
<vo>276</vo>
<is>39</is>
<sp>36100</sp>
<op>36109</op>
<k1>Alanine/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Motifs</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Aspartic Acid/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Catalysis</k1>
<k1>Cysteine/chemistry</k1>
<k1>DNA Ligases/biosynthesis/genetics/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Dose-Response Relationship, Drug</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Evolution, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors</k1>
<k1>Models, Biological</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>NAD/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Phylogeny</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Protein Structure, Tertiary</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Tyrosine/chemistry</k1>
<k1>Zinc/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Zinc Fingers</k1>
<ab>We report the production, purification, and characterization of an NAD(+)-dependent DNA ligase encoded by the Amsacta moorei entomopoxvirus (AmEPV), the first example of an NAD(+) ligase from a source other than eubacteria. AmEPV ligase lacks the zinc-binding tetracysteine domain and the BRCT domain that are present in all eubacterial NAD(+) ligases. Nonetheless, the monomeric 532-amino acid AmEPV ligase catalyzed strand joining on a singly nicked DNA in the presence of a divalent cation and NAD(+). Neither ATP, dATP, nor any other nucleoside triphosphate could substitute for NAD(+). Structure probing by limited proteolysis showed that AmEPV ligase is punctuated by a surface-accessible loop between the nucleotidyltransferase domain, which is common to all ligases, and the N-terminal domain Ia, which is unique to the NAD(+) ligases. Deletion of domain Ia of AmEPV ligase abolished the sealing of 3&amp;#39;-OH/5&amp;#39;-PO(4) nicks and the reaction with NAD(+) to form ligase-adenylate, but had no effect on phosphodiester formation at a pre-adenylated nick. Alanine substitutions at residues within domain Ia either reduced (Tyr(39), Tyr(40), Asp(48), and Asp(52)) or abolished (Tyr(51)) sealing of a 5&amp;#39;-PO(4) nick and adenylyl transfer from NAD(+) without affecting ligation of DNA-adenylate. We conclude that: (i) NAD(+)-dependent ligases exist in the eukaryotic domain of the phylogenetic tree; and (ii) ligase structural domain Ia is a determinant of cofactor specificity and is likely to interact directly with the nicotinamide mononucleotide moiety of NAD(+).</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: GM63611-01/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; JID: 2985121R; 52-90-4 (Cysteine); 53-84-9 (NAD); 55520-40-6 (Tyrosine); 56-41-7 (Alanine); 56-84-8 (Aspartic Acid); 7440-66-6 (Zinc); EC 6.5.1.- (DNA Ligases); 2001/07/17 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Molecular Biology Program, Sloan-Kettering Institute, New York, New York 10021, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 11459847; M105643200 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1074/jbc.M105643200</do>
<wp>20010717</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>11459847</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3009</id>
<a1>Stern,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Attenuation of B5R mutants of rabbitpox virus in vivo is related to impaired growth and not an enhanced host inflammatory response</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Jun 23</fd>
<vo>233</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>118</sp>
<op>129</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Anti-Inflammatory Agents/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Chick Embryo</k1>
<k1>Dexamethasone/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Gene Deletion</k1>
<k1>Inflammation</k1>
<k1>Lung/virology</k1>
<k1>Membrane Glycoproteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia/immunology/pathology/physiopathology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development/immunology</k1>
<k1>Viral Envelope Proteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<ab>The rabbitpox virus (RPV) B5R protein, synthesized late in infection, is found as a 45-kDa membrane-associated protein of the envelope of infectious extracellular enveloped virus (EEV) and as a 38-kDa protein secreted from the cell by a process independent of morphogenesis. The protein is not found associated with intracellular mature virus (IMV). Deletion of the gene attenuates the virus (RPV delta B5R) in animals (mice and rabbits), has relatively little effect on formation of IMV, prevents EEV formation in some but not all cells, and leads to a reduced host range. Analysis of the sequence of the protein suggests relatedness to factor H of the complement cascade. Collectively, these observations suggest that attenuation of the virus in vivo could be linked to an inhibition of the inflammatory response, a deficiency in growth, or both. In this report we have analyzed the behavior of RPV delta B5R in infected mice and rabbits and conclude that attenuation of the mutant virus likely results from simple failure to grow within the infected animal and that the inflammatory response probably contributes little to the observed attenuation.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI157322/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32 AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Anti-Inflammatory Agents); 0 (Membrane Glycoproteins); 0 (Viral Envelope Proteins); 134034-10-9 (42kDa protein, Vaccinia virus); 50-02-2 (Dexamethasone); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9201221; S0042-6822(97)98556-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1997.8556</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9201221</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3063</id>
<a1>Szabo,C.</a1>
<a1>Dharmgrongartama,B.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The regulation of transcription in bacteriophage T5-infected Escherichia coli</t1>
<jf>Biochemistry</jf>
<jo>Biochemistry</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<fd>Mar 11</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>989</sp>
<op>997</op>
<k1>Bacterial Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Coliphages/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA Viruses/metabolism</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genes</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Weight</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Precipitin Tests</k1>
<k1>Protein Binding</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>The expression of bacteriophage T5-specific RNA and protein in infected cells is temporally separated into three classes: class I (preearly), class II (early), and class III (late). By immunoprecipitation techniques we have shown that T5 infection of cells leads to the synthesis of one class I polypeptide (11,000 daltons) and two class II polypeptides (90,000 and 15,000 daltons) capable of binding to the RNA polymerase of the host Escherichia coli cell. One of the class II polypeptides (90,000 daltons) is the product of gene C2, which is an essential gene product required for the initiation of class III RNA synthesis. The colicinogenic factor, ColIb, is a plasmid which prevents the normal synthesis of class II and the III bacteriophage T5-specific RNA in infected colicinogenic (ColIb+) cells. In T5-infected colicinogenic cells, only the T5 class I polypeptide is found associated with the RNA polymerase. Mutants of T5, designated T5h minus, are capable of growth on both noncolicinogenic and ColIb+ hosts. Extracts of T5h minus infected ColIb+ cells were shown to lack a small class I polypeptide (12,000 daltons) as compared to T5-infected cells. The h minus mutation, however, has no effect on the levels of the class I T5 polypeptide of similar molecular weight which is bound to the RNA polymerase. One effect of the h minus mutation is to enhance the quantities of the two class II polypeptides bound to the enzyme.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0370623; 0 (Bacterial Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0006-2960; 0006-2960</sn>
<an>PMID: 1092331</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1092331</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3062</id>
<a1>Szabo,C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Purification and properties of a bacteriophage T5-modified form of Escherichia coli RNA polymerase</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1975</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>15</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>1042</sp>
<op>1046</op>
<k1>Coliphages/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>DNA Viruses/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases/analysis/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Escherichia coli/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Peptides/analysis</k1>
<k1>Transcription, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Tritium</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>A modified form of Escherichia coli RNA polymerase that contains one of the three T5-specific polypeptides known to interact with the host enzyme was purified from bacteriophage T5-infected cells. The properties of this T5-modified enzyme appeared identical to those of the RNA polymerase derived from uninfected non-colicinogenic cells and to a fully active enzyme isolated from T5-infected ColIb+ cells after the limited in vivo transcription of T5 genes allowed by the plasmid had ceased.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; JID: 0113724; 0 (Peptides); 10028-17-8 (Tritium); EC 2.7.7.6 (DNA-Directed RNA Polymerases); OID: NLM: PMC354552; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<an>PMID: 1090747</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1090747</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC354552</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3010</id>
<a1>Takahashi,A.</a1>
<a1>Hirata,H.</a1>
<a1>Yonehara,S.</a1>
<a1>Imai,Y.</a1>
<a1>Lee,K. K.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Mesner,P. W.</a1>
<a1>Okazaki,T.</a1>
<a1>Sawai,H.</a1>
<a1>Kishi,S.</a1>
<a1>Yamamoto,K.</a1>
<a1>Okuma,M.</a1>
<a1>Sasada,M.</a1>
<t1>Affinity labeling displays the stepwise activation of ICE-related proteases by Fas, staurosporine, and CrmA-sensitive caspase-8</t1>
<jf>Oncogene</jf>
<jo>Oncogene</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Jun 12</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>23</is>
<sp>2741</sp>
<op>2752</op>
<k1>Affinity Labels/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antigens, CD95/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Caspase 6</k1>
<k1>Caspase 8</k1>
<k1>Caspase 9</k1>
<k1>Caspases</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Activation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Jurkat Cells</k1>
<k1>Laminin/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Oligopeptides/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Staurosporine/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins</k1>
<ab>The activation of multiple interleukin-1beta converting enzyme-related proteases (caspases) in apoptotic mammalian cells raises questions as to whether the multiple active caspases have distinct roles in apoptotic execution as well as how these proteases are organized in apoptotic signaling pathways. Here we used an affinity-labeling agent, YV(bio)KD-aomk, to investigate the caspases activated during apoptotic cell death. YV(bio)KD-aomk identified six distinct polypeptides corresponding to active caspases in Fas-stimulated Jurkat T cells. On staurosporine treatment, four polypeptides were detected. Competition experiments showed that the labeled caspases have distinct substrate preferences. Stepwise appearance of the labeled caspases in each cell death event was consistent with the view that the activated caspases are organized into protease cascades. Moreover, we found that stepwise activation of caspases similar to that induced by Fas ligation is triggered by exposing non-apoptotic Jurkat cell extracts to caspase-8 (MACH/FLICE/Mch5). Conversely, CrmA protein, a viral suppressor of Fas-induced apoptosis, inhibited the protease activity of caspase-8. Overall, these findings provide evidence that caspase-8, a CrmA-sensitive protease, is responsible for initiating the stepwise activation of multiple caspases in Fas-stimulated cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 8711562; 0 (Affinity Labels); 0 (Antigens, CD95); 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Laminin); 0 (Oligopeptides); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (acetyl-aspartyl-glutamyl-valyl-aspartal); 143313-51-3 (L 709049); 151186-83-3 (laminin A); 62996-74-1 (Staurosporine); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 2.4.2.30 (Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP6 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP8 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (CASP9 protein, human); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 6); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 8); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspase 9); EC 3.4.22.- (Caspases); EC 3.4.22.- (Cysteine Endopeptidases); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0950-9232; 0950-9232</sn>
<ad>Department of Hematology and Oncology, Graduate School of Medicine, Kyoto University, Sakyo-ku, Japan.</ad>
<an>PMID: 9190889</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1038/sj.onc.1201131</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>9190889</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3014</id>
<a1>Takahashi,A.</a1>
<a1>Musy,P. Y.</a1>
<a1>Martins,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Poirier,G. G.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Earnshaw,W. C.</a1>
<t1>CrmA/SPI-2 inhibition of an endogenous ICE-related protease responsible for lamin A cleavage and apoptotic nuclear fragmentation</t1>
<jf>The Journal of biological chemistry</jf>
<jo>J.Biol.Chem.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Dec 20</fd>
<vo>271</vo>
<is>51</is>
<sp>32487</sp>
<op>32490</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Caspase 1</k1>
<k1>Cell-Free System</k1>
<k1>Chickens</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>DNA Fragmentation/drug effects</k1>
<k1>Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Enzyme Inhibitors/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Lamin Type A</k1>
<k1>Lamins</k1>
<k1>Nuclear Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Serpins/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/pharmacology</k1>
<ab>CrmA, a poxvirus gene product with a serpin-like structure, blocks a variety of apoptotic death events in cultured cells. Based on the ability of CrmA to inhibit the interleukin-1beta converting enzyme in vitro, it has been speculated that interleukin-1beta converting enzyme-related proteases (caspases) essential for apoptosis are the cellular targets of CrmA. Here we found that rabbitpox virus CrmA/SPI-2 inhibits the cleavage of lamin A mediated by a caspase in our cell-free system of apoptosis. In the presence of CrmA/SPI-2, nuclear apoptosis in vitro was blocked at an intermediate stage after collapse of the chromatin against the nuclear periphery and before nuclear shrinkage and disintegration into apoptotic body-like fragments. Using N-(acetyltyrosinylvalinyl-Nepsilon-biotinyllysyl) aspartic acid [(2,6-dimethylbenzoyl)oxy] methyl ketone, which derivatizes the active forms of caspases, we could show that one of five caspases active in the extracts is inhibited both by CrmA/SPI-2 and by a peptide spanning the lamin A apoptotic cleavage site. These results reveal that CrmA/SPI-2 can inhibit a caspase responsible both for lamin A cleavage and for the nuclear disintegration characteristic of apoptosis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20090929; GR: AI 15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: CA69008/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; GR: Wellcome Trust/United Kingdom; JID: 2985121R; 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Enzyme Inhibitors); 0 (Lamin Type A); 0 (Lamins); 0 (Nuclear Proteins); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 2.4.2.30 (Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerases); EC 3.4.- (Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.- (Cysteine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.36 (Caspase 1); EC 3.4.99.- (lamin proteinase); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0021-9258; 0021-9258</sn>
<ad>Institute of Cell and Molecular Biology, University of Edinburgh, Michael Swann Building, The King&#39;s Buildings, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh EH9 3JR, Scotland, United Kingdom. bill.earnshaw@ed.ac.uk</ad>
<an>PMID: 8955067</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8955067</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2963</id>
<a1>Tang,Z.</a1>
<a1>Parekh,P.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Tan,W.</a1>
<t1>Generating aptamers for recognition of virus-infected cells</t1>
<jf>Clinical chemistry</jf>
<jo>Clin.Chem.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>55</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>813</sp>
<op>822</op>
<k1>Aptamers, Nucleotide/analysis/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line, Tumor</k1>
<k1>Cell Survival</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/analysis/chemistry/genetics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>SELEX Aptamer Technique/instrumentation/methods</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The development of molecular probes capable of recognizing virus-infected cells is essential to meet the serious clinical, therapeutic, and national-security challenges confronting virology today. We report the development of DNA aptamers as probes for the selective targeting of virus-infected living cells. METHODS: To create aptamer probes capable of recognizing virus-infected cells, we used cell-SELEX (systematic evolution of ligands via exponential enrichment), which uses intact infected live cells as targets for aptamer selection. In this study, vaccinia virus-infected and -uninfected lung cancer A549 cells were chosen to develop our model probes. RESULTS: A panel of aptamers has been evolved by means of the infected cell-SELEX procedure. The results demonstrate that the aptamers bind selectively to vaccinia virus-infected A549 cells with apparent equilibrium dissociation constants in the nanomolar range. In addition, these aptamers can specifically recognize a variety of target infected cell lines. The aptamers&amp;#39; target is most likely a viral protein located on the cell surface. CONCLUSIONS: The success of developing a panel of DNA-aptamer probes capable of recognizing virus-infected cells via a whole living cell-SELEX selection strategy may increase our understanding of the molecular signatures of infected cells. Our findings suggest that aptamers can be developed as molecular probes for use as diagnostic and therapeutic reagents and for facilitating drug delivery against infected cells.</ab>
<no>GR: 1-U54-AI-057157/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 GM079359/GM/NIGMS NIH HHS/United States; GR: R21CA122648/CA/NCI NIH HHS/United States; JID: 9421549; 0 (Aptamers, Nucleotide); 0 (DNA, Viral); 2009/02/26 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1530-8561; 0009-9147</sn>
<ad>Departments of Chemistry, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19246617; clinchem.2008.113514 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1373/clinchem.2008.113514</do>
<wp>20090226</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19246617</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3025</id>
<a1>Thompson,J. P.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Ali,A. N.</a1>
<a1>Crenshaw,B. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The effects of serpin gene mutations on the distinctive pathobiology of cowpox and rabbitpox virus following intranasal inoculation of Balb/c mice</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>197</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>328</sp>
<op>338</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Brain/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Lethal Dose 50</k1>
<k1>Lung/anatomy &amp; histology/microbiology/pathology</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Insertional</k1>
<k1>Organ Size</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/pathology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Deletion</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Viremia/pathology</k1>
<ab>Intranasal infection of Balb/c mice with 106 plaque forming units (PFU) of wild-type cowpox virus (CPV) and rabbitpox virus (RPV) induced strikingly different pulmonary pathology despite nearly identical clinical signs of illness and LD50. Intranasal infection with CPV induced severe peribronchial, peribronchiolar, and perivascular hemorrhage with a mixed inflammatory cell infiltrate, bronchial and bronchiolar epithelial cell hyperplasia with intracytoplasmic acidophilic inclusion bodies, and alveolar hemorrhage and edema. In contrast, infection with RPV induced a mixed peribronchial and peribronchiolar inflammatory cell infiltrate, multifocal areas of bronchiolar epithelial cell coagulation necrosis, alveolar edema, and a conspicuous absence of pulmonary hemorrhage. Viremia was not detected following CPV infection and only 1 of 11 mice had brain-associated virus at death. Mice infected with RPV exhibited a viremia 2-3 days after infection and all mice had virus associated with the brain at death. Mice infected with viruses containing certain serine protease inhibitor (SPI) gene mutations (CPV delta SPI-1, CPV delta SPI-3, and RPV SPI-1-) exhibited no difference in clinical disease manifestation when compared with those infected with wild-type viruses. However, inactivation of the SPI-2 genes in either CPV or RPV resulted in disease attenuation and alteration of pulmonary pathology. Mice infected with the CPV delta SPI-2 mutant showed decreased pulmonary hemorrhage, reduced inflammation, and an absence of alveolar edema, while mice infected with the RPV delta SPI-2 mutant had a marked increase in intrapulmonary inflammatory cells and only a transient viremia.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Serpins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Small Animal Clinical Sciences, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8212568; S0042-6822(83)71594-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1993.1594</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8212568</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2991</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Baquero,M. T.</a1>
<a1>Yuan,S.</a1>
<a1>Thoennes,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The cowpox virus serpin SPI-3 complexes with and inhibits urokinase-type and tissue-type plasminogen activators and plasmin</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jul 5</fd>
<vo>272</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>267</sp>
<op>280</op>
<k1>Acute-Phase Proteins/biosynthesis/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism/physiology</k1>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Bacteriophage T7/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Fibrinolysin/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Genetic Vectors/genetics</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Macromolecular Substances</k1>
<k1>Models, Chemical</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/enzymology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/physiology</k1>
<k1>Serpins/physiology</k1>
<k1>Tissue Plasminogen Activator/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Urokinase-Type Plasminogen Activator/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/physiology</k1>
<k1>alpha-2-Antiplasmin/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The orthopoxvirus serpin SPI-3 is N-glycosylated and suppresses fusion between infected cells. Although SPI-3 contains motifs conserved in inhibitory serpins, no proteinase inhibition by SPI-3 has been demonstrated, and mutations within the serpin reactive center loop (RCL) do not affect the ability to regulate cell fusion. We demonstrate here that SPI-3 protein expressed by transcription/translation in vitro is able to form SDS-stable complexes with the serine proteinases plasmin, urokinase-type plasminogen activator (uPA), and tissue-type plasminogen activator (tPA), consistent with inhibitory activity of the serpin. Weaker complexes were noted with factor Xa and thrombin. Mutation of Arg-340/Ser-341 at the predicted P1/P1&amp;#39; sites within the RCL prevented the formation of complexes between SPI-3 and plasmin, uPA, or tPA, suggesting that the arginine at the P1 position was required for complex formation. SPI-3 protein lacking the N-terminal signal peptide was purified by means of an N-terminal His(10)-tag and gave complete inhibition in vitro of plasmin, uPA, and tPA and partial inhibition of factor Xa. SPI-3 is therefore a bifunctional protein that acts as a proteinase inhibitor and suppresses infected cell-cell fusion. As a proteinase inhibitor, SPI-3 has similar specificity to the leporipoxvirus SERP1 protein of myxoma virus, although the two serpins are less than 30% identical overall. The inhibition constants of SPI-3 for plasmin, uPA, and tPA were determined to be 0.64, 0.51, and 1.9 nM, respectively, very similar to the corresponding K(i) values of SERP1.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091119; CI: Copyright 2000; GENBANK/AF216779; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Acute-Phase Proteins); 0 (Macromolecular Substances); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 0 (alpha-2-Antiplasmin); EC 3.4.21.68 (Tissue Plasminogen Activator); EC 3.4.21.7 (Fibrinolysin); EC 3.4.21.73 (Urokinase-Type Plasminogen Activator); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10873770; S0042-6822(00)90377-5 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.2000.0377</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10873770</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2970</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Dilling,B. P.</a1>
<a1>Prins,C.</a1>
<a1>Cresawn,S. G.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Condit,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Vaccinia virus temperature-sensitive mutants in the A28 gene produce non-infectious virions that bind to cells but are defective in entry</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Sep 15</fd>
<vo>366</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>62</sp>
<op>72</op>
<k1>3&#39; Untranslated Regions</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Fusion</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>DNA Viruses/genetics/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Haplorhini</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Temperature</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Vaccines</k1>
<k1>Virion/genetics/physiology</k1>
<ab>The vaccinia virus temperature-sensitive mutations Cts6 and Cts9 were mapped by marker rescue and DNA sequencing to the A28 gene. Cts6 and Cts9 contain an identical 2-bp deletion truncating the A28 protein and removing the fourth conserved cysteine near the C-terminus. Cts9 mutant virions produced at 40 degrees C were non-infectious and unable to cause cytopathic effect. However, the mutant A28 protein localized to purified mature virions (MV) at 31 degrees C and 40 degrees C. MV of Cts9 produced at 40 degrees C bound to cells but did not enter cells. Low pH treatment of Cts9-infected cells at 18 h p.i. failed to produce fusion from within at 40 degrees C, but gave fusion at 31 degrees C. Adsorption of Cts9 mutant virions to cells followed by low pH treatment showed a defect in fusion from without. The Cts9 phenotype suggests that the A28 protein is involved in both virus entry and cell-cell fusion, and supports the linkage between the two processes.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: R01 AI015722-24/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI055560-01A1/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI055560-02/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI055560-03/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI055560-04/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R01 AI055560-05/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R21 AI055560-01/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (3&amp;#39; Untranslated Regions); 0 (Viral Vaccines); NIHMS31037; OID: NLM: NIHMS31037; OID: NLM: PMC2062567; 2007/01/09 [received]; 2007/02/05 [revised]; 2007/03/12 [accepted]; 2007/05/17 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA. pturner@mgm.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17499330; S0042-6822(07)00173-0 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2007.03.060</do>
<wp>20070517</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17499330</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2062567</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2965</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The vaccinia virus fusion inhibitor proteins SPI-3 (K2) and HA (A56) expressed by infected cells reduce the entry of superinfecting virus</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Oct 25</fd>
<vo>380</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>226</sp>
<op>233</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Luciferases/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Staining and Labeling/methods</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Vero Cells</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virus Attachment</k1>
<k1>Virus Internalization</k1>
<ab>The orthopoxvirus SPI-3 (K2) and A56 (hemagglutinin, HA) proteins interact and together prevent cell-cell fusion. SPI-3/A56 has been proposed to prevent the superinfection of previously infected cells by reducing virus-cell fusion. Binding of mature virions of vaccinia virus (VV) to VV-infected cells was unaffected by SPI-3 or A56 on the surface of infected cells. Entry of VV into infected cells was assessed using VV-P(T7)-luc carrying the luciferase reporter under T7 control. Cells infected with VV or cowpox virus (CPV) expressing T7 RNA polymerase and lacking SPI-3 and/or A56 were superinfected with VV-P(T7)-luc, and luciferase activity was measured. Inactivation of SPI-3 or A56 from the pre-infecting virus resulted in greater luciferase expression from the superinfecting VV-P(T7)-luc. Antibody against SPI-3 present during infection with wild-type CPV-T7 increased luciferase expression from superinfecting VV-P(T7)-luc. The SPI-3/A56 complex on the infected cell surface therefore appears to reduce the entry of virions into infected cells.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091124; GR: R56 AI-015722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: R56 AI015722-25/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (A56R protein, Orthopoxvirus); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 1.13.12.- (Luciferases); NIHMS74440; OID: NLM: NIHMS74440; OID: NLM: PMC2668523; 2008/04/25 [received]; 2008/05/22 [revised]; 2008/07/22 [accepted]; 2008/08/28 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1096-0341; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. pcturner@ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18760436; S0042-6822(08)00481-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2008.07.020</do>
<wp>20080828</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18760436</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2668523</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2973</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The cowpox virus fusion regulator proteins SPI-3 and hemagglutinin interact in infected and uninfected cells</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Mar 30</fd>
<vo>347</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>88</sp>
<op>99</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Viral</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cell Membrane/virology</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/immunology/pathogenicity/physiology</k1>
<k1>Epitope Mapping</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/genetics/immunology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Membrane Fusion/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Models, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Protein Conformation</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Proteins/genetics/immunology/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Serpins/chemistry/genetics/immunology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/chemistry/genetics/immunology/physiology</k1>
<ab>The serpin SPI-3 and the hemagglutinin (HA) encoded by cowpox virus (CPV) block cell-cell fusion, and colocalize at the cell surface. wtCPV does not fuse cells, but inactivation of either gene leads to fusion. SPI-3 mAb added to wtCPV-infected cells caused fusion, confirming that SPI-3 protein at the cell surface prevents fusion. The SPI-3 mAb epitope mapped to an 85-amino acid region at the C-terminus. Removal of either 44 residues from the SPI-3 C-terminus or 48 residues following the N-terminal signal sequence resulted in fusion. Interaction between SPI-3 and HA proteins in infected cells was shown by coimmunoprecipitation. SPI-3/HA was not associated with the A27L &amp;quot;fusion&amp;quot; protein. SPI-3 and HA were able to associate in uninfected cells in the absence of other viral proteins. The HA-binding domain in SPI-3 resided in the C-terminal 229 residues, and did not include helix D, which mediates cofactor interaction in many other serpins.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI 057157/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (Antibodies, Viral); 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); 0 (Recombinant Proteins); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 2005/07/21 [received]; 2005/11/04 [revised]; 2005/11/07 [accepted]; 2005/12/27 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Box 100266/1600 SW Archer Road, ARB R2-231, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA. pturner@mgm.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 16378629; S0042-6822(05)00749-X [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.virol.2005.11.012</do>
<wp>20051227</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16378629</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2983</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Poxvirus immune modulators: functional insights from animal models</t1>
<jf>Virus research</jf>
<jo>Virus Res.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>88</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>35</sp>
<op>53</op>
<k1>Adjuvants, Immunologic/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Disease Models, Animal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Mice, Inbred BALB C</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/immunology/virology</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<ab>Poxviruses express several different classes of immune modulators that suppress the host response to infection, including soluble cytokine binding proteins, serpins, chemokine binding proteins, a complement control protein, and members of the semaphorin and Toll/IL-1 receptor families. Biochemical activity of these proteins has been demonstrated by many in vitro studies. Conservation in evolution of poxvirus immune modulators implies that these genes are functional in vivo, but the results of infecting animals with knockout viruses have not always been clear cut. Studies involving different animal models are reviewed, and the criteria for suitable models are discussed. Challenges include finding an appropriate animal host, and using an inoculation route that resembles the process of natural infection. The fact that multiple immune modulators can target the same pathway at different steps may explain why single knockout mutants are not always attenuated in animals.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 8410979; 0 (Adjuvants, Immunologic); 0 (Viral Proteins); RF: 140; ppublish</no>
<pp>Netherlands</pp>
<sn>0168-1702; 0168-1702</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610-0266, USA. pturner@mgm.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 12297326; S0168170202001193 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>12297326</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3018</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Orthopoxvirus fusion inhibitor glycoprotein SPI-3 (open reading frame K2L) contains motifs characteristic of serine proteinase inhibitors that are not required for control of cell fusion</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>69</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>5978</sp>
<op>5987</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Cell Fusion</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cercopithecus aethiops</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>DNA Primers</k1>
<k1>DNA Replication</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutagenesis, Site-Directed</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Serpins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication</k1>
<ab>The cowpox virus (CPV) SPI-3 gene (open reading frame K2L in vaccinia virus) is one of three orthopoxvirus genes whose products are members of the serpin (serine proteinase inhibitor) superfamily. The CPV SPI-3 gene, when overexpressed by using the vaccinia virus/T7 expression system, synthesized two proteins of 50 and 48 kDa. Treatment with the N glycosylation inhibitor tunicamycin converted the two SPI-3 proteins to a single 40-kDa protein, close to the size of 42 kDa predicted from the DNA sequence, suggesting that the SPI-3 protein, unlike the other two orthopoxvirus serpins, is a glycoprotein. Immunoblotting with an anti-SPI-3 antibody showed that the SPI-3 protein is synthesized early in infection prior to DNA replication. SPI-3 inhibits cell-cell fusion during infections with both CPV and vaccinia virus. A transfection assay was devised to test engineered mutants of SPI-3 for the ability to inhibit fusion. Two mutants with C-terminal deletions of 156 and 70 amino acids were completely inactive in fusion inhibition. Site-directed mutations were constructed near the C terminus of SPI-3, in or near the predicted reactive-site loop which is conserved in inhibitory serpins. Substitutions within the loop at the P1 to P1&amp;#39; positions and P5 to P5&amp;#39; positions, inclusive, did not result in any loss of activity, nor did changes at the P17 to P10 residues in the stalk of the reactive loop. Therefore, SPI-3 does not appear to control cell fusion by acting as a serine proteinase inhibitor.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (DNA Primers); 0 (Recombinant Fusion Proteins); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC189493; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7666502</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7666502</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC189493</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3031</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>An orthopoxvirus serpinlike gene controls the ability of infected cells to fuse</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>66</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>2076</sp>
<op>2085</op>
<k1>Antibodies, Monoclonal/immunology</k1>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Western</k1>
<k1>Cell Fusion</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral</k1>
<k1>Hemagglutinins, Viral/genetics</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics/physiology</k1>
<k1>Restriction Mapping</k1>
<k1>Serpins/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Envelope Proteins/immunology</k1>
<ab>Most orthopoxviruses encode a functional hemagglutinin (HA), which is nonessential for virus growth in cell culture. However, inactivation of the HA gene leads to the formation of polykaryocytes (syncytia) by fusion of infected cells at neutral pH. Fusion is not observed when a functional HA gene is present. Deletion of open reading frames (ORFs) K2, K3, and K4 within the HindIII K fragment of the HA-positive (HA+) vaccinia virus strain WR also led to fusion of cells upon infection at neutral pH. A novel ORF inactivation procedure utilizing the polymerase chain reaction was used to specifically implicate the K2 ORF in this phenomenon. The K2 ORF (the viral SPI-3 gene) encodes a protein resembling serine protease inhibitors (serpins). Inactivation of the SPI-3 gene in any of the HA+ orthopoxviruses tested caused infected cells to fuse in a manner which appeared identical to that seen for HA- mutants, although fusion was most pronounced with cowpox virus. SPI-3-negative strains fused despite the fact that the HA was expressed and processed normally, i.e., cells infected with SPI-3 mutants remained functionally hemadsorption positive, and analysis of the HA protein by Western immunoblot suggested that posttranslational modifications of the HA protein appeared normal. Fusion triggered by SPI-3 mutants, like that for HA- mutants, was inhibited by the monoclonal antibody C3 directed against the vaccinia virus 14-kDa envelope protein. Therefore SPI-3- and HA-mediated fusion share a requirement for the 14-kDa protein, suggesting linkage of the seemingly disparate SPI-3 and HA genes through a common pathway which normally acts to prevent fusion of cells infected with wild-type virus.</ab>
<no>LR: 20081120; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Antibodies, Monoclonal); 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Hemagglutinins, Viral); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Envelope Proteins); OID: NLM: PMC288998; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1548753</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1548753</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC288998</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3029</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>A PCR-based method for manipulation of the vaccinia virus genome that eliminates the need for cloning</t1>
<jf>BioTechniques</jf>
<jo>BioTechniques</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>764</sp>
<op>771</op>
<k1>Base Sequence</k1>
<k1>Blotting, Southern</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>DNA, Single-Stranded</k1>
<k1>Genetic Techniques</k1>
<k1>Genome, Viral</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Polymerase Chain Reaction</k1>
<k1>Thymidine Kinase/genetics</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<ab>A general method is described for altering specific genes of vaccinia virus (VV). We demonstrate and evaluate the procedure by gene inactivation, using a dominant selectable marker in conjunction with recombinant polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Primers based on the sequence of the target gene enable amplification of flanking arms and their subsequent attachment to the gpt cassette that confers resistance to mycophenolic acid. Linear PCR constructs are transfected into cells infected with wild-type vaccinia virus. Mutant viruses with gpt inserted into the target gene by homologous recombination are then selected by growth in the presence of MPA. This technique was applied to the vaccinia virus thymidine kinase gene and compared to the traditional method of constructing gpt-containing plasmids by cloning. The PCR scheme was found to be highly efficient and could theoretically be used to insert any foreign DNA element into any nonessential target gene for which partial or complete sequence information is available. The procedure can potentially be used for a wide variety of genetic modifications, including the insertion of foreign genes, with poxviruses and other DNA viruses. Genomes of microorganisms, such as bacteria and yeast that can be transformed with linear DNA, are also candidates for manipulation by this methodology.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-157222/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 8306785; 0 (DNA, Single-Stranded); EC 2.7.1.21 (Thymidine Kinase); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0736-6205; 0736-6205</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610-0266.</ad>
<an>PMID: 1418979</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>1418979</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3041</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The molecular pathogenesis of poxviruses</t1>
<jf>Current topics in microbiology and immunology</jf>
<jo>Curr.Top.Microbiol.Immunol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>163</vo>
<sp>125</sp>
<op>151</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae/genetics/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Poxviridae Infections/genetics</k1>
<k1>Virulence</k1>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 0110513; RF: 135; ppublish</no>
<pp>GERMANY</pp>
<sn>0070-217X; 0070-217X</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology and Medical Microbiology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2173654</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2173654</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2998</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Sancho,M. C.</a1>
<a1>Thoennes,S. R.</a1>
<a1>Caputo,A.</a1>
<a1>Bleackley,R. C.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Myxoma virus Serp2 is a weak inhibitor of granzyme B and interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme in vitro and unlike CrmA cannot block apoptosis in cowpox virus-infected cells</t1>
<jf>Journal of virology</jf>
<jo>J.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>8</is>
<sp>6394</sp>
<op>6404</op>
<k1>Amino Acid Sequence</k1>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Apoptosis</k1>
<k1>Caspase 1/antagonists &amp; inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/pathogenicity</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel</k1>
<k1>Genes, Viral</k1>
<k1>Granzymes</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>LLC-PK1 Cells</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Molecular Sequence Data</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Peptides/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Sequence Homology, Amino Acid</k1>
<k1>Serine Endopeptidases/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Substrate Specificity</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/genetics/isolation &amp; purification/metabolism</k1>
<ab>The Serp2 protein encoded by the leporipoxvirus myxoma virus is essential for full virulence (F. Messud-Petit, J. Gelfi, M. Delverdier, M. F. Amardeilh, R. Py, G. Sutter, and S. Bertagnoli, J. Virol. 72:7830-7839, 1998) and, like crmA of cowpox virus (CPV), is reported to inhibit the interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme (ICE, caspase-1) (F. Petit, S. Bertagnoli, J. Gelfi, F. Fassy, C. Boucraut-Baralon, and A. Milon, J. Virol. 70:5860-5866, 1996). Serp2 and CrmA both contain Asp at the P1 position within the serpin reactive site loop and yet are only 35% identical overall. Serp2 protein was cleaved by ICE but, unlike CrmA, did not form a stable complex with ICE that was detectable by native gel electrophoresis. Attempts to covalently cross-link ICE-serpin inhibitory complexes were successful with CrmA, but no complex between ICE and Serp2 was visible after cross-linking. Purified His10-tagged Serp2 protein was a relatively poor inhibitor of ICE, with a Ki of 80 nM compared to 4 pM for CrmA. Serp2 protein resembled CrmA in that a stable complex with the serine proteinase granzyme B was detectable after sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. However, Serp2 was less effective at inhibiting granzyme B activity (Ki = 420 nM) than CrmA (Ki = 100 nM). Finally, Serp2 was tested for the ability to replace CrmA and inhibit apoptosis in LLC-PK1 cells infected with a CPV recombinant deleted for CrmA but expressing Serp2. Unlike wild-type-CPV-infected cells, apoptosis was readily observed in cells infected with the recombinant virus, as indicated by the induction of both nuclear fragmentation and caspase-mediated cleavage of DEVD-AMC [acetyl-Asp-Glu-Val-Asp-(amino-4-methyl coumarin)]. These results indicate that Serp2 is unable to functionally substitute for CrmA within the context of CPV and that the inhibition spectra for Serp2 and CrmA are distinct.</ab>
<no>LR: 20091118; GENBANK/AF141941; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0113724; 0 (Cysteine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Peptides); 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serp2 protein, myxoma virus); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Proteins); 96282-35-8 (interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme inhibitor); EC 3.4.21.- (GZMB protein, human); EC 3.4.21.- (Granzymes); EC 3.4.21.- (Gzmb protein, mouse); EC 3.4.21.- (Serine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.36 (Caspase 1); OID: NLM: PMC112719; ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-538X; 0022-538X</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10400732</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10400732</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC112719</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3042</id>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Young,D. C.</a1>
<a1>Flanegan,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Interference with vaccinia virus growth caused by insertion of the coding sequence for poliovirus protease 2A</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>173</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>509</sp>
<op>521</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Capsid/biosynthesis/genetics</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cloning, Molecular</k1>
<k1>Cysteine Endopeptidases/genetics</k1>
<k1>DNA, Viral/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Gene Expression Regulation, Viral</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mutation</k1>
<k1>Nucleic Acid Hybridization</k1>
<k1>Plasmids</k1>
<k1>Poliovirus/enzymology/genetics</k1>
<k1>Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</k1>
<k1>Protein Biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>RNA, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Transfection</k1>
<k1>Tumor Cells, Cultured</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Synthetic</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics/growth &amp; development</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins</k1>
<ab>Attempts were made to express noninfectious derivatives of full-length type 1 (Mahoney) and type 2 (Lansing) poliovirus cDNAs in live recombinant vaccinia viruses for vaccine purposes. Vaccinia virus (VV) would not tolerate insertions of polio cDNA containing the coding sequence for the polio protease 2A. However, polio cDNA with the 2A gene deleted either in vivo or in vitro could be inserted into VV and stably maintained. Genetic evidence indicated that expression of the polio 2A gene in trans from transfected plasmid DNA was deleterious to vaccinia virus within the same cell. The 2A product presumably interferes with VV growth by modifying the host translational machinery such that translation of host and vaccinia capped mRNAs is inhibited. Polio cDNA containing a mutated 2A gene whose product is no longer active in host protein shutoff could be inserted into VV. However, inserts containing the intact mutated 2A gene did not synthesize detectable poliovirus protein, although they did produce polio-specific RNA. Expression of polio-specific protein was detected from a VV-polio recombinant containing cDNA encoding the capsid proteins plus an incomplete 2A gene. These results have implications regarding possible vaccine construction, and suggest a mechanism for interference between polio and vaccinia viruses in mixed infection.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; GR: AI-15539/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (DNA, Viral); 0 (Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated); 0 (RNA, Viral); 0 (Vaccines, Synthetic); 0 (Viral Proteins); EC 3.4.22.- (Cysteine Endopeptidases); EC 3.4.22.29 (picornain 2A, Picornavirus); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Immunology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32610.</ad>
<an>PMID: 2556841; 0042-6822(89)90563-1 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>2556841</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3023</id>
<a1>van der Leek,M. L.</a1>
<a1>Feller,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Sorensen,G.</a1>
<a1>Isaacson,W.</a1>
<a1>Adams,C. L.</a1>
<a1>Borde,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Pfeiffer,N.</a1>
<a1>Tran,T.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<a1>Gibbs,E. P.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of swinepox virus as a vaccine vector in pigs using an Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease (pseudorabies) virus gene insert coding for glycoproteins gp50 and gp63</t1>
<jf>The Veterinary record</jf>
<jo>Vet.Rec.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jan 1</fd>
<vo>134</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>13</sp>
<op>18</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antibodies, Viral/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Evaluation Studies as Topic</k1>
<k1>Herpesvirus 1, Suid/genetics/immunology/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Pseudorabies/immunology/prevention &amp; control</k1>
<k1>Suipoxvirus/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Swine</k1>
<k1>Vaccines, Synthetic/administration &amp; dosage/immunology</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/genetics</k1>
<k1>Viral Envelope Proteins/genetics/immunology</k1>
<k1>Virus Shedding</k1>
<ab>Pigs were vaccinated by scarification or intramuscular injection with a swinepox virus-Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease (pseudorabies) recombinant (rSPV-AD) constructed by inserting the linked Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease virus genes coding for glycoproteins gp50 and gp63, attached to a vaccinia virus p7.5 promoter, into the thymidine kinase gene of swinepox virus. By 21 days after vaccination, 90 and 100 per cent of the animals vaccinated by scarification or intramuscular injection, respectively, had developed serum neutralising antibodies to Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease virus. Upon challenge with virulent virus, significantly fewer vaccinated pigs developed clinical Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease, nasal shedding of challenge virus was markedly reduced, and the vaccinated groups of pigs maintained or gained weight during the week after challenge whereas the unvaccinated control group lost weight. No transmission of rSPV-AD to in-contact controls was detected during the three weeks before challenge. In a second experiment, serum neutralising antibodies to Aujeszky&amp;#39;s disease virus persisted for 150 days after the pigs were vaccinated with rSPV-AD by scarification or intramuscular injection and all the pigs showed an anamnestic response when they were revaccinated.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071115; JID: 0031164; 0 (Antibodies, Viral); 0 (Vaccines, Synthetic); 0 (Viral Envelope Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>ENGLAND</pp>
<sn>0042-4900; 0042-4900</sn>
<ad>College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville 32611.</ad>
<an>PMID: 8128561</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>8128561</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2990</id>
<a1>Wang,Y. X.</a1>
<a1>Turner,P. C.</a1>
<a1>Ness,T. L.</a1>
<a1>Moon,K. B.</a1>
<a1>Schoeb,T. R.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The cowpox virus SPI-3 and myxoma virus SERP1 serpins are not functionally interchangeable despite their similar proteinase inhibition profiles in vitro</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jul 5</fd>
<vo>272</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>281</sp>
<op>292</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Cell Fusion</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Cowpox virus/enzymology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Glycosylation</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mice</k1>
<k1>Myxoma virus/enzymology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Myxomatosis, Infectious/enzymology/virology</k1>
<k1>Open Reading Frames/genetics</k1>
<k1>Phenotype</k1>
<k1>Rabbits</k1>
<k1>Recombination, Genetic</k1>
<k1>Serine Proteinase Inhibitors/metabolism</k1>
<k1>Serpins/biosynthesis/genetics/physiology/secretion</k1>
<k1>Vaccinia virus/enzymology/physiology</k1>
<k1>Viral Fusion Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/physiology/secretion</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis/genetics/physiology/secretion</k1>
<ab>The myxoma virus (MYX) serpin SERP1 is a secreted glycoprotein with anti-inflammatory activity that is required for full MYX virulence in vivo. The cowpox virus (CPV) serpin SPI-3 (vaccinia virus ORF K2L) is a nonsecreted glycoprotein that blocks cell-cell fusion, independent of serpin activity, and is not required for virulence of vaccinia virus or CPV in mice. Although SPI-3 has only 29% overall identity to SERP1, both serpins have arginine at the P1 position in the reactive center loop, and SPI-3 has a proteinase inhibitory profile strikingly similar to that of SERP1 [Turner, P. C., Baquero, M. T., Yuan, S., Thoennes, S. R., and Moyer, R. W. (2000) Virology 272, 267-280]. To determine whether SPI-3 and SERP1 were functionally equivalent, a CPV variant was constructed where the SPI-3 gene was deleted and replaced with the SERP1 gene regulated by the SPI-3 promoter. Cells infected with CPVDeltaSPI-3::SERP1 secrete SERP1 and show extensive fusion, suggesting that SERP1 is unable to functionally substitute for SPI-3 in fusion inhibition. In the reciprocal experiment, both copies of SERP1 were deleted from MYX and replaced with SPI-3 under the control of the SERP1 promoter. Cells infected with the MYXDeltaSERP1::SPI-3 recombinant unexpectedly secreted SPI-3, suggesting either that the cellular secretory pathway is enhanced by MYX or that CPV encodes a protein that prevents SPI-3 secretion. MYXDeltaSERP1::SPI-3 was as attenuated in rabbits as MYXDeltaSERP1::lacZ, indicating that SPI-3 cannot substitute for SERP1 in MYX pathogenesis.</ab>
<no>LR: 20071114; CI: Copyright 2000; GR: AI-15722/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; GR: T32-AI07110/AI/NIAID NIH HHS/United States; JID: 0110674; 0 (Serine Proteinase Inhibitors); 0 (Serpins); 0 (Viral Fusion Proteins); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, College of Medicine, Gainesville, Florida, 32610, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10873771; S0042-6822(00)90378-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.2000.0378</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10873771</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3019</id>
<a1>Winter,J.</a1>
<a1>Hall,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Moyer,R. W.</a1>
<t1>The effect of inhibitors on the growth of the entomopoxvirus from Amsacta moorei in Lymantria dispar (gypsy moth) cells</t1>
<jf>Virology</jf>
<jo>Virology</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Aug 20</fd>
<vo>211</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>462</sp>
<op>473</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Antiviral Agents/pharmacology</k1>
<k1>Cell Line</k1>
<k1>Entomopoxvirinae/drug effects/physiology</k1>
<k1>Kinetics</k1>
<k1>Lepidoptera/cytology/metabolism/virology</k1>
<k1>Microscopy, Electron</k1>
<k1>Moths/cytology/virology</k1>
<k1>Plaque Assay</k1>
<k1>Viral Proteins/biosynthesis</k1>
<k1>Virus Replication/drug effects</k1>
<ab>Within the family of Poxviridae, the entomopoxviruses are the most distant relatives of the more well-known and intensively studied orthopoxviruses (vaccinia and variola). The growth of the entomopoxvirus from Amsacta moorei (AmEPV) has been characterized in cell culture and compared to that of vaccinia virus (VV), the prototypic orthopoxvirus. The overall characteristics of infected cell cultures were generally similar between the two viruses. One striking difference noted was the apparent absence of proteolytic processing of late AmEPV viral proteins, a hallmark of vertebrate poxvirus infections associated with viral morphogenesis. AmEPV, like VV, was found to be sensitive to all the inhibitors of viral infection tested including phosphonoacetic acid, 1-beta-D-arabinofuranosylcytosine, and isatin-beta-thiosemicarbazone (IBT), a compound associated with the rather specific inhibition of vertebrate poxviruses. While both VV and AmEPV are inhibited by IBT, the inhibition of AmEPV, unlike that of VV, is not accompanied by either a breakdown of ribosomal RNA or a global inhibition of late viral protein synthesis. Instead, in the presence of IBT, AmEPV enveloped, immature virions form devoid of a well-differentiated core, which unlike mature virions fail to insert into occlusion bodies.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 0110674; 0 (Antiviral Agents); 0 (Viral Proteins); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0042-6822; 0042-6822</sn>
<ad>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, University of Florida, College of Medicine, Gainesville 32610-0266, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 7645250; S0042-6822(85)71428-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&#39;t; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<do>10.1006/viro.1995.1428</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>7645250</pmid></reference></refworks>
