
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3092</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Wound healing</t1>
<yr>2008</yr>
<no>p. cm.; Entry: 20080425; Update: 20081111</no>
<a2>Thomas,Regan</a2>
<t2>Advanced Therapy in Facial/Plastic Reconstructive Surgery</t2>
<pp>B C Decker Inc</pp>
<sn>9781550093759; 1550093754 Vendor Info: Baker and Taylor Baker &amp; Taylor YBP Library Services (BTCP BKTY YANK) 179.00 Status: active</sn>
<an>226357240</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>WorldCat; Book; OCLC; WorldCat</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3096</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Angiofibroma</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>115</sp>
<op>122</op>
<a2>Roland,P. S.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology Clinical Case Studies Oral Board Exam Review</t2>
<pb>Anadem Publishing, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Columbus, OH</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3095</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Nasal fracture</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>163</sp>
<op>163-167</op>
<a2>Roland,P. S.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology Clinical Case Studies Oral Board Exam Review</t2>
<pb>Anadem Publishing, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Columbus, OH</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3099</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Otitis media with meningitis</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>70</sp>
<op>70-78</op>
<a2>Roland,P. S.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology Clinical Case Studies Oral Board Exam Review</t2>
<pb>Anadem Publishing, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Columbus, OH</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3097</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Sialolithiasis</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>182</sp>
<op>182-187</op>
<a2>Roland,P. S.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology Clinical Case Studies Oral Board Exam Review</t2>
<pb>Anadem Publishing, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Columbus, OH</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3098</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Transection of Stensen&amp;#39;s duct</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<sp>188</sp>
<op>188-192</op>
<a2>Roland,P. S.</a2>
<t2>Otolaryngology Clinical Case Studies Oral Board Exam Review</t2>
<pb>Anadem Publishing, Inc.</pb>
<pp>Columbus, OH</pp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3094</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Hyaluronic fillers, neurotoxins and beyond</t1>
<jo>Practical Tips</jo>
<vo>1</vo>
<a2>Dayan,S. H.</a2><a2> Bassichis,B. A.</a2>
<t2>Practical Tips</t2>
<pb>College of Cosmetic Medicine</pb>
<pp>Chicago, IL</pp>
<t3>Practical Tips Series</t3>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1756</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Botulinum neurotoxins: fundamentals for the facial plastic surgeon</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>Jul-Aug</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>260</sp>
<op>266</op>
<k1>Anti-Dyskinesia Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Botulinum Toxins/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Facial Paralysis/drug therapy/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Surgery, Plastic/adverse effects</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>The most commonly performed nonsurgical cosmetic procedure in the facial plastic surgery armamentarium involves the various commercial preparations of botulinum neurotoxins. These drugs have undergone a transformation from public health scourge to near ubiquitous therapeutic modality across the entire medical spectrum. Herein, the history of botulinum neurotoxins is reviewed, including an exploration of their pharmacology, neuromuscular junction physiology, a description of the commercially available preparations, and the recent research concerning the practicalities of their clinical use.</ab>
<no>JID: 8000029; 0 (Anti-Dyskinesia Agents); 0 (Botulinum Toxins); RF: 71; 2006/07/29 [received]; 2006/09/07 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Division of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, PO Box 100264, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. robert.adelson@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17606044; S0196-0709(06)00209-2 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.amjoto.2006.09.002</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17606044</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1755</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Bassischis,B. A.</a1>
<t1>Objective assessment of the accuracy of computer-simulated imaging in rhinoplasty</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>May-Jun</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>155</op>
<k1>Computer Simulation/standards</k1>
<k1>Face</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Image Processing, Computer-Assisted/methods/standards</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nose/surgery</k1>
<k1>Nose Deformities, Acquired/surgery</k1>
<k1>Photography/methods</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Period</k1>
<k1>Reproducibility of Results</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Rhinoplasty/methods</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: The objective of the study was to evaluate the accuracy by which computer-simulated rhinoplasty images reflect surgical results in 6-month postoperative photographs. METHODS: We performed a retrospective, objective evaluation of 5 features of the facial profile in the computer-simulated images and in the 6-month postoperative photographs of 36 rhinoplasty patients. Data recorded for the nasolabial angle, nasofrontal angle, columella tip angle, columella/infratip lobule ratio, and an established method of assessing tip projection were subjected to statistical analysis by 2-tailed t test and analysis of variance testing. RESULTS: Simulated and actual measurements of columella tip angle were found to be significantly different (P = .021). The set of measurements taken from computer-simulated images at the nasolabial angle (P = .301), nasofrontal angle (P = .471), columellar/infratip lobule ratio (P = .402), and tip projection ratio (P = .547) were not statistically different from the respective measurements recorded from the 6-month follow-up images. CONCLUSIONS: No significant difference was found between the measurements recorded from computer-simulated images and those recorded from 6-month postoperative photographs in 4 of the 5 features of the facial profile studied. The accuracy and predictive value of computer-simulated images is demonstrated and quantified for the first time.</ab>
<no>JID: 8000029; 2006/12/05 [received]; 2007/04/09 [revised]; 2007/04/15 [accepted]; 2008/03/19 [aheadofprint]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1532-818X; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Division of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Florida School of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32606, USA. robert.adelson@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18439946; S0196-0709(07)00050-6 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.amjoto.2007.04.008</do>
<wp>20080319</wp>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18439946</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1757</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<t1>Integrity of craniofacial plating systems after multiple sterilization procedures</t1>
<jf>Journal of oral and maxillofacial surgery : official journal of the American Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons</jf>
<jo>J.Oral Maxillofac.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>65</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>940</sp>
<op>944</op>
<k1>Bone Plates</k1>
<k1>Bone Screws</k1>
<k1>Equipment Reuse/standards</k1>
<k1>Materials Testing</k1>
<k1>Reconstructive Surgical Procedures/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Sterilization/methods</k1>
<k1>Titanium</k1>
<ab>PURPOSE: To determine the effect of multiple autoclave sterilization cycles on the integrity of titanium plates and screws used in craniofacial reconstruction. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Torque to fracture was evaluated for 36 titanium 6AL-4V (Ti 6/4) screws divided evenly into 3 groups and tested as machined (control), after 10 cycles of autoclaving or after 50 cycles of autoclaving. Sterilization was carried out by autoclaving for 15 minutes followed by 8 minutes of drying at 270 degrees to 272 degrees F. The maximum torque attained before fracture was recorded. Rotating beam specimens were crafted from single lots of Ti 6/4, commercially pure titanium grade 4 (CP4) and commercially pure titanium grade 2 (CP2), and then subjected to testing in a standard rotating beam device as machined (control), after 10 cycles of autoclaving or after 50 cycles of autoclaving. The cycles required to fracture the specimen at a given applied stress were recorded for each material and for the number of autoclavings carried out before testing. RESULTS: Although there was a trend toward decreased strength and increased ability to fracture with increased number of autoclave cycles, this did not reach statistical significance. Torque to fracture testing for 7 mm Ti 6/4 screws showed no significant difference in the maximum torque reached before fracture between controls, those screws that had been autoclaved 10 times (P &amp;lt; .500 +/- 5.70) and those that had been autoclaved 50 times (P &amp;lt; .398 +/- 4.08). Rotating beam specimens of Ti 6/4, CP4, and CP2 showed no significant difference in cycles to fracture regardless of the number of sterilization cycles to which the material was subjected. CONCLUSIONS: Repeated cycles of autoclaving had no significant effect on the integrity of titanium plates and screws routinely used in craniofacial surgery.</ab>
<no>JID: 8206428; 7440-32-6 (Titanium); 2005/11/13 [received]; 2005/12/16 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0278-2391; 0278-2391</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Division Chief, Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA. robert.adelson@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17448845; S0278-2391(06)01391-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; AIM; D; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.joms.2005.12.059</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17448845</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1765</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Miles,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Hoblitt,S. L.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<t1>Metastatic breast cancer of the oral cavity</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jul-Aug</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>279</sp>
<op>281</op>
<k1>Adenocarcinoma/drug therapy/secondary/surgery</k1>
<k1>Biopsy, Fine-Needle</k1>
<k1>Breast Neoplasms/pathology</k1>
<k1>Chemotherapy, Adjuvant</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Immunohistochemistry</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/drug therapy/secondary/surgery</k1>
<k1>Palliative Care</k1>
<k1>Postmenopause</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To present a rare case of breast carcinoma initially presenting as an oral cavity mass. STUDY DESIGN: Case report with review of the literature. RESULTS: A case is presented of a postmenopausal woman with a remote history of treated breast carcinoma who was declared disease-free 2 years before presentation. She presented with an enlarging vestibule mass consistent with metastatic breast carcinoma. Subsequent investigations revealed widely metastatic disease for which the patient was referred for palliative chemotherapy. CONCLUSIONS: Metastatic disease to the oral cavity represents only 1% of all oral cavity malignancies. A high index of clinical suspicion is necessary when evaluating patients with a history of non-head and neck carcinoma.</ab>
<no>LR: 20070724; JID: 8000029; RF: 7; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0196-0709; 0196-0709</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15991097; S0196070905000104 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15991097</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1758</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Verret,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Shen,Y.</a1>
<t1>Liposarcoma of the tongue: case report and review of the literature</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>11</is>
<sp>749</sp>
<op>751</op>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Liposarcoma/diagnosis/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/diagnosis/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>Liposarcoma is the most common soft-tissue malignancy in adults, but the appearance of a liposarcoma in the head and neck region is distinctly unusual. Intraoral liposarcomas represent a particularly interesting subset of this tumor in that (1) they are exceedingly rare and (2) affected patients tend to have a better prognosis than do patients with a similar lesion located elsewhere in the head and neck. An understanding of the histologic subtypes and corresponding clinical behavior of liposarcomas will assist physicians in appropriately managing these patients. Most of these tumors can be effectively treated with conservative surgery. We report the rare case of a well-differentiated liposarcoma arising in the tongue of a 55-year-old man. We also discuss the typical pathologic findings in these malignancies and review the diagnosis, associated controversies, management, and prognosis.</ab>
<no>JID: 7701817; RF: 21; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. robert.adelson@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 17168154</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>17168154</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1767</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<t1>Metastatic head and neck carcinoma to a percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy site</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>339</sp>
<op>343</op>
<k1>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell/secondary</k1>
<k1>Enteral Nutrition/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Fatal Outcome</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Gastroscopy</k1>
<k1>Gastrostomy/instrumentation</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Liver Neoplasms/secondary</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Muscle Neoplasms/secondary</k1>
<k1>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local/pathology</k1>
<k1>Rectus Abdominis/pathology</k1>
<k1>Stomach Neoplasms/secondary</k1>
<k1>Tongue Neoplasms/pathology</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: Percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG) tube placement is a safe and widely accepted alternate route for enteral alimentation in the head and neck cancer patient population. Cancer metastatic to a PEG tube exit site is a rare but serious complication of this procedure. We sought to determine the route of spread responsible for PEG site metastases such that we may prevent further occurrences of this highly morbid condition. We also report a case of PEG site metastasis at our institution. METHODS: We performed a MEDLINE search for the years 1962 to 2002 and conducted a review of the literature. In the case at our institution, a 63-year-old man was referred to our institution with recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the right base of tongue; he also had a 1.5-cm left apical lung nodule. He underwent PEG tube placement at the time of staging panendoscopy. Six months after the original tube placement, he had an ulcerated mass develop at the PEG site; biopsy of the mass revealed squamous cell carcinoma histologically identical to the base of tongue tumor. He also had recurrent lung cancer and four hepatic lesions develop. RESULTS: In our MEDLINE search, of the five patients diagnosed with PEG site disease &amp;gt;10 months after PEG placement, all five (100%) had synchronous distant metastatic disease. In the group of patients diagnosed with PEG site metastases &amp;lt; or =10 months after PEG placement, only four (24%) of 17 had synchronous distant metastatic disease. All patients underwent PEG placement by means of the &amp;quot;pull&amp;quot; technique. Direct implantation with a variable-sized initial tumor burden can explain all cases of PEG site metastasis. The presence of distant metastases is representative of the natural history of advanced head and neck malignancies. Smaller initial tumor implants present later than would larger initial tumor burdens, when the patient is more likely to have distant metastatic disease. In the case at our institution, the patient did not respond to treatment for his hepatic and PEG site metastases and his lung cancer, and he died 4 months after detection of the PEG site metastasis. CONCLUSIONS: PEG site metastases are iatrogenic complications of PEG tube placement in patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the upper aerodigestive tract. The use of laparoscopic, open, or the &amp;quot;push&amp;quot; technique of PEG tube placement in patients with head and neck cancer may prevent direct implantation of malignant cells into an enteral access site.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061005; JID: 8902541; RF: 17; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1043-3074; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery at the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center in Dallas, Texas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15712297</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.20159</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15712297</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1754</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Karimi,K.</a1>
<a1>Herrero,N.</a1>
<t1>Isolated congenital absence of the left lower lateral cartilage</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>138</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>793</sp>
<op>794</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nasal Cavity/abnormalities</k1>
<k1>Nasal Septum/abnormalities</k1>
<k1>Rhinoplasty</k1>
<no>JID: 8508176; 2008/02/10 [received]; 2008/02/26 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Division of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Department of Otolaryngology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32606, USA. robert.adelson@ent.ufl.edu</ad>
<an>PMID: 18503858; S0194-5998(08)00176-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2008.02.018</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18503858</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1775</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Marple,B. F.</a1>
<t1>Fungal rhinosinusitis</t1>
<yr>2006</yr>
<sp>417</sp>
<op>417-428</op>
<k1>Head -- surgery</k1>
<k1>Neck -- surgery</k1>
<k1>Otorhinolaryngologic Diseases -- surgery</k1>
<no>[edited by] Byron J. Bailey, Jonas T. Johnson, Shawn D. Newlands ; illustrated by Victoria J. Forbes, Anthony Pazos, and Christine Gralapp. : [edited by] Byron J. Bailey, Jonas T. Johnson, Shawn D. Newlands ; illustrated by Victoria J. Forbes, Anthony Pazos, and Christine Gralapp.; 2 v. : ill. ; 28 cm.; Alternate title: Head and neck surgery--otolaryngology; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Bailey,Byron J.</a2><a2> Johnson,Jonas T.</a2><a2>Newlands,Shawn D.</a2>
<t2>Head &amp;amp; neck surgery--otolaryngology</t2>
<ed>4</ed>
<pb>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</pb>
<pp>Philadelphia</pp>
<sn>0781755611 (alk. paper)</sn>
<cn>WV168.H432 2006 (Jacksonville UFHSCL Borland)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1774</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Marple,B. F.</a1>
<t1>Fungal diseases of the frontal sinus</t1>
<yr>2005</yr>
<sp>101</sp>
<op>101-114</op>
<no>ID: 318299024</no>
<a2>Draf,Wolfgang</a2><a2> Kountakis,Stilianos</a2><a2>Senior,Brent</a2>
<t2>The Frontal Sinus</t2>
<pb>Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg</pb>
<pp>[New York]</pp>
<sn>9783540211433 3540211438 9783540276074 3540276076</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1766</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Marple,B. F.</a1>
<t1>Fungal rhinosinusitis: state-of-the-art diagnosis and treatment</t1>
<jf>The Journal of otolaryngology</jf>
<jo>J.Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>34 Suppl 1</vo>
<sp>S18</sp>
<op>23</op>
<k1>Acute Disease</k1>
<k1>Debridement</k1>
<k1>Granuloma/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mycoses/diagnosis/therapy</k1>
<k1>Rhinitis/diagnosis/microbiology/surgery/therapy</k1>
<k1>Sinusitis/diagnosis/microbiology/surgery/therapy</k1>
<ab>The past 30 years has been witness to a period of tremendous growth and innovation within the field of rhinology, facilitating a better understanding and improved management techniques for a variety of local and systemic conditions manifesting within the nose and paranasal sinuses. Of these disease states, the spectrum of conditions considered under the rubric of fungal rhinosinusitis best exemplifies modern rhinology&amp;#39;s position as a truly multidisciplinary specialty. We review the classification of the various forms of fungal rhinosinusitis and their clinical presentations, radiologic findings, and treatment options.</ab>
<no>LR: 20051116; JID: 7610513; RF: 38; ppublish</no>
<pp>Canada</pp>
<sn>0381-6605; 0381-6605</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas, 5323 Harry Hines Blvd, Dallas, TX 75390-9035, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16089236</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16089236</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1773</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Marple,B. F.</a1>
<t1>Orbital complications of frontal sinusitis</t1>
<yr>2005</yr>
<sp>59</sp>
<op>59-66</op>
<no>ID: 318299024</no>
<a2>Draf,Wolfgang</a2><a2> Kountakis,Stilianos</a2><a2>Senior,Brent</a2>
<t2>The Frontal Sinus</t2>
<pb>Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg</pb>
<pp>[New York]</pp>
<sn>9783540211433 3540211438 9783540276074 3540276076</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1762</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Murray,A. D.</a1>
<t1>Minimally invasive transoral catheter-assisted drainage of a danger-space infection</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>84</vo>
<is>12</is>
<sp>785</sp>
<op>786</op>
<k1>Catheterization</k1>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Drainage/methods</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Retropharyngeal Abscess/therapy</k1>
<k1>Streptococcal Infections/therapy</k1>
<k1>Streptococcus pyogenes</k1>
<ab>We report the case of a 3-year-old boy who was brought to the emergency department for evaluation of a prolonged upper respiratory infection and diminished neck movement. Computed tomography identified a unilocular abscess extending from the level of C2 inferiorly to the diaphragm at the level of the T9 vertebral body. We successfully treated this transcervical, transthoracic infection surgically via a transoral approach to the retropharyngeal abscess combined with catheter drainage and irrigation of the abscess cavity at a depth of 13 cm. At 25 months of follow-up, the patient exhibited no evidence of recurrent disease or postsurgical complications. In this article, we describe our minimally invasive technique for managing unusual deep-space neck infections in children.</ab>
<no>JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Division of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Department of Otolaryngology, University of Miami Fla. School of Medicine, 1504 Bay Rd., #1014, Miami Beach, FL 33139, USA. robertadelson@mac.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 16408558</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16408558</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1770</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Samy,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Lindberg,G.</a1>
<t1>T-cell prolymphocytic leukemia presenting as an ear canal mass</t1>
<jf>Otology &amp; neurotology : official publication of the American Otological Society, American Neurotology Society [and] European Academy of Otology and Neurotology</jf>
<jo>Otol.Neurotol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1006</sp>
<op>1008</op>
<k1>Biopsy, Needle</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Ear Canal/pathology/radiography</k1>
<k1>Fatal Outcome</k1>
<k1>Flow Cytometry</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss/etiology</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Leukemia, T-Cell/diagnosis/drug therapy/pathology</k1>
<k1>Leukocyte Count</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: We discuss the first reported case of a chronic leukemia involving the external auditory canal. STUDY DESIGN: Case report and review of the literature (Medline, 1962-2003). METHODS AND RESULTS: An adult man in good health came to receive medical attention because of a sensation of aural fullness. Radiologic and physical examination demonstrated an ovoid soft tissue mass of the lateral external auditory canal that, after biopsy and flow cytometry studies, was found to be T-cell prolymphocytic leukemia. The patient presented with minimal disease in a highly symptomatic location, allowing early initiation of therapy and extending his life by nearly four times the average life expectancy for this aggressive chronic leukemia. CONCLUSION: Lymphomas of the external auditory canal are extremely rare neoplasms. Only a few cases have previously been reported, and all of the previous reports involve acute leukemias. This report indicates that chronic leukemias can present with otologic manifestations such as an external auditory canal mass.</ab>
<no>JID: 100961504; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1531-7129; 1531-7129</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery, Division of Otology/Neurotology/Skull Base Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas 75390, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15547434; 00129492-200411000-00024 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15547434</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1772</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Vories,A.</a1>
<t1>Spontaneous cervical haematoma resulting from intrathoracic pathology</t1>
<jf>The Journal of laryngology and otology</jf>
<jo>J.Laryngol.Otol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>118</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>471</sp>
<op>473</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hematoma/epidemiology/etiology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mammary Arteries/surgery</k1>
<k1>Marfan Syndrome/complications</k1>
<k1>Neck/surgery</k1>
<k1>Neurofibromatosis 1/complications</k1>
<k1>Sternum/surgery</k1>
<ab>Spontaneous cervical haematomas are rare occurrences for which a wide variety of aetiologies have been reported. Although the pathogenesis of this condition can be quite diverse, all known cases have emanated from a cervical source. The authors report the first case of a spontaneous cervical haematoma arising from an intrathoracic source. A case review and Medline search from 1962-2003 was carried out. No prior experience with intrathoracic sources for cervical haematomas has previously been reported. Transcervical haematoma evacuation confirmed the intrathoracic origin and a median sternotomy was required to gain control of this haemorrhage. Thoracic sources should be considered in the differential diagnosis of a spontaneous cervical haematoma. Preparations for a combined procedure with a thoracic surgeon can be predicted pre-operatively based on imaging studies.</ab>
<no>LR: 20041117; JID: 8706896; ppublish</no>
<pp>England</pp>
<sn>0022-2151; 0022-2151</sn>
<ad>Department of Otorlaryngology - Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA. rdadelson@mac.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 15285870</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1258/002221504323219644</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15285870</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1760</id>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Zito,J.</a1>
<a1>Romaguera,R. L.</a1>
<t1>Invasive fungal adenoiditis</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>134</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>713</sp>
<op>714</op>
<k1>Adenoids/microbiology</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Antifungal Agents/therapeutic use</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Endoscopy</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Mucor/isolation &amp; purification</k1>
<k1>Mucormycosis/diagnosis/microbiology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Otorhinolaryngologic Surgical Procedures/methods</k1>
<k1>Severity of Illness Index</k1>
<k1>Sinusitis/diagnosis/microbiology/therapy</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<no>LR: 20060627; JID: 8508176; 0 (Antifungal Agents); EIN: Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2006 Jun;134(6):1065; 2005/11/09 [received]; 2005/12/15 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Miami School of Medicine, FL, USA. robertadelson@mac.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 16564404; S0194-5998(05)02266-7 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2005.12.018</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16564404</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1761</id>
<a1>Cochran,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Zhou,C. Q.</a1>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>An innovative method of facilitating ranula excision with methylene blue injection</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>159, 163</sp>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Injections, Intralesional</k1>
<k1>Methylene Blue/administration &amp; dosage</k1>
<k1>Ranula/diagnosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Staining and Labeling/methods</k1>
<no>JID: 7701817; 61-73-4 (Methylene Blue); ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16615596</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16615596</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1753</id>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Sabatini,P. R.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of closed reduction alone versus primary open repair of acute nasoseptal fractures</t1>
<jf>Journal of otolaryngology - head &amp; neck surgery = Le Journal d&#39;oto-rhino-laryngologie et de chirurgie cervico-faciale</jf>
<jo>J.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Aug</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>502</sp>
<op>506</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Fracture Fixation/methods</k1>
<k1>Fractures, Bone/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nasal Bone/injuries/surgery</k1>
<k1>Nasal Septum/injuries/surgery</k1>
<k1>Prospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: Nasoseptal injuries have traditionally been treated via closed reduction. Historically, the high incidence of postreduction deformities has led some surgeons to consider alternative approaches to obtain superior results. Here we compare simple closed reduction versus primary open repair of the nasoseptal fracture. STUDY DESIGN: This was a prospective study of 40 consecutive patients treated with simple closed reduction of their combined nasal bone and septal fracture versus 40 patients treated with closed reduction of their nasal bone fracture and open treatment of the septum. Group outcomes were then compared. RESULTS: In the closed reduction group, 60% had significant postoperative septal deviation, whereas only 12.5% suffered from residual septal deformity in the open group. This resulted in a statistically significant reduction (p &amp;lt; .01) of patients requiring a second operation to formally address the septum. CONCLUSION: By addressing the septum through an open approach, a statistically significant reduction in the number of patients requiring revision rhinoplasty was achieved.</ab>
<no>JID: 101479544; ppublish</no>
<pp>Canada</pp>
<sn>1916-0216</sn>
<ad>Otolaryngology and Facial Plastic Surgery Associates, Fort Worth, Texas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19128583</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Comparative Study; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19128583</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1764</id>
<a1>DeFatta,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Verret,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Gomez,A.</a1>
<a1>Myers,L. L.</a1>
<t1>Kaposiform hemangioendothelioma: case report and literature review</t1>
<jf>The Laryngoscope</jf>
<jo>Laryngoscope</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>115</vo>
<is>10</is>
<sp>1789</sp>
<op>1792</op>
<k1>Child, Preschool</k1>
<k1>Gadolinium/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Hemangioendothelioma/diagnosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Mouth Neoplasms/diagnosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Radiopharmaceuticals/diagnostic use</k1>
<k1>Sarcoma/diagnosis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Surgery, Oral/methods</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>We report the identification of a kaposiform hemangioendothelioma (KH) in the oropharynx of a 3-year-old boy. This is a rare endothelial-derived spindle cell neoplasm affecting children and early adolescents with features common to capillary hemangioma and Kaposi sarcoma. Nine cases of head and neck KH have been reported, this being the first in the otolaryngology literature. Our patient underwent wide local excision and has remained tumor free for over 1 year. KH should be considered in the differential diagnosis of a vascular lesion demonstrating unexpected behavior from that of a hemangioma.</ab>
<no>JID: 8607378; 0 (Radiopharmaceuticals); 7440-54-2 (Gadolinium); RF: 14; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0023-852X; 0023-852X</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Children&#39;s Medical Center, Dallas, 75390, USA. rdefat@parknet.pmh.org</ad>
<an>PMID: 16222196; 00005537-200510000-00014 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; Review; IM</sf>
<do>10.1097/01.mlg.0000176539.94515.75</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16222196</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1769</id>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R.</a1>
<t1>Use of the endoscopic forehead-lift to improve brow position in persistent facial paralysis</t1>
<jf>Archives of facial plastic surgery : official publication for the American Academy of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Inc.and the International Federation of Facial Plastic Surgery Societies</jf>
<jo>Arch.Facial Plast.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Jan-Feb</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>51</sp>
<op>54</op>
<k1>Endoscopy</k1>
<k1>Eyebrows</k1>
<k1>Facial Paralysis/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Forehead</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Rhytidoplasty/methods</k1>
<ab>Traditionally, the asymmetrical brow in facial paralysis has been treated with open procedures. There are few data that support the use of endoscopic procedures to treat patients with facial palsy or paralysis. We sought to evaluate a single surgeon&amp;#39;s experience with the use of endoscopic forehead-lifts to treat asymmetrical brow positioning resulting from facial nerve disorders. All cases involving patients who underwent endoscopic brow-lifts by the senior author (Y.D.) from 1997 through 2003 with a minimum follow-up of 12 months were retrospectively reviewed. Demographic data were collected, and patient satisfaction was determined from postoperative interviews conducted at follow-up visits. Standard photographs were used to measure the degree of preoperative and postoperative brow asymmetry. A total of 31 cases were available for review. The average age of our patient population was 47 years (age range, 22-76 years), with a male-female ratio of almost 1.5:1. Twenty-three patients had a complete paralysis, and 8 patients had a palsy. The average preoperative difference in height at the desired apex of brow was 5.9 mm, with a range of 3.0 to 9.0 mm. The average postoperative difference (as measured at 12 months) in brow position was only 1.3 mm, with a range of 0 to 3 mm. Adjunctive periorbital procedures were performed in the majority of patients (90%) at the time of endoscopic brow-lifting. All patients felt that their brow position was much improved after surgery. No major complications were encountered. A single patient underwent a secondary open direct browpexy to optimize his result. Endoscopic brow-lifting may be associated with favorable outcomes in the majority of patients with facial nerve palsy or paralysis. Performing concurrent adjunctive periorbital procedures as deemed necessary to optimize lower eyelid position, eyelid closure, and upper eyelid symmetry appears to be safe and reliable.</ab>
<no>JID: 100883500; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1521-2491; 1521-2491</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, The University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA. yducic@sbcglobal.net</ad>
<an>PMID: 15655175; 7/1/51 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archfaci.7.1.51</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15655175</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1752</id>
<a1>Imola,M. J.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>The secondary correction of post-traumatic craniofacial deformities</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>139</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>654</sp>
<op>660</op>
<k1>Adolescent</k1>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Facial Asymmetry/etiology/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Facial Bones/injuries/pathology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Follow-Up Studies</k1>
<k1>Fracture Fixation, Internal</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Reconstructive Surgical Procedures</k1>
<k1>Recovery of Function</k1>
<k1>Reoperation</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Skull Fractures/etiology/pathology/surgery</k1>
<k1>Time Factors</k1>
<k1>Treatment Outcome</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE: To analyze the aesthetic and functional outcomes in a large series of patients who underwent secondary correction of post-traumatic craniofacial deformities (PTCD) and to highlight the underlying principles and formulate treatment guidelines. METHODS: A single surgeon&amp;#39;s retrospective case series of 57 patients who underwent correction of PTCD. OUTCOME MEASURES: Evaluation by multiple surgeons who assessed aesthetic results and functional parameters after secondary correction of PTCD. RESULTS: A good to excellent aesthetic outcome was achieved in the majority of patients. Traumatic telecanthus, enophthalmos, and occlusal deformity were the deformities most refractory to secondary correction. Aesthetic results were adversely affected by the severity and number of pre-existing abnormalities and by the presence of established deformities (beyond 6 to 12 months). CONCLUSIONS: The basic principles of treatment include an initial major osseous reconstructive surgery to restore an anatomically correct craniofacial architecture followed by selective ancillary procedures to address soft tissue deficits and functional deformities. Soft tissue deformity is the major deterrent to achieving an ideal outcome.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; 2008/04/21 [received]; 2008/06/25 [revised]; 2008/07/23 [accepted]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Colorado, Denver, CO, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 18984259; S0194-5998(08)01267-9 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2008.07.031</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18984259</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1750</id>
<a1>Karimi,K.</a1>
<a1>Jadidian,A.</a1>
<a1>Glavin,F. L.</a1>
<a1>Chhatwal,H.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Laryngeal involvement in progressive nodular histiocytosis: a case report</t1>
<jf>Archives of Otolaryngology--Head &amp; Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Arch.Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>May</fd>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>513</sp>
<op>516</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Airway Obstruction/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Histiocytosis, Non-Langerhans-Cell/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Laryngeal Diseases/pathology/radiography/surgery</k1>
<k1>Tomography, X-Ray Computed</k1>
<no>JID: 8603209; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1538-361X; 0886-4470</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, College of Medicine, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA. kiankarimi@gmail.com</ad>
<an>PMID: 20479385; 136/5/513 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; AIM; IM</sf>
<do>10.1001/archoto.2010.49</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>20479385</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1763</id>
<a1>Simons,R. L.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Rhinoplasty in male patients</t1>
<jf>Facial plastic surgery : FPS</jf>
<jo>Facial Plast.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Nov</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>240</sp>
<op>249</op>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Nose/anatomy &amp; histology</k1>
<k1>Patient Satisfaction</k1>
<k1>Rhinoplasty/methods/psychology</k1>
<k1>Sex Factors</k1>
<ab>The complexities of rhinoplasty are further emphasized when this operation is undertaken in the male patient, and a growing percentage of the rhinoplasty population comprises men. We review the senior author&amp;#39;s approach to rhinoplasty analysis, preoperative consultation, and surgical techniques that have been successfully employed for over 40 years. Specific recommendations and modifications to these techniques are discussed as they relate to the rhinoplasty operation in male patients.</ab>
<no>JID: 8405303; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0736-6825; 0736-6825</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology--Head and Neck Surgery, Division of Facial Plastic Surgery, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, Florida, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 16575702</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; D</sf>
<do>10.1055/s-2006-939503</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16575702</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1768</id>
<a1>Smith,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R.</a1>
<t1>The utility of the temporalis muscle flap for oropharyngeal, base of tongue, and nasopharyngeal reconstruction</t1>
<jf>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</jf>
<jo>Otolaryngol.Head.Neck.Surg.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>132</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>373</sp>
<op>380</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Nasopharynx/surgery</k1>
<k1>Oropharynx/surgery</k1>
<k1>Reconstructive Surgical Procedures/methods</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Surgical Flaps</k1>
<k1>Tongue/surgery</k1>
<ab>OBJECTIVE:To determine the efficacy of temporalis muscle flap reconstruction of various defects of the oropharynx, nasopharynx, and base of tongue. STUDY DESIGN:Retrospective chart review of a consecutive series of 24 patients who underwent a total of 26 temporalis flaps (2 bilateral) by the senior author (Y.D.) from September 1997 to August 2003 for reconstruction of defects of the oropharynx, nasopharynx, and base of tongue. METHODS: Variables and outcomes that were examined included defect location, size, adjunctive therapy, complications, and ability to tolerate oral intake at follow-up. RESULTS: There was no evidence of flap failure in our series of patients. There were 2 cases of minor flap loss related to early prosthetic rehabilitation. Two cases of transient frontal nerve paralysis were noted. A 30.8% rate of complication (all minor) was noted in this study. At a mean follow-up of 12 months, 54.2% of patients were tolerating a full diet, 37.5% were tolerating most of their nutrition by mouth, and 8.3% were g-tube dependent. CONCLUSION: The temporalis muscle flap represents an excellent alternative in reconstruction of otherwise difficult-to-reconstruct defects of the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and base of tongue. Donor site aesthetics are well accepted by patients with primary hydroxyapatite cement cranioplasty with or without secondary lipotransfer.</ab>
<no>JID: 8508176; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0194-5998; 0194-5998</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15746846; S0194599804020212 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1016/j.otohns.2004.09.140</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15746846</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1751</id>
<a1>Smith,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Ducic,Y.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<t1>Temporalis muscle flap for reconstruction of skull base defects</t1>
<jf>Head &amp; neck</jf>
<jo>Head Neck</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>Feb</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>199</sp>
<op>203</op>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Postoperative Complications</k1>
<k1>Reconstructive Surgical Procedures</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>Skull Base/surgery</k1>
<k1>Skull Base Neoplasms/surgery</k1>
<k1>Surgical Flaps</k1>
<k1>Temporal Muscle/surgery</k1>
<ab>BACKGROUND: The temporalis muscle flap (TMF) is a valuable reconstructive technique utilized in a variety of challenging defects. However, its use for repair of skull base defects is less commonly reported. METHODS: A retrospective chart review was conducted for 35 patients who underwent reconstruction of skull base defects between March 1999 and July 2006 at a tertiary referral hospital. Patients with skull base defects after trauma or extirpative surgery underwent reconstruction with a TMF. The measured outcomes were as follows: defect size/location, need for additional flaps, bone necrosis, hardware exposure, dehiscence, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) leak, and meningitis. RESULTS: Forty-two patients underwent reconstruction with a TMF, and 35/42 patient records were available for review. No flap failures, 1 transient CSF leak, 3 hardware exposures distant from the temporalis recipient site, and 3 hydroxyapatite cement infections or foreign body reaction were observed. CONCLUSION: The TMF represents a versatile reconstructive technique employed with minimal morbidity and a low complication rate to repair defects of the skull base.</ab>
<no>CI: Copyright 2009; JID: 8902541; ppublish</no>
<pb>Wiley Periodicals, Inc</pb>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>1097-0347; 1043-3074</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19557763</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1002/hed.21170</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19557763</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1759</id>
<a1>Verret,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>Defatta,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Asymmetric sensorineural hearing loss evaluation with T2 FSE-MRI in a public hospital</t1>
<jf>Acta Oto-Laryngologica</jf>
<jo>Acta Otolaryngol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>Jul</fd>
<vo>126</vo>
<is>7</is>
<sp>705</sp>
<op>707</op>
<k1>Adult</k1>
<k1>Aged</k1>
<k1>Aged, 80 and over</k1>
<k1>Echo-Planar Imaging/economics</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural/diagnosis/etiology</k1>
<k1>Hospitals, County/economics</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Male</k1>
<k1>Middle Aged</k1>
<k1>Retrocochlear Diseases/diagnosis</k1>
<k1>Retrospective Studies</k1>
<k1>United States</k1>
<ab>CONCLUSIONS: T2-weighted fast-spin echo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can be an economically beneficial protocol for screening patients with asymmetric sensorineural hearing loss without other neurologic findings in a public hospital population. OBJECTIVE: The goal of this study was to determine if fast spin echo T2 MRI is similar to gadolinium-enhanced MRI in evaluating asymmetric sensorineural hearing loss in a county hospital population. PATIENTS AND METHODS: This was a retrospective chart review of all outpatients seen at a public hospital, comprising patients with no other cranial nerve findings who underwent gadolinium-enhanced MRI of the internal auditory canal and brain between January 2002 and September 2003. Patients with &amp;gt;15 dB difference in hearing at one frequency or 10 dB hearing difference at two frequencies underwent gadolinium-enhanced MRI scan with FSE T2 sequence as part of the examination protocol. RESULTS: A total of 146 patients were identified who met all the inclusion criteria for the study. Of the 146 MRI scans performed, abnormalities were seen on 71 of them, the majority of which were inconsequential. No acoustic neuromas were identified in our study population. Cost savings of over 100,000 dollars would have been realized if only T2 FSE protocols had been used.</ab>
<no>JID: 0370354; ppublish</no>
<pp>Norway</pp>
<sn>0001-6489; 0001-6489</sn>
<ad>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX 75390, USA. djverret@sbcglobal.net</ad>
<an>PMID: 16803708; L3U17660248K2470 [pii]</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; IM</sf>
<do>10.1080/00016480500504184</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>16803708</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>1771</id>
<a1>Verret,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Adelson,R. T.</a1>
<a1>McClay,J.</a1>
<t1>Airway foreign body</t1>
<jf>Ear, nose, &amp; throat journal</jf>
<jo>Ear Nose Throat J.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>9</is>
<sp>605</sp>
<op>606</op>
<k1>Airway Obstruction/etiology/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Bronchoscopy</k1>
<k1>Diagnosis, Differential</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Foreign Bodies/complications/radiography/therapy</k1>
<k1>Humans</k1>
<k1>Infant</k1>
<no>JID: 7701817; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0145-5613; 0145-5613</sn>
<ad>Division of Pediatric Otolaryngology, Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 15529641</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Case Reports; Journal Article; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>15529641</pmid></reference></refworks>
