<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2308</id>
<a1>Barker,K. R.</a1>
<a1>Pederson,Gary A.</a1>
<a1>Windham,Gary L.</a1>
<t1>Plant and nematode interactions</t1>
<yr>1998</yr>
<sp>771</sp>
<k1>Nematode plant relationships</k1>
<k1>Plant nematodes</k1>
<no>coeditors, Kenneth R. Barker, Gary A. Pederson, Gary L. Windham. : coeditors, Kenneth R. Barker, Gary A. Pederson, Gary L. Windham.; Alternate title: Plant nematode interactions; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<t2>Agronomy ; no. 36</t2>
<pb>Crop Science Society of America; Soil Science Society of America</pb>
<pp>Madison, Wisc. : American Society of Agronomy</pp>
<cn>SB998.N4.P43 1998 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB998.N4P43 1998 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred); SB998.N4P43 1998 (IFAS CENTERS Ft. Pierce)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3519</id>
<a1>Chellemi,D. O.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Secker,I.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Adaptation of soil solarization to the integrated management of soilborne pests of tomato under humid conditions</t1>
<jf>Phytopathology</jf>
<jo>Phytopathology</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>87</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>250</sp>
<op>258</op>
<ab>ABSTRACT Soil solarization was shown to be cost effective, compatible with other pest management tactics, readily integrated into standard production systems, and a valid alternative to preplant fumigation with methyl bromide under the tested conditions. Solarization using clear, photoselective, or gas-impermeable plastic was evaluated in combination with metham sodium, 1,3-dichloropropene + chloropicrin, methyl bromide + chloropicrin, pebulate, or cabbage residue. Strip solarization, applied to 20-cm-high, 0.9-m-wide beds, was conducted to achieve compatibility with standard production practices and resulted in soil temperatures 2 to 4 degrees C above those temperatures resulting when using conventional flatbed solarization. Soil temperatures were 1 to 2 degrees C higher at the edges of the raised beds, eliminating any border effects associated with solarization. Following a 40- to 55-day solarization period, the plastic was painted white and used as a production mulch for a subsequent tomato crop. The incidence of Southern blight and the density of Paratrichodorus minor and Criconemella spp. were lower (P &amp;lt; 0.05) in solarized plots. No differences (P &amp;lt; 0.05) in the incidence of Fusarium wilt and the density of nutsedge and Helicotylenchus spp. were observed between plots receiving solarization and plots fumigated with a mixture of methyl bromide + chloropicrin. The severity of root galling was lower (P &amp;lt; 0.05) when soil solarization was combined with 1,3-dichloropropene + chloropicrin (16.2 + 3.4 g/m(2)) and a gas-impermeable film. The incidence of bacterial wilt was not affected by soil treatments. Marketable yields in plots using various combinations of soil solarization and other tactics were similar (P &amp;lt; 0.05) to yields obtained in plots fumigated with methyl bromide + chloropicrin. The results were validated in several large scale field experiments conducted by commercial growers.</ab>
<no>JID: 9427222; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0031-949X; 0031-949X</sn>
<an>PMID: 18945167</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<do>10.1094/PHYTO.1997.87.3.250</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>18945167</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3533</id>
<a1>Chellemi,D. O.</a1>
<a1>Olson,S. M.</a1>
<a1>Scott,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Reduction of phytoparasitic nematodes on tomato by soil solarization and genotype</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>4 Suppl</is>
<sp>800</sp>
<op>805</op>
<ab>The effects of soil solarization and tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum) genotype on populations of plant-parasitic nematodes and bacterial wilt were examined in North Florida. Maximum soil temperatures achieved under solarization treatments using a photoselective polyethylene mulch were 49.5, 46, and 40.5 C at depths of 5, 15, and 25 cm, respectively. Soil solarization reduced (P &amp;lt; 0.05) populations of Paratrichodorus minor, Rotylenchulus reniformis, and Criconemella spp. 85 days after transplanting on the cultivar Solar Set. Soil solarization reduced (P &amp;lt; 0.10) populations of P. minor, R. reniformis, and Criconemella spp. on the breeding line Fla. 7421. Reductions of P. minor and Criconemella spp. on Solar Set and Fla. 7421 were similar to those achieved by fumigation with a 67:33 mixture of methyl bromide and chloropicrin (448 kg/ha). Fla. 7421 reduced (P &amp;lt; 0.10) populations of R. reniformis compared with Solar Set. Neither soil solarization nor fumigation reduced the incidence of bacterial wilt on the susceptible cultivar Solar Set. This study demonstrates the ability of soil solarization to provide season-long control of plant-parasitic nematodes of tomato under a climatic regime characterized by periods of abundant rainfall and extended cloud cover.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619444; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279843</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279843</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619444</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3530</id>
<a1>Chen,S.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Kimbrough,J. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Fungi Associated with Females and Cysts of Heterodera glycines in a Florida Soybean Field</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>296</sp>
<op>303</op>
<ab>Fungal colonization was determined for females and cysts of Heterodera glycines on soybean roots or in rhizosphere soil from a Florida soybean field. A total of 1,620 females and cysts were examined in 1991, and 1,303 were examined in 1992. More than 35 species of fungi were isolated from females and cysts. The frequency of fungi colonizing white and yellow females was low, but a high frequency of fungi was encountered in brown cysts, which increased with time of exposure of the cysts to the soil. No single fungal species predominated in the nematode females or cysts in this field. Rarely was a female or cyst colonized by more than one fungus. The common fungi isolated from the females and cysts were Neocosmospora vasinfecta, Fusarium solani, Fusarium oxysporum, Dictyochaeta coffeae, Dictyochaeta heteroderae, Pyrenochaeta terrestris, Exophiala pisciphila, Gliocladium catenulatum, Stagonospora heteroderae, and a black yeast-like fungus. The communities of common fungal species isolated from cysts in several regions in the southeastern United States appear to be similar.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619503; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279895</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279895</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619503</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3522</id>
<a1>Chen,Z. X.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<a1>Hewlett,T. E.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of Meloidogyne arenaria Race 1 by Soil Application of Endospores of Pasteuria penetrans</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>159</sp>
<op>168</op>
<ab>The potential of Pasteuria penetrans for suppressing Meloidogyne arenaria race 1 on peanut (Arachis hypogaea) was tested over a 2-year period in a field microplot experiment. Endospores of P. penetrans were mass-produced on M. arenaria race 1 infecting tomato plants. Endospores were inoculated in the first year only at rates of 0, 1,000, 3,000, 10,000, and 100,000 endospores/g of soil, respectively, into the top 20 cm of microplots that were previously infested with M. arenaria race 1. One peanut seedling was planted in each microplot. In the first year, root gall indices and pod galls per microplot were significantly reduced by 60% and 95% for 100,000 endospores/g of soil, and 20% and 65% for 10,000 endospores/g of soil, respectively. Final densities of second-stage juveniles (J2) in soil were not significantly different among the treatments. The number of endospores attached to J2 and percentage of J2 with attached endospores significantly increased with increasing endospore inoculation levels. Pasteuria penetrans significantly reduced the densities of J2 that overwintered. In the second year, root and pod gall indices, respectively, were significantly reduced by 81% and 90% for 100,000 endospores/g of soil, and by 61% and 82% of 10,000 endospores/g of soil. Pod yields were significantly increased by 94% for 100,000 and by 57% for 10,000 endospores/g of soil, respectively. The effect of P. penetrans on final densities of J2 in soil was not significant. Regression analyses verified the role of P. penetrans in the suppression of M. arenaria. The minimum number of endospores required for significantly suppressing M. arenaria race 1 on peanut was 10,000 endospores/g of soil.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619680; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277131</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277131</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619680</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3518</id>
<a1>Chen,Z. X.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Mitchell,D. J.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Hewlett,T. E.</a1>
<t1>Suppression Mechanisms of Meloidogyne arenaria Race 1 by Pasteuria penetrans</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>8</op>
<ab>The biological control of Meloidogyne arenaria on peanut (Arachis hypogaea) by Pasteuria penetrans was evaluated using a six x six factorial experiment in field microplots over 2 years. The main factors were six inoculum levels of second-stage juveniles (J2) of M. arenaria race 1 (0, 40, 200, 1,000, 5,000, and 25,000 J2/microplot, except that the highest level was 20,000 J2/microplot in 1995) and six infestation levels of P. penetrans as percentages of J2 with endospores attached (0, 20, 40, 60, 80, and 100%). The results were similar in 1994 and 1995. Numbers of eggs per root system, J2 per 100 cm(3) soil at harvest, root galls, and pod galls increased with increasing nematode inoculum levels and decreased with increasing P. penetrans infestation levels (P  0.05). There were no statistical interaction effects between the inoculum levels of J2 and the infestation levels of P. penetrans (P &amp;gt; 0.05). When the infestation level was increased by 10%, the number of eggs per root system, root galls, and pod galls decreased 7.8% to 9.4%, 7.0% to 8.5%, and 8.0% to 8.7% in 1994 and 1995, respectively, whereas J2 per 100 cm(3) soil decreased 8.8% in 1995 (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05). The initial infestation level of P. penetrans contributed 81% to 95% of the total suppression of pod galls, whereas the infection of J2 of the subsequent generations contributed only 5% to 19% suppression of pod galls. The major suppressive mechanism of M. arenaria race 1 by P. penetrans on peanut is the initial endospore infestation of J2 at planting.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619759; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274127</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274127</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619759</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3495</id>
<a1>Cherr,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Scholberg,J. M. S.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Mbuya,O. S.</a1>
<t1>Growth and Yield of Sweet Corn Following Green Manure in a Warm Temperate Environment on Sandy Soil</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<k1>green manure</k1>
<k1>Sweets</k1>
<k1>Corn</k1>
<k1>Crops</k1>
<k1>Summer</k1>
<k1>Winter</k1>
<k1>Rapids</k1>
<k1>Sandy soils</k1>
<k1>Fertilizing</k1>
<k1>Ear</k1>
<k1>Receiving</k1>
<k1>Rainfall</k1>
<k1>Drying</k1>
<k1>Manure</k1>
<k1>Emergence</k1>
<k1>Legumes</k1>
<k1>Leaf area index</k1>
<k1>Agronomy</k1>
<k1>Leaching</k1>
<k1>Decomposition</k1>
<k1>Uptakes</k1>
<k1>Residues</k1>
<k1>Climate</k1>
<k1>VAR</k1>
<ab>Legumes used as green manure (GMN) may provide on-farm sources of N for subsequent crops. In warm-humid climates on sandy soils, however, there is a need to evaluate effects on growth and yield of subsequent crops when GMN substitutes for chemical N fertilizer. We collected time-series data for 2years to evaluate growth and ear yield response of sweet corn (Zea mays L. var. Rugosa) in annual rotation with GMN (summer, winter or summer plus winter GMN) and supplemented with 0, 67 or 133kgchemicalNha-1. Control treatments receiving 0, 67, 133, 200 or 267kgchemicalNha-1 were used for comparison. Rotation with summer plus winter GMN resulted in more growth and yield benefit for sweet corn than did the other GMN rotations. Compared with control treatments receiving the same chemical N rates, rotation with summer plus winter GMN increased sweet corn ear yield, leaf area index and total plant dry weight and N content by 15-30%. Despite these benefits, use of high chemical N rate (267kgchemicalNha-1) resulted in ear yields at least 20% greater than sweet corn rotated with any GMN and fertilized with reduced N rates. Largest increases in sweet corn dry weight and N content occurred between 4 and 6weeks after emergence in all treatments. After this period of rapid growth, sweet corn fertilized with 267kgchemicalNha-1 showed higher N content than all other treatments. Prior to this period of rapid growth, multiple rainfall events in excess of 30mm may have resulted in leaching of N from GMN residue. Considering the high rainfall levels, low water and N retention capability of sandy soils and rapid N release from GMN during decomposition, future research of GMN in this environment should evaluate options to better match GMN termination with time of greatest potential N uptake from a subsequent crop.</ab>
<no>SO: Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science, vol. 193, no. 1, pp. 1-9, Feb.     2007</no>
<pb>Wiley-Blackwell Publishing, Inc., 350 Main Street, Commerce Place, Malden, Malden, MA, 02148-5018, USA, [mailto:subscrip@blackwellpublishing.com], [URL:http://www.blackwellpublishing.com]</pb>
<sn>0931-2250</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<db>Recent References Related to Technology</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3559</id>
<a1>Cherr,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Scholberg,J. M. S.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Mbuya,O. S.</a1>
<t1>Growth and Yield of Sweet Corn Following Green Manure in a Warm Temperate Environment on Sandy Soil</t1>
<yr>2007</yr>
<k1>green manure</k1>
<k1>Sweets</k1>
<k1>Corn</k1>
<k1>Crops</k1>
<k1>Summer</k1>
<k1>Winter</k1>
<k1>Rapids</k1>
<k1>Sandy soils</k1>
<k1>Fertilizing</k1>
<k1>Ear</k1>
<k1>Receiving</k1>
<k1>Rainfall</k1>
<k1>Drying</k1>
<k1>Manure</k1>
<k1>Emergence</k1>
<k1>Legumes</k1>
<k1>Leaf area index</k1>
<k1>Agronomy</k1>
<k1>Leaching</k1>
<k1>Decomposition</k1>
<k1>Uptakes</k1>
<k1>Residues</k1>
<k1>Climate</k1>
<k1>VAR</k1>
<ab>Legumes used as green manure (GMN) may provide on-farm sources of N for subsequent crops. In warm-humid climates on sandy soils, however, there is a need to evaluate effects on growth and yield of subsequent crops when GMN substitutes for chemical N fertilizer. We collected time-series data for 2years to evaluate growth and ear yield response of sweet corn (Zea mays L. var. Rugosa) in annual rotation with GMN (summer, winter or summer plus winter GMN) and supplemented with 0, 67 or 133kgchemicalNha-1. Control treatments receiving 0, 67, 133, 200 or 267kgchemicalNha-1 were used for comparison. Rotation with summer plus winter GMN resulted in more growth and yield benefit for sweet corn than did the other GMN rotations. Compared with control treatments receiving the same chemical N rates, rotation with summer plus winter GMN increased sweet corn ear yield, leaf area index and total plant dry weight and N content by 15-30%. Despite these benefits, use of high chemical N rate (267kgchemicalNha-1) resulted in ear yields at least 20% greater than sweet corn rotated with any GMN and fertilized with reduced N rates. Largest increases in sweet corn dry weight and N content occurred between 4 and 6weeks after emergence in all treatments. After this period of rapid growth, sweet corn fertilized with 267kgchemicalNha-1 showed higher N content than all other treatments. Prior to this period of rapid growth, multiple rainfall events in excess of 30mm may have resulted in leaching of N from GMN residue. Considering the high rainfall levels, low water and N retention capability of sandy soils and rapid N release from GMN during decomposition, future research of GMN in this environment should evaluate options to better match GMN termination with time of greatest potential N uptake from a subsequent crop.</ab>
<no>SO: Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science, vol. 193, no. 1, pp. 1-9, Feb.     2007</no>
<pb>Wiley-Blackwell Publishing, Inc., 350 Main Street, Commerce Place, Malden, Malden, MA, 02148-5018, USA, [mailto:subscrip@blackwellpublishing.com], [URL:http://www.blackwellpublishing.com]</pb>
<sn>0931-2250</sn>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<db>Recent References Related to Technology</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2299</id>
<a1>Conference on Environmentally Sound Agriculture</a1>
<a1>Bottcher,A. B.</a1>
<a1>Campbell,K. L.</a1>
<a1>Clemson University</a1>
<a1>Florida Cooperative Extension Service</a1>
<a1>Graham,W. D.</a1>
<a1>University of Florida Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences</a1>
<a1>fi apl0071A. B</a1>
<t1>Proceedings of the Conference on Environmentally Sound Agriculture : (what can be done now?)</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<k1>Agricultural ecology -- Congresses</k1>
<k1>Agriculture -- Environmental aspects -- Congresses</k1>
<no>editor, A.B. &amp;quot;Del&amp;quot; Bottcher ; co-editors, K.L. Campbell, W.D. Graham ; April 16-18, 1991, Delta Orlando Resort, Orlando Florida, USA ; sponsored and published by Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida ; co-sponsored by, Clemson University ... [et al.]. : editor, A.B. &amp;quot;Del&amp;quot; Bottcher ; co-editors, K.L. Campbell, W.D. Graham ; April 16-18, 1991, Delta Orlando Resort, Orlando Florida, USA ; sponsored and published by Florida Cooperative Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida ; co-sponsored by, Clemson University ... [et al.].; 2 v. : ill., maps ; 28 cm.; Alternate title: Proceedings for the Environmentally Sound Agriculture Conference.; 50011 Cover title: Proceedings for the Environmentally Sound Agriculture Conference.</no>
<pb>The Service and the Institute</pb>
<pp>Gainesville, FL</pp>
<cn>S589.7.C66 1991 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); S589.7.C66 1991 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); S589.7.C66 1991 (IFAS CENTERS Belle Glade)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3573</id>
<a1>Conner,J. M.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Pitts,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Delivery of Steinernema riobravis through a drip irrigation system</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>95</sp>
<op>100</op>
<k1>entomopathogenic nematodes</k1>
<k1>biological control agents</k1>
<k1>microirrigation</k1>
<k1>insect control</k1>
<k1>biological control</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>steinernema riobravis</k1>
<k1>F821</k1>
<k1>P210</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1998. v. 28 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22000025</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3510</id>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Miller,G. L.</a1>
<t1>Yield Reduction and Root Damage to Cotton Induced by Belonolaimus longicaudatus</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>205</sp>
<op>209</op>
<ab>Sting nematode (Belonolaimus longicaudatus) is recognized as a pathogen of cotton (Gossypium hirsutum), but the expected damage from a given population density of this nematode has not been determined. The objective of this study was to quantify the effects of increasing initial population densities (Pi) of B. longicaudatus on cotton yield and root mass. In a field plot study, nematicide application and cropping history were used to obtain a wide range of Pi values. Cotton yields were regressed on Pi density of B. longicaudatus to quantify yield losses in the field. In controlled environmental chambers, cotton was grown in soil infested with increasing Pi&amp;#39;s of B. longicaudatus. After 40 days, root systems were collected, scanned on a desktop scanner, and root lengths were measured. Root lengths were regressed on inoculation density of B. longicaudatus to quantify reductions in the root systems. In the field, high Pi&amp;#39;s (&amp;gt;100 nematodes/130 cm(3) of soil) reduced yields to near zero. In controlled environmental chamber studies, as few as 10 B. longicaudatus/130 cm(3) of soil caused a 39% reduction in fine cotton roots, and 60 B. longicaudatus/130 cm(3) of soil caused a 70% reduction. These results suggest that B. longicaudatus can cause significant damage to cotton at low population densities, whereas at higher densities crop failure can result.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620440; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270967</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270967</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620440</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3504</id>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Effect of sorghum-sudangrass and velvetbean cover crops on plant-parasitic nematodes associated with potato production in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>285</sp>
<op>288</op>
<ab>In a 3-year field study, population densities of Belonolaimus longicaudatus and other plant-parasitic nematodes and crop yields were compared between potato (Solanum tuberosum) cropping systems where either sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor x S. arundinaceum) or velvetbean (Mucuna pruriens) was grown as a summer cover crop. Population densities of B. longicaudatus, Paratrichodorus minor, Tylenchorhynchus sp., and Mesocriconema sp. increased on sorghum-sudangrass. Population densities of P. minor and Mesocriconema sp. increased on velvetbean. Sorghum-sudangrass increased population densities of B. longicaudatus and Mesocriconema sp. on a subsequent potato crop compared to velvetbean. Potato yields following velvetbean were not greater than following sorghum-sudangrass despite reductions in population densities of B. longicaudatus.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620518; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19265888</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19265888</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620518</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3507</id>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Damage Function and Economic Threshold for Belonolaimus longicaudatus on Potato</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>318</sp>
<op>322</op>
<ab>Belonolaimus longicaudatus has long been recognized as a pathogen of potato (Solanum tuberosum). However, a damage function relating expected yield of potato to population densities of B. longicaudatus at planting has not been derived, and the economic threshold for nematicide application is unknown. The objectives of this study were to derive the damage function of B. longicaudatus on potato and to calculate the economic threshold population density. The damage function data for B. longicaudatus on potato were obtained from an ongoing field study to evaluate cropping systems and nematode management practices. Soil samples were collected from experimental field plots, and nematodes were extracted from a 130-cm(3) subsample with a centrifugal-flotation method. A damage function was derived by linear regression of potato yield on nematode population density at planting. Based on this derived damage function and published potato prices, the economic threshold for nematicide application was calculated at 2 to 3 B. longicaudatus/130 cm(3) of soil, which was near the detection threshold based on methodology used in this study.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620459; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270983</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270983</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620459</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3509</id>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Population Dynamics of Belonolaimus longicaudatusin a Cotton Production System</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>210</sp>
<op>214</op>
<ab>Belonolaimus longicaudatus is a recognized pathogen of cotton (Gossypium hirsutum), but insufficient information is available on the population dynamics and economic thresholds of B. longicaudatus in cotton production. In this study, data collected from a field in Florida were used to develop models predicting population increases of B. longicaudatus on cotton and population declines under clean fallow. Population densities of B. longicaudatus increased on cotton, reaching a carrying capacity of 139 nematodes/130 cm(3) of soil, but decreased exponentially during periods of bare fallow. The model indicated that population densities should decrease each year of monocropped cotton, if an alternate host is not present between sequential cotton crops. Economic thresholds derived from published damage functions and current prices for cotton and nematicides varied from 2 to 5 B. longicaudatus/130 cm(3) of soil, depending on the nematicide used.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620437; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270968</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270968</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620437</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3541</id>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Evaluation of Two Soybean Cultivars and Aldicarb Treatment in Soil Infested with Plant-parasitic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>678</sp>
<op>681</op>
<ab>The soybean cultivars Davis and Leflore were grown in a northern Florida experimental site infested with eight species of plant-parasitic nematodes. Meloidogyne incognita appeared to become the predominant pathogen, suppressing Davis soybean yield regardless of aldicarb treatment. Soybean yields of Leflore were 1.4-fold to 3.5-fold greater than yields of Davis, but aldicarb did not affect yields of either cultivar. Davis soybean yield was negatively correlated with the at-plant density of M. incognita, whereas Leflore seed yield was not negatively correlated with any nematode.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619208; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283184</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283184</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619208</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3547</id>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Interaction of three plant-parasitic nematodes on corn and soybean</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>783</sp>
<op>791</op>
<ab>Interaction of Belonolaimus longicaudatus, Meloidogyne incognita, and Pratylenchus brachyurus on corn and B. longicaudatus, M. incognita, and Heterodera glycines on soybean was investigated in micropiots during two seasons for corn and one season for soybean. Changes in population densities and effects on plant growth of each nematode on corn or soybean alone and in mixed culture were compared. No interactions occurred on corn in 1987. In 1988, midseason population densities of B. longicaudatus were greater in corn plots infested with M. incognita (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05), but at harvest, population densities or B. longicaudatus were less in corn plots infested with P. brachyurus (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05). Except for stalk weight at harvest, plant growth was not affected by any treatment. In soybean, midseason densities of M. incognita were increased in combination with H. glycines (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05), but this trend reversed at harvest. Soybean yield was reduced in plots infested with H. glycines (P &amp;lt;/= 0.001), whereas B. longicaudatus or M. incognita had no effect on plant growth either singly or in mixed culture.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619101; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19287797</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19287797</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619101</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3553</id>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Standardization of nematicide application rates</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>Annals 1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>5</op>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618690; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19290264</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19290264</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618690</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3528</id>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>El-Morshedy,M. M.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Sampling Citrus Fibrous Roots and Tylenchulus semipenetrans</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>442</sp>
<op>451</op>
<ab>Sampling precision was investigated for Tylenchulus semipenetrans juveniles and males in soil and females from roots and for citrus fibrous root mass density. For the case of two composite samples of 15 cores each, counts of juvenile and male nematodes were estimated to be within 40% of mu, at P  1,500 nematodes/100 cm(3) soil. A similar level of alpha was estimated for measurements of fibrous root mass density, but at a precision level of 25% of mu. Densities of female nematodes were estimated with less precision than juveniles and males. Precision estimates from a general sample plan derived from Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law were in good agreement with estimates from individual orchards. Two aspects involved in deriving sampling plans for management advisory purposes were investigated. A minimum of five to six preliminary samples were required to appreciably reduce bias toward underestimation of sigma. The use of a Student&amp;#39;s t value rather than a standard normal deviate in formulae to estimate sample size increased the estimates by an average of three units. Cases in which the use of z rather than Student&amp;#39;s t is appropriate for these formulae are discussed.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619518; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279914</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279914</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619518</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2302</id>
<a1>Evans,K.</a1>
<a1>Trudgill,D. L.</a1>
<a1>Webster,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Plant parasitic nematodes in temperate agriculture</t1>
<yr>1993</yr>
<sp>648</sp>
<k1>Nematode diseases of plants</k1>
<k1>Plant nematodes</k1>
<k1>Plant nematodes -- Control</k1>
<no>edited by K. Evans, D.L. Trudgill and J.M. Webster. : edited by K. Evans, D.L. Trudgill and J.M. Webster.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<pb>CAB International</pb>
<pp>Wallingford</pp>
<sn>0851988083; 0851988083</sn>
<cn>SB998.N4P5261 1993 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB 998 .N4P532 1993 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB998.N4P5261 1993 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred); SB998.N4P5261 1993 (IFAS CENTERS Ft. Pierce)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3582</id>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Population densities of Meloidogyne incognita and other nematodes following seven cultivars of cowpea</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>21</sp>
<op>26</op>
<k1>Vigna unguiculata</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Mesocriconema</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus brachyurus</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus scribneri</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F120</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1993. v. 23 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND93040254</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3543</id>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Nematode densities associated with corn and sorghum cropping systems in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>668</sp>
<op>672</op>
<ab>Final densities (Pf) of Meloidogyne incognita and Pratylenchus spp. increased more than ten-fold over initial densities (Pi) on corn (Zea mays) cultivars grown at three sites in north Florida. The Pf of M. incognita following sorghum (Sorghum bicolor) were much lower (P &amp;lt;/=0.001) than Pf following corn at the two sites in which sorghum was grown. At one of these sites, Pf of M. incognita was &amp;lt;/= 5/100 cm(3) soil, and at the other site Pf &amp;lt; Pi. At one site, population densities of Criconemella sphaerocephala increased to higher levels on sorghum than on corn, but Pf of Pratylenchus spp. were greater (P &amp;lt;/= 0.01) on corn. Few differences in nematode densities were observed among the different corn cultivars tested.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619202; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283182</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283182</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619202</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3498</id>
<a1>Hixson,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Trenholm,L. E.</a1>
<t1>Saline Irrigation Affects Belonolaimus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus on Seashore Paspalum</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>37</sp>
<op>44</op>
<ab>Seashore paspalum (Paspalum vaginatum) has great potential for use in salt-affected turfgrass sites. Use of this grass on golf courses, athletic fields, and lawns in subtropical coastal areas may aid in conservation of freshwater resources. Belonolaimus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus are considered among the most damaging root pathogens of turfgrasses in Florida. Glasshouse experiments were performed in 2002 and 2003 to examine the effects of increasing levels of irrigation salinity on B. longicaudatus and H. galeatus. Irrigation treatments were formulated by concentrating deionized water to six salinity levels (0, 5, 10, 15, 20, and 25 dS/m). Final population densities of H. galeatus followed a negative linear regression (r(2) = 0.92 and 0.83; P &amp;lt;= 0.01) with increasing salinity levels. Final population densities of B. longicaudatus were quadratically (r(2) = 0.72 and 0.78; P &amp;lt;= 0.01) related to increasing salinity levels from 0 to 25 dS/m. An increase in population densities of B. longicaudatus was observed at moderate salinity levels (10 and 15 dS/m) compared to 0 dS/m. Root-length comparisons revealed that B. longicaudatus caused root stunting at low salinity levels, 0 to 10 dS/m, but roots were not affected at 15 to 25 dS/m. These results indicate that the ability of B. longicaudatus to feed and stunt root growth was negatively affected at salinity levels of 15 dS/m and above.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620935; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262841</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262841</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620935</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3500</id>
<a1>Hixson,A. C.</a1>
<a1>Crow,W. T.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Trenholm,L. E.</a1>
<t1>Host Status of &amp;#39;SeaIsle 1&amp;#39; Seashore Paspalum (Paspalum vaginatum) to Belonolaimus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>493</sp>
<op>498</op>
<ab>Belonolaimus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus are considered among the most damaging pathogens of turfgrasses in Florida. However, the host status of seashore paspalum (Paspalum vaginatum) is unknown. Glasshouse experiments were performed in 2002 and 2003 to determine the tolerance of &amp;#39;SeaIsle 1&amp;#39; seashore paspalum to a population of B. longicaudatus and a population of H. galeatus, and to compare to &amp;#39;Tifdwarf&amp;#39; bermudagrass for differences. Both nematode species reproduced well on either grass, but only B. longicaudatus consistently reduced root growth as measured by root length. Belonolaimus longicaudatus reduced root growth (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) by 35% to 45% at 120 days after inoculation on both grasses. In 2003, higher inoculum levels of H. galeatus reduced root growth (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) by 19.4% in seashore paspalum and by 14% in bermudagrass after 60 and 120 days of exposure, respectively. Percentage reductions in root length caused by H. galeatus and B. longicaudatus indicated no differences between grass species, although Tifdwarf bermudagrass supported higher soil population densities of both nematodes than SeaIsle 1 seashore paspalum.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620796; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262830</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262830</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620796</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2301</id>
<a1>International Nematology Congress</a1>
<a1>Gommers,Fred J.</a1>
<a1>Maas,Paul W. Th</a1>
<t1>Nematology from molecule to ecosystem : proceedings Second International Nematology Congress, 11-17 August 1990, Veldhoven, the Netherlands</t1>
<yr>1992</yr>
<sp>306</sp>
<k1>Nematode diseases of plants -- Congresses</k1>
<k1>Nematodes -- Anatomy -- Congresses</k1>
<k1>Nematodes -- Ecology -- Congresses</k1>
<k1>Nematodes -- Molecular aspects -- Congresses</k1>
<no>edited by Fred J. Gommers, Paul W. Th. Maas. : edited by Fred J. Gommers, Paul W. Th. Maas.; Alternate title: Proceedings Second International Nematology Congress; 50411 Includes bibliographical references.</no>
<pb>European Society of Nematologists</pb>
<pp>Inwergrowie, Dundee, Scotland</pp>
<sn>9067542539</sn>
<cn>QL391 .N4I5 1990 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB998.N4I58 1990 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3560</id>
<a1>Jansson,RK</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Sampling plans for the sweet potato weevil (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) on sweet potato in Southern Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<vo>83</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>1901</sp>
<op>1906</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: pest control</k1>
<k1>sampling</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Coleoptera</k1>
<k1>Curculionidae</k1>
<k1>Cylas formicarius elegantulus</k1>
<k1>Ipomoea batatus</k1>
<k1>USA, Florida</k1>
<k1>methodology</k1>
<ab>Sampling program for the sweet potato weevil, Cylas formicarius elegantulus (Summers), were developed for 0.2-ha and 0.4-ha plots of sweet potato (Ipomoea batatas (L.) Lam.). Taylor&amp;#39;s power law was fit to data on spatial dispersion of sweet potato weevil, and results were used to develop relationships between number of sample units and levels of precision for selected mean densities per plant. Results were similar whether the sample unit was the whole plant or a region from 15 cm below to 10 cm above the crown. Total numbers of weevils in the whole-plant samples were linearly related with numbers in the subsample (region from 15 cm below to 10 cm above the crown). Spatial statistics indicated that weevil populations were aggregated. The numbers of plant samples (whole-plant or region of plant) needed to estimate weevil populations reliably were too high and required too much time to be practical.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0022-0493</sn>
<ad>IFAS, Univ. Florida, Trop. Res. and Educ. Cent., 18905 S.W. 280 St., Homestead, FL 33031, USA</ad>
<an>2418270</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>Z 05156 Techniques; Z 05207 Agricultural &amp; general applied entomology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Entomology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3566</id>
<a1>Larson,B.</a1>
<a1>Stimac,J. L.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>MacVean,C.</a1>
<t1>Effects of cropping system on nematode population densities in small-scale highland Guatemalan agriculture</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>177</sp>
<op>191</op>
<k1>Zea mays</k1>
<k1>Phaseolus vulgaris</k1>
<k1>intercropping</k1>
<k1>Vicia faba</k1>
<k1>Brassica oleracea var. italica</k1>
<k1>Coriandrum sativum</k1>
<k1>Amaranthus cruentus</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Physalis</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>continuous cropping</k1>
<k1>Guatemala</k1>
<k1>physalis pruinosa</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 2000. v. 30 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22792534</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3502</id>
<a1>Macchia,E. T.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Syvertsen,J. S.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Perennial Peanut (Arachis glabrata) Ground Cover on Nematode Communities in Citrus</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>450</sp>
<op>457</op>
<ab>The effects of perennial peanut (Arachis glabrata) ground cover on the nematode community in a citrus orchard were examined. Samples were taken from two different ground cover treatments (perennial peanut or bare ground) at each of three distances from the tree trunk. Richness, measured as total numbers of nematode genera per sample, and total numbers of nematodes were greatest in the perennial peanut treatment (P &amp;lt; 0.05). Abundance of many genera of bacterivores, fungivores, and omnivores were increased by the perennial peanut ground cover. Total numbers of plant parasites were greater in perennial peanut treatments on three of the five sampling dates (P &amp;lt; 0.05), mainly due to trends in numbers of Mesocriconema. Distance from a tree trunk and the interaction of ground cover treatments and proximity to a tree trunk were most influential for Belonolaimus and Hoplolaimus. Although differences among treatments were observed for nematode genera and trophic groups, ecological indices were not consistently sensitive to treatments. Among several ecological indices evaluated, richness was most often affected by ground cover treatment.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620683; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262779</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262779</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620683</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3578</id>
<a1>Mannion,C. M.</a1>
<a1>Schaffer,B.</a1>
<a1>Ozores-Hampton,M.</a1>
<a1>Bryan,H. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Nematode population dynamics in municipal solid waste-amended soil during tomato and squash cultivation</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>17</sp>
<op>24</op>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>Cucurbita maxima</k1>
<k1>composts</k1>
<k1>crop rotation</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>planting date</k1>
<k1>harvest date</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>efficacy</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1994. v. 24 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20453131</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3583</id>
<a1>Mashela,P.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Salinity reduces resistance to tylenchulus semipenetrans in citrus rootstocks</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>7</sp>
<op>12</op>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>calcium chloride</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>rootstocks</k1>
<k1>sodium chloride</k1>
<k1>soil salinity</k1>
<k1>Tylenchulus semipenetrans</k1>
<k1>fecundity</k1>
<k1>susceptibility</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1992. v. 22 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND92050289</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3540</id>
<a1>Mashela,P.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Graham,J. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Leaching Soluble Salts Increases Population Densities of Tylenchulus semipenetrans</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>103</sp>
<op>108</op>
<ab>The effect of salinity on population densities of Tylenchulus semipenetrans was measured on 3-month-old salt-tolerant Rangpur lime growing on either loamy sand, sand, or organic mix and on 4-month-old salt-sensitive Sweet lime in organic mix. Salinity treatments were initiated by watering daily with 25 mol/m(3) NaCl + 3.3 mol/m(3) CaCl for 3 days and every other day with 50 mol/m(3) NaC1 + 6.6 mol/m(3) CaC1 for one week, with no salt (NS) treatments as controls. Salinity was discontinued in one treatment (DS) by leaching with tap water prior to inoculation with nematodes, whereas the continuous salinity (CS) treatment remained unchanged. Overall, in Rangpur lime organic soil supported the highest population densities of T. semipenetrans, followed by loamy sand and sand. The DS treatment resulted in the highest (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) mean population densities of T. semipenetrans in the three soil types. Similarly, the DS treatment in Sweet lime resulted in the highest (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) nematode populations. The DS treatment predisposed citrus to nematode infection through accumulated salt stress, whereas leaching soluble salt in soil solution offered nematodes a suitable nonosmotic habitat. Nematode females under the DS treatment also had the highest (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) fecundity.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619237; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283210</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283210</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619237</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3538</id>
<a1>Mashela,P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Damage Potential and Reproduction of Belonolaimus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus on Alyceclover</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>438</sp>
<op>441</op>
<ab>Alyceclover (Alysicarpus spp.) is an annual, high-quality leguminous forage, suitable for production under tropical and subtropical climates where the husbandry of conventional leguminous forages, Trifolium spp., is uneconomical. The damage potential and reproduction of Belonolairaus longicaudatus and Hoplolaimus galeatus on alyceclover were studied under greenhouse conditions, using sand and sandy clay loam soil materials, respectively. Both nematode species reproduced on alyceclover, but only B. longicaudatus was pathogenic. Symptoms of B. longicaudatus damage were suppression of shoot yield, limited root system, stunting, incipient wilting, and occasional seedling mortality. In one experiment, the threshold-damage density was three nematodes/100 cm(3) sand, whereas in the other experiment it was zero nematodes.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619285; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283020</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283020</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619285</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3585</id>
<a1>Mashela,P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Correlation of Belonolaimus longicaudatus, Hoplolaimus galeatus, and soil texture with yield of alyceclover (Alysicarpus spp.)</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>177</sp>
<op>184</op>
<k1>Alysicarpus</k1>
<k1>Alysicarpus vaginalis</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>Belonolaimus longicaudatus</k1>
<k1>Mesocriconema</k1>
<k1>Hoplolaimus galeatus</k1>
<k1>soil texture</k1>
<k1>yield components</k1>
<k1>genotype</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>alysicarpus ovalifolius</k1>
<k1>gainesville, florida</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J200</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1991. v. 21 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND92012454</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2307</id>
<a1>McGovern,R. J.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Physical methods of soil sterilization for disease management including soil solarization</t1>
<yr>1997</yr>
<sp>283</sp>
<op>283-313</op>
<k1>Phytopathogenic microorganisms -- Control</k1>
<k1>Phytopathogenic microorganisms -- Control -- Environmental aspects</k1>
<k1>Plant diseases</k1>
<no>edited by Nancy A. Rechcigl and Jack E. Rechcigl. : edited by Nancy A. Rechcigl and Jack E. Rechcigl.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Rechcigl,Jack E.</a2><a2> Rechcigl,Nancy A.</a2>
<t2>Environmentally safe approaches to crop disease control</t2>
<pb>CRC Press</pb>
<pp>Boca Raton</pp>
<t3>Agriculture &amp;amp; environment series</t3>
<sn>0849326273</sn>
<cn>SB731.E58 1997 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB731.E58 1997 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2293</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Nematode communities in managed pastures in north Florida</t1>
<yr>1998</yr>
<sp>319</sp>
<op>320</op>
<no>ID: 247139625</no>
<a2>Goede,Ron G. M. de</a2>
<t2>Nematode communities of Northern temperate grassland ecosystems</t2>
<pb>Focus-Verl.</pb>
<pp>Gieen</pp>
<sn>3883494712 9783883494715</sn>
<la>Undetermined</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2306</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Cultural control of plant-parasitic nematodes</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<sp>149</sp>
<op>149-163</op>
<k1>Pests -- Biological control -- Florida</k1>
<no>edited by David Rosen, Fred D. Bennett, John L. Capinera. : edited by David Rosen, Fred D. Bennett, John L. Capinera.; Alternate title: Biological control, a Florida perspective.; Alternate title: Pest management in the subtropics, a Florida perspective; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Bennett,Fred D.</a2><a2> Capinera,John L.</a2><a2>Rosen,David</a2>
<t2>Pest management in the subtropics : biological control, a Florida perspective</t2>
<pb>Intercept</pb>
<pp>Andover</pp>
<sn>0946707464; 0946707464</sn>
<cn>SB975.P471 1994 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB975.P471 1994 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB950.2 .F6P471 1994 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB975.P471 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Belle Glade); SB975.P471 1994 (IFAS C(TRUNCATED)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2292</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management in sustainable agriculture</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>20-22 April 1994</fd>
<sp>517</sp>
<op>522</op>
<no>ID: 30956858</no>
<a2>Campbell,Kenneth L.,</a2><a2> Graham,Wendy D.</a2><a2> Bottcher,A. B.</a2><a2> University of Florida. Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences.</a2><a2> American Society of Agricultural Engineers. Soil and Water Division.</a2><a2> American Society of Agricultural Engineers. Florida Section.</a2><a2>Conference on Environmentally Sound Agriculture</a2>
<t2>Environmentally sound agriculture : proceedings of the second conference, 20-22 April 1994, Orlando, Florida</t2>
<ed>Orlando, Florida</ed>
<pb>American Society of Agricultural Engineers</pb>
<pp>St. Joseph, Mich., USA</pp>
<sn>0929355474 9780929355474</sn>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2297</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Extraction of nematodes and sampling methods</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<sp>13</sp>
<op>13-47</op>
<k1>Nematodes -- Control</k1>
<k1>Plant nematodes -- Control</k1>
<no>edited by R.H. Brown and B.R. Kerry. : edited by R.H. Brown and B.R. Kerry.; 50411 Includes bibliographies and index.</no>
<a2>Brown,R. H.</a2><a2> Kerry,B. R.</a2>
<t2>Principles and practice of nematode control in crops</t2>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>Sydney N.S.W.</pp>
<sn>0121376400</sn>
<cn>SB998.N45P74x 1987 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); QL391 .N4P69 1987 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB998.N4P74 1987 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2296</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Plot size and design for acquisition of field data in nematology</t1>
<yr>1987</yr>
<sp>52</sp>
<op>58</op>
<k1>Nematocides</k1>
<k1>Nematodes -- Research</k1>
<k1>Nematologists -- United States</k1>
<no>edited by Joseph A. Veech and Donald W. Dickson. : edited by Joseph A. Veech and Donald W. Dickson.; 50411 Includes bibliographies and index.</no>
<a2>Dickson,D. W.</a2><a2> Society of Nematologists</a2><a2>Veech,Joseph A.</a2>
<t2>Vistas on nematology : a commemoration of the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Society of Nematologists</t2>
<pb>Society of Nematologists</pb>
<pp>Hyattsville, Md.</pp>
<cn>QL391.N4V571 1987 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); QL391 .N4V4 1987 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); QL391.N4V571 1987 (IFAS CENTERS Immokalee)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2305</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<t1>Economic thresholds and nematode management</t1>
<jo>Advances in plant pathology</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<vo>11</vo>
<sp>147</sp>
<op>171</op>
<k1>Plant diseases</k1>
<k1>Plant diseases -- Periodicals</k1>
<no>v. : ill. ; 24 cm.; Publishing history: Vol. 1-11.; Continued by: Advances in botanical research 0065-2295 (DLC)^^^62021144 (OCoLC)1461155; Indexed by: 51011 Chemical abstracts 0009-2258</no>
<pb>Academic Press</pb>
<pp>London ; New York</pp>
<sn>0736-4539</sn>
<cn>SB599.A381 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB599.A38 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB599.A38 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2295</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Ferris,J. M.</a1>
<a1>Ferris,V. R.</a1>
<t1>Model synthesis and validation: primary consumers</t1>
<yr>1982</yr>
<sp>141</sp>
<op>156</op>
<k1>Soil ecology</k1>
<k1>Soil nematodes</k1>
<no>edited by Diana W. Freckman ; foreword by J.A. Wallwork. : edited by Diana W. Freckman ; foreword by J.A. Wallwork.; 50411 Includes bibliographies.</no>
<a2>Freckman,Diana W.</a2>
<t2>Nematodes in soil ecosystems</t2>
<ed>1</ed>
<pb>University of Texas Press</pb>
<pp>Austin</pp>
<sn>0292755260; 0292755260</sn>
<cn>QL391 .N4N384 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); QL391.N4N384 1982 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2291</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Population densities of root-knot nematodes following corn and sorghum in cropping systems</t1>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>June 15-17, 1993</fd>
<sp>26</sp>
<op>26-29</op>
<no>ID: 52446630</no>
<a2>Bollich,Patrick Keith</a2>
<t2>Proceedings of the 1993 Southern Conservation Tillage Conference for Sustainable Agriculture</t2>
<ed>Monroe, Louisiana</ed>
<pb>Tennessee Valley Authority</pb>
<pp>Knoxville</pp>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ul>http://www.ag.auburn.edu/nsdl/sctcsa/Proceedings/1993/1993%5FSCTCSA.pdf</ul>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Conference Proceedings</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2279</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Cropping systems for management of plant-parasitic nematodes</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>June 18-20, 1991</fd>
<vo>Special Report 148</vo>
<sp>50</sp>
<op>52</op>
<no>ID: 24113813</no>
<a2>Keisling,Terry C.</a2>
<t2>Proceedings of the 1991 Southern Conservation Tillage Conference</t2>
<ed>North Little Rock</ed>
<pb>Arkansas Agricultural Experiment Station</pb>
<pp>Fayetteville, Ark.</pp>
<la>English</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2298</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Jansson,R. K.</a1>
<t1>Spatial patterns of Cylas formicarius in sweet potato fields and developent of a sampling plan</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<sp>157</sp>
<op>167</op>
<k1>Insect pests -- Control</k1>
<k1>Sweet potatoes -- Diseases and pests -- Control</k1>
<no>edited by Richard K. Jansson and Kandukuri V. Raman. : edited by Richard K. Jansson and Kandukuri V. Raman.; Series note: Studies in insect biology; 50011 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<a2>Jansson,Richard K.</a2><a2> Raman,Kandukuri V.</a2>
<t2>Sweet potato pest management : a global perspective</t2>
<pb>Westview Press</pb>
<pp>Boulder, CO</pp>
<t3>Westview studies in insect biology</t3>
<sn>0813378257; 8120406354 (India)</sn>
<cn>SB608.S98S94 1991 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); S608 .S98S94 1991 (IFAS CENTERS Homestead); S608 .S98S94 1991 (IFAS CENTERS Belle Glade)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3511</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Host Suitability of Potential Cover Crops for Root-knot Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>619</sp>
<op>623</op>
<ab>Several potential cover crops were evaluated for their susceptibility to Meloidogyne arenaria race 1, M. incognita race 1, and M. javanica in a series of five greenhouse experiments. No galls or egg masses were observed on roots of castor (Ricinus communis), cowpea (Vigna unguiculata cv. Iron Clay), crotalaria (Crotalaria spectabilis), or American jointvetch (Aeschynomene americana). Occasional egg masses (rating &amp;lt;/=1.0 on 0-5 scale) were observed on marigold (Tagetes minuta) in one test with M. incognita, on sesame (Sesamum indicum cv. Paloma) in a test with M. arenaria, and on sunn hemp (Crotalaria juncea cv. Tropic Sun) in 1 of 2 tests with M. incognita; otherwise, these crops were free of egg masses. Numbers of second-stage juveniles (J2) hatched from eggs per root system were low (&amp;lt;/=10/pot) for the abovementioned crops. Egg-mass levels and numbers of hatched J2 of M. incognita on pearl millet (Pennisetum typhoides, Tifleaf II hybrid) were comparable to those on a susceptible tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum cv. Rutgers). In a test with M. arenaria, egg mass levels and numbers of J2 on Japanese millet (Echinochloa frumentacea) were similar to those on tomato. Japanese millet was susceptible to each of the nematode isolates tested. However, several of the crops evaluated were very poor hosts or non-hosts of the nematode isolates, including several legumes (cowpea, crotalaria, jointvetch, sunn hemp) that have potential use in both nematode and nitrogen management.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620418; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270926</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270926</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620418</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3577</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Changes in population densities of Meloidogyne spp. and Paratrichodorus minor on winter rye cover crops</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>160</op>
<k1>Secale cereale</k1>
<k1>cover crops</k1>
<k1>crop rotation</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne arenaria</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population dynamics</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1994. v. 24 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20478034</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3584</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Nematological problems in tropical and subtropical fruit tree crops</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>103</sp>
<op>116</op>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>crop damage</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>literature reviews</k1>
<k1>site factors</k1>
<k1>problem analysis</k1>
<k1>nomenclature</k1>
<k1>tropical tree fruits</k1>
<k1>subtropical tree fruits</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1992. v. 22 (1); Literature review; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND92050300</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3552</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Symposium on tropical and pacific nematology-introduction</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1988</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>171</sp>
<op>172</op>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618815; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19290199</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19290199</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618815</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3557</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Simulated sampling strategies for nematodes distributed according to a negative binomial model</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>517</sp>
<op>522</op>
<ab>A FORTRAN computer program was developed to simulate nematode soil sampling strategies consisting of various numbers of samples per field, with each sample consisting of various numbers of soil cores. The program assumes that the nematode species involved fit a negative binomial distribution. Required input data are estimates of the mean and k values, the number of samples per field and cores per sample in the strategy to be investigated, and the number of times the simulation is to be replicated. Output consists of simulated values of the relative deviation from the mean and standard error to mean ratio, both averaged over all replications. The program was used to compare 150 simulated sampling strategies for Meloidogyne incognita, involving all combinations of two mean values (2.0 and 10.0 la.rvae/10 cm(3) soil), three k values (1.35, 0.544, and 0.294), five different numbers of samples per field (1, 2, 4. 10, 20), and five different numbers of cores per sample (1, 2, 4, 10, 20). Simulations resulting from different mean values were similar, but best results were obtained with higher k values and 20 cores per sample. Relatively few 20-core samples were needed to obtain average deviations from the mean of 20-25%.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618223; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19295746</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19295746</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618223</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3596</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Rotylenchulus reniformis on snap bean and methods for control by oxamyl</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>89</sp>
<op>95</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Oct 1980. v. 10 (2); 19 ref&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND81018620</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3597</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Campbell,C. W.</a1>
<t1>Relationship between nematode density and weed density in avocado groves</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1980</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>96</sp>
<op>102</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Oct 1980. v. 10 (2); 19 ref&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND81018621</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3525</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Tropical Rotation Crops on Meloidogyne incognita and Other Plant-Parasitic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>535</sp>
<op>544</op>
<ab>In a field experiment conducted on sandy soil in Florida during the 1993 season, rotation crops of castor (Ricinus communis), velvetbean (Mucuna deeringina), &amp;#39;Mississippi Silver&amp;#39; cowpea (Vigna unguiculata), American jointvetch (Aeschynomene americana), &amp;#39;Dehapine 51&amp;#39; cotton (Gossypium hirsutum), and &amp;#39;SX-17&amp;#39; sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor x S. sudanense) were effective in maintaining low population densities (450/100 cm(3) soil) resulted after &amp;#39;Clemson Spineless&amp;#39; okra (Hibiscus esculentus) and &amp;#39;Kirby&amp;#39; soybean (Glycine max). Following a winter cover crop of rye (Secale cereale), densities of M. incognita following the six most effective rotation crops (1993 season) remained relatively low (&amp;lt;/=32/100 cm(3) soil) through midseason of an eggplant (Solanum melongena) crop planted in 1994, but increased by the end of the eggplant crop. The rotation crops planted during 1993 had little effect on yield of eggplant in 1994. Eggplant yield was inversely correlated with preplant densities (Pi) of Belonolaimus longicaudatus (r = -0.282; P &amp;lt;/= 0.10; 46 dr), but not with Pi of M. incognita. A separate microplot experiment conducted in 1994 revealed that final densities (Pf) of M. incognita race 1 following 13 different crop cultivars were lower (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) than Pf following a &amp;#39;Pioneer X304C&amp;#39; corn (Zea mays) control, but only &amp;#39;Mississippi Silver&amp;#39; cowpea and &amp;#39;Sesaco 16&amp;#39; sesame (Sesamum indicum) resulted in lower (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) Pf of Paratrichodorus minor than the corn control. It is critical that rotation crops intended for suppression of individual Meloidogyne spp. be evaluated for their response to other nematode pests as well.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619646; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277319</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277319</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619646</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3546</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Determining consistency of spatial dispersion of nematodes in small plots</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>65</sp>
<op>72</op>
<ab>Nematode population densities in field plots were estimated by collecting samples consisting of 12 soil cores. Plots encompassed a variety of plant hosts and sampling dates, and provided data on the population densities of seven species of plant-parasitic nematodes. Three separate samples were collected per plot on each sampling date to obtain estimates of the mean and variance of numbers for each species. For each nematode species, these estimates were used to derive the Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law regression over plots having identical hosts and sampling dates. For some nematode species, comparisons of regression equations among different sampling dates on the same host revealed similarities in values of a and b from Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law. Parameters of Taylor&amp;#39;s Power Law relationships were used to develop sampling plans and to obtain estimates of sample precision. Precision estimates from specific and general sampling plans are illustrated for Belonolaimus longicaudatus.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619134; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283095</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283095</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619134</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3548</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Vertical Distribution of Plant-parasitic Nematodes in Sandy Soil under Soybean</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>22</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>90</sp>
<op>96</op>
<ab>Vertical distribution of five plant-parasitic nematodes was examined in two north Florida soybean fields in 1987 and 1988. Soil samples were collected from 0-15 cm, 15-30 cm, and 30-45 cm deep at each site. Soil at the three depths consisted of approximately 96% sand. More than 50% of Belonolaimus longicaudatus population densities occurred in the upper 15-cm soil layer at planting, but the species became more evenly distributed through the other depths as the season progressed. Criconemella sphaerocephala was evenly distributed among the three depths in one field but was low (&amp;lt; 20% of the total density) in the upper 15 cm at a second site. Maximum population densities of Pratylenchus brachyurus were observed at 15-30 cm on most sampling dates. Vertical distributions of Meloidogyne incognita and Paratrichodorus minor were erratic and showed seasonal variation. A diagnostic sample from the upper 0-15 cm of these soybean fields revealed only a minority of the populations of most of the phytoparasitic species present.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619006; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19287693</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19287693</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619006</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3551</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Effects and dynamics of a nematode community on maize</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>462</sp>
<op>471</op>
<ab>Relationships between nematode density and yield and between final and preplant population levels were examined in small maize plots on sandy soils in north-central Florida. Plant-parasitic nematodes present in the community included Belonolaimus longicaudatus, Criconemella sphaerocephala, Meloidogyne incognita, Paratrichodorus minor, Pratylenchus brachyurus, and a Xiphinema sp. Plant growth--including stand count, grain yield, stalk weight, and size of young plants--often was inversely correlated (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) with densities of B. longicaudatus and occasionally with P. brachyurus, but not with densities of other species or with a range of soil variables. More severe losses in grain yields from B. longicaudatus occurred in 1987 than in 1988, although mean preplant nematode densities in February were similar in both years (4.4 vs. 3.9/100 cm(3) soil). Final population densities of most nematode species were linearly related (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) to densities measured at planting or earlier. These relationships were stronger (higher r(2)) with the ectoparasites B. longicaudatus and C. sphaerocephala than with the endoparasites M. incognita and P. brachyurus. No significant correlations were found between population densities of different nematode species.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618965; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19287639</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19287639</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618965</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3550</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<t1>Effects and dynamics of a nematode community on soybean</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>490</sp>
<op>499</op>
<ab>The relationships between densities of all members of a plant-parasitic nematode community and yield of &amp;#39;Davis&amp;#39; soybean and between final and preplant population levels were examined in small plots on sandy soils in north-central Florida. Plant-parasitic nematodes present in the community included Belonolaimus longicaudatus, Criconemella sphaerocephala, Meloidogyne incognita, Paratrichodorus minor, Pratylenchus brachyurus, and Xiphinema sp. Plant growth, including stand count, soybean yield (kg/ha), and size of young plants, was occasionally inversely correlated (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) with densities of B. longicaudatus or P. brachyurus, but not with densities of other species or with a range of soil variables. The nature of this relationship varied with season, with more severe stand losses noted during 1987 than in 1988. Final population densities (Pf) of most nematode species showed significant (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) linear relationships to densities measured at planting or earlier (Pi). These relationships were stronger (higher r(2)) with the ectoparasite B. longicaudatus than with the endoparasites M. incognita and P. brachyurus. Criconemella sphaerocephala declined under soybean cultivation, reaching levels near zero after two seasons. A quadratic model showed an improvement (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) over the linear model in describing the relationship between Pf and Pi measured at planting for B. longicaudatus, and gave a better indication of the leveling off of Pf at high values of Pi.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618969; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19287643</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19287643</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618969</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3579</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Brito,J. A. de</a1>
<t1>Host status of selected tropical rotation crops to four populations of root-knot nematodes</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>45</sp>
<op>53</op>
<k1>tropical and subtropical crops</k1>
<k1>crop rotation</k1>
<k1>crops</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne arenaria</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne javanica</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1994. v. 24 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20453138</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3539</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>Candanedo-Lay,E. M.</a1>
<a1>Hewlett,T. E.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Damage Functions for Meloidogyne arenaria on Peanut</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>193</sp>
<op>198</op>
<ab>Microplot experiments were conducted in 1989 and 1990 to determine the relationship between yield of peanut (Arachis hypogaea) and inoculum density ofMeloidogyne arenaria race 1. Nine inoculum densities were used, ranging from 0-200 eggs/100 cm(3) soil (1989) or from 0-100 eggs/100 cm(3) (1990), and each density was replicated 10 times. In 1989, higher final densities (mean of 1,171 juveniles [J2]/100 cm(3) soil) were obtained in plots inoculated with 0.5 to 50 eggs/100 cm(3) soil than in plots inoculated with 100 to 200 eggs/100 cm(3) (313 J2/100 cm(3) soil). In 1990, final densities of M. arenaria reached high levels (&amp;gt;/= 1,111 J2/100 cm(3) soil) in all inoculated plots. Pod yield and dry weight of foliage at harvest were negatively correlated (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) with inoculum density in both seasons. In 1989, the relationship between pod weight (y) and initial density (x) was described by Seinhorst&amp;#39;s equation, with y = 0.088 + 0.91(0.90)x(1) and r(2) = 0.826. In 1990, the relationship was y = 0.22 + 0.78(0.97)x(1) and r(2) = 0.794. These equations suggest tolerance limits of approximately 1 egg/100 cm(3) soil, which may require specialized methods, such as bioassay, for detection.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619245; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283223</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283223</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619245</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3531</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>de Brito,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Hewlett,T. E.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Tropical Rotation Crops on Meloidogyne arenaria Population Densities and Vegetable Yields in Microplots</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>175</sp>
<op>181</op>
<ab>The effects of 12 summer crop rotation treatments on population densities of Meloidogyne arenaria race 1 and on yields of subsequent spring vegetable crops were determined in microplots. The crop sequence was: (i) rotation crops during summer 1991 ; (ii) cover crop of rye (Secale cereale) during winter 1991-92; (iii) squash (Cucurbita pepo) during spring 1992; (iv) rotation crops during summer 1992; (v) rye during winter 1992-93; (vi) eggplant (Solanum melongena) during spring 1993. The 12 rotation treatments were castor (Ricinus communis), cotton (Gossypium hirsutum), velvetbean (Mucuna deeringiana), crotalaria (Crotalaria spectabilis), fallow, hairy indigo (Indigofera hirsuta), American jointvetch (Aeschynomene americana), sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor x S. sudanense), soybean (Glycine max), horsebean (Canavalia ensiformis), sesame (Sesamum indicum), and peanut (Arachis hypogaea). Compared to peanut, the first eight rotation treatments resulted in lower (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) numbers of M. arenaria juveniles on most sampling dates. Soybean, horsebean, and sesame rotations were less effective in suppressing nematodes. Yield of squash was greater (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) following castor, cotton, velvetbean, and crotalaria than following peanut. Compared to the peanut rotation, yield of eggplant was enhanced (P &amp;lt;/= 0.10) following castor, crotalaria, hairy indigo, American jointvetch, and sorghum-sudangrass. Several of these rotation crops may provide a means for depressing M. arenaria population densities on a short-term basis to enhance yields in a subsequent susceptible vegetable crop.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619497; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279880</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279880</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619497</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3529</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dickson,D. W.</a1>
<a1>de Brito,J. A.</a1>
<a1>Hochmuth,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Tropical rotation crops influence nematode densities and vegetable yields</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>308</sp>
<op>314</op>
<ab>The effects of eight summer rotation crops on nematode densities and yields of subsequent spring vegetable crops were determined in field studies conducted in north Florida from 1991 to 1993. The crop sequence was as follows: (i) rotation crops during summer 1991; (ii) cover crop of rye (Secale cereale) during winter 1991-92; (iii) &amp;#39;Lemondrop L&amp;#39; squash (Cucurbita pepo) during spring 1992; (iv) rotation crops during summer 1992; (v) rye during winter 1992-93; (vi) &amp;#39;Classic&amp;#39; eggplant (Solanum melongena) during spring 1993. The eight summer crop rotation treatments were as follows: &amp;#39;Hale&amp;#39; castor (Ricinus communis), velvetbean (Mucuna deeringiana), sesame (Sesamum indicum), American jointvetch (Aeschynomene americana), weed fallow, &amp;#39;SX- 17&amp;#39; sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor x S. sudanense), &amp;#39;Kirby&amp;#39; soybean (Glycine max), and &amp;#39;Clemson Spineless&amp;#39; okra (Hibiscus esculentus) as a control. Rotations with castor, velvetbean, American jointvetch, and sorghum-sudangrass were most effective in maintaining the lowest population densities of Meloidogyne spp. (a mixture of M. incognita race 1 and M. arenaria race 1), but Paratrichodorus minor built up in the sorghum-sudangrass rotation. Yield of squash was lower (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) following sorghum-sudangrass than after any of the other treatments except fallow. Yield of eggplant was greater (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) following castor, sesame, or American jointvetch than following okra or fallow. Several of the rotation crops evaluated here may be useful for managing nematodes in the field and for improving yields of subsequent vegetable crops.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619506; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279897</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279897</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619506</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3549</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Root-knot Nematodes on Areca catechu</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>21</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>717</sp>
<op>719</op>
<ab>No root galling or egg mass formation was noted on betel palm (Areca catechu) 3 or 9 months after inoculation with Meloidogyne arenaria, M. hapla, M. incognita races 1 and 3, or M. javanica. Compared with uninoculated controls, a reduction (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) in fresh root weight was noted after 3 months with M. incognita race 1 but not with other species or races, No differences (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) in root weight between controls and inoculated plants were observed at 9 months, nor were any differences found in top weight at 3 or 9 months.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2629662; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19287679</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19287679</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2629662</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3567</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Short-term effects of cattle grazing on nematode communities in Florida pastures</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>211</sp>
<op>221</op>
<k1>free-living nematodes</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>species diversity</k1>
<k1>grazing intensity</k1>
<k1>cattle</k1>
<k1>pastures</k1>
<k1>seasonal variation</k1>
<k1>subtropics</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>communities</k1>
<k1>J100</k1>
<k1>L300</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 2000. v. 30 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22792537</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3512</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Nematode Population Fluctuations during Decomposition of Specific Organic Amendments</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>37</sp>
<op>44</op>
<ab>Population densities of nematodes in field soil without plants were monitored for 10 months following application of organic amendments to pots in a greenhouse. The four treatments consisted of three different kinds of organic amendments: homogeneous crop residues of maize (Zea mays, C:N = 48.0:1), Texas panicum (Panicum texanum, C:N = 32.9:1), or velvetbean (Mucuna pruriens, C:N = 18.6:1), plus a control without any amendment. Plant-parasitic nematodes declined in all treatments due to absence of a food source. Bacterivore numbers increased following amendment application and remained greater than initial population levels until 4 months after application. Fungivore numbers were higher than initial levels until 6 months after amendment application and did not decline below the initial numbers during the course of the experiment. On several sampling dates, the bacterivorous genera Cervidellus and Eucephalobus were most abundant in pots with maize residues. Among the fungivores, Aphelenchoides numbers early in the experiment were greatest in pots amended with velvetbean, whereas numbers of Aphelenchus, Nothotylenchus, and Tylenchidae (mainly Filenchus) were greatest during the latter half of the experiment following the maize amendment. Omnivorous nematodes, particularly Eudorylaimus, showed two peaks in abundance during the course of the experiment. Results provided some evidence that population levels of some genera of bacterivores and fungivores may be affected by specific organic amendments.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620342; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270873</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270873</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620342</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3523</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Responses of Some Common Cruciferae to Root-knot Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>550</sp>
<op>554</op>
<ab>Ten cultivated plants of the family Cruciferae were evaluated for susceptibility to Meloidogyne arenaria race 1, M. incognita races 1 and 3, and M. javanica in a series of four separate greenhouse tests. After 62-64 days, or 1,032-1,072 degree days (10 C base), several of the crops evaluated showed moderate to severe levels of galling (&amp;gt; 3.0 on 0-5 scale) and moderate numbers of egg masses (&amp;gt;2.0 on 0-5 scale) in response to each of the nematode species and races. Among the plants tested, collard (Brassica oleracea var. acephala) cv. Georgia Southern was the least susceptible (fewest galls and egg masses) to each of the four nematode isolates. Similar low levels of infection were obtained with broccoli (B. oleracea var. botrytis) cv. De Cicco in response to M. incognita race 1 and M. arenaria. Numbers of second-stage juveniles hatched from eggs per root system were variable in the test with M. arenaria, but lowest on collard for each of the other nematodes. Some commonly grown crucifers are hosts to several different species and races of Meloidogyne, which should be considered if these crops are included in cropping systems.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619653; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277321</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277321</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619653</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3526</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Response of some common annual bedding plants to three species of meloidogyne</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4 Suppl</is>
<sp>773</sp>
<op>777</op>
<ab>Twelve ornamental bedding plant cultivars were grown in soil infested with isolates of Meloidogyne incognita race 1, M. javanica, or M. arenaria race 1 in a series of tests in containers in a growth room. Root galling (0-5 scale) and eggs/plant were evaluated 8-10 weeks after soil infestation and seedling transplantation. Snapdragon, Antirrhinum majus cv. First Ladies, was extensively galled and highly susceptible (mean gall rating &amp;gt;/=4.2 and &amp;gt;/=14,500 eggs/plant), and Celosia argentea cv. Century Mix and Coleus blumei cv. Rainbow were susceptible (&amp;gt;1,500 eggs/plant) to all three Meloidogyne isolates. Response of Petunia x hybrida varied with cultivar and nematode isolate. Little or no galling or egg production from any Meloidogyne isolate was observed on Ageratum houstonianum cv. Blue Mink, Lobularia maritima cv. Rosie O&amp;#39;Day, or Tagetes patula cv. Dwarf Primrose. Galling was slight (mean rating 4.0 and &amp;gt;/=7,900 eggs/plant) by M. javanica and M. arenaria but was nearly free of galling from M. incognita. Zinna elegans cv. Scarlet was nearly free of galling from M. incognita and M. arenaria but was susceptible (mean gall rating = 2.9; 3,400 eggs/plant) to M. javanica.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619562; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279963</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279963</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619562</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3544</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Extraction Efficiency of Belonolaimus longicaudatus from Sandy Soil</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>511</sp>
<op>518</op>
<ab>Numbers of Belonolaimus longicaudatus extracted from sandy soils (91-92% sand) by sieving and centrifugation were only 40-55% of those extracted by sieving and incubation on a Baermann tray. Residues normally discarded at each step of the sieving plus Baermann tray extraction procedure were examined for nematodes to obtain estimates of extraction efficiencies. For third-stage and fourth-stage juveniles, males, and females, estimates of extraction efficiency ranged from 60 to 65% in one experiment and 73 to 82% in another. Estimated extraction efficiencies for second-stage juveniles were lower (33% in one experiment, 67% in another) due to losses during sieving. When sterilized soil was seeded with known numbers of B. longicaudatus, 60% of second-stage juveniles and 68-76% of other stages were recovered. Most stages of B. longicaudatus could be extracted from these soils by sieving plus Baermann incubation with an efficiency of 60-70%.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619192; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283162</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283162</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619192</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3570</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<a1>McGovern,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Extraction of Meloidogyne incognita from caladium corms</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>245</sp>
<op>248</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>extraction</k1>
<k1>corms</k1>
<k1>Caladium bicolor</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1999. v. 29 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22042605</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3516</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Compost and Maize Cultivars on Plant-parasitic Nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>731</sp>
<op>736</op>
<ab>Effects of yard waste compost and maize (Zea mays) cultivar on population densities of plant-parasitic nematodes were examined in four experiments in north Florida. In one experiment, eight maize cultivars were evaluated; the other three experiments involved split-plot designs with compost treatments as main plots and maize cultivars as subplots. The three compost treatments used in these experiments were: 269 mt/ha of a yard-waste compost applied to the soil surface as a mulch, 269 mt/ha of compost incolporated into the soil, and an unamended control. No interactions between compost treatment and cultivar occurred in any experiment. Effects of compost treatment on Mesocriconema spp., Meloidogyne incognita, and Pratylenchus spp. were inconsistent, whereas significant effects of compost on population densities of Paratrichodorus minor were found on four of six sampling occasions. Cultivar affected final population densities (Pf) of M. incognita. In two tests, Pf of M. incognita on a Florida subtropical experimental hybrid (Howard III) were only 36% and 23% of Pf on the standard tropical hybrid (Pioneer Brand X304C). In an integrated approach to management of nematodes in maize, the effects of compost amendment and culfivar choice acted independently. Apparently, cultivar choice is more important than amendment with yard waste compost for management of M. incognita population levels in a maize rotation crop.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619831; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274277</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274277</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619831</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3520</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of yard waste compost on nematode densities and maize yield</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>655</sp>
<op>660</op>
<ab>The effects of a yard waste compost on densities of plant-parasitic nematodes and forage yield of maize (Zea mays) were determined over three seasons in two sites in north Florida. In each test, the experimental design was a randomized complete block with five replications and three treatments: 269 mt/ha of a yard waste compost C:N ratio = 35:1 to 46:1) applied to the soil surface as a mulch, 269 mt/ha of compost incorporated into the soil, and an unamended control. Of the nematodes found in these sites, Paratrichodorus minor was affected most by compost treatments, with densities at harvest reduced by a compost treatment on at least one sampling date in all three seasons (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05). Meloidogyne incognita was not consistently affected by compost application. Densities of Criconemella spp. and Pratylenchus spp. were reduced by compost treatment much more often in the third season than in the first two seasons of the study (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05). Forage yield of maize was increased (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) by both compost treatments in every test, with yield increases ranging from 10% to 212% over yield levels in unamended control plots and varying with season (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05). Use of yard waste compost on agricultural sites may provide a beneficial amendment for crop production and a convenient means for disposal of a common waste product from urban areas. Effects of this compost with high C:N ratio on nematodes were long-term, often not appearing until the third season of the study.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619736; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277191</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277191</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619736</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3575</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Cultural practices improve crop tolerance to nematodes</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>53</sp>
<op>60</op>
<k1>Cucurbita pepo</k1>
<k1>Abelmoschus esculentus</k1>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>Pratylenchus</k1>
<k1>Mesocriconema</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>composts</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>efficacy</k1>
<k1>crop establishment</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<k1>F110</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1995. v. 25 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20498515</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3524</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of yard waste compost on plant-parasitic nematode densities in vegetable crops</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>545</sp>
<op>549</op>
<ab>The effects of yard-waste compost on densities of plant-parasitic nematodes were determined on four crops at two sites in north Florida. Separate experiments were conducted with sweet corn (Zea mays), cowpea (Vigna unguiculata), yellow squash (Cucurbita pepo), and okra (Hibiscus esculentus). In each test, the design was a randomized complete block replicated four times and involving three treatments: 269 mt/ha yard-waste compost applied to the soil surface as a mulch, 269 mt/ha compost incorporated into the soil, and an unamended control. Final population densities of Criconemella spp. and Meloidogyne incognita were lower in plots receiving a compost treatment than in unamended control plots in only one of eight tests (P  0.10). Vegetable yields were either unaffected by treatment or, in some tests, were lowest following the mulch treatment (P &amp;lt;/= 0.10). Results indicate that the yard-waste compost used had little effect on densities of plant-parasitic nematodes associated with short-term (ca. 4 months) vegetable crops.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619647; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277320</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277320</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619647</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3527</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of tillage and crop residue management on nematode densities on corn</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>4 Suppl</is>
<sp>669</sp>
<op>674</op>
<ab>Effects of winter cover crop management on nematode densities associated with a subsequent corn (Zea mays) crop were examined in five sites in north Florida. Two sites had received winter cover crops of lupine (Lupinus angustifolius), and one site each had rye (Secale cereale), hairy vetch (Vicia villosa), and crimson clover (Trifolium incarnatum). In each site, five different management regimes were compared: 1) conventional tillage after the cover crop was removed for forage; 2) conventional tillage with the cover crop retained as green manure; 3) no-till with the cover crop mowed and used as a mulch; 4) no-till with the cover crop removed as forage; and 5) fallow. Sites were sampled at corn planting and harvest for estimates of initial (Pi) and final (Pf) nematode population densities, respectively. Whether the cover crop was removed as forage or retained as green manure or mulch had no effect (P &amp;gt; 0.10) on population densities of any plant-parasitic nematode before or after corn at any site. Differences between conventional-till and no-till treatments were significant (P &amp;lt;/= 0.10) only in one experiment for Paratrichodorus minor and two experiments for Pratylenchus spp. Compared with other treatments, fallow reduced (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) Pi of P. minor in two of three cases and Pf of Meloidogyne incognita in one of five sites, but enhanced soil Pf of Pratylenchus spp. in three of five sites. Tillage practices and management of cover crop residues had little consistent effect on nematodes, and these practices should be considered based on agronomic benefits rather than for nematode management.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619568; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279946</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279946</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619568</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3532</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of crop rotation and tillage on nematode densities in tropical corn</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>4 Suppl</is>
<sp>814</sp>
<op>819</op>
<ab>Effects of tillage and crop rotation on nematode densities in tropical corn (Zea mays cv. Pioneer X304C) were examined in a factorial experiment with two rotation crops and two tillage practices (no-till vs. conventional-till), conducted in each of three seasons (1990-1992) in north Florida. The rotation treatments consisted of sorghum (Sorghum bicolor cv. DeKalb BR64) or soybean (Glycine max) grown during the 1989 season. Densities of Meloidogyne incognita (race 1) remained lower throughout the growing season in corn following sorghum than in corn plots following soybean. This effect was observed clearly even in the third consecutive corn crop. In 1990, densities of Criconemella spp. were initially higher in plots planted to sorghum the previous year, but by the end of the subsequent corn crop, no differences were evident. Paratrichodorus minor and Pratylenchus spp. (primarily P. scribneri) were mostly unaffected by the crop rotation treatments, but in a few instances, Pratylenchus spp. densities were higher in conventional than in no-till plots. In general, tillage had little effect on densities of most nematodes examined, and rotation appears to be more important than tillage for managing plant-parasitic nematodes under these conditions.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619441; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279846</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279846</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619441</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3535</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Population Dynamics of Plant-parasitic Nematodes on Cover Crops of Corn and Sorghum</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>446</sp>
<op>453</op>
<ab>Buildup of plant-parasitic nematode populations on corn (Zea mays), soybean (Glycine max), and sorghum (Sorghum bicolor) were compared in 1991 and 1992. Final population densities (Pf) of Meloidogyne incognita were lower following sorghum than after soybean in both seasons, and Pf after sorghum was lower than Pf after corn in 1992. In both seasons, Pf differed among the sorghum cultivars used. No differences in Pf on corn, sorghum, and soybean were observed for Criconemella spp. (a mixture of C. sphaerocephala and C. ornata) or Paratrichodorus minor in either season. Pf levels of Pratylenchus spp. (a mixture of P. brachyurus and P. scribneri) were greatest after corn in 1992, but no differences with crop treatments were observed in 1991. When data from field tests conducted with corn and sorghum during the past four seasons were pooled, negative linear relationships between ln(Pf/Pi) and ln(Pi) were observed for Criconemella spp. and P. minor on each crop, and for M. incognita on corn (Pi = initial population density). Although ln(Pf/Pi) and ln(Pi) were not related for M. incognita with pooled sorghum data, separate relationships were derived for various sorghum cultivars. Regression equations from pooled data were used to obtain estimates of equilibrium density and maximum reproductive rate, and these estimates were used to construct models expressing nematode Pf across a range of initial densities. Many of these models were robust, encompassing a range of sites, season, crop cultivars, and planting dates. Quadratic models derived from pooled field data provided an alternative method for expressing Pf as a function of Pi.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619400; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279793</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279793</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619400</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3537</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Comparison of nematode population densities on six summer crops at seven sites in north Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>699</sp>
<op>706</op>
<ab>Densities of plant-parasitic nematodes were compared on six crops grown for forage during the summer of 1991 at seven sites in north central Florida. The cropping treatments were &amp;#39;Howard&amp;#39; soybean (Glycine max), &amp;#39;Deltapine 105&amp;#39; soybean, velvetbean (Mucuna deeringiana), &amp;#39;California Blackeye #5&amp;#39; cowpea (Vigna unguiculata), &amp;#39;Pioneer 3098&amp;#39; tropical corn (Zea mays), and &amp;#39;Asgrow Chaparral&amp;#39; sorghum (Sorghum bicolor). Highest final densities (Pf) of Meloidogyne incognita and Criconemella spp. were obtained following corn or sorghum at most sites. The lowest Pf of M. incognita occurred after velvetbean at all seven sites, but Pf after cowpea were equivalent to Pf after velvetbean at four of seven sites. Cultivar choice is critical in planning rotations to suppress M. incognita because results obtained here and elsewhere have shown great differences among sorghum and cowpea cultivars. The Pf of Pratylenchus spp. were lowest following velvetbean at four of seven sites. There were no differences in densities of Paratrichodorus minor among crops, but populations increased at a greater rate if initial density (Pi) was low. Multiplication rates (Pf/Pi) of most nematode species on most crops varied inversely with Pi. An accurate impression of nematode multiplication and host status could not be obtained unless a range of Pi was examined.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2629877; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283048</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283048</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2629877</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3542</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Nematode population changes and forage yields of six corn and sorghum cultivars</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>673</sp>
<op>677</op>
<ab>Two temperate corn (Zea mays) hybrids (Pioneer 3320 and Northrup King 508), two tropical corn cultivars (Pioneer X304C hybrid and Florida SYN-1 experimental open pollinated cultivar), the sorghum (Sorghum bicolor) x sudangrass (Sorghum sudanense) hybrid DeKalb SX-17, and the sorghum hybrid DeKalb FS25E were compared for effect on nematode densities and forage yield in three plantings (one single-crop and one double-crop system) in Florida. Final population densities of Meloidogyne incognita in the three plantings ranged from 0 to 13/100 cm(3) soil on the two Sorghum spp. and were lower (P &amp;lt;/= 0.001) than those obtained on the corn cultivars (range 147 to 762/100 cm(3) soil). Early planted temperate corn and sorghum generally gave higher forage yields than did tropical corn. As second crops in double-cropping systems, tropical corn cultivars generally produced greater yields than temperate corn hybrids did. At 35% dry matter, double crop forage corn yield ranged from 51.1 to 64.8 ton/ha, and sorghum ranged from 79.8 to 102.2 ton/ ha. Tropical corn, forage sorghum, and sorghum-sudangrass were profitably grown at all planting dates. Late summer planting of temperate corn was unprofitable. DeKalb SX-17 sorghum x sudangrass first crop plus the ratoon double crop gave the highest net return of $1,133/ha. Among the corn cultivars, Florida SYN-1 gave the highest double crop net return of $652/ha.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619199; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283183</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283183</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619199</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3580</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Littell,R. C.</a1>
<t1>Probability of detecting nematode infestations in quarantine samples</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>177</sp>
<op>181</op>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>quarantine</k1>
<k1>probability analysis</k1>
<k1>quality controls</k1>
<k1>certification</k1>
<k1>infestation</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1993. v. 23 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20380434</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3505</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>McGovern,R. J.</a1>
<t1>Effects of solarization and ammonium amendments on plant-parasitic nematodes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>537</sp>
<op>541</op>
<ab>The effects of soil solarization and ammonium bicarbonate or ammonium sulfate against plant-parasitic nematodes on yellow squash (Cucurbita pepo) and on vinca (Catharanthus roseus) were evaluated at two sites. Solarization for 3 weeks in the spring suppressed population levels of Belonolaimus longicaudatus, Criconemella spp., and Dolichodorus heterocephalus throughout the growing season on both crops at both sites. Levels of Meloidogyne incognita were suppressed initially, but population densities increased by the end of the crop in several cases. In one site, numbers of Paratrichodorus minor resurged following solarization to levels that were greater than those present in unsolarized control plots. The effect of solarization was not enhanced by combination with ammonium amendments, but, in one site, application of ammonium bicarbonate or ammonium sulfate resulted in lower numbers of B. longicaudatus than in the unamended control. Additional research and improved efficacy of candidate amendments are required before they can be successfully integrated with solarization for nematode management. Efficacy of solarization against plant-parasitic nematodes was achieved despite a relatively short (3 weeks) solarization period.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620486; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19271007</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19271007</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620486</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3588</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Hair,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematodes associated with the edible aroid genera Xanthosoma and Colocasia and their effects on yield</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>165</sp>
<op>180</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F110</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1983. v. 13 (2); Literature review; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND84071771</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3589</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Hair,S. K.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematodes of cassava, Manihot esculenta Crantz</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>261</sp>
<op>287</op>
<k1>tropics</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1983. v. 13 (2); Literature review; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND84071779</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3569</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Ozores-Hampton,M.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Conner,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Nematode management, soil fertility, and yield in organic vegetable production</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>205</sp>
<op>213</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>pest management</k1>
<k1>soil solarization</k1>
<k1>composts</k1>
<k1>crop rotation</k1>
<k1>Capsicum annuum</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>crop yield</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>organic production</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>organic amendments</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F110</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1999. v. 29 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22042567</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3586</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematode losses during centrifugal extraction from two soil types</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>147</sp>
<op>161</op>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>centrifugation</k1>
<k1>extraction</k1>
<k1>losses from soil</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>sandy loam soils</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>marl soils</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1987. v. 17 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND90011414</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3587</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematode losses during sieving from two soil types</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>17</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>125</sp>
<op>146</op>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>losses from soil</k1>
<k1>sieving</k1>
<k1>sandy loam soils</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>marl soils</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1987. v. 17 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND90011423</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3555</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Nematode persistence after fumigation: a methodological problem</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>209</sp>
<op>211</op>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618374; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19295903</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19295903</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618374</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3591</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Error estimates for nematode soil samples composed of cores of unequal sizes Phytonematodes, soil fauna, Florida</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>27</sp>
<op>36</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J100</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1983. v. 13 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND83092486</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3590</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Influence of summer management strategies on nematode populations in a subtropical agroecosystem Crop pests, fallow, weed hosts, Florida</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1983</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>13</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>8</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1983. v. 13 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND83092483</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3556</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Estimating relative error in nematode numbers from single soil samples composed of multiple cores</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Oct</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>522</sp>
<op>529</op>
<ab>Spatial distributions of several species of plant-parasitic nematodes were determined in each of three fallow vegetable fields and in smaller subunits of those fields. Goodness of fit to each of several theoretical distributions was tested hy means of a X(2) test. Distributions for most species showed good agreement with a negative binomial model. An exception occurred with Crictmemella sp., which showed a better fit to the Neyman Type A distribution. For nematodes distributed according to the negative binomial model, the number of cores per composite sample needed to achieve specified relative errors was calculated. For a given nematode species, such as Quinisulcius actus (Allen) Siddiqi or Meloidogyne incognita (Kofoid &amp;amp;White) Chitwood, the k values for the negative binomial distribution increased as field size decreased, with the result that fewer cores were needed to achieve the same level of precision in a smaller field. Best results were achieved when the single sample was used to estimate populations in fields of 0.25-0.45 ha in size. When using only a single composite sample to estimate mixed populations of the nematodes studied here in a field of that size, approximately 22 cores per composite sample would be needed to estimate all population means within a standard error to mean ratio of 25%. Considerably, more cores were needed to maintain a given level of precision in fields of 1.0 ha or greater, and it may be necessary to subdivide larger unils (ca. 1.5 ha and up) for accurate sampling.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618208; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19295747</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19295747</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618208</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3593</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Plans for the collection of nematode soil samples from fruit groves Avocado, guava, mango, Tahiti lime, Florida</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>257</sp>
<op>267</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1982. v. 12 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND83090700</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3592</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<t1>Spatial arrangement of nematodes around four species of tropical fruit trees Avocado, guava, mango, Tahiti lime, Florida</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>255</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1982. v. 12 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND83090699</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3595</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Goldweber,S.</a1>
<t1>Plant-parasitic nematodes associated with mango and relationship to tree condition</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1981</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>9</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 1981. v. 11 (1); 11 ref&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<an>IND81076608</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3554</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Parrado,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Tyson,R. V.</a1>
<a1>Reynolds,J. S.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Criconemella onoensis on Potato</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1987</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>19</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>228</sp>
<op>232</op>
<ab>Criconemella onoensis (Luc) Luc and Raski increased to high (458-1,290/100 cm(3)) soil population densities in four fields planted to cover crops of sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench x S. arundinaceum (Desv.) Stapf var. sudanense (Stapf) Hitchc. &amp;#39;Funk FP-4&amp;#39;) during the summer of 1984 in southeastern Florida. Three pathogenicity tests conducted in the greenhouse with C. onoensis on potato (Solanum tuberosum L. &amp;#39;La Rouge&amp;#39;) using three different methods (inoculation, chemical treatment of infested soil, or pasteurization of infested soil) revealed no significant (P = 0.10) differences in plant growth, despite significant (P = 0.05) differences in population densities of C. onoensis between treated and control pots in each test. In these three tests, the maximum initial density of C. onoensis used was 720/100 cm(3) soil and the maximum final density was 686/100 cm(3) soil. Application of 933 liters/ha of Vapam to a field site with a pretreatment density of 1,120 C. onoensis/100 cm(3) soil significantly (P = 0.05) reduced populations compared with untreated control plots, but yields remained higher in control plots. Apparently C. onoensis has no significant effect on potato growth at the population densities tested.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618634; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19290134</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19290134</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618634</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3565</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Porazinska,D. L.</a1>
<t1>Elements of sustainable agriculture</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>9</op>
<k1>farming systems</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>agroecosystems</k1>
<k1>sustainability</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. June 2001. v. 31 (1); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND23242022</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3574</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Stansly,P. A.</a1>
<a1>Noling,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Obreza,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Conner,J. M.</a1>
<t1>Impact of organic soil amendments and fumigation on plant-parasitic nematodes in a southwest Florida vegetable field</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>181</sp>
<op>198</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>Criconemoides</k1>
<k1>Hemicycliophora</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>composts</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide</k1>
<k1>soil fumigation</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>Lycopersicon esculentum</k1>
<k1>crop management</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>methyl bromide alternatives</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<k1>F110</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1997. v. 27 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND21985089</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3558</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Waddill,V. H.</a1>
<t1>Partitioning yield loss on yellow squash into nematode and insect components</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<fd>Jan</fd>
<vo>14</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>110</sp>
<op>118</op>
<ab>The effect of a contplex of several insect and nematode pests on yield of yellow squash (Cucurbita pepo L.) was examined in two field tests in southern Florida. Applications of permethrin for insect control and oxamyl primarily for nematode control plus some insect control were made alone and in combination to achieve differential reduction of various insect and nematode components contributing to yield loss. The effect of these components on yield was further analyzed by multiple regression. Yield losses in weight of small fruit to nematode and insect pests together were estimated at 23.4% and 30.4% in each of the two tests, respectively. In the first test, this loss was attributed to the melonworm, Diaphania hyalinata, while in the second test, it was attributed to D. hyalinata and the nematodes Quinisulcius acutus and particularly Rotylenchulus reniforrnis. D. hyalinata accounted for further losses of 9.0% and 10.3%, respectively, from direct damage to the fruit. Despite the presence of low levels of Diabrotica balteata, Liriomyza sativae, and Myzus persicae, yields were little affected by these pests. Prediction of yield loss by multiple regression analysis was more accurate when both insect and nematode populations were present in the plots than when nematodes alone were present.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2618141; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19295683</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19295683</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2618141</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3561</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Walter,DE</a1>
<t1>Comparison of soil extraction methods for nematodes and microarthropods</t1>
<jf>Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment</jf>
<jo>Agric.Ecosyst.Environ.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>201</sp>
<op>207</op>
<k1>Article Subject Terms: soil fauna</k1>
<k1>Article Taxonomic Terms: Arthropoda</k1>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>catching methods</k1>
<ab>Active extraction techniques, dependent on the behavior of soil animals, and passive techniques, dependent on specific gravity or sedimentation rate, are widely used in the extraction of both nematodes and microarthropods. No method is completely suitable for extraction of both nematodes and microarthropods. Since no extraction method is 100% efficient, the estimation of extraction efficiency can provide a basis for evaluating extraction performance and comparing results of different methods.</ab>
<no>RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<t2>Symposium on Modern Techniques in Soil Ecology, Athens, GA (USA), 1-4 Feb 1991</t2>
<sn>0167-8809</sn>
<ad>Nematol. Lab., Build. 78, 0611-IFAS, Univ. Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611-0611, USA</ad>
<an>2698925</an>
<la>English; English</la>
<cl>D 04002 Surveying and remote sensing; Z 05156 Techniques; D 04600 Soil; D 04659 Insects; D 04660 Arachnids; D 04665 Crustaceans; D 04656 Nematodes; Z 05209 Soil entomology</cl>
<sf>Journal Article; Conference; Entomology Abstracts; Ecology Abstracts</sf>
<db>Biological Sciences</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3564</id>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>Frederick,J. J.</a1>
<t1>Host suitability of caladium varieties to Meloidogyne incognita</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>97</sp>
<op>101</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>root-knot nematodes</k1>
<k1>host plants</k1>
<k1>Caladium bicolor</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>varietal resistance</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>germplasm evaluation</k1>
<k1>potted foliage plants</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<no>Nematropica. 2004 June, v. 34, no. 1; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND43670829</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://purl.fcla.edu/fcla/nematropica</lk>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3568</id>
<a1>Perez,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Correlation between Paratrichodorus minor population levels and corky ringspot symptoms on potato</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>247</sp>
<op>251</op>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>Paratrichodorus minor</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>Tobacco rattle virus</k1>
<k1>incidence</k1>
<k1>planting date</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>disease control</k1>
<k1>plant diseases and disorders</k1>
<k1>disease incidence</k1>
<k1>disease severity</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F833</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 2000. v. 30 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22792541</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3506</id>
<a1>Perez,E. E.</a1>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Niche Distribution of Paratrichodorus minor and Belonolaimus longicaudatus Following Fumigation on Potato and Cabbage</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>343</sp>
<op>348</op>
<ab>An experiment was conducted to determine population changes and niche variation in the soil at two depths (0 to 20 cm and 20 to 40 cm) of Paratrichodorus minor and Belonolaimus longicaudatus populations following fumigation. Eight plots each of potato (Solanum tuberosum) and cabbage (Brassica oleracea var. capitata), fumigated with 1, 3-dichloropropene or nonfumigated, were established. Eight plots of sorghum-sudangrass hybrid (Sorghum bicolor x S. arundinaceum var. sudanense) were also used to monitor depth distribution (0 to 20 cm and 20 to 40 cm) of B. longicaudatus and P. minor following each cabbage/potato season. Soil samples were taken 0 to 20 cm and 20 to 40 cm deep during the potato/cabbage, and sorghum-sudangrass growing seasons. During the 1993-94 and 1994-95 potato/cabbage seasons, P. minor was found at highest numbers at 20 to 40 cm, whereas numbers of B. longicaudatus were highest at 0 to 20 cm. During the 1994 and 1995 sorghum-sudangrass growing seasons, B. longicaudatus numbers were highest at 0 to 20 cm. Paratrichodorus minor numbers were highest at 0 to 20 cm and at 20 to 40 cm deep in the 1994 and 1995 sorghum-sudangrass growing seasons, respectively. Reduction by soil fumigation of B. longicaudatus at 0 to 20 cm deep did not affect depth distribution or cause P. minor populations to increase in potato or cabbage plots. Paratrichodorus minor numbers increased at 20 to 40 cm deep in the 1994-95 cabbage season after soil fumigation.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620474; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19270987</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19270987</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620474</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2309</id>
<a1>Pimentel,David</a1>
<t1>Encyclopedia of pest management</t1>
<yr>2002</yr>
<sp>929</sp>
<k1>Pesticide resistance</k1>
<k1>Pests -- Biological control</k1>
<k1>Pests -- Control</k1>
<no>edited by David Pimentel. : edited by David Pimentel.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<pb>Marcel Dekker</pb>
<pp>New York</pp>
<sn>0824706323; 0824706323 (alk. paper)</sn>
<cn>SB950.7.E53 2002 (SCIENCE LIBRARY Reference)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2304</id>
<a1>Ploetz,Randy C.</a1>
<t1>Compendium of tropical fruit diseases</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<sp>88</sp>
<k1>Tropical fruit -- Diseases and pests</k1>
<k1>Tropical fruit -- Diseases and pests -- Handbooks, manuals, etc</k1>
<no>edited by R.C. Ploetz ... [et al.]. : edited by R.C. Ploetz ... [et al.].; Series note: Disease compendium series of the American Phytopathological Society; Series note: The Disease compendium series of the American Phytopathological Society; 50411 Includes bibliographical references and index.</no>
<t2>Disease compendium series.</t2>
<pb>APS Press</pb>
<pp>St. Paul, Minn.</pp>
<sn>0890541620</sn>
<cn>SB608.F8C641 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Belle Glade); SB731.A36T8 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Lake Alfred); SB608.F8C641 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Ft. Pierce); SB608.F8 C4 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Immokalee); SB608.F8C64 1994 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB 608 .F8C(TRUNCATED)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3594</id>
<a1>Pohronezny,K.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Meloidogyne-fungal complexes in tomato roots in calcareous soils</t1>
<jf>Nematologia mediterranea</jf>
<yr>1981</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>151</sp>
<op>157</op>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F831</k1>
<no>Nematologia mediterranea. Dec 1981. v. 9 (2); Includes 11 ref&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0391-9749</sn>
<an>IND82042037</an>
<la>English</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL QL391.N4N42</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3515</id>
<a1>Porazinska,D. L.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Graham,J. H.</a1>
<a1>Wheaton,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Parsons,L. R.</a1>
<t1>Nematode Community Composition under Various Irrigation Schemes in a Citrus Soil Ecosystem</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>170</sp>
<op>178</op>
<ab>Interest in the sustainability of farming practices has increased in response to environmental problems associated with conventional agricultural management often adopted for the production of herbaceous crops, ornamentals, and fruit crops. Availability of measures of the status of the soil ecosystem is of immediate importance, particularly for environmental assessment and monitoring programs. This study investigated the effects of various irrigation regimes (an example of an agricultural management practice) on the structure of the nematode fauna in a citrus orchard in the sandy ridge area of Central Florida. Ecological measures such as community structure indices, diversity indices, and maturity indices were assessed and related to irrigation intensity. Maturity index was an effective measure in distinguishing differences between irrigation regimes, whereas other indices of community structure were not. Of various nematode genera and trophic groups, only omnivores and the omnivore genera. Aporcelaimellus and Eudorylaimus responded to irrigation treatments.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620287; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274207</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274207</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620287</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3572</id>
<a1>Porazinska,L.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Duncan,L. W.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<a1>Wheaton,T. A.</a1>
<a1>Parsons,L. R.</a1>
<t1>Relationships between soil chemical status, soil nematode community, and sustainability indices</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>249</sp>
<op>262</op>
<k1>free-living nematodes</k1>
<k1>bioindicators</k1>
<k1>irrigation</k1>
<k1>soil chemistry</k1>
<k1>Citrus</k1>
<k1>sustainable agriculture</k1>
<k1>soil ecology</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>sustainability</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<k1>J100</k1>
<k1>P210</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1998. v. 28 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22038471</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3545</id>
<a1>Powers,L. E.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Size Differences Among Root-knot Nematodes on Resistant and Susceptible Alyceclover Genotypes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>Apr</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>243</sp>
<op>248</op>
<ab>The influence of plant resistance on the size of individual root-knot nematodes was determined in greenhouse experiments. Five genotypes of alyceclover were inoculated with second-stage juveniles of Meloidogyne incognita race 3 or M. arenaria race 1. Plants were harvested at selected intervals and stained for detection of the nematodes, which were dissected from the roots. Length, width, and sagittal-sectional area of each animal were measured using an image-analysis system, and areas of nematodes in all stages were compared at different times and across alyceclover lines. Nematodes feeding on roots of resistant lines were consistently smaller than those on susceptible plants, with significant differences in growth detected after the final molt. Similar results were observed with both nematode species.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619158; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19283120</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19283120</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619158</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3576</id>
<a1>Powers,L. E.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Soil nematode community structure in two tropical pastures</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>24</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>133</sp>
<op>141</op>
<k1>free-living nematodes</k1>
<k1>species diversity</k1>
<k1>trophic relationships</k1>
<k1>soil water content</k1>
<k1>grassland soils</k1>
<k1>subtropics</k1>
<k1>tropics</k1>
<k1>seasonal variation</k1>
<k1>community ecology</k1>
<k1>Honduras</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>J100</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1994. v. 24 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20478028</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3536</id>
<a1>Powers,L. E.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Energetics of Meloidogyne incognita on Resistant and Susceptible Alyceclover Genotypes</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>257</sp>
<op>264</op>
<ab>To determine the energy cost of a population of Meloidogyne incognita on the roots of alyceclover, nematode biomass was estimated and equations in the literature were used to calculate energy budgets. Amounts of energy consumed, respired, or used in production of nematode biomass were calculated. Results suggested that severe infestations of root-knot nematodes can remove significant quantities of energy from their hosts. Over a 36-day period, a population of 2.6 females of M. incognita per root system removed less than 0.4 calories of energy from a resistant alyceclover plant but over 11 calories were removed by 28 females from a susceptible alyceclover. The calculations indicate that on the resistant alyceclover line, 53% of the energy assimilated by the root-knot population was allocated to respiration, with only 47% allocated to production, whereas on the susceptible line, 65% of the assimilated energy was allocated to production. Such energy demands by the parasite could result in significant reductions in yield quantity and quality at a field production level.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619363; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279766</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279766</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619363</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3534</id>
<a1>Powers,L. E.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of mixed cropping on a soil nematode community in honduras</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>25</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>666</sp>
<op>673</op>
<ab>Nematode-resistant tropical legumes are effective in reducing populations of plant-parasitic nematodes when used in rotation systems. Mixed cropping is a common practice of many small farmers in Central America, but little is known about the effects of tropical legumes on nematode communities under these systems. To examine the effects of intercropping on the nematode fauna associated with squash (Cucurbita pepo) and cucumber (Cucumis sativa) in Honduras, two field experiments were conducted to compare nematode density and diversity in soil under cucurbits grown as a monocrop with that in soil under cucurbits intercropped with alfalfa (Medicago sativa) or hairy indigo (Indigofera hirsuta). A parallel series of field tests compared soil nematode communities associated with a cucurbit monocrop and a cucurbit intercropped with marigold (Tagetes patula), which may decrease nematode populations through the production of toxic root exudates. Among all four tests, over a period of 90 days, there were no consistent differences in densities of various nematode genera or trophic groups in intercropped versus monocropped plants, nor were there consistent differences in community diversities among treatments.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619433; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19279824</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19279824</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619433</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2294</id>
<a1>Powers,Laura E.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Ecological principles of agriculture</t1>
<yr>2000</yr>
<sp>433</sp>
<k1>Agricultural ecology</k1>
<no>Laura E. Powers, Robert McSorley. : Laura E. Powers, Robert McSorley.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references.</no>
<pb>Delmar</pb>
<pp>Albany, NY</pp>
<sn>0766806537</sn>
<cn>S589.7.P69 2000 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2133</id>
<a1>Powers,Laura E.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,Robert,</a1>
<a1>Pozuelo,Alfredo</a1>
<t1>Principios ecolgicos en agricultura</t1>
<yr>2001</yr>
<no>ID: 52497694</no>
<pb>International Thomson : Paraninfo</pb>
<pp>Madrid; Mxico</pp>
<sn>842832784X 9788428327848</sn>
<la>Spanish</la>
<db>/z-wcorg/</db>
<ds>http://worldcat.org</ds>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3513</id>
<a1>Ritzinger,C. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Castor and Velvetbean Organic Amendments on Meloidogyne arenaria in Greenhouse Experiments</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>624</sp>
<op>631</op>
<ab>Effectiveness of castor (Ricinus communis) and velvetbean (Mucuna deeringiana) amendments was tested for suppression of the root-knot nematode (Meloidogyne arenaria) and growth of okra (Hibiscus esculentus) in three greenhouse experiments. Regression analysis was used to relate nematode population data or plant growth responses to various rates (0, 1, 2, 4, or 8 g/560 cm(3) soil pot) of each amendment in separate experiments. In general, plant growth parameters responded positively to the amendment rate until a level of about 4 g to 5 g of velvetbean or castor amendment/pot. Similar trends were observed for nematode galls, egg masses, and second-stage juveniles extracted from root systems. In most circumstances, quadratic equations best expressed the relationships between plant or nematode parameters and rates of velvetbean or castor amendment, leading to the assumption that a best rate of the amendment for plant growth or nematode suppression can be predicted. In a third experiment, in which both amendments were compared directly, velvetbean amendment was more efficient than castor in suppressing nematodes as well as in improving plant growth.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620327; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274257</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274257</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620327</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3514</id>
<a1>Ritzinger,C. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Meloidogyne arenaria and Mulch Type on Okra in Microplot Experiments</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>4S</is>
<sp>616</sp>
<op>623</op>
<ab>The effects of perennial peanut (Arachis glabrata) hay, an aged yard-waste compost (mainly woodchips), and a control treatment without amendment were determined on two population levels of root-knot (Melaidogyne arenaria) nematode over three consecutive years in field microplots. Okra (Hibiscus esculentus, susceptible to the root-knot nematode) and a rye (Secale cereale) cover crop (poor nematode host) were used in the summer and winter seasons, respectively. The organic amendment treatments affected plant growth parameters. In the first year, okra yields were greatest in peanut-amended plots. Yield differences with amendment treatment diminished in the second and third years. Okra plant height, total fruit weight, and fruit number were greater with the lower population level of the root-knot nematode. Residual levels of nutrients in soil were greater where root-knot nematode levels and damage were higher and plant growth was poor. Nutrient levels affected the growth of a subsequent rye cover crop.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620323; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274256</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274256</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620323</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3571</id>
<a1>Ritzinger,C. H. S. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Effect of fresh and dry organic amendments on Meloidogyne arenaria in greenhouse experiments</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>173</sp>
<op>185</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne arenaria</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>greenhouse production</k1>
<k1>organic amendments</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1998. v. 28 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND22038457</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3508</id>
<a1>Smith,H. A.</a1>
<a1>Koenig,R. L.</a1>
<a1>McAuslane,H. J.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Effect of silver reflective mulch and a summer squash trap crop on densities of immature Bemisia argentifolii (Homoptera: Aleyrodidae) on organic bean</t1>
<jf>Journal of economic entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Econ.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>Jun</fd>
<vo>93</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>726</sp>
<op>731</op>
<k1>Animals</k1>
<k1>Crops, Agricultural</k1>
<k1>Cucurbitaceae</k1>
<k1>Fabaceae/virology</k1>
<k1>Female</k1>
<k1>Geminiviridae</k1>
<k1>Hemiptera</k1>
<k1>Insect Control/methods</k1>
<k1>Plants, Medicinal</k1>
<k1>Polyethylene</k1>
<k1>Population Density</k1>
<k1>Silver</k1>
<ab>Polyethylene mulch with a reflective silver stripe and a yellow summer squash, Cucurbita pepo L., trap crop were tested alone and in combination as tactics to reduce densities of Bemisia argentifolii Bellows &amp;amp; Perring eggs and nymphs, and incidence of bean golden mosaic geminivirus on snap bean, Phaseolus vulgaris L. Egg densities were consistently higher on squash than on bean, but egg densities and virus incidence were not lower on bean grown with squash than on bean grown in monoculture. Silver reflective mulch reduced egg densities compared with bean grown on bare ground during the first week after crop emergence for 2 of the 3 yr that the study was conducted. However, egg suppression by silver mulch was not enhanced by the presence of a squash trap crop when both tactics were combined. The obstacles to suppressing B. argentifolii through the use of trap crops are discussed.</ab>
<no>LR: 20061115; JID: 2985127R; 7440-22-4 (Silver); 9002-88-4 (Polyethylene); ppublish</no>
<pp>UNITED STATES</pp>
<sn>0022-0493; 0022-0493</sn>
<ad>Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Gainesville 32611, USA.</ad>
<an>PMID: 10902322</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article; Research Support, U.S. Gov&#39;t, Non-P.H.S.; IM</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>10902322</pmid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Whole</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2300</id>
<a1>Southern Regional Tropical Corn Symposium</a1>
<a1>Brown,Elston</a1>
<a1>Foundation for Agronomic Research</a1>
<a1>Potash &amp; Phosphate Institute</a1>
<a1>Teare,I. D.</a1>
<t1>The Southern Regional Tropical Corn Symposium</t1>
<yr>1991</yr>
<sp>72</sp>
<k1>Corn -- Southern States -- Congresses</k1>
<no>sponsored by North Florida Research &amp;amp; Education Center, Pioneer Hi-Bred International, Inc. ; edited by Iwan D. Teare, Elston Brown. : sponsored by North Florida Research &amp;amp; Education Center, Pioneer Hi-Bred International, Inc. ; edited by Iwan D. Teare, Elston Brown.; Alternate title: Proceedings, Southern Regional Tropical Corn Symposium.; 50011 Cover title: Proceedings, Southern Regional Tropical Corn Symposium, Quincy, Florida, June 27-28, 1991.; 50412 Includes bibliographical references (p. 66-69).</no>
<t2>PPI/FAR technical bulletin ; 1991-3</t2>
<pb>Potash &amp; Phosphate Institute PPI ; Foundation for Agronomic Research FAR in cooperation with the Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida</pb>
<pp>Atlanta, Ga.</pp>
<cn>SB191.M2S681 1991 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB191.M2S681 1991 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3517</id>
<a1>Sydenham,G. M.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Temperature on Resistance in Phaseolus vulgaris Genotypes and on Development of Meloidogyne Species</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1997</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>90</sp>
<op>103</op>
<ab>Phaseolus vulgaris lines with heat-stable resistance to Meloidogyne spp. may be needed to manage root-knot nematodes in tropical regions. Resistance expression before and during the process of nematode penetration and development in resistant genotypes were studied at pre- and postinoculation temperatures of 24 degrees C and 24 degrees C, 24 degrees C and 28 degrees C, 28 degrees C and 24 degrees C, and 28 degrees C and 28 degrees C. Resistance was effective at all temperature regimes examined, with fewer nematodes in roots of a resistant line compared with a susceptible line. Preinoculation temperature did not modify resistance expression to later infections by root-knot nematodes. However, postinoculation temperatures affected development of Meloidogyne spp. in both the resistant and susceptible bean lines tested. The more rapid development of nematodes to adults at the higher postinoculation temperature of 28 degrees C in both bean lines suggests direct temperature effects on nematode development instead of on resistance expression of either of two gene systems. Also, resistance was stable at 30 degrees C and 32 degrees C.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619758; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19274137</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19274137</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619758</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3521</id>
<a1>Sydenham,G. M.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Dunn,R. A.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Resistance in Phaseolus vulgaris on Development of Meloidogyne Species</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>485</sp>
<op>491</op>
<ab>Use of resistant Phaseolus vulgaris germplasm has a potential role in limiting damaging effects of Meloidogyne spp. on bean production. Effects of two genetic resistance systems in common bean germptasm on penetration and development of Meloidogyne spp. were studied under growth room conditions at 22 degrees C to 25 degrees C. Nemasnap (gene system 1) and G1805 (gene system 2) were inoculated with second-stage juveniles (J2) of M. incognita race 2 and M. arenaria race 1, respectively; Black Valentine was used as the susceptible control. Up to 7 days after inoculation, there were no differences in numbers of M. incognita J2 penetrating roots of Black Valentine and Nemasnap; subsequently, more nematodes were present in Black Valentine roots (P &amp;lt; 0.05). More nematodes reached advanced stages of development in Black Valentine than in Nemasnap roots (P &amp;lt; 0.05). Total numbers of M. arenaria were greater in Black Valentine than in G 1805 roots from 14 days after inoculation (P &amp;lt; 0.05). Advanced stages of development occurred earlier and in greater numbers in Black Valentine plants than in G1805 plants. In these studies, resistance to M. incognita race 2 and M. arenaria race 1 in bean germplasm, which contain gene system 1 and gene system 2, respectively, was expressed by delayed nematode development rather than by differential penetration compared with susceptible plants.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2619713; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19277166</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19277166</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2619713</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3497</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Exposure Time to Lethal Temperatures for Meloidogyne incognita Suppression and Its Implication for Soil Solarization</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2008</yr>
<fd>Mar</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>7</sp>
<op>12</op>
<ab>Meloidogyne incognita eggs or J2 were incubated in test tubes containing sand:peat mix and immersed in a water bath heated to 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44 and 45 degrees C for a series of time intervals. Controls were maintained at 22 degrees C. Nematodes surviving or hatching were collected from Baermann trays after three weeks of incubation. Regression analyses between percent survival or egg hatch and hours of heat treatment were performed for each temperature. Complete suppression of egg hatch required 389.8, 164.5, 32.9, 19.7 and 13.1 hours at 38, 39, 40, 41 and 42 degrees C, respectively. Complete killing of J2 required 47.9, 46.2, 17.5 and 13.8 hours at 39, 40, 41 and 42 degrees C, respectively. J2 were not completely killed at 38 degrees C within 40 hours of treatment, but were killed within one hour at 44 and 45 degrees C. Effect of temperature on nematode killing is not determined by heat units. Oscillating temperature between cool and warm did not interfere with the nematode suppressive effect by the heat treatment. Six-week solarization in the field during the summers of 2003 and 2004 in Florida accumulated heat exposure times in the top 15 cm of soil that surpassed levels required to kill M. incognita as determined in the water bath experiments. Although near zero M. incognita were detected right after solarization, the nematode population densities increased after a cycle of a susceptible pepper crop. Therefore, future research should address failure of solarization to kill nematodes in the deeper soil layers.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2586528; 2007/11/19 [received]; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<ad>Department of Plant and Environmental Protection Sciences, University of Hawaii at Manoa, Honolulu, HI 96822 Department of Entomology and Nematology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611.</ad>
<an>PMID: 19259512</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19259512</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2586528</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3562</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Host status of several cut flower crops to the root-knot nematode, Meloidogyne incognita</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2005</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>45</sp>
<op>52</op>
<k1>Meloidogyne incognita</k1>
<k1>root-knot nematodes</k1>
<k1>races</k1>
<k1>host plants</k1>
<k1>ornamental plants</k1>
<k1>cut flowers</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>pest resistance</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>plant growth</k1>
<k1>plant tolerance</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<no>Nematropica. 2005 June, v. 35, no. 1; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND43781038</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://purl.fcla.edu/fcla/nematropica</lk>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3501</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Crotalaria juncea Amendment on Squash Infected with Meloidogyne incognita</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>290</sp>
<op>296</op>
<ab>Two greenhouse experiments were conducted to examine the effect of Crotalaria juncea amendment on Meloidogyne incognita population levels and growth of yellow squash (Cucurbita pepo). In the first experiment, four soils with a long history of receiving yard waste compost (YWC+), no-yard-waste compost (YWC-), conventional tillage, or no-tillage treatments were used; in the second experiment, only one recently cultivated soil was used. Half of the amount of each soil received air-dried residues of C. juncea as amendment before planting squash, whereas the other half did not. Crotalaria juncea amendment increased squash shoot and root weights in all soils tested, except in YWC+ soil where the organic matter content was high without the amendment. The amendment suppressed the numbers of M. incognita if the inoculum level was low, and when the soil contained relatively abundant nematode-antagonistic fungi. Microwaved soil resulted in greater numbers of M. incognita and free-living nematodes than frozen or untreated soil, indicating nematode-antagonistic microorganisms played a role in nematode suppression. The effects of C. juncea amendment on nutrient cycling were complex. Amendment with C. juncea increased the abundance of free-living nematodes and Harposporium anguillulae, a fungus antagonistic to them in the second experiment but not in the first experiment. Soil histories, especially long-term yard waste compost treatments that increased soil organic matter, can affect the performance of C. juncea amendment.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620769; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262819</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262819</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620769</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3499</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of winter cover crops on nematode population levels in north Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>517</sp>
<op>523</op>
<ab>Two experiments were conducted in north-central Florida to examine the effects of various winter cover crops on plant-parasitic nematode populations through time. In the first experiment, six winter cover crops were rotated with summer corn (Zea mays), arranged in a randomized complete block design. The cover crops evaluated were wheat (Triticum aestivum), rye (Secale cereale), oat (Avena sativa), lupine (Lupinus angustifolius), hairy vetch (Vicia villosa), and crimson clover (Trifolium incarnatum). At the end of the corn crop in year 1, population densities of Meloidogyne incognita were lowest on corn following rye or oat (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05), but no treatment differences were observed in year 2. Wheat was a good host to Paratrichodorus minor, whereas vetch was a poor host, but numbers of P. minor were not lower in vetch-planted plots after corn was grown. The second experiment used a split-plot design in which rye or lupine was planted into field plots with histories of five tropical cover crops: soybean (Glycine max), cowpea (Vigna unguiculata), sorghum-sudangrass (Sorghum bicolor x S. sudanense), sunn hemp (Crotalaria juncea), and corn. Population densities of M. incognita and Helicotylenchus dihystera were affected by previous tropical cover crops (P &amp;lt;/= 0.05) but not by the winter cover crops present at the time of sampling. Plots planted to sunn hemp in the fall maintained the lowest M. incognita and H. dihystera numbers. Results suggest that winter cover crops tested did not suppress plant-parasitic nematodes effectively. Planting tropical cover crops such as sunn hemp after corn in a triple-cropping system with winter cover crops may provide more versatile nematode management strategies in northern Florida.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620786; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262833</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262833</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620786</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3563</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Relationship of soil management history and nutrient status to nematode community structure</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>June</fd>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>83</sp>
<op>95</op>
<k1>Nematoda</k1>
<k1>soil nematodes</k1>
<k1>community structure</k1>
<k1>species diversity</k1>
<k1>population density</k1>
<k1>trophic relationships</k1>
<k1>soil amendments</k1>
<k1>yard waste composts</k1>
<k1>soil organic matter</k1>
<k1>soil nutrient dynamics</k1>
<k1>nutrient content</k1>
<k1>conventional tillage</k1>
<k1>no-tillage</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>nematode trophic groups</k1>
<k1>organic amendments</k1>
<k1>long term treatment</k1>
<k1>soil nutrient cycling</k1>
<k1>J100</k1>
<k1>J500</k1>
<k1>J700</k1>
<no>Nematropica. 2004 June, v. 34, no. 1; Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND43670828</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<lk>http://purl.fcla.edu/fcla/nematropica</lk>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3503</id>
<a1>Wang,K. H.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Gallaher,R. N.</a1>
<t1>Effect of Crotalaria juncea Amendment on Nematode Communities in Soil with Different Agricultural Histories</t1>
<jf>Journal of Nematology</jf>
<jo>J.Nematol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>Sep</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>294</sp>
<op>301</op>
<ab>Effect of sunn hemp (Crotalaria juncea) hay amendment on nematode community structure in the soil surrounding roots of yellow squash (Cucurbita pepo) infected with root-knot nematodes was examined in two greenhouse experiments. Soils were from field plots treated long-term (LT) with yard-waste compost or no yard-waste compost in LT experiment, and from a short-term (ST) agricultural site in ST experiment. Soils collected were either amended or not amended with C. juncea hay. Nematode communities were examined 2 months after squash was inoculated with Meloidogyne incognita. Amendment increased (P &amp;lt; 0.05) omnivorous nematodes in both experiments but increased only bacterivorous nematodes in ST experiment (P &amp;lt; 0.05), where the soil had relatively low organic matter (&amp;lt;2%). This effect of C. juncea amendment did not occur in LT experiment, in which bacterivores were already abundant. Fungivorous nematodes were not increased by C. juncea amendment in either experiment, but predatory nematodes were increased when present. Although most nematode faunal indices, including enrichment index, structure index, and channel index, were not affected by C. juncea amendment, structure index values were affected by previous soil organic matter content. Results illustrate the importance of considering soil history (organic matter, nutrient level, free-living nematode number) in anticipating changes following amendment with C. juncea hay.</ab>
<no>JID: 9884299; OID: NLM: PMC2620648; ppublish</no>
<pp>United States</pp>
<sn>0022-300X; 0022-300X</sn>
<an>PMID: 19262764</an>
<la>eng</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol>
<pmid>19262764</pmid>
<pmcid>PMC2620648</pmcid></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Book, Section</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>2303</id>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<t1>Management of nematodes and soil-borne pathogens in subtropical potato production</t1>
<yr>1994</yr>
<sp>202</sp>
<op>202-213</op>
<k1>Potatoes -- Disease and pest resistance</k1>
<k1>Potatoes -- Diseases and pests</k1>
<k1>Potatoes -- Protection</k1>
<no>edited by Geoffrey W. Zehnder ... [et al.]. : edited by Geoffrey W. Zehnder ... [et al.].; Alternate title: Potato pest biology and management; Alternate title: Potato pest biology and management.; 50012 &amp;quot;This book...is an outgrowth of the International Conference on Potato Pest Management that was held in Jackson Hole, Wyoming on 12-17 October, 1991.&amp;quot;--p. xiii.; 50411 Includes bibliographical references.</no>
<pa>International Conference on Potato Pest Management</pa>
<a2>Zehnder,Geoffrey W.</a2><a2> Powelson,M. L.</a2><a2> Jansson,R. K.</a2><a2>Raman,K. V.</a2>
<t2>Advances in potato pest biology and management</t2>
<pb>American Phytopathological Society Press</pb>
<pp>St. Paul, Minn.</pp>
<sn>0890541647</sn>
<cn>SB608.P8A37 1994 (SCIENCE LIBRARY General Collection); SB 608 .P8A38 1994 (DIVISION OF PLANT INDUSTRY General Collection); SB608.P8A37 1994 (IFAS CENTERS Homestead)</cn>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3581</id>
<a1>Weingartner,D. P.</a1>
<a1>McSorley,R.</a1>
<a1>Goth,R. W.</a1>
<t1>Management strategies in potato for nematodes and soil-borne diseases in subtropical Florida</t1>
<jf>Nematropica</jf>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>Dec</fd>
<vo>23</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>233</sp>
<op>245</op>
<k1>Solanum tuberosum</k1>
<k1>cultivars</k1>
<k1>plant parasitic nematodes</k1>
<k1>plant diseases and disorders</k1>
<k1>plant pathogenic bacteria</k1>
<k1>plant viruses</k1>
<k1>nematode control</k1>
<k1>nematicides</k1>
<k1>chemical control</k1>
<k1>cultural control</k1>
<k1>disease control</k1>
<k1>Florida</k1>
<k1>F822</k1>
<k1>F830</k1>
<k1>F200</k1>
<no>Nematropica. Dec 1993. v. 23 (2); Includes references&lt;br&gt;RX: 850816 (on Jul 07, 2010)</no>
<sn>0099-5444</sn>
<an>IND20380456</an>
<la>English; Spanish</la>
<sf>Journal Article</sf>
<cn>DNAL SB998.N4N4</cn>
<db>AGRICOLA</db>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
