
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<refworks xmlns:refworks="www.refworks.com/xml/">


<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3906</id>
<a1>Abdallah,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Pollenz,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Droog,F. N.</a1>
<a1>Nunamaker,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Murphy,K. E.</a1>
<t1>Isolation and characterization of a cDNA clone coding for a glutathione S-transferase class delta enzyme from the biting midge Culicoides variipennis sonorensis Wirth and Jones</t1>
<jf>Biochemical genetics</jf>
<jo>Biochem.Genet.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>11-12</is>
<sp>377</sp>
<op>390</op>
<ab>Culicoides variipennis sonorensis is the primary vector of bluetongue viruses in North America. Glutathione S-transferases (GSTs) are enzymes that catalyze nucleophilic substitutions, converting reactive lipophilic molecules into soluble conjugates. Increased GST activity is associated with development of insecticide resistance. Described here is the isolation of the first cDNA encoding a C. variipennis GST. The clone consists of 720 translated bases encoding a protein with a M-r of similar to 24,800 composed of 219 amino acids. The deduced amino acid sequence is similar (64%-74%) to class Delta (previously named Theta) GSTs from the dipteran genera Musca. Drosophila, Lucilia and Anopheles. The cDNA was subcloned into pET-11b, expressed in Epicurian coli BL21 (DE3) and has a specific activity of similar to 28,000 units/mg for the substrate 1-chloro-2,4-dinitrobenzene.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0006-2928</sn>
<an>000166867100004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3892</id>
<a1>Anderson,Sheri L.</a1>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<a1>Smartt,Chelsea T.</a1>
<t1>Effects of West Nile Virus Dose and Extrinsic Incubation Temperature on Temporal Progression of Vector Competence in Culex Pipiens Quinquefasciatus</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>2010</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>26</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>103</sp>
<op>107</op>
<ab>Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus were fed blood containing either 7.0 +/- 0.1 logs plaque-forming units (pfu)/ml (high dose) or 5.9 +/- 0.1 logs pfu/ml (low dose) of West Nile virus and held at extrinsic incubation temperatures (EIT) of 28 degrees C or 25 degrees C. Approximately 20 mosquitoes per dose were collected after incubation periods (EP) of 4, 6, 8, and 12 days postinfection (dpi). Infection rates were influenced by EIT and virus dose but not by IP. Body titer was significantly higher for mosquitoes fed the high dose and held at 28 C at the later IPs (6, 8, and 12 dpi). However, leg titer was significantly higher for mosquitoes at the later IPs but did not differ between EITs or doses. Because infection rates varied with EIT and dose, there is likely a midgut infection barrier influenced by these factors that is not influenced by IP. Dissemination rates were influenced by all 3 factors consistent with the presence of a midgut escape barrier. Dissemination rate, body titer, and leg titer were dependent on IP, indicating the need to investigate multiple time points in vector competence studies to elucidate critical events in infection and dissemination.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>000276230200015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3898</id>
<a1>Bishop,Jeanette V.</a1>
<a1>Mejia,J. Santiago</a1>
<a1>De Leon,Adalberto A. Perez</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<a1>Titus,Richard G.</a1>
<t1>Salivary gland extracts of Culicoides sonorensis inhibit murine lymphocyte proliferation and no production by macrophages</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>75</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>532</sp>
<op>536</op>
<ab>Culicoides biting midges serve as vectors of pathogens affecting humans and domestic animals. Culicoides sonorensis is a vector of several arboviruses in North American that cause substantial economic losses to the US livestock industry. Previous studies showed that C sonorensis saliva, like the saliva of many hematophagous arthropods, contains numerous pharmacological agents that affect hemostasis and early events in the inflammatory response, which may enhance the infectivity of Culicoides-borne pathogens. This paper reports on the immunomodulatory properties of C. sonorensis salivary gland extracts on murine immune cells and discusses the possible immunomodulatory role of C. sonorensis saliva in vesicular stomatitis virus infection of vertebrate hosts. Splenocytes treated with C sonorensis mitogens were significantly affected in their proliferative response, and peritoneal macrophages secreted significantly less NO. A 66-kDa glycoprotein was purified from C. sonorensis salivary gland extract, which may be in part responsible for these observations and may be considered as a vaccine candidate.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>000240476400029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3903</id>
<a1>Bram,R. A.</a1>
<a1>George,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Reichard,R. E.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Threat of foreign arthropod-borne pathogens to livestock in the United States</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2002</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>39</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>405</sp>
<op>416</op>
<ab>There are many exotic animal pathogens throughout the world that, if introduced into the United States, could have a significant detrimental impact on the health of livestock, agricultural economy, the environment, and public health. Many of these pathogens are arthropod-borne and potential vectors are readily available in the United States. A number of these arthropod-borne pathogens are discussed here as examples that illustrate the potential risk and the consequences of inadvertent introductions. Several International agencies have a role in global surveillance and in controlling animal diseases should they begin to expand their range. The risk to the United States is considerable. We propose that the United States invest in the improved infrastructure needed to reduce the risk of foreign arthropod-borne pathogens. Current U.S. programs focus on the exclusion of pathogens through regulation of animal movements and products, surveillance, especially trained animal disease diagnosticians, research support, international cooperation and, should pathogens enter our country, the resources for their prompt eradication. We suggest that the United States needs to develop a comprehensive, updated strategic plan to assess all aspects of current and future requirements, objectives, and resources needed to protect its national interests.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000178371900002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3895</id>
<a1>Chadee,Dave D.</a1>
<a1>Kittayapong,Pattamaporn</a1>
<a1>Morrison,Amy C.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<t1>A breakthrough for global public health</t1>
<jf>Science</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>JUN 22</fd>
<vo>316</vo>
<is>5832</is>
<sp>1703</sp>
<op>1704</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0036-8075</sn>
<an>000247400500030</an>
<do>10.1126/science.1138904</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3899</id>
<a1>De Leon,A. A. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Transmission of vesicular stomatitis new jersey virus to cattle by the biting midge Culicoides sonorensis (Diptera : Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>323</sp>
<op>329</op>
<ab>Laboratory-reared Culicoides sonorensis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones were infected with vesicular stomatitis virus serotype New Jersey (family Rhabdoviridae, genus Vesiculovirus, VSNJV) through intrathoracic inoculation. After 10-d incubation at 25 degrees C, these insects were allowed to blood feed on four steers. Two other steers were exposed to VSNJV through intralingual inoculation with 108 tissue culture infective dose(50) VSNJV. All six steers became seropositive for VSNJV. The results demonstrate the ability of C. sonorensis to transmit VSNJV to livestock. Only the animals intralingually inoculated with VSNJV showed clinical signs in the form of vesicles at the site of inoculation. Uninfected C. sonorensis allowed to feed on the exposed animals did Hot become infected with VSNJV. Animals infected by C. sonorensis showed a slower antibody response compared with intralingually inoculated animals. This is probably because of different amounts of virus received via insect transmission and syringe inoculation. A significant difference was found in the serum acute-phase protein alpha-1-acid glycoprotein in animals that received VSNJV through C. sonorensis transmission. These animals had previously been exposed to insect attack in the field compared with intralingually inoculated animals and C. sonorensis-infected animals that had been protected from insect attack. The failure to observe clinical signs of vesicular stomatitis through transmission of VSNJV by C. sonorensis may explain widespread subclinical infections during vesicular stomatitis epidemics.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000236184600029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3920</id>
<a1>Deleon,A. A. P.</a1>
<a1>Lloyd,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Sexual Dimorphism and Developmental-Change of the Salivary-Glands in Adult Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>898</sp>
<op>902</op>
<ab>Salivary glands of adult male and female Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett) were sexually dimorphic when examined by phase contrast light microscopy. Female salivary glands were larger and more complex than those in males. Each female gland consisted of a main gland, which was subdivided into a proximal neck and a distal body with reference to the salivary duct, and four accessory glands. Each male salivary gland consisted of a pear-shaped body with a constriction, or neck, that divided it into a proximal and a distal portion, with reference to the salivary duct. Salivary glands of both sexes increased in length from emergence to day 3, followed by a sex-specific pattern of decrease. Based on these morphological observations, we suggest that the salivary glands of female C. variipennis are specialized in the production of secretory materials for bloodfeeding.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1994PP73300015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3918</id>
<a1>Holbrook,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae) Complex in California</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>JUL</fd>
<vo>32</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>413</sp>
<op>419</op>
<ab>Genetic relationships were examined among 24 collections, representing 23 populations of Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett) using isozyme electrophoresis of 11 protein encoding loci. The populations were collected from alkaline or fresh water larval habitats in California. Distance analysis demonstrated that C. v. occidentalis Wirth and Jones and C. v. sonorensis Wirth and Jones are genetically distinct. All C. v. occidentalis were geographically isolated from each other in highly alkaline or saline larval habitats, whereas C. v. sonorensis populations were collected from artificial freshwater habitats that were polluted with organic wastes. Higher levels of gene flow were found between C. v. sonorensis populations than from C. v. sonorensis populations to nearby C. v. occidentalis populations, indicative of genetic isolation between subspecies. Northern California C. v. sonorensis were genetically distinguishable from southern California C. v. sonorensis. The relationship between this variation and bluetongue disease epidemiology in California is discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1995RG29100004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3914</id>
<a1>Holbrook,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Brady,R.</a1>
<t1>Genetic variation in populations of Culicoides variipennis complex in the six New England states, USA</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>APR</fd>
<vo>10</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>173</sp>
<op>180</op>
<ab>We investigated the identity and distribution of members of the Culicoides variipennis complex in the six New England states of the U.S.A., a region where bluetongue transmission has not been detected. Analyses of seven polymorphic isozyme-encoding loci showed that only C.variipennis, not considered to be a vector of the bluetongue viruses, was present. The populations of C.variipennis were significantly more hetero-zygous than C.v.sonorensis and C.v.occidentalis populations from similar studies in the state of California. Estimates of genetic diversity among populations of C.v.variipennis in New England were similar to C.v.sonorensis in the state of Colorado, but were significantly more genetically divergent than California populations of C.v.occidentalis. The impact of these findings on the status of New England as a possible bluetongue-free region for the purpose of international trade in ruminant livestock and their germplasm is discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>A1996UL34300010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3907</id>
<a1>Holbrook,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Schmidtmann,E. T.</a1>
<a1>McKinnon,C. N.</a1>
<a1>Bobian,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Grogan,W. L.</a1>
<t1>Sympatry in the Culicoides variipennis complex (Diptera : Ceratopogonidae): A taxonomic reassessment (vol 37, pg 65, 2000)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2000</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>37</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>II</sp>
<op>II</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000089625000002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3915</id>
<a1>Hunt,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Handling small arbovirus vectors safely during biosafety level 3 containment: Culicoides variipennis sonorensis (Diptera: Ceratopogonidae) and exotic bluetongue viruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>271</sp>
<op>277</op>
<ab>Equipment and procedures are described for biosafety level 3 (BL-3) containment work with small, zoophilic arthropods. BL-3 classified pathogens always must be manipulated in biological safety cabinets. Procedures, including physical barriers and handling methods, that prevent the escape of potentially virus-infected insects are discussed, and the use of a monitoring system for insect security is explained. The inability to recover escaped minute, flying insects poses a major difference from similar work with larger insects, such as mosquitoes. Methods were developed for the safe and secure handling of Culicoides variipennis sonorensis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones infected with exotic bluetongue viruses during BL-3 containment.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1996UH44700001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3917</id>
<a1>Hunt,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Cold-Storage Effects on Egg Hatch in Laboratory-Reared Culicoides-Variipennis Sonorensis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>11</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>335</sp>
<op>338</op>
<ab>The effects of cold storage (5 degrees C) on the hatching rates of laboratory-reared Culicoides variipennis sonorensis eggs were examined. Mortality increased with storage time. Average maximum embryo survivorship for 4 trials was 55.0 +/- 4.2 (+/-SEM) days. Alternating daily cycles of high and then low mean hatching rates occurred and possibly were due to location differences in temperature within the temperature-controlled rearing system. During cold storage at 5 degrees C, C. v. sonorensis eggs may be kept for ca. 28 days with an anticipated hatching rate of about 50%.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>A1995RW37600008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3931</id>
<a1>Hunt,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Mckinnon,C. N.</a1>
<t1>Environmental-Factors Affecting Mortality of Adult Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae) in the Laboratory</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>5</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>387</sp>
<op>391</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>A1989AQ64400015</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3897</id>
<a1>Lord,Cynthia C.</a1>
<a1>Rutledge,C. Roxanne</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<t1>Relationships between host viremia and vector susceptibility for arboviruses</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>623</sp>
<op>630</op>
<ab>Using a threshold model where a minimum level of host viremia is necessary to infect vectors affects our assessment of the relative importance of different host species in the transmission and spread of these pathogens. Other models may be more accurate descriptions of the relationship between host viremia and vector infection. Under the threshold model, the intensity and duration of the viremia above the threshold level is critical in determining the potential numbers of infected mosquitoes. A probabilistic model relating host viremia to the probability distribution of virions in the mosquito bloodmeal shows that the threshold model will underestimate the significance of hosts with low viremias. A probabilistic model that includes avian mortality shows that the maximum number of mosquitoes is infected by feeding on hosts whose viremia peaks just below the lethal level. The relationship between host viremia and vector infection is complex, and there is little experimental information to determine the most accurate model for different arthropod-vector-host systems. Until there is more information, the ability to distinguish the relative importance of different hosts in infecting vectors will remain problematic. Relying on assumptions with little support may result in erroneous conclusions about the importance of different hosts.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000242788500027</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3934</id>
<a1>Lorenz,L.</a1>
<a1>Beaty,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Aitken,T. H. G.</a1>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>The Effect of Colonization upon Aedes-Aegypti - Susceptibility to Oral Infection with Yellow-Fever Virus</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>690</sp>
<op>694</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1984TD91100028</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3921</id>
<a1>Maclachlan,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Nunamaker,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Katz,J. B.</a1>
<a1>Sawyer,M. M.</a1>
<a1>Akita,G. Y.</a1>
<a1>Osburn,B. I.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Detection of Bluetongue Virus in the Blood of Inoculated Calves - Comparison of Virus Isolation, Pcr Assay, and In-Vitro Feeding of Culicoides-Variipennis</t1>
<jf>Archives of Virology</jf>
<jo>Arch.Virol.</jo>
<yr>1994</yr>
<vo>136</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>8</op>
<ab>The interval after infection when bluetongue virus (BTV) was present in the blood of calves inoculated with BTV serotype 10 (BTV 10) was evaluated by virus isolation (VI) in embryonated chicken eggs (ECE), BTV-specific polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and in vitro blood feeding of vector Culicoides variipennis (C.v.) sonorensis. BTV nucleic acid was detected by PCR in blood cells for 16 to 20 weeks after infection whereas infectious virus was detected by VI in ECE for 2 to 8 weeks. BTV was detected in calf blood by in vitro feeding of C.v. sonorensis for only O to 2 weeks after inoculation of calves with BTV 10. Selected bloods which were positive by PCR analysis but not by VI in ECE were not infectious for sheep. The data are consistent with the hypothesis that prolonged viremia in BTV-infected cattle results from association of the virus with blood cells, especially erythrocytes. The fact that calf blood that contained viral nucleic acid as determined by PCR analysis, but not infectious virus as determined by VI in ECE, was not infectious for either the insect vector or sheep suggests that cattle whose blood contains BTV nucleic acid but not infectious virus are unimportant to the epidemiology of BTV infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0304-8608</sn>
<an>A1994NN73700001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3929</id>
<a1>Miller,B. R.</a1>
<a1>Monath,T. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Ezike,V. I.</a1>
<t1>Epidemic Yellow-Fever Caused by an Incompetent Mosquito Vector</t1>
<jf>Tropical Medicine and Parasitology</jf>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>396</sp>
<op>399</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0177-2392</sn>
<an>A1989CF14100002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3919</id>
<a1>Mullens,B. A.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Holbrook,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,L. H.</a1>
<t1>Effects of Temperature on Virogenesis of Bluetongue Virus Serotype-11 in Culicoides-Variipennis-Sonorensis</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1995</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>9</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>71</sp>
<op>76</op>
<ab>Culicoides variipennis sonorensis females were fed bluetongue virus serotype 11 mixed in sheep blood and were held at constant temperatures of 32, 27, 21 and 15-degrees-C. Virogenesis, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), proceeded significantly faster at higher temperatures. Based on ELISA absorbance greater-than-or-equal-to 0.2, some flies first were categorized as infected after 1 day, 2 days and 4 days at 32, 27 and 21-degrees-C, respectively. Peak levels of virus antigen were seen after 5-7, 7-13 and 18-22 days for flies held at 32, 27 and 21-degrees-C, respectively. There was no significant virus replication in flies held at 15-degrees-C for 22 days, but latent virus replicated and was detected easily (44% infection) 4-10 days after these flies were transferred to 27-degrees-C. The implications for temperature effects on bluetongue epizootiology are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>A1995PZ47000010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3908</id>
<a1>Nunamaker,R. A.</a1>
<a1>Brown,S. E.</a1>
<a1>McHolland,L. E.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Knudson,D. L.</a1>
<t1>First-generation physical map of the Culicoides variipennis (Diptera : Ceratopogonidae) genome</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>771</sp>
<op>775</op>
<ab>Recombinant cosmids labeled with biotin-11-dUTP or digoxigenin by nick translation were used as in situ hybridization probes to metaphase chromosomes of Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett). Failed fluorescent signals were detected on each arm of sister chromatids and were ordered along the 3 chromosomes. Thirty-three unique probes were mapped to the 3 chromosomes of C. variipennis (2n = 6): 7 to chromosome 1, 20 to chromosome 2, and a to chromosome 3. This work represents the first stage in generating a physical map of the genome of C. variipennis.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000083719200020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3896</id>
<a1>Perez De Leon,Adalberto A.</a1>
<a1>O&#39;Toole,Donal</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<t1>Infection of guinea pigs with vesicular stomatitis New Jersey Virus transmitted by Culicoides sonorensis (Diptera : Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2006</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>43</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>568</sp>
<op>573</op>
<ab>Intrathoracically inoculated Culicoides sonorensis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones were capable of transmitting vesicular stomatitis New Jersey virus (family Rhabdoviridae, genus Vesiculovirus, VSNJV) during blood feeding on the abdomen of six guinea pigs. None of the guinea pigs infected in this manner developed clinical signs of vesicular stomatitis despite seroconversion for VSNJV. Guinea pigs infected by intradermal inoculations of VSNJV in the abdomen also failed to develop clinical signs of vesicular stomatitis. Three guinea pigs given intradermal inoculations of VSNJV in the foot pad developed lesions typical of vesicular stomatitis. Transmission by the bite of C. sonorensis may have facilitated guinea pig infection with VSNJV because a single infected C. sonorensis caused seroconversion and all guinea pigs infected by insect bite seroconverted compared with 50% of the guinea pigs infected by intradermal inoculation with a higher titer VSNJV inoculum. The role of C. sonorensis in the transmission of VSNJV is discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000242788500019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3941</id>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Arnold,J.</a1>
<t1>Genetics and the Origin of a Vector Population - Aedes-Aegypti, a Case-Study</t1>
<jf>Science</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>1980</yr>
<vo>208</vo>
<is>4450</is>
<sp>1385</sp>
<op>1387</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0036-8075</sn>
<an>A1980JV48500025</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3922</id>
<a1>Raich,T. J.</a1>
<a1>Archer,J. L.</a1>
<a1>Robertson,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Beaty,B. J.</a1>
<t1>Polymerase Chain-Reaction Approaches to Culicoides (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae) Identification</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1993</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>30</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>228</sp>
<op>232</op>
<ab>Molecular genetic approaches such as polymerase chain amplification (PCR) of target genomic sequences are finding wide application in systematic and taxonomic studies of arthropods. PCR-based techniques that preclude the need for target DNA sequence information of the species of interest facilitate molecular taxonomic studies. Two such techniques, tDNA-PCR (DNA encoding tRNAs is the analyte) and RAPD-PCR (randomly amplified polymorphic DNA) were investigated for their ability to differentiate certain North American Culicoides spp. larvae and adults.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1993KJ31500029</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3893</id>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Lord,Cynthia C.</a1>
<a1>Pesko,Kendra</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<t1>Environmental and Biological Factors Influencing Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say (Diptera: Culicidae) Vector Competence for Saint Louis Encephalitis Virus</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>2009</yr>
<fd>AUG</fd>
<vo>81</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>264</sp>
<op>272</op>
<ab>Complex interactions between environmental and biological factors influence the susceptibility of Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus to St. Louis encephalitis virus and could affect the epidemiology of virus transmission. Similar interactions Could have epidemiologic implications for other vector-virus systems. We conducted an experiment to examine four such factors in combination: mosquito age, extrinsic incubation temperature (EIT), virus dose, and colony The proportion of mosquitoes with body infections or disseminated infections varied between colonies, and was dependant oil age, EIT, and dose. We also show that the probability of a body or leg infection interacted in complex ways between colonies, ages, EITs. and doses. The complex interactive effects of environmental and biological factors Must be taken into account for studies of vector competence and epidemiology, especially when laboratory studies are used to generalize to natural transmission dynamics where the extent of variation is largely unknown.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>000268360400016</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3894</id>
<a1>Richards,Stephanie L.</a1>
<a1>Mores,Christopher N.</a1>
<a1>Lord,Cynthia C.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,Walter J.</a1>
<t1>Impact of extrinsic incubation temperature and virus exposure on vector competence of Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus say (Diptera : Culicidae) for West Nile virus</t1>
<jf>Vector-Borne and Zoonotic Diseases</jf>
<yr>2007</yr>
<fd>WIN</fd>
<vo>7</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>629</sp>
<op>636</op>
<ab>Culex pipiens quinquefasciatus Say mosquitoes from a laboratory colony were exposed to artificial blood meals containing West Nile virus (WNV) and held at incubation temperatures approximating average daily temperatures that occur during Florida arboviral periods. Mosquitoes fed blood meals containing 6.2 logs plaque-forming units (pfu) WNV/mL and held at 25 degrees C, 28 degrees C, or 30 degrees C for 13 days exhibited significantly different rates of infection (30%, 52%, 93%) and dissemination (33%, 22%, 81%) across temperatures. In a separate experiment, Cx. p. quinquefasciatus mosquitoes were provided artificial blood meals with graded doses of WNV from 3.7 to 5.8 logs pfu/mL and maintained at 28 degrees C for 13 days. Rates of infection increased as a function of virus dose, but neither body titers nor dissemination rates were significantly different for mosquitoes that were infected by ingesting different amounts of WNV. Our findings indicate that efficiency of WNV infection and dissemination, and thereby transmission, in Cx. p. quinquefasciatus populations similar to our tested colony may also be diminished when fed blood meals containing less than 5.8 logs pfu WNV/mL and when environmental temperature falls below 30 degrees C. The relationship between the infection rate and dissemination rate changed at different temperatures. This relationship is likely complex and dependent on diverse interactions between factors such as incubation temperature and viremia, which should also be assessed for field populations.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>1530-3667</sn>
<an>000252490000018</an>
<do>10.1089/vbz.2007.0101</do>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3902</id>
<a1>Rutledge,C. R.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Lord,C. C.</a1>
<a1>Stark,L. M.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>West Nile virus infection rates in Culex nigripalpus (Diptera : culicidae) do not reflect transmission rates in Florida</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>253</sp>
<op>258</op>
<ab>We describe the first documented field transmission of West Nile (WN) virus by a North American mosquito. WN was first detected in northern Florida in 2001. An intensive mosquito trapping and surveillance program was conducted in this region for four nights to assess mosquito transmission of WN. Four mosquito traps, each with a single sentinel chicken, were placed at five different locations on each of four nights. A total of 11,948 mosquitoes was collected, and 14 mosquito pools were found to contain WN, giving a minimum infection rate between 1.08 and 7.54 per 1,000. Only one of the 80 sentinel chickens seroconverted to WN, demonstrating a single mosquito transmission event during the study and a mosquito transmission rate of between 0.8 and I per 1,000. Culex nigripalpus Theobald was responsible for WN transmission to the sentinel chicken, although both Cx. nigripalpus and Culex quinquefasciatus Say were found infected with WN. Mosquito transmission rates are reported in this study for the first time for a WN outbreak. This information is essential to determine risk of human and animal infection.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000183019100002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3911</id>
<a1>Schmidtmann,E. T.</a1>
<a1>Holbrook,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Day,E.</a1>
<a1>Taylor,T.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Culicoides variipennis (Diptera : Ceratopogonidae) complex in Virginia</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>35</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>818</sp>
<op>824</op>
<ab>Immature Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett) were sampled from aquatic habitats throughout Virginia, reared to adults, and examined by isozyme electrophoresis to assess their taxonomic status. Data from 22 counties showed that C. v. variipennis is widespread and common, the predominant taxon throughout Virginia, and genetically similar to C. v. variipennis in Maryland. Because C v. variipennis is considered an inefficient vector of the bluetongue viruses, this observation is consistent with the low seroprevalence of bluetongue in indigenous livestock of the mid-Atlantic region. Culicoides v. sonorensis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones, considered to be the primary North American vector of the bluetongue viruses, was recovered in large numbers only from a wastewater lagoon at a dairy in southeastern Virginia, but also was detected at low levels in 6 other counties. Comparison of genetic distances and patterns of discriminating alleles among Virginia populations of C. v. variipennis and C. v. sonorensis showed that respective subspecies are genetically distinct and show no evidence of introgression, irrespective of geographic- and habitat-level sympatry. The persistence of a pure C. v. sonorensis population in a dairy wastewater lagoon may reflect physicochemical factors that influence the distribution of immature C. variipennis complex populations. A better understanding of the distribution of the C. variipennis complex will benefit regionalization of U.S. exports of livestock and livestock germplasm to bluetongue-free countries.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000076210500034</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3905</id>
<a1>Schmidtmann,E. T.</a1>
<a1>Lloyd,J. E.</a1>
<a1>Bobian,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Kumar,R.</a1>
<a1>Waggoner,J. W.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Legg,D.</a1>
<t1>Suppression of mosquito (Diptera : Culicidae) and black fly (Diptera : Simuliidae) blood feeding from Hereford cattle and ponies treated with permethrin</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2001</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>38</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>728</sp>
<op>734</op>
<ab>The blood feeding of mosquitoes and black flies from Hereford cattle and ponies treated with commercial formulations of permethrin was evaluated using an animal enclosure trap sample system that allowed comparison of insect blood-feeding levels between treated and nontreated animals. Blood feeding of both Aedes dorsalis Meigen and A. melanimon Dyar from heifers treated with pour-on concentrate and whole body spray treatments was reduced significantly by 79-88% at 4 d posttreatment, with apparent but not significant reductions of 61-68% at 11 d posttreatment. Simulium bivittatum Malloch and S. griseum Coquillett blood feeding was reduced significantly by 96% to &amp;gt; 99% at 4 d posttreatment, but apparent reductions of 30-87% at 11 d posttreatment were not significant. Blood feeding of S. bivittatum from ponies treated with a permethrin fly wipe was reduced significantly by 98 and 87% at 1 and 7 d posttreatment, respectively. No evidence of treatment-induced mortality was observed for recently blood-fed female mosquitoes or black flies captured from treated animals and held for 24 h. The potential benefit of using permethrin to protect livestock from insect-transmitted pathogens was estimated with a model based on level of host attack, pathogen infection rate in the vector, and suppression of blood feeding. Suppression of blood feeding by 90% is predicted to prevent the exposure of a host to a pathogen for up to 10 d at 1,000 insect feedings per d when the vector population infection rate is one insect per 1,000. Ifinsect feedings are lower (100/d) and the insect infection rate remains at one per 1,000, protection is predicted for 100 d. In contrast, a 90% suppression of blood feeding is predicted to provide protection for less than 1 d at 1,000 feeding per day and a vector infection rate of one insect per 100.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000171279100018</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3909</id>
<a1>Schmidtmann,E. T.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Hunt,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,L. H.</a1>
<a1>Hurd,H. S.</a1>
<t1>1995 epizootic of vesicular stomatitis (New Jersey serotype) in the western United States: An entomologic perspective</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1999</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>36</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>1</sp>
<op>7</op>
<ab>Entomologic and epizootic data are reviewed concerning the potential for transmission of vesicular stomatitis (VS) virus by insects, including field data from case-positive premises in New Mexico and Colorado during the 1995 outbreak of the New Jersey serotype (VSNJ). As with previous outbreaks of VSNJ in the western United States, the 1995 epizootic illustrated that risk of exposure is seasonal, increasing during warm weather and decreasing with onset of cool weather; virus activity spread from south to north along river valleys of the southwestern and Rocky Mountain states; clinical disease was detected most commonly in horses, but also occurred in cattle and 1 Ilama; and most infections were subclinical. Overall, 367 case-positive premises were identified during the 1995 outbreak, with foci of virus activity along the Rio Grande River south of Albuquerque, NM, in southwestern Colorado, and along the Colorado River near Grand Junction, CO. The establishment of a 16-km (10-mile) radius zone of restricted animal movement around confirmed positive premises, along with imposition of state and international embargoes, created economic hardship for livestock owners and producers. The importance of defining the role of blood-feeding insects as biological vectors of VSNJ virus relative to risk factors that promote high levels of insect transmission, such as the presence of livestock along western river valleys, blood feeding activity, and frequent transport of animals for recreational purposes, is emphasized as a basis for developing effective disease management.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000078085200001</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3900</id>
<a1>Spielman,A.</a1>
<a1>Andreadis,T. G.</a1>
<a1>Apperson,C. S.</a1>
<a1>Cornel,A. J.</a1>
<a1>Day,J. F.</a1>
<a1>Edman,J. D.</a1>
<a1>Fish,D.</a1>
<a1>Harrington,L. C.</a1>
<a1>Kiszewski,A. E.</a1>
<a1>Lampman,R.</a1>
<a1>Lanzaro,G. C.</a1>
<a1>Matuschka,F. R.</a1>
<a1>Munstermann,L. E.</a1>
<a1>Nasci,R. S.</a1>
<a1>Norris,D. E.</a1>
<a1>Novak,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Pollack,R. J.</a1>
<a1>Reisen,W. K.</a1>
<a1>Reiter,P.</a1>
<a1>Savage,H. M.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Wesson,D. M.</a1>
<t1>Outbreak of West Nile virus in North America</t1>
<jf>Science</jf>
<jo>Science</jo>
<yr>2004</yr>
<fd>NOV 26</fd>
<vo>306</vo>
<is>5701</is>
<sp>1473</sp>
<op>1473</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0036-8075</sn>
<an>000225442700020</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3901</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Reflections on the Anopheles gambiae genome sequence, transgenic mosquitoes and the prospect for controlling malaria and other vector borne diseases</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>2003</yr>
<fd>SEP</fd>
<vo>40</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>597</sp>
<op>606</op>
<ab>The completion of the Anopheles gambiae Giles genome sequencing project is a milestone toward developing more effective strategies in reducing the impact of malaria and other vector borne diseases. The successes in developing transgenic approaches using mosquitoes have provided another essential new tool for further progress in basic vector genetics and the goal of disease control. The use of transgenic approaches to develop refractory mosquitoes is also possible. The ability to use genome sequence to identify genes, and transgenic approaches to construct refractory mosquitoes, has provided the opportunity that with the future development of an appropriate genetic drive system, refractory transgenes can be released into vector populations leading to nontransmitting mosquitoes. An. gambiae populations incapable of transmitting malaria. This compelling strategy will be very difficult to achieve and will require a broad substantial research program for success. The fundamental information that is required on genome structure, gene function and environmental effects on genetic expression are largely unknown. The ability to predict gene effects on phenotype is rudimentary, particularly in natural populations. As a result, the release of a refractory transgene into natural mosquito populations is imprecise and there is little ability to predict unintended consequences. The new genetic tools at hand provide opportunities to address an array of important issues, many of which can have immediate impact on the effectiveness of a host of strategies to control vector borne disease. Transgenic release approaches represent only one strategy that should be pursued. A balanced research program is required.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>000185604800002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3904</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Pharmacological factors in the saliva of blood-feeding insects - Implications for vesicular stomatitis epidemiology</t1>
<jf>Tropical Veterinary Diseases - Control and Prevention in the Context of the New World Order</jf>
<yr>2000</yr>
<vo>916</vo>
<sp>444</sp>
<op>452</op>
<ab>Vesicular stomatitis (VS) epizootics in the Western United States have caused substantial economic losses to U.S. livestock industries in 1995, 1997, and 1998. The role of arthropods in transmitting VS to U.S. livestock is unclear. In particular, the impact of arthropod salivary gland factors in VS infections in livestock needs study. Pharmacological effects of arthropod salivary gland factors on animals are reviewed. The potential effects of arthropod saliva on the transmission and spread of VS virus to livestock in the Western U.S. is presented with emphasis on the biting midge, Culicoides sonorensis. Information is discussed with attention to vector potential of C. sonorensis, and its use as a model for evaluating insect salivary gland pharmacology on livestock response to VS.</ab>
<no>PT: S</no>
<a2>House,JA</a2><a2> Kocan,KM</a2><a2>Gibbs,E. P. J.</a2>
<t2>ANNALS OF THE NEW YORK ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</t2>
<sn>0077-8923; 1-57331-281-9</sn>
<an>000171939300058</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3916</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Culicoides variipennis and bluetongue-virus epidemiology in the United States</t1>
<jf>Annual Review of Entomology</jf>
<jo>Annu.Rev.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>41</vo>
<sp>23</sp>
<op>43</op>
<ab>The bluetongue viruses are transmitted to ruminants in North America by Culicoides variipennis. US annual losses of approximately $125 million are due to restrictions on the movement of livestock and germplasm to bluetongue-free countries. Bluetongue is the most economically important arthropod-borne animal disease in the United States. Bluetongue is absent in the northeastern United States because of the inefficient vector ability there of C. variipennis for bluetongue. The vector of bluetongue virus elsewhere in the United States is C. variipennis sonorensis. The three C. variipennis subspecies differ in vector competence for bluetongue virus in the laboratory. Understanding C. variipennis genetic variation controlling bluetongue transmission will help identify geographic regions at risk for bluetongue and provide opportunities to prevent virus transmission. Information on C. variipennis and bluetongue epidemiology will improve trade and provide information to protect US livestock from domestic and foreign arthropod-borne pathogens.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0066-4170</sn>
<an>A1996TP40300003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3924</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Genetic Differentiation among Populations of Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae), the North-American Vector of Bluetongue Virus</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>85</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>140</sp>
<op>147</op>
<ab>Genetic relationships among 24 populations of Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett) were examined using isozyme electrophoresis of 21 protein-encoding loci. Estimates of genetic similarity based on gene frequency differences among populations were consistent with the existence of three North American subspecies, C. v. occidentalis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones, C. v. sonorensis Wirth &amp;amp; Jones, and C. v. variipennis. A stepwise discriminant analysis determined several allozymes which, when used in two canonical variables, accounted for 97% of the dispersion between subspecies. The geographic and genetic relationships among the three subspecies provide support for the hypothesis that the subspecies may be different species. The genetic relationships of the three subspecies to C. gigas Root &amp;amp; Hoffman suggest that C. v. occidentalis diverged from a C. variipennis-like ancestor from which C. v. sonorensis and C. v. variipennis later evolved. The implications of the genetic structure of the C. variipennis complex for the epidemiology of bluetongue disease in North America are discussed.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>A1992HK83000004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3923</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Microgeographic and Temporal Genetic-Variation in Populations of the Bluetongue Virus Vector Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1992</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>29</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>384</sp>
<op>394</op>
<ab>Seven Colorado populations of the bluetongue virus vector Culicoides variipennis (Coquillett) were analyzed for genetic variation at 19-21 isozyme loci. Permanent populations, which overwinter as larvae, showed little temporal genetic change at 19 loci. PGD and MDH showed seasonal changes in gene frequencies, attributable to selection at two permanent populations. Two temporary populations showed low heterozygosity compared with permanent populations. Independent estimates of gene flow, calculated using F(ST) and the private allele method, were Nm* = 2.15 and 6.95, respectively. Colorado C. variipennis permanent populations showed high levels of gene flow which prevented significant genetic differentiation due to genetic drift. Temporary populations showed significant gene frequency differences from nearby permanent populations due to the &amp;quot;founder effect&amp;quot; associated with chance colonization.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1992HR47700002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3925</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Control of Oral-Susceptibility to Infection of Culicoides-Variipennis with Bluetongue Virus</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>45</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>666</sp>
<op>671</op>
<ab>A family selection scheme, based on the progeny from individual females, was used to select several families of the insect vector Culicoides variipennis that were resistant or susceptible to oral infection with bluetongue virus. Genetic crosses between families showed results consistent with control by a single genetic locus (blu). Reciprocal crosses suggested a maternal effect in which the genotype of the mother determined the phenotype of the offspring. The dominant and recessive natures of the resistant (blu(r)) and susceptible (blu(s)) alleles were determined by the sex of the parent. The results provide the first evidence to suggest a genetic locus controlling insect vector competence for infection with an arbovirus.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1991HA01500003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3928</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Variation in Laboratory and Field Populations of the Vector of Bluetongue Virus, Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>JAN</fd>
<vo>27</vo>
<is>1</is>
<sp>24</sp>
<op>30</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1990CH94800004</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3938</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Geographic and Temporal Patterns of Genetic-Variation of Aedes-Aegypti in New-Orleans</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>31</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>849</sp>
<op>853</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1982NZ62500024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3943</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Identification and Linkage Relationships of 3 Hexokinase Genes in Aedes-Aegypti</t1>
<jf>Biochemical genetics</jf>
<jo>Biochem.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>16</vo>
<is>5-6</is>
<sp>571</sp>
<op>575</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0006-2928</sn>
<an>A1978FU55900017</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3940</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Howard,D. J.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Control of Hexokinase Variation in Insects</t1>
<jf>Biochemical genetics</jf>
<jo>Biochem.Genet.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>20</vo>
<is>1-2</is>
<sp>47</sp>
<op>57</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0006-2928</sn>
<an>A1982NG18800005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3913</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>MacLachlan,N. J.</a1>
<a1>Thompson,L. H.</a1>
<a1>Hunt,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Patton,J. F.</a1>
<t1>Susceptibility of Culicoides variipennis sonorensis to infection by polymerase chain reaction-detectable bluetongue virus in cattle blood</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1996</yr>
<fd>MAY</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>5</is>
<sp>481</sp>
<op>485</op>
<ab>Cattle bloods containing only polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-detectable bluetongue-10 viral nucleic acid, but as determined by virus isolation techniques, not bluetongue-10 virus, were incapable of infecting intrathoracically inoculated Culicoides variipennis sonorensis. These insects also failed to transmit bluetongue-10 virus when fed on sheep. Cattle whose blood contain only PCR-detectable bluetongue viral nucleic acid, but no infectious virus, are unlikely to play a role in the epidemiology of bluetongue. The biological significance of PCR-based detection assays and their effect on animal health regulations on the international trade of livestock and livestock germplasm is discussed. Bluetongue virus infection provides a very useful model with which to study arthropod-transmitted RNA virus infections of humans and other animals.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1996UP63200008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3926</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Mecham,J. O.</a1>
<t1>Sources of Variation in an Enzyme-Linked Immunoassay of Bluetongue Virus in Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae)</t1>
<jf>Journal of medical entomology</jf>
<jo>J.Med.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1991</yr>
<fd>MAR</fd>
<vo>28</vo>
<is>2</is>
<sp>287</sp>
<op>288</op>
<ab>An enzyme-linked immunoassay for detecting bluetongue virus in infected Culicoides variipennis was evaluated using a nested analysis of variance to determine sources of experimental error in the procedure. The major source of variation was differences among individual insects (84% of the total variance). Storing insects at -70-degrees-C for two months contributed to experimental variation in the ELISA reading (14% of the total variance) and should be avoided. Replicate assays of individual insects were shown to be unnecessary, since variation among replicate wells and plates was minor (2% of the total variance).</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2585</sn>
<an>A1991FA26300019</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3937</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Analysis of Culex-Pipiens Populations in the Central Valley of California</t1>
<jf>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</jf>
<jo>Ann.Entomol.Soc.Am.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>76</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>715</sp>
<op>720</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0013-8746</sn>
<an>A1983QY74100024</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3942</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<t1>World-Wide Survey of Genetic-Variation in the Yellow-Fever Mosquito, Aedes-Aegypti</t1>
<jf>Genetical research</jf>
<jo>Genet.Res.</jo>
<yr>1979</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>215</sp>
<op>229</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0016-6723</sn>
<an>A1979JG90300002</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3944</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Genetic Structure of East-African Domestic Populations of Aedes-Aegypti</t1>
<jf>Nature</jf>
<jo>Nature</jo>
<yr>1978</yr>
<vo>272</vo>
<is>5653</is>
<sp>535</sp>
<op>537</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0028-0836</sn>
<an>A1978ET37900043</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3912</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Robertson,M. A.</a1>
<a1>Murphy,K. E.</a1>
<t1>Culicoides variipennis and bluetongue disease - Research on arthropod-borne animal diseases for control and prevention in the year 2000</t1>
<jf>Vector-Borne Pathogens: International Trade and Tropical Animal Diseases</jf>
<yr>1996</yr>
<vo>791</vo>
<sp>219</sp>
<op>226</op>
<no>PT: S</no>
<a2>Camus,E.</a2><a2> House,JA</a2><a2>Uilenberg,G.</a2>
<t2>ANNALS OF THE NEW YORK ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</t2>
<sn>0077-8923; 0-89766-955-X</sn>
<an>000070968700023</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3932</id>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Aitken,T. H. G.</a1>
<a1>Miller,B. R.</a1>
<a1>Amato,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Lorenz,L.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<a1>Beaty,B. J.</a1>
<t1>Oral Infection of Aedes-Aegypti with Yellow-Fever Virus - Geographic-Variation and Genetic Considerations</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1219</sp>
<op>1224</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1985AUY8000031</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3910</id>
<a1>Venter,G. J.</a1>
<a1>Paweska,J. T.</a1>
<a1>van Dijk,A. A.</a1>
<a1>Mellor,P. S.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Vector competence of Culicoides bolitinos and C-imicola for South African bluetongue virus serotypes 1, 3 and 4</t1>
<jf>Medical and veterinary entomology</jf>
<jo>Med.Vet.Entomol.</jo>
<yr>1998</yr>
<fd>OCT</fd>
<vo>12</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>378</sp>
<op>385</op>
<ab>The susceptibility of field-collected Culicoides bolitinos to infection by oral ingestion of bluetongue virus serotypes 1, 3 and 4 (BLU 1, 3 and 4) was compared with that of field-collected C. imicola and laboratory reared C. variipennis sonorensis. The concentration of the virus per millilitre of bloodmeal was 10(5.0) and 10(6.0)TCID(50) for BLU 4 and 10(7.2)TCID(50) for BLU 1 and 3. Of 4927 C. bolitinos and 9585 C. imicola fed, 386 and 287 individual midges survived 10 days extrinsic incubation, respectively. Midges were assayed for the presence of virus using a microtitration assay on BHK-21 cells and/or an antigen capture ELISA. Infection prevalences for the different serotypes as determined by virus isolation ranged from 22.7 to 82.0% in C, bolitinos and from 1.9 to 9.8% in C. imicola; infection prevalences were highest for BLU 1, and lowest for BLU 4 in both species. The mean log(10) TCID50 titre of the three BLU viruses per single fly was higher in C, bolitinos than in C. imicola. The results suggested that C. bolitinos populations are capable vectors of the BLU viruses in South Africa. A high correlation was found between virus isolation and ELISA results for the detection of BLU 1, and less for BLU 4; the ELISA failed to detect the presence of BLU 3 in infected flies. The C. v. sonorensis colonies had a significantly lower susceptibility to infection with BLU 1, 3 and 4 than C. bolitinos and C. imicola. However, since infection prevalence of C. v. sonorensis was determined only by ELISA, this finding may merely reflect the insensitivity of this assay at low virus titres, compared to virus isolation.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0269-283X</sn>
<an>000076933100005</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3933</id>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Aitken,T. H. G.</a1>
<a1>Beaty,B. J.</a1>
<a1>Lorenz,L.</a1>
<a1>Amato,G. D.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Selection for Susceptibility and Refractoriness of Aedes-Aegypti to Oral Infection with Yellow-Fever Virus</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1985</yr>
<vo>34</vo>
<is>6</is>
<sp>1225</sp>
<op>1231</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1985AUY8000032</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3927</id>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Analysis of Rock Hole and Domestic Aedes-Aegypti on the Caribbean Island of Anguilla</t1>
<jf>Journal of the American Mosquito Control Association</jf>
<jo>J.Am.Mosq.Control Assoc.</jo>
<yr>1990</yr>
<fd>DEC</fd>
<vo>6</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>625</sp>
<op>630</op>
<ab>Genetic variation was characterized at 11 enzyme coding loci in Aedes aegypti collected from 3 rock hole and 4 domestic sites on the island of Anguilla, West Indies. The pattern of gene frequency variation suggests that these mosquito samples do not constitute a single panmictic population, but there are no large consistent differences between rock hole and domestic forms to parallel the East African sylvan-domestic dichotomy. With the exception of one of the domestic populations, two loci did however show some gene frequency differences consistent with genetic differentiation between the 2 habitat types. We conclude that whereas there may be some degree of differentiation between the 2 habitat types, local eradication attempts and sporadic gene flow cause temporal and spatial volatility that is sufficient to swamp these differences.</ab>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>8756-971X</sn>
<an>A1990EU61700008</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3939</id>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Linkage of an Idh Locus with Sex and 2 Lethals in Aedes-Aegypti</t1>
<jf>Journal of Heredity</jf>
<jo>J.Hered.</jo>
<yr>1982</yr>
<vo>73</vo>
<is>4</is>
<sp>291</sp>
<op>294</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-1503</sn>
<an>A1982NY39600010</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3935</id>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Genetic-Heterogeneity among Caribbean Populations of Aedes-Aegypti</t1>
<jf>American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</jf>
<jo>Am.J.Trop.Med.Hyg.</jo>
<yr>1984</yr>
<vo>33</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>492</sp>
<op>498</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0002-9637</sn>
<an>A1984SV27100027</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3936</id>
<a1>Wallis,G. P.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<a1>Powell,J. R.</a1>
<t1>Macrogeographic Genetic-Variation in a Human Commensal - Aedes-Aegypti, the Yellow-Fever Mosquito</t1>
<jf>Genetical research</jf>
<jo>Genet.Res.</jo>
<yr>1983</yr>
<vo>41</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>241</sp>
<op>258</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0016-6723</sn>
<an>A1983RB18000003</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference>
<reference>
<rt>Journal Article</rt>
<sr> Print(0)</sr>
<id>3930</id>
<a1>Wechsler,S. J.</a1>
<a1>Mcholland,L. E.</a1>
<a1>Tabachnick,W. J.</a1>
<t1>Cell-Lines from Culicoides-Variipennis (Diptera, Ceratopogonidae) Support Replication of Bluetongue Virus</t1>
<jf>Journal of invertebrate pathology</jf>
<jo>J.Invertebr.Pathol.</jo>
<yr>1989</yr>
<fd>NOV</fd>
<vo>54</vo>
<is>3</is>
<sp>385</sp>
<op>393</op>
<no>PT: J</no>
<sn>0022-2011</sn>
<an>A1989AW90600012</an>
<ol>Unknown(0)</ol></reference></refworks>
